<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5372019" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>common and deadliest diseases in the 
world. 
1 2 According to a report from the 
WHO, CVD is responsible for 17.5 million 
deaths annually worldwide. 
3 It was the 
leading cause of death and reduction in a 
human's expected lifespan. 
4 In 2012, about 
3.5 million deaths in China were attributable 
to CVDs, which means there would be a CVD 
death every 10 s in China. 
5 Among all the 
disease-associated deaths in China, it was 
concluded that over 40% of them were due 
to CVDs. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Hypertension is considered as the major 
contributor to CVDs. 
7 A report indicated that 
the prevalence of hypertension in Chinese 
adults increased from 18.8% in 2002 to 24.4% 
in 2012, while the control rate increased only 
from 6.1% to 9.3%. 
6 Furthermore, according 
to a recent large-scale survey in China with </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This study is one of the largest ongoing prospect-
ive population studies to evaluate target organ 
damages (TODs) in the community-dwelling 
elderly Chinese, which is authorised and funded 
by the Shanghai municipal government. 
▪ A systematic framework of a cardiovascular (CV) 
risk survey was conducted, with considerations 
on conventional CV risk factors, asymptomatic 
TODs, CV diseases, future events and mortality. 
▪ Left ventricular ejection fraction was measured 
by the M-mode echocardiograph, but not by 
Simpson's method. 
▪ The risk score is based on the elderly partici-
pants, who are already at significant risk due to 
their old age. However, collected data and the 
later risk score can also be used for validation in 
younger cohorts. 
▪ Some measurements in this study need highly 
specialised equipment, which is hard to scale to 
a larger population. </p>

<p>Ji H, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013880. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013880 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Protocol </p>

<p>205 167 men (41.0%) and 295 056 women (59.0%), </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>32.5% of the cohort participants had hypertension with 
an overall control rate of only 4.2%. This great challenge 
is due in part to the absence of a domestic CV risk score 
in China. 
Given the perniciousness of CVDs, an established CV 
risk score is essential to guide prevention and therapy in 
China. 
9 10 In fact, in the USA and Europe, many well-
known population studies with great professional 
achievements were conducted, and some mature CV risk 
score systems have already been established and applied 
efficiently, such as the Framingham Risk Score and the 
European SCORE Risk Charts. 
11 12 These studies 
pushed the transition from a poor understanding of 
CVDs to a more mature one going forward. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>The current risk scores in the USA and Europe are 
based on a mainly Caucasian general population. 
However, in China, things would be different. According 
to the World Population Ageing 2013, it will take China 
only 26 years to experience the population ageing, 
which means there is a rapid ageing trend in China. On 
the other hand, China also had the most rapid urbanisa-
tion in history. These two trends will interact in import-
ant ways with each other and will have a profound effect 
on Chinese CV health. Therefore, it would be inappro-
priate to apply those risk scores directly in the Chinese 
elderly. In Shanghai, the biggest urbanised city in China, 
the proportion aged over 60 years is 28.8% (Elderly popu-
lation and cause of aging monitoring statistics of Shanghai in 
2014 Accession Number: http://www.shmzj.gov.cn/ 
Attach/Attaches/201506/20150610104009609.doc). In 
this respect, Shanghai could be a good representative of 
the future Chinese population, with the deep urbanisa-
tion and the geriatric population. We therefore selected 
community-based citizens in Shanghai as our target 
population. The characteristics and successful experi-
ence on the CV risk control in this Shanghai geriatric 
population, acting as an exemplary role, could be extra-
polated to the future Chinese society. It means that 
effective interventions for the future Chinese would be 
designed 10-20 years sooner. 
Established CV risk prediction models are mainly 
based on the conventional risk factors such as age, sex, 
blood pressure, cholesterol, etc. However, if based only 
on the conventional risk factors, there is a fall in the pre-
dictive abilities of future risk in the older population. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>In the elderly, novel biomarkers are warranted to 
improve the risk stratification instead of relying on a 
model that is based only on established risk factors. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Asymptomatic target organ damage (TOD), as an inter-
mediate state between risk factors and clinical events, 
may be a good marker for risk stratification in the 
elderly. 
16 It might better represent exposure to risk 
factors than the risk factor itself. 
17 Therefore, we would 
like to add valuable TODs, together with conventional 
risk factors, into the risk assessment model in the elderly. 
As mentioned above, China is lacking in a well-
established domestic CV risk score system at present, and </p>

<p>prevention strategies as well as treatments for CVDs 
need significant improvement. There is an urgent desire 
in China to establish a CV risk score based on a Chinese 
population study, especially for the elderly. So we will 
perform a systematical framework of CV risk assessment 
for community-based elderly participants (&gt;65 years) in 
the northern Shanghai area. The assessments include 
conventional CV risk factors, TODs and related diseases. 
Our objective is to establish a Chinese CV risk score, the 
Northern Shanghai Risk Score, to guide future risk 
assessments and interventions for the elderly in China. 
This paper is to describe the design and method plan 
for this study. </p>

<p>METHOD 
Study design and sample size 
The Northern Shanghai Study is a prospective 
community-based ongoing study. This study was 
approved by the Shanghai Tenth People's Hospital 
Institutional Review Board and was conducted under 
financial support from the Shanghai municipal govern-
ment (grant ID: 2013ZYJB0902 and 15GWZK1002). The 
preliminary sample size is expected to be 3000-4000 
participants. </p>

<p>Participant eligibility criteria 
The inclusion criteria include: (1) age 65 years or more; 
(2) informed consent should be signed voluntarily; (3) 
local residents from communities in northern Shanghai 
and (4) available for long-term follow-up. The individual 
should be excluded, if the individual: (1) was diagnosed 
with serious heart disease (NYHA≥IV) or end-stage 
renal disease (CKD ≥4 stage); (2) suffered from cancer 
or his/her life expectancy is &lt;5 years; (3) had stroke 
within 3 months; (4) is not willing to participate in the 
clinical study; (5) has to quit the trial due to other dis-
eases; (6) violates the protocol or (7) loses contact with 
the laboratory staff. </p>

<p>Recruitment 
First, according to the Elderly population and cause of aging 
monitoring statistics of Shanghai in 2014, northern 
Shanghai region has the largest population of elderly 
adults in Shanghai, with a total population of 1.57 
million and an elderly proportion of over 19%. Thus, 
northern Shanghai region, including Zhabei district and 
Putuo district, was selected from Shanghai. Second, we 
use a computer-generated list of communities, and 10 
communities were randomly selected for the first-phase 
enrolment. Other communities in the list will be ran-
domly selected for the later enrolment. According to the 
inclusion and exclusion criteria, we invite all the eligible 
older people (over 65 years) to participate in this study. 
The recruitment strategies include: (1) posting study 
recruitment files in the neighbourhood committees and 
community hospitals; (2) according to the health file, 
community hospitals recruit the potential participants </p>



<p>Ji H, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013880. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013880 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>by telephone; (3) hand out recruitment flyers directly to 
the potential participants. Contact number is included 
in all the recruitment files and flyers. Before data collec-
tion, the field staff will give a brief oral questionnaire 
according to the inclusion and exclusion criteria. When 
the eligible individual shows their interest in participat-
ing in this study, the individual will be sufficiently 
informed, and they will sign the consent form. </p>

<p>Social, clinical and biological parameters 
Information is obtained from the standardised question-
naire, including gender, age, education level, smoking 
habits, drinking habits, history of diabetes, renal insuffi-
ciency and CVD. CVDs include chronic heart failure, 
peripheral vascular disease, hypertension, arrhythmia 
and previous CV event (the presence of a history of myo-
cardial infarction (MI) and/or stroke and/or cardiac 
revascularisation with either angioplasty or coronary 
artery bypass graft (CABG)). 
Participants must disrobe and remove shoes and stand 
straight before their body height and body weight are 
measured. Waist circumference and hip circumference 
are measured by a flexible rule, with waistline and 
hipline referring to the smallest waist and the greatest 
circumferences, respectively. The body mass index is cal-
culated by dividing body weight (kg) by the squared 
body height (m 
2 ). 
Venous blood samples are obtained after an overnight 
fast. Total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol 
and triglycerides are measured by standard methods, </p>

<p>18 19 </p>

<p>and the Friedewald formula is used to calculate the low-
density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol (LDL-c). 
20 Other 
biological parameters like plasma/urine albumin and cre-
atinine are measured by standard methods at local labora-
tories. The urine albumin-to-creatinine ratio (UACR) is 
also calculated. The serum and urine samples will be 
stored at −80°C. Prior to storage, the date, number of vials 
and recorder's name will be recorded. </p>

<p>Office blood pressure measurement 
After an overnight fast, brachial blood pressure is mea-
sured in the morning with the participants' bladder 
empty, free of tobacco or caffeine for at least 30 min 
before the measurement. The blood pressure is mea-
sured in the sitting position, after resting for 5 min, 
using a semiautomatic oscillometric device (Omron 
Healthcare, Kyoto, Japan), according to the recommen-
dations of the European Society of Hypertension. 
21 The 
average value is calculated for further analysis. </p>

<p>Ultrasonography 
All the ultrasonography measurements, including echo-
cardiography and carotid ultrasonography, are per-
formed by a single experienced cardiologist, who is 
unaware of previous results. All measurements are per-
formed with a MyLab 30 CV machine (ESAOTE SpA, 
Genoa, Italy), according to the American Society of 
Echocardiography (ASE) recommendations. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>The echocardiography is performed in the left decubi-
tus position. Left ventricular (LV) internal diameter at 
end-diastole (LVIDd) and septal (SWTd) and posterior 
wall thickness at end-diastole (PWTd) are measured dir-
ectly. The formula: </p>

<p>LVM (g ) ¼ 0:8 Â ½1:04 Â ½ðLVIDd þ PWTd þ SWTdÞ </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>À (LVIDd) 
3 þ 0:6 </p>

<p>is used to calculated the LV mass, based on modelling 
the LV as a prolate ellipse of revolution. 
22 The left ven-
tricular ejection fraction (LVEF) is calculated by 
Teichholz's formula, and the left atrium (LA) size is 
measured in the parasternal long axis and apical four-
chamber views. Left atrial volume is calculated using the 
ellipse model formula: </p>

<p>left atrial volume ¼ p Â ðSA1 Â SA2 Â LAÞ = 6 </p>

<p>In this equation, SA1 is the M-mode left atrial dimension 
in the parasternal short-axis view and SA2 and LA are 
measurements of short and long axes in the apical four-
chamber view at ventricular end-systole. 
23 The heart dia-
stolic function is also measured, including the peak E 
(early diastolic), peak A (late diastolic) velocities and 
the primary early diastolic velocities (Ea) with the PW 
and TDI Doppler. The primary early diastolic velocities 
(Ea) are measured by the lateral tissue Doppler signals. 
Carotid ultrasonography is evaluated at common 
carotid arteries of both sides using a 7.5 MHz transducer. 
Carotid artery intima-media thickness (CIMT) is mea-
sured on the left common carotid artery, 2 cm from the 
bifurcation, and is always performed on plaque-free arter-
ial segments. Intima-media thickness (IMT) is measured 
manually. The border is determined from changes of 
density of the section which is perpendicular to the vessel 
wall. Common, internal and external carotid arteries are 
all scanned longitudinally and transversely to determine 
the presence of plaques. The plaque is defined as IMT of 
the internal carotid artery of more than 1.5 mm 
24 or a 
localised echo-structure encroaching into the vessel 
lumen with the arterial wall above 50% thicker than 
neighbouring sites. The measuring process is performed 
by the same sonographer as the echocardiography. </p>

<p>Four-limb blood pressure measurement 
Four-limb blood pressures of participants are measured 
by VP-1000 (Omron Healthcare, Kyoto, Japan) automat-
ically, performed by trained staff. Bilateral ankle brachial 
index (ABI), the ratio of the ankle systolic blood pres-
sure (SBP) divided by the brachial SBP, could be read 
from the device and the lower ABI is applied for further 
analysis in subsequent studies. </p>

<p>Pulse wave velocity 
Pulse wave velocity (PWV), which can be estimated by 
the SphygomoCor device (AtCor, Australia), is measured 
in a defined segment to assess the arterial stiffness. 
25 It </p>

<p>Ji H, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013880. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013880 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>is recommended that the arterial stiffness should be 
determined non-invasively by the measurement of 
carotid-femoral PWV (cf-PWV) (Class I; Level of 
Evidence A) as a golden standard. 
26 27 The measure-
ment is performed with applanation tonometry 
(SphygmoCor, AtCor Medical, Australia), by two trained 
observers blinded to the other results according to the 
European Expert Consensus on Arterial Stiffness. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Participants need to rest quietly in a temperature-
controlled room for at least 10 min prior to the initial 
pulse pressure waveform measurements. The pulse ana-
lysis will be performed with sensors in the right radial, 
carotid and femoral arteries in a supine position. 
Recordings were made simultaneously with an ECG 
signal, which provided an R-timing reference. 
Simultaneously, the delay is estimated and the cf-PWV is 
calculated by the integral software automatically (m/s). 
The superficial distance covered by the pulse wave will 
be taken with a tape from the suprasternal notch to the 
carotid and femoral arteries at the sensor location. 
29 An 
operator index &gt;80% is considered as a reliable meas-
urement, in which the quality and reproducibility of the 
tonometry measurements are automatically tested. </p>

<p>Pulse wave analysis 
Pulse wave analysis, which can be observed on the com-
monly used device-SphygomoCor device (AtCor, 
Australia), 
30 is measured to estimate central haemo-
dynamic parameters. 
31 SphygmoCor is used to perform 
the applanation tonometry on a radial artery with the 
methodology previously described. 
30 After a 10 min rest 
in the supine position, the brachial BP is obtained with 
the SphygomoCor device. Then a radial waveform is 
recorded by one trained and experienced physician with 
a tonometry-based probe. The central waveform is esti-
mated by the inbuilt software, automatically, with the 
help of a validated generalised transfer function. 
Eventually, the central waveform is calibrated by the cal-
culated brachial mean and diastolic blood pressure 
(DBP), in order to obtain the central SBP and DBP. 
The SphygmoCor device provides a quality index, and 
only PWs with an operator index above 80 are accepted. 
The data are accepted only when a variation of heart 
rate is no greater than 5%. </p>

<p>Electrocardiography 
The 12-lead electrocardiograph is recorded at 25 mm/s 
and 1 mV/cm standardisation with standard equipment 
after at least a 5 min rest. Electrocardiographic QRS 
wave voltage is detected in this study. Parameters are 
recorded and calculated, including the voltage of the S 
wave of the chest lead V1 (SV1), S wave of the lead V3 
(SV3), R wave of the lead V5 (RV5), R wave of the lead 
aVL (RaVL) and the duration of QRS wave. Several 
indexes to distinguish the LV hypertrophy are as follows: 
Sokolow-Lyon-Rappaport index (SV1 or SV2+RV5 or 
RV6≥4.0 mv in men and SV1 or SV2+RV5 or RV6≥3.5mv 
in women), Cornell criterion (SV3+RaVL≥2.8mv in men </p>

<p>and SV3+RaVL ≥2.8 mv in women) and Cornell Product 
((SV3+RaVL)×QRS duration≥244mvÁms in men and 
(SV3+RaVL+0.6)×QRS duration≥244 mvÁms in women). </p>

<p>Evaluation of peripheral artery involvement 
The ABI is used to evaluate the peripheral artery 
involvement. 
32 Brachial-ankle index and brachial-ankle 
PWV are assessed automatically by inbuilt software using 
a VP-1000 device (Omron, Japan). This measurement is 
performed in the morning without coffee or tobacco for 
at least 8 hours prior to measuring and in an ambient 
temperature of 22-24°C. </p>

<p>Definition of TODs 
Generally, asymptomatic TODs include cardiac, arterial 
and renal TODs. 
LV hypertrophy is defined as LVMI ≥115 g/m 
2 (men) 
or LVMI ≥95 g/m 
2 (women). 
33 As for the arterial TODs, 
they are defined as increased CIMT (CIMT &gt;0.9 mm) or 
peripheral artery disease (ABI&lt;0.9). Chronic kidney dis-
eases (creatinine clearance rate (CCR) &lt;60 mL/min/ 
1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) and microalbuminuria (UACR &gt;30 mg/mmol) 
represent renal TODs. Specifically, LV diastolic dysfunc-
tion is present when ≥3 listed variables meet these 
cut-off values (septal e′, 7 cm/s, lateral e′, 10 cm/s, 
average E/e′ ratio, 14, LA volume index, 34 mL/m 
2 ). </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>Clinical outcome 
The primary outcome is a composite of major adverse 
cardiovascular events (MACE), including CV death, non-
fatal stroke, non-fatal MI or revascularisation ( percutan-
eous coronary intervention (PCI) or CABG). Non-fatal 
stroke is defined as the new onset of neurological defi-
ciency symptoms or signs lasting for at least 24 hours 
accompanied by evidence from either cranial CT or 
MRI. Non-fatal MI is defined by canonical chest pain 
symptoms and/or characteristic electrocardiographic 
changes with a rise of either troponin I &gt;1.0 ng/mL or 
troponin T &gt;0.1 ng/mL. Coronary revascularisation with 
either PCI or CABG is defined as a history of either 
stent implantation (PCI) or CABG. A death diagnosis is 
identified on the basis of a death certificate given by the 
related hospital. The end point is defined by a combin-
ation of a questionnaire, dropping-in follow-up and 
review of the computerised medical records of clinic 
visits and hospitalisations, conducted by a blinded end 
point evaluating committee. 
The secondary outcome includes: (1) subclinical 
organ damage which is defined as LV hypertrophy or 
decreased diastolic function or increased carotid IMT 
and/or the presence of plaque or hardening of the 
arteries or renal insufficiency (CKD3 period) or 
increased microalbuminuria; (2) newly diagnosed CV or 
cerebrovascular disease (including newly diagnosed 
hypertension, transient ischaemic attack, etc), or newly 
diagnosed renal insufficiency with proteinuria or newly 
diagnosed diabetes mellitus (table 1). </p>



<p>Ji H, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013880. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013880 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Statistical analytic approach for primary aim 
Survival curves are generated by the Cox proportional 
hazards regression model and survival among groups 
will be compared using the log-rank test. The receiver 
operating characteristic (ROC) curve is used to evaluate 
the effect of influential factors on the occurrence of 
MACEs. A two-sided significance level of 5% is defined 
as the level of statistical significance. The analyses are 
conducted with <rs id="software-3" type="software">SAS</rs> software, <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">V.9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, 
North Carolina, USA). </p>

<p>Development of the risk score at baseline and follow-up 
Individuals will be randomly selected to be exploratory 
and validation set. The score will be created on the 
exploratory set and tested on the validation set. Risk 
factors including TODs and conventional risk factors are 
selected. The TODs with a predictable value for cardio-
vascular events (CVE) are LV hypertrophy, arterial stif-
fening, carotid hypertrophy, lower limb atherosclerosis, 
microalbuminuria and renal function decline. 
35 The 
conventional risk factors for CVE include age, gender, 
smoking, obesity, diabetes, hypertension, blood glucose 
and lipid profile. The independent variables are defined 
and categorised as follows: LV hypertrophy: LV mass 
index &gt;115 g/m 
2 for men and &gt;95 g/m 
2 for women; 
arterial stiffening: cf-PWV&gt;12 m/s; carotid hypertrophy: 
IMT ≥0.9 mm; lower limb atherosclerosis: ABI ≤0.9; 
microalbuminuria: UACR &gt;30 mg/mmol; renal function 
decline: stage 2 CKD: eGFR 60-89 mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(MDRD); stage 3 or more CKD: eGFR &lt;60 mL/min/ 
1.73 m 
2 (MDRD); age is categorised into two groups: </p>

<p>65-80 years and over 80 years; obesity: BMI≥28.0 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. 
To estimate significant predictors of CVE, univariate ana-
lyses will be performed. In principle, only parameters 
with inflated coefficients are entered into the model. At 
baseline, considering that TODs are the basics of this 
model, multiple logistic regression (MLR) will be used 
to calculate β-coefficient of risk factors for CVE and to 
compare coefficients between TODs and conventional 
risk factors. Considering CVE as the dependent variable, 
variables significant at 5% will be included in MLR with 
stepwise backward elimination. 
36 At follow-up, the β 
coefficient in the Cox regression of each independent 
prognostic variable will be modified into an integral 
number to construct a prognostic score model (ie, exp 
(β)=HR). 
37 A p value of ≤0.05 is considered significant. 
In the scoring system, based on the magnitude of its 
regression coefficient, points will be assigned to each 
variable. Finally, by adding the score for each variable in 
the risk model, a sum score will be calculated for each 
participant. An ROC curve and area under the curve 
(AUC) will be assessed to stratify patients at a high risk 
of CVE. Sensitivity and specificity will be calculated for 
each cut-off score. The cut-off score with a maximum 
Youden index will be considered as the optimum. </p>

<p>Validation of the risk score 
Since individuals are randomly selected to be explora-
tory and validation set, the performance of the risk 
score will be evaluated in the validation set as well as the 
entire sample. The predictive performance of the risk 
score will be evaluated with the AUCs in ROC curves, </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline visit and patient follow-up </p>

<p>Time-points </p>

<p>Measure 
Baseline </p>

<p>Every 
2 years </p>

<p>Every 
5 years </p>

<p>Consent form 
• 
• 
• 
Baseline questionnaire (age, gender, smoking history, family history, medication 
history, symptoms and signs of HF) </p>

<p>• 
• </p>

<p>Follow-up questionnaire (including newly diagnosed cardiovascular or cerebrovascular 
events, kidney disease and DM) </p>

<p>• 
• </p>

<p>Body height, body weight, body mass index (BMI) and waist circumference and hip 
circumference </p>

<p>• 
• </p>

<p>Four-limb blood pressure measurement 
• 
• 
Office blood pressure measurement (3 times in a row) 
• 
• 
• 
Venous blood biochemical parameters (blood glucose, blood lipid profile, serum 
creatinine and uric acid, pro-BNP, homocysteine) </p>

<p>• 
• 
• </p>

<p>Urinalysis (urine microalbumin and urine creatinine) 
• 
• 
Blood and/or urine sample collection 
• 
• 
• 
Electrocardiogram (rhythm, SV1+RV5) 
• 
• 
Vascular ultrasonography (bilateral carotid IMT) 
• 
• 
Echocardiography (LVM, LAV, LVEF, E/Ea, E/A) 
• 
• 
Determination of arterial elasticity (PWA, PWV) 
• 
• 
Evaluation of peripheral artery involvement 
• 
• 
• 
Major adverse cardiovascular events 
• 
• 
Cardiovascular deaths 
• 
• 
All-cause deaths 
• 
• </p>

<p>Ji H, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013880. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013880 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>including sensitivity and specificity. During the evalu-
ation, net reclassification indices will be used to measure 
the improvement of risk estimation by classifying indivi-
duals to a more correct category. 
38 Furthermore, the 
proportion of individuals who have a score above the 
optimal cut-off value in the risk score will be compared 
with those with a low risk score. </p>

<p>Data entry and management of data files 
All data are entered into computerised database with 
<rs id="software-4" type="software">SAS</rs> software, <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">V.9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, North Carolina, 
USA). Values that are out of range or represent errors of 
faulty logic are avoided by double check. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Until now, the Northern Shanghai Study is one of the 
largest Chinese domestic population studies. We are 
aiming at building a CV risk score to guide the future 
risk assessments and interventions for the elderly 
Chinese. Since the burden from the chronic diseases is 
growing, 
9 10 our study will also contribute to Chinese CV 
health by establishing the CV profile of the Chinese 
ageing population. 
In the literature, risk predictive models have been 
established in various populations and in different set-
tings. 
39 Though the ability to predict the occurrence of 
future events in old persons has been studied, there are 
few studies that have published a risk estimation system 
which can be used to calculate risks in this age group in 
clinical practice. </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Some well-established CV risk scores from famous 
population studies were widely adopted, such as the 
Framingham Risk Score and the European SCORE Risk 
Charts. 
11-13 In fact, most of them were conducted in the 
general population focusing on conventional risk factors 
such as smoking, blood pressure, lipid profile, glucose 
level, etc. However, for the elderly, the long-term expos-
ure and accumulated microdamages from conventional 
risk factors have been converted into TODs. In this 
respect, just considering the conventional risk factors in 
the risk assessment strategy for the elderly may be 
inadequate. </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Taking a '70 years old chain smoker' with severe ath-
erosclerosis, for example, we prefer to reverse, terminate 
or at least control the process of atherosclerosis (TOD), 
instead of just advising him to quit his long-term 
formed smoking. For this patient, the CV risk from long-
term exposure to smoking has turned into severe athero-
sclerosis. The intervention of smoking cessation would 
be less beneficial compared with the lipid-lowering 
therapy. For the Chinese elderly, some TODs are more 
likely to be reversible than the inveterate risk factors like 
smoking. Actually, many asymptomatic TODs have been 
proved to be modifiable by medications, even in the late 
stage. For example, angiotensin receptor blockade 
(losartan) has been validated for reversing cardiac 
hypertrophy. 
41 Therefore, we suggest the transition of </p>

<p>the CV risk assessment from conventional risk factors 
(like age, gender and smoking) to the combination of 
asymptomatic TODs and risk factors in the elderly, 
which might be more compatible with the ageing 
population. 
In summary, we propose to establish a CV risk score 
system based on the TODs and conventional CV risk 
factors, focusing on the elderly. In this way, we can 
provide a more accurate CV assessment as well as a more 
effective guidance for treatment and intervention. 
Meanwhile, we may have a chance to provide the 
Chinese policymakers and opinion leaders with con-
structive suggestions regarding effective countermea-
sures to the national CV burden. 
Of note, we select Shanghai as the representative 
region, because the current proportion of those aged 
over 60 in Shanghai is 28.8%, which is similar to the esti-
mated 28.1% of future China in 2040 (Elderly population 
and cause of aging monitoring statistics of Shanghai in 
2014). </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>At the baseline analysis, this study seeks to show the 
CV profile of about 4000 participants, and to determine 
subclinical TODs with conventional CV risks. We will 
analyse the change of the TOD indicators at every 2-5 
years, and we will conduct new enrolment at the same 
time. Additionally, it is also expected that the subsequent 
follow-up studies in the Northern Shanghai Study will 
reveal the feasibility and necessity of establishing the 
Northern Shanghai Score. 
We believe that the CV risk score based on TODs and 
CV risk factors for the elderly Chinese can make a better 
prediction for future CV events, providing a more feas-
ible intervention. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
This protocol outlines the design and method of the 
Northern Shanghai Study. Results coming from this 
study will be used to construct the Northern Shanghai 
Risk Score, so as to guide the future assessments and 
interventions. </p>

<p>Contributors HJ, JX, SY, CC, XF, BB, YZho, JT, YL and YZha acquired the 
original data for this study. YZha and YX formulated the methods and 
designed the protocol. HJ and JX drafted the manuscript. HX helped us with 
the writing and language review. All authors contributed to revisions and 
approved the final version of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding This framework of cardiovascular risk assessment is conducted with 
financial support from the Shanghai municipal government (grant ID. 
2013ZYJB0902 and 15GWZK1002). YZha was supported by the National 
Nature Science Foundation of China (grant ID: 81300239 and 81670377). </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Shanghai Tenth People's Hospital Institutional Review Board. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided </p>



<p>Ji H, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013880. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013880 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Ji H, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013880. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013880 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>