<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5089661" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The cytokinesis-block micronucleus (CBMN) assay is a well-established technique that 
can be employed in triage radiation biodosimetry to estimate whole body doses of radia-
tion to potentially exposed individuals through quantitation of the frequency of micronu-
clei (MN) in binucleated lymphocyte cells (BNCs). The assay has been partially 
automated using traditional microscope-based methods and most recently has been 
modified for application on the ImageStream X (IS X ) imaging flow cytometer. This modi-
fication has allowed for a similar number of BNCs to be automatically scored as com-
pared to traditional microscopy in a much shorter time period. However, the MN 
frequency measured was much lower than both manual and automated slide-based meth-
ods of performing the assay. This work describes the optimized analysis template which 
implements newly developed functions in the <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> V R data analysis software for the IS X 
that enhances specificity for BNCs and increases the frequency of scored MN. A new dose 
response calibration curve is presented in which the average rate of MN per BNC is of 
similar magnitude to those presented in the literature using automated CBMN slide scor-
ing methods. In addition, dose estimates were generated for nine irradiated, blinded sam-
ples and were found to be within 60.5 Gy of the delivered dose. Results demonstrate that 
the improved identification accuracy for MN and BNCs in the IS X -based version of the 
CBMN assay will translate to increased accuracy when estimating unknown radiation 
doses received by exposed individuals following large-scale radiological or nuclear 
emergencies. IT is desirable to estimate doses received by individuals potentially exposed to ioniz-</p>

<p>ing radiation following a radiation accident as quickly as possible. When physical 
dosimetry through the use of dosimeters is not possible, such as in the case of a 
large-scale radiological emergency, biological dosimetry must be used to determine 
the dose. Rapid and accurate dose estimations are necessary to determine the proper 
treatment course for individuals requiring medical attention as well as to provide 
reassurance to those who have not been exposed. Based on the current capabilities of 
biodosimetry methods, it has been suggested that individuals receiving whole body 
doses of less than about 1.5-2 Gy can be followed as outpatients, but those receiving 
significant doses (&gt;2 Gy) should receive medical treatment in hospital (1,2). The 
median lethal dose (LD 50 ) for total body doses of ionizing radiation in humans is 
generally accepted to be 4 Gy (3). Above the 4 Gy threshold, clinical symptoms such </p>

<p>1 Amnis -MilliporeSigma, Seattle, WA, 
98119 </p>

<p>2 Environmental and Radiation Health 
Sciences Directorate, Health Canada, 
Ottawa, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>Received 12 November 2015; Revised 5 
May 2016; Accepted 10 May 2016 </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be 
found in the online version of this article. </p>

<p>*Correspondence to: R. C. Wilkins; 
Consumer and Clinical Radiation Protec-
tion Bureau, Health Canada, 775 Brook-
field Road, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada. 
E-mail: Ruth.Wilkins@hc-sc.gc.ca </p>

<p>Published online 6 June 2016 in Wiley 
Online Library (wileyonlinelibrary.com) </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1002/cyto.a.22887 </p>

<p>V C 2016 The Authors. Cytometry Part A 
published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on 
behalf of ISAC </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the 
terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial License, 
which permits use, distribution and 
reproduction in any medium, provided 
the original work is properly cited and is 
not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>Cytometry Part A 89A: 653À662, 2016 </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>as high fever, infection and bleeding will manifest themselves 
within a few days of exposure and medical treatment is likely 
to begin before dose estimates from biodosimetry are avail-
able. However, below this threshold these physical symptoms 
may not appear for several weeks and as such, rapid and accu-
rate dose estimations for individuals exposed to doses below 
the LD 50 is essential. 
The cytokinesis-block micronucleus (CBMN) assay is fre-
quently used in radiation biodosimetry to estimate unknown 
doses by correlating the rate of micronuclei (MN) per 
binucleated cell (BNC) in peripheral blood lymphocytes to a 
dose (4,5). The assay is traditionally performed using manual 
microscopy and is capable of generating accurate and repro-
ducible dose estimations between 0.3 and 4 Gy (6-8). A num-
ber of studies have illustrated that linear-quadratic dose 
response calibration curves can be obtained using automated 
or semi-automated slide scoring with the <rs type="software">MNScore</rs> software 
module on the Metafer slide scanning platform (MetaSystems, 
Germany) (7-10). The results of these works indicated that 
the overall MN frequency in these curves was reduced at 
higher doses (3 or 4 Gy) by a factor between one and a half 
and three when compared to manual slide scoring. The 
reduced number of MN in automated slide scoring appears to 
be related to the strictness of scoring criteria in image analysis 
that can cause MN that would be typically scored manually to 
be missed. For example, MN that are in very close proximity 
to the main nucleus may be missed by automated systems 
(8,10). This is a limitation to the sensitivity of the assay and 
its applicability in the low dose region; however, it is less of an 
issue for rapid dose estimation in the higher dose regions. 
A traditional flow cytometry based version of the MN 
assay in the field of toxicology has been previously described 
(11) and over the last several years has been configured into a 
commercially available kit by Litron Laboratories (12-15) that 
can be performed on a number of cell lines including mouse 
lymphoma and TK6 cells. In this method, MN are liberated 
through lysis of the cell membrane and scored through appli-
cation of a data analysis template that differentiates MN from 
the main nuclei. The increase in the number of MN can be 
directly correlated to the toxicity of various compounds and 
the method has had considerable success in the field of toxi-
cology. One of the limitations of this assay, however, is the 
generation of false positives by apoptosis inducing com-
pounds that are not necessarily genotoxic (14) thus requiring 
validation by manual microscopy. Furthermore, this method 
is not directly applicable to radiation biodosimetry. In the 
CBMN assay for radiation biodosimetry, the fundamental 
parameter of measure is the rate of MN per BNC in human 
lymphocyte cells in first mitosis (16). To quantify this parame-
ter, MN must be scored inside the cytoplasm of a BNC and 
therefore, the Litron Laboratories method is less than ideal. 
A novel method recently developed by our group (17-19) 
uses imaging flow cytometry (FCM) on the ImageStream X 
(IS X ) imaging flow cytometer (MilliporeSigma, Billerica, MA) 
to automate the CBMN assay. The IS X system combines the 
speed of traditional FCM with the high resolution image capa-
bilities of microscopy. Similar to traditional FCM, cells are </p>

<p>labelled with fluorescent dyes and are passed in suspension 
through the flow cell of the cytometer. In the IS X , a bright-
field (BF) LED light source and at least one solid state laser 
(405, 488, and 658 nm in our system) orthogonally interro-
gate each cell, creating transmitted and scattered light signals. 
The transmitted and scattered light is collected by one of three 
high numerical aperture lenses (203, 403, or 603) and 
undergoes spectral decomposition into specific wavelength 
ranges within roughly 400-800 nm. The wavelength ranges 
are then focused onto separate channels of a charge-coupled 
device (CCD) camera that takes the place of photomultiplier 
tubes found in traditional flow cytometers. Each channel cap-
tures optically divided sub-images which can be viewed indi-
vidually or can be combined to view the co-location of several 
signals. In this way, the IS X generates high resolution imagery 
for each cell that passes through the instrument that allows 
for visual confirmation of micronucleus identification 
(20-22). This is a substantial advantage over traditional FCM 
methods. 
The IS X is capable of capturing high-resolution images of 
individual cells at a rate of up to 5,000 cells per second. The 
new IS X -CBMN method is able to process cell samples sus-
pended in solution and eliminates the need to create micro-
scope slides, thereby reducing the time required for sample 
preparation (17-19). All images captured on the IS X are saved 
to a data file which is analyzed using the Image Data Explora-
tion and Analysis Software (<rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> V R ) built specifically for the 
IS X . Previously, we generated dose response calibration curves 
from 0-4 Gy (17,19) and 0-10 Gy (18) but in both cases, while 
a large number of BNCs were scored (about 2,000), a reduc-
tion in MN frequency by a factor of about 5-10 was observed 
when compared to curves generated by automated and man-
ual slide-scoring methods respectively. 
This paper describes the optimization of the <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> anal-
ysis template for identifying and scoring BNCs and MN in the 
IS X -based version of the CBMN assay. In this work, we re-
analyzed existing data in order to demonstrate improvements 
in the accuracy of identifying and separating BNCs from other 
cells and cellular debris, as well as improved detection of MN 
through the use of a newly developed MN mask. The resulting 
increase in MN frequency is evident in the improved dose 
response calibration curve in which the rate of MN per BNC 
is comparable in magnitude to those presented by other 
authors using automated slide-scoring versions of the CBMN 
assay. Finally the improved accuracy of the template is evi-
denced by the re-analysis of blinded samples to generate dose 
estimations to within 60.5 Gy of the delivered dose following 
only 5 minutes of data collection on the IS X . </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Blood Collection and Irradiation, the CBMN Assay and 
Data Collection on the IS X 
Blood collection, irradiation, and processing was per-
formed previously as described by Rodrigues et al. (17-19) 
and all data was saved as raw image files for analysis in <rs id="software-18" type="software">IDEAS</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-18" type="version-number">version 6.2</rs>). For the dose response calibration curve, </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p> 
Optimized Analysis of the CBMN Assay with Imaging FCM </p>

<p>peripheral blood was collected with informed consent 
(approved by Health Canada's Research Ethics Board) from 
healthy, non-smoking anonymous donors (three male and 
three female between the ages of 27 and 48). For the blinded 
samples, nine blood samples were collected from five healthy 
anonymous donors (males between the ages of 34 and 56 years 
of age) in 6 mL lithium-heparinized Vacutainer V R tubes (BD 
Biosciences, Mississauga, ON) with the same health and his-
torical radiation exposure criteria as described above. Each 
whole blood sample was then irradiated to a known dose 
between 0 and 4 Gy and blinded before culture. The doses 
were 0, 0.5, 0.7, 1.3, 1.7, 2.4, 2.9, 3.1, and 3.9 Gy. The CBMN 
assay was performed on all samples according to the proce-
dure described in Rodrigues et al. (17-19). Briefly, whole 
blood samples were diluted with RPMI 1640 culture medium 
containing 10% fetal bovine serum, 2 mmol L-glutamine, 100 
U/mL penicillin, 100 mg/mL streptomycin (Sigma-Aldrich, 
Oakville, ON) and 1% PHA (Life Technologies, Burlington, 
ON) to achieve 20 mL cultures in 25 cm 2 vented flasks. The 
cultures were incubated for 24 h before the addition of cyto-
chalasin B (Sigma-Aldrich) then incubated for an additional 
48 h. Cell suspensions were centrifuged, resuspended in FACS 
Lysing Solution (BD Biosciences) to lyse red blood cells and 
fix lymphocytes, washed twice with PBS and resuspended in 
100 mL of PBS. All samples in solution were stained with a 
1:100 dilution of DRAQ5 (eBioscience, San Diego, CA) to a 
final concentration of 1.25 nM per 1310 7 cells/mL and run 
on the IS X at 403 magnification with the 658 nm laser set to 
20 mW to allow DRAQ5 signal to be collected in channel 5 
and the BF LED in channel 1 (18). Early in the development 
of this method we examined the extended depth of field 
(EDF) option on the IS X and found no improvement in image 
quality and therefore, all data were collected without the EDF. 
For the calibration curve, approximately 100,000 events were 
collected in about 20 min at each dose point for each donor. 
For the blinded samples, events were collected for 40 min in 
5 min increments. For all acquisitions, a minimum area 
threshold was set to 75 pixels (18.75 mm 2 ) in both channels 1 
and 5 resulting in a collection speed of approximately 100-
150 events per second which was related directly to the cell 
concentrations of 1-2 3 10 7 cells/mL. An event is defined as 
any image collected by the IS X that meets both criteria and is 
stored in the data file. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>BNC and MN Mask Development and Gating Strategy 
in <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> 
In <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs>, a mask identifies pixels within a defined region 
of in an image. Optimized BNC and MN masks were devel-
oped by applying and combining several new and existing 
mask functions in <rs id="software-5" type="software">IDEAS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">version 6.2</rs>). The steps to create 
both masks are outlined below. 
The BNC mask was optimized to better delineate pixels 
in the main nuclei to allow more precise classification of 
BNCs based on the intensity, shape, and size of individual 
nuclei. This was achieved by applying three sequential mask </p>

<p>functions as shown in Figure 1A. The first row shows the BF 
image and the second row shows the unmasked DRAQ5-
stained nuclei. The third row shows the default event mask 
(superimposed blue on the main nuclei and MN) which is 
designed to highlight all pixels above background in an 
image. To create a BNC-specific mask, the Levelset function 
(fourth row) was first used to create a tight mask around the 
two main nuclei (intensity setting: medium, contour detail 
scale: 3). Next, the Watershed function was applied to the 
Levelset mask which allowed for separation of the two main 
nuclei by creating a border for the intensity valley within the 
nuclear image (fifth row). The Range function was then 
applied to the Watershed (Levelset) mask to exclude spots 
smaller than the main nuclei by setting a minimum area 
threshold of 115 pixels (28.7 mm 2 ) resulting in the final BNC 
mask that excludes the MN in both images (sixth row). In 
order to quantify features of individual nuclei within the 
BNC mask, the Component mask was applied to identify 
individual nuclei using Area as the ranking feature (seventh 
and eighth rows). 
The new MN mask, created using a combination of the 
Spot, Dilate and Morphology functions, identifies DRAQ5 
stained spots that are separate from the main nuclei. This 
more specific MN mask allowed the minimum area to be 
reduced from 10 pixels (2.5 mm 2 ) to 6 pixels (1.5 mm 2 ), 
thereby allowing the scoring of smaller MN as compared to 
the previous analysis. Figure 1B demonstrates the process for 
two BNCs containing MN with the first row illustrating the 
cytoplasm visualized in the BF channel. The first spot identifi-
cation function (second row) highlights spots in the image 
with radii between 1 and 4 pixels and a spot-to-cell back-
ground value of 2 and the Levelset function mask (third row), 
dilated by two pixels, identifies the main nuclei. Subtracting 
the dilated Levelset function mask from the first spot identifi-
cation mask gives the first MN spot mask (fourth row) and 
ensures that no spots highlighted in the main nuclei are iden-
tified as MN. The second spot identification function (fifth 
row) highlights spots in the image with radii between 1 and 4 
pixels and a spot-to-cell background value of 1 and the mor-
phology function mask dilated by three pixels (sixth row), is 
used to highlight the main nuclei. Subtracting the morphol-
ogy function mask from the second spot identification mask 
gives the second MN spot mask (seventh row) and allows for 
smaller nuclei (1.5 mm 2 ) to be masked than can be achieved 
by the first MN spot mask while ensuring that no small arti-
facts near the edge of the main nuclei are incorrectly masked 
as MN. The final spot mask (eighth row) is a combination of 
the two spot masks and ensures that MN identified by either 
mask are correctly scored. 
Figure 2 shows images captured by the IS X that highlight 
the improvements in the optimized BNC and MN masks over 
the original masks. The optimized BNC mask more tightly 
highlights the main nuclei in comparison to the original BNC 
mask (Fig. 2A). Small and large MN residing close to the 
main nuclei that were previously enveloped by the original 
BNC mask are no longer enveloped by the optimized BNC 
mask and are now correctly scored by the optimized MN </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Cytometry Part A 89A: 653À662, 2016 </p>

<p>
Figure 1. (A) The various steps used to create the optimized BNC mask illustrating improvement over the default mask (third row) through 
sequential combination of the Levelset (fourth row), Watershed (fifth row) and Range functions. The final BNC mask (sixth row) as well as 
the new component masks to highlight individual main nuclei (seventh and eighth rows) are shown. (B) The steps used to create the opti-
mized MN mask. The spot identification function (second row) and dilated Levelset function (third row) are used to create the first spot 
mask (fourth row) while the spot identification function (fifth row) and the dilated morphology function (sixth row) are used to create the 
second spot mask (seventh row). Both spot masks are combined such that MN masked by either function are scored (eighth row). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Various cell images illustrating the improvement of the optimized BNC and MN masks over the original masks. (A) A BNC with 
zero MN. (B) A BNC with one MN that was enveloped by the original BNC mask. (C, D) BNCs with two and three MN, respectively, showing 
that the original BNC mask enveloped one of the MN. (E, F) BNCs with MN that were unmasked by the original MN mask now being cor-
rectly identified by the optimized MN mask. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p> 
Optimized Analysis of the CBMN Assay with Imaging FCM </p>

<p>mask (Figs. 2B-2D). In addition, smaller MN and MN that 
were previously missed by the limitations of the original MN 
mask are now correctly scored by the optimized MN mask 
(Figs. 2E and 2F). </p>

<p>Gating Strategy in <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> 
To filter, identify and score BNCs and MN, an opti-
mized analysis template using new features and image 
masks developed by Amnis V R was created in <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs>. To </p>

<p>Figure 3. (A) Bivariate plot of DRAQ5 Gradient RMS versus BF Gradient RMS for the selection of focused cells. (B) Bivariate plot of BF 
ASPECT RATIO versus BF AREA for elimination of small debris and multicellular aggregates. (C) Histogram of DRAQ5 INTENSITY used to 
eliminate events with insufficient nuclear stain. (D) Bivariate plot of DRAQ5 AREA versus BF CONTRAST for elimination of apoptotic cells. (E) 
A SPOT COUNT histogram following application of the BNC mask which separated cells containing two separate masked nuclear spots from 
all other events. (F) Bivariate plot of ASPECT RATIO INTENSITY components allowing for circularity comparison of the two main nuclei. (G) 
Bivariate plot of COMPONENT INTENSITY RATIO versus COMPONENT AREA RATIO allowing for selection of events which contained two 
main nuclei that were similar in both area and intensity. (H) Bivariate plot of ASPECT RATIO INTENSITY versus SHAPE RATIO that allowed 
for removal of events that contained two distinct but overlapping nuclei. (I) Bivariate plot of DRAQ5 SYMMETRY versus the ratio of BNC 
AREA to Levelset AREA for selection of cells with two well-separated, distinct nuclei. The tagged BNC and non-BNC populations are repre-
sented by the yellow squares/bins and blue squares/bins, respectively. Representative images captured by the IS X are shown in each panel. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Cytometry Part A 89A: 653À662, 2016 </p>

<p>
quantitate the gating process, separate populations contain-
ing 100 BNCs and 100 non-BNCs were selected at each dose 
point for one donor by manually highlighting (tagging) 
images from the original unfiltered population without vis-
ualizing the analysis area in <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs>. This ensured unbiased 
selection of images. BNCs and non-BNCs were tagged 
according to the traditional scoring criteria described by 
Fenech et al. (9). These events (BNCs, yellow; non-BNCs, 
blue) were then identified on each panel in Figure 3 such 
that they could be tracked sequentially through the tem-
plate. This allowed gate dimensions to be optimized such 
that no more than 10% of the BNC population was gated 
out in any plot and as many as possible non-BNC events 
were gated out. Details of the features, functions, masks and 
gating strategies used to optimize the data analysis template 
are summarized in Table 1. To automatically count the fre-
quency of MN within the final BNC population, the SPOT 
COUNT feature was applied to the newly developed MN 
mask and a histogram of MN frequency was generated </p>

<p>(Fig. 4), similar to the histograms generated in our previous 
work (17,18). Representative images are also shown to dem-
onstrate typical events found in each bin. </p>

<p>Dose Response Calibration Curves and Blinded 
Samples 
Six independent experiments with six different donors 
were carried out in a previous study to generate a dose 
response calibration curve (18). In the current study, the data 
files from that work were re-analyzed with the optimized 
<rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> template described above to demonstrate improve-
ment in detection and scoring of BNCs and MN. 
One-hundred BNC and one-hundred non-BNC events 
were tagged in data files across the 0-4 Gy dose range for one 
donor in order to illustrate the efficiency with which each gate 
filtered these populations by incorporating the BNC scoring cri-
teria described by Fenech et al. (9). Their distribution is dem-
onstrated in Figure 3 and Table 2 provides supporting statistics 
across the dose range for both the original and optimized gating </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary of all features used to develop the IDEAS 
V R analysis template described in Figure 3. The feature and purpose for its use 
as well as the gate boundaries used in each panel in Figure 3 are shown </p>

<p>FIGURE 
PANEL 
FEATURES </p>

<p>GATE BOUNDARIES 
(MIN/MAX) 
PURPOSE OF FEATURE </p>

<p>3A 
DRAQ5 GRADIENT RMS 
BF GRADIENT RMS </p>

<p>15/NA 
55/NA </p>

<p>Selects for single, non-apoptotic, DNA-positive cells </p>

<p>3B 
BF ASPECT RATIO </p>

<p>BF AREA </p>

<p>0.5/1 </p>

<p>85/650 </p>

<p>Eliminates coincident doublet events, retains the 
majority of BNCs 
Eliminates small debris and multicellular aggregates </p>

<p>3C 
DRAQ5 INTENSITY 
1 3 10 5 /NA 
Removes events with insufficient nuclear content to 
be a BNC </p>

<p>3D 
DRAQ5 AREA 
BF CONTRAST </p>

<p>10/300 
0/35 </p>

<p>Removes apoptotic events </p>

<p>3E 
SPOT COUNT 
1.5/2.5 
Removes all events that do not have two distinct 
nuclei </p>

<p>3F 
ASPECT RATIO INTENSITY COMPONENT 1 
ASPECT RATIO INTENSITY COMPONENT 2 </p>

<p>0.65/1 
0.65/1 </p>

<p>Compares the circularity of each of the main nuclei 
in each BNC against one another a </p>

<p>3G 
COMPONENT INTENSITY RATIO (BNC) 
COMPONENT AREA RATIO (BNC) </p>

<p>0.65/1 </p>

<p>0.5/1 </p>

<p>Selects for BNCs having two nuclei with similar 
DRAQ5 intensity a 
Selects for BNCs having two nuclei with similar area </p>

<p>3H 
ASPECT RATIO INTENSITY 
SHAPE RATIO </p>

<p>0.35/0.7 
0.2/0.7 </p>

<p>Selects for events that contain two distinct, non-
overlapping nuclei a </p>

<p>3I 
DRAQ5 SYMMETRY 
AREA BNC/AREA Levelset </p>

<p>0/15 </p>

<p>0.8/1 </p>

<p>Differentiates between objects that have two-fold 
versus three-fold axes of symmetry. Objects within 
the gate boundaries have only two DRAQ5 stained 
nuclei 
Removes events where a significant proportion of 
the nuclear image was eliminated following applica-
tion of the range mask to the Levelset mask </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Based on scoring criteria developed by Fenech et al. (9). </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p> 
Optimized Analysis of the CBMN Assay with Imaging FCM </p>

<p>and masking strategies. The optimized <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> analysis template 
demonstrates an improvement across the dose range in BNC 
detection accuracy, recovering 25% of the tagged BNCs elimi-
nated with the original template, and eliminating 83% of tagged 
non-BNCs retained with the original template. On average, 849 
BNCs were scored across the 0-4 Gy dose range for each donor 
at each data point (Table 2), a reduction of a factor of about 
three as compared to the 2647 BNCs identified by the original 
BNC mask on average across the dose range. This reduction 
demonstrates that the gating strategy more effectively filters 
unwanted events and that the optimized BNC mask is more 
selective of true BNCs within the final population. Further-
more, Table 2 demonstrates that the optimized MN mask iden-
tified more MN (an average of 99 MN across the dose range) 
than the original MN mask (an average of 87 MN across the 
dose range) despite the fact that fewer BNCs were identified, </p>

<p>illustrating an increase in sensitivity of the optimized MN 
mask. 
Figure 5A presents the rate of MN per BNC as a function 
of dose for all six donors, the average rate of MN per BNC at 
the 95% confidence intervals as determined in <rs id="software-27" type="software">Matlab</rs> (ver-
sion 7.11.0.584, <rs corresp="#software-27" type="creator">Mathworks</rs>, MA). A quadratic increase with 
dose up to 4 Gy is expected from biological considerations 
(3), historical work on the CBMN assay (4,5,23) and from our 
previous work with IS X -CBMN method (17-19) and was 
observed in this work. At 0 Gy, the average rate of MN per 
BNC at 0 Gy for all six donors was 0.022 which was within the 
0-0.040 range typical of background MN frequencies (24). 
Variability in the rate of MN per BNC with increasing dose, 
which was observed in our previous work (17-19), was once 
again observed here as the rate of MN per BNC varied 
between approximately 0.30-0.45 for all donors at 4 Gy. </p>

<p>Table 2. The percentage of 100 tagged BNCs and non-BNCs remaining following application of each gate in the optimized <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> V R analy-
sis template at each dose point for one donor. The percentage of events remaining in the final BNC population in the original analysis 
template is also shown (18). The numbers of BNCs and MN scored are also shown for one donor across the dose range from both the opti-
mized and original analysis templates </p>

<p>GATE </p>

<p>% BNCs REMAINING 
% NON-BNCs REMAINING </p>

<p>0 Gy 
1 Gy 
2 Gy 
3 Gy 
4 Gy 
AVG. 
0 Gy 
1 Gy 
2 Gy 
3 Gy 
4 Gy 
AVG. </p>

<p>BF &amp; DRAQ5 Focus 
86 
92 
96 
91 
89 
91 
27 
56 
64 
75 
80 
60 
Single cells 
86 
88 
96 
84 
89 
89 
24 
50 
30 
59 
64 
45 
DRAQ5 positive 
86 
88 
96 
84 
89 
89 
24 
49 
30 
59 
64 
45 
Non-apoptotic 
84 
88 
96 
81 
89 
88 
17 
34 
12 
30 
44 
27 
Two nuclear spots 
83 
84 
88 
81 
86 
84 
10 
0 
8 
6 
14 
8 
Round 
81 
83 
87 
80 
85 
83 
9 
0 
6 
6 
9 
6 
Similar intensity/area 
81 
83 
85 
78 
83 
82 
8 
0 
5 
4 
6 
5 
Elongated 
78 
79 
84 
76 
82 
80 
3 
0 
3 
3 
3 
2 
Symmetric nuclei 
(final BNC population) </p>

<p>78 
79 
82 
75 
80 
79 
0 
0 
3 
0 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Original template 
(final population) </p>

<p>76 
86 
79 
61 
59 
72 
14 
3 
1 
5 
6 
6 </p>

<p>BNCs SCORED 
MN SCORED </p>

<p>0 Gy 
1 Gy 
2 Gy 
3 Gy 
4 Gy 
AVG. 
0 Gy 
1 Gy 
2 Gy 
3 Gy 
4 Gy 
AVG. </p>

<p>Optimized template 
1,088 
1,016 
692 
721 
728 
849 
21 
49 
78 
147 
203 
99 
Original template 
2,169 
2,939 
2,497 
2,864 
2,766 
2,647 
20 
42 
70 
127 
174 
87 </p>

<p>Figure 4. Histogram of the SPOT COUNT applied to the MN mask using final BNC population from a sample irradiated with 2 Gy. Repre-
sentative images captured by the IS X are shown in each panel. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Cytometry Part A 89A: 653À662, 2016 </p>

<p>
However, the deviation from the average rate of MN per BNC 
was calculated to be only 15% on average for all donors across 
the dose range, compared to 26% in our previous work (18). 
The average rate of MN per BNC (Y) as a function of dose 
(D) was fitted to the following quadratic equation in <rs type="software">Matlab</rs>: </p>

<p>Y 5 0:0185 1 0:0237D 1 0:0106D 2 : 
(1) </p>

<p>Figure 5B shows the average calibration curve for the rate 
of MN per BNC from both Figure 5A and our previous work 
(18). Also plotted in Figure 5B are calibration curves from 
Schunck et al. (7), Willems et al. (25), De Sanctis et al. (26), and 
Thierens et al. (27). These curves were plotted using the quad-
ratic equations provided by the authors and demonstrate the 
variability between calibration curves using automated slide-
scoring based versions of the CBMN assay. In addition, Figure 
5B demonstrates that the rate of MN per BNC has increased by 
a factor of about six at the 4 Gy dose, illustrating the effective-
ness and accuracy of both the optimized BNC and MN masks. 
Figures 5C and 5D show graphical representations of the 
delivered dose (Gy) versus the estimated dose (Gy) (black </p>

<p>circles) for all nine blinded samples after collecting data on 
the IS X for 40 and 5 min, respectively. Also plotted are the 
dose estimations from our previous work (19) (black squares), 
the ideal line with a slope of 1 where the delivered dose and 
the estimated dose would be equal (dashed line) as well as the 
60.5 Gy lines (dotted lines). All dose estimations were deter-
mined using <rs id="software-10" type="software">CABAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-10" type="version-number">v2</rs> (Chromosome Aberration Calculation 
Software) (28) and the error bars represent the standard errors 
(SE) on the dose estimations. Figure 5C illustrates that after 
40 min of data collection, the newly optimized analysis tem-
plate was able to estimate blinded doses to within 0.5 Gy of 
the delivered dose in all but the 0.73 Gy sample (0.59 Gy 
higher than the delivered dose). The error bars associated 
with each data point are also within the 60.5 Gy lines in all 
but the 0.73 Gy sample. On average, 1,873 BNCs were scored 
for each sample after 40 minutes of data collection. 
Figure 5D illustrates that after only 5 min of data collec-
tion, optimized analysis template was able to correctly esti-
mate more blinded samples to within 0.5 Gy of the delivered 
dose than was possible with the original analysis template. 
Seven of the nine blinded samples were estimated correctly to </p>

<p>Figure 5. (A) The rate of MN per BNC versus dose for six donors (three male, three female). The average rate of MN per BNC at each dose 
point is also plotted, the error bars represent the standard error of the mean and the dashed lines represent the 95% confidence intervals. 
(B) The average rate of MN per BNC from A (squares) and the average rate of MN per BNC from our previous work in Rodrigues et al. (18) 
(circles) including error bars which represent the standard error of the mean. The rate of MN per BNC from Schunck et al. (7) (solid line), 
Willems et al. (25) (dashed line), De Sanctis et al. (26) (dashed-dotted line), and Thierens et al. (27) (dotted line) are also plotted using the 
equations provided in those publications. (C, D) Estimated dose (Gy) versus delivered dose (Gy) determined by the IS X -CBMN method for 
nine blinded samples using the optimized (circles) and original (squares) <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> V R analysis templates following 40 min (C) and 5 min (D) of 
data collection. The dashed line represents a slope of one, where the estimated dose would equal the delivered dose and the dotted lines 
represent 60.5 Gy from the ideal slope. The error bars represent the standard error on the estimated dose. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p> 
Optimized Analysis of the CBMN Assay with Imaging FCM </p>

<p>within 0.5 Gy as compared to only three of the nine samples 
with the original analysis template. On average, 280 BNCs 
were scored for each sample after only 5 minutes of data 
collection. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In several recent publications, we have introduced a 
newly developed method for performing the CBMN assay 
using imaging FCM as a dose estimation tool in radiation bio-
dosimetry (17-19). In the present study, we developed a new 
analysis strategy using mask functions recently implemented 
in <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs>, and evaluated the performance of this analysis 
compared to our previous approach. First, hand-tagged truth 
populations (BNC and non-BNC, MN, and non-MN events) 
were selected which allowed for the identification of features 
that were able to distinguish between these populations. 
Direct visualization of the locations of these populations (Fig. 
3) also allowed for ranges of all features to be optimized. Sec-
ond, we discovered that an analysis template optimized for a 
single data file was, in many cases, not ideal for all conditions. 
By merging data collected from multiple donors at multiple 
dose points, the most optimized analysis template for all data 
files was achieved. Finally, data collected from blinded samples 
was used to confirm the accuracy of the optimized analysis. 
These strategies enabled us to substantially increase the com-
parability of this assay to previous published results in the lit-
erature and improve accuracy when generating dose 
estimations compared to our previous work. 
Figure 3 shows the sequential application of bivariate 
plots and histograms in the analysis template and demon-
strates the effectiveness with which BNCs could be separated 
from cellular debris and other undesired objects in the data 
acquired by the IS X . While identification of focused, single 
cells can be attained from the BF images, the addition of a 
DRAQ5 nuclear stain also allows apoptotic cells to be gated 
out based on the hallmarks of apoptosis (chromatin conden-
sation, nuclear condensation, and increased blebbing) without 
the use of an additional viability dye (13). All DRAQ5 stained 
BNCs were shown to fall between 1 3 10 5 AU and 1 3 10 6 AU 
of intensity indicating that the main nuclei show a relatively 
uniform uptake of DRAQ5. This result may allow for 
improved data collection to be obtained through the applica-
tion of more stringent intensity classifiers on the IS X which 
would filter out more unwanted events during acquisition. 
Furthermore, the newly created BNC mask was able to better 
differentiate images with two DRAQ5 stained objects from 
those with zero, one or three or more DRAQ5 stained objects 
compared to the previous versions of the <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> template. 
Several of the new features developed in <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> that simulta-
neously compare the main nuclei to one another based on cir-
cularity, size, staining intensity and symmetry, allowed BNCs 
to be further differentiated from other undesired events. By 
implementing these cell-specific parameters in the <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> 
template, 99% of the tagged non-BNCs were correctly filtered 
from the final population on average across the dose range. In 
addition, 25% of the tagged BNCs eliminated with the origi-</p>

<p>nal template were recovered and 83% of the tagged non-BNCs 
retained with the original template were eliminated. 
Figure 5 demonstrates that the optimized <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> analysis 
template generates a dose response calibration curve that is of 
similar magnitude to those presented in the literature and that 
the dose estimations from blinded samples generated using 
this curve are more accurate. The rate of MN per BNC as a 
function of dose demonstrates some variability between 
donors. This variability in the CBMN assay has been well 
documented in the literature and Kacprzak et al. (29) showed 
that for five donors, the rate of MN per 1,000 BNC was rela-
tively consistent at 0 Gy but had an approximate range of 0.2-
0.6 at 5 Gy. While the variability between donors across the 
dose range has been reduced in this work to 15% compared to 
26% in our previous analysis template (18), the need for gen-
erating a calibration curve that is based on the rate of MN per 
BNC from multiple donors is demonstrated. In addition, the 
magnitude of the rate of MN per BNC in this work has 
increased by a factor of about four in comparison to our pre-
vious work, on average, across the dose range, illustrating the 
effectiveness of the optimized BNC and MN masks. In previ-
ous versions of the <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> analysis template, MN close to the 
main nuclei and smaller MN could not be scored due to the 
limitations in the available masking parameters, however the 
optimized MN mask is now able to correctly score these 
events which has led to the observed improvement. 
In order to determine if the improvement in BNC and 
MN identification corresponded to an increase in accuracy 
when generating dose estimations, data acquired from nine 
samples previously irradiated and blinded (19) were re-
analyzed. Figure 5C demonstrates that the optimized <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> 
analysis template was able to correctly estimate eight of the 
nine doses to within 0.5 Gy after 40 min of data collection, 
with only the 0.73 Gy sample falling outside the 60.5 Gy 
limits. Figure 5D illustrates the improved accuracy of the 
optimized analysis template and demonstrates that dose esti-
mations for seven of the nine doses were correct to within 
0.5 Gy after only 5 min of data collection. This is a signifi-
cant improvement over the original analysis template which 
was only able to correctly estimate three of the nine doses to 
within 0.5 Gy following 5 min of data collection. On average, 
280 BNCs were scored for each blinded sample after only 5 
min of data collection, but in some cases, &lt;200 BNCs were 
scored. McNamee et al. have previously recommended that 
200 BNCs be scored to provide reliable dose estimations 
(23). Furthermore, in a recent publication De Amicis et al. 
were able to successfully identify doses up to 4 Gy, within 0.5 
Gy of the delivered dose by scoring only 100 BNCs (30). The 
results of this work are consistent with the results of De Ami-
cis et al. and demonstrate that scoring approximately 100 
BNCs was sufficient to produce accurate dose estimations 
between 0 and 4 Gy. Overall, this demonstrates that the new 
<rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> analysis template is able to provide dose estimations 
with acceptable accuracy (within 60.5 Gy) after only 5 min 
of data collection and in some cases, after scoring only 100 
BNCs. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Cytometry Part A 89A: 653À662, 2016 </p>

<p>
This paper has introduced the application of new features 
and masks developed in the <rs type="software">IDEAS</rs> software designed specifi-
cally for improved detection of BNCs and MN in the IS X -
based version of the CBMN assay with applications in radia-
tion biodosimetry. Using these tools, an optimized data analy-
sis template was created which more effectively identified 
BNCs and quadrupled the frequency of scored MN across the 
0-4 Gy dose range. This new analysis method allowed for the 
generation of a dose response calibration curve that was simi-
lar in magnitude to those presented in the literature which 
were generated by automated slide scoring methods. Finally, 
dose estimations of blinded samples were correctly generated 
to within 0.5 Gy of the delivered dose following only 5 
minutes of data collection on the IS X , a marked improvement 
over our previous work. The improved analysis template, 
combined with the reduction in data collection time on the 
IS X , will allow for increased accuracy and throughput when 
performing biodosimetry to estimate unknown radiation 
doses received by exposed individuals following large-scale 
radiological or nuclear emergencies. </p>

<p>LITERATURE CITED </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p> 
Optimized Analysis of the CBMN Assay with Imaging FCM </p>

</text></tei>