<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5256325" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective To investigate the predictive value of enhanced-magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and fluoroscopic </p>

<p>factors regarding the effects of transforaminal epidural steroid injections (TFESIs) in low back pain (LBP) patients 
with lumbosacral radiating pain. 
Methods A total of 51 patients who had LBP with radiating pain were recruited between January 2011 and </p>

<p>December 2012. The patient data were classified into the two groups 'favorable group' and 'non-favorable group' 
after 2 weeks of follow-up results. The favorable group was defined as those with a 50%, or more, reduction of 
pain severity according to the visual analogue scale (VAS) for back or leg pain. The clinical and radiological data 
were collected for univariate and multivariate analyses to determine the predictors of the effectiveness of TFESIs 
between the two groups. 
Results According to the back or the leg favorable-VAS group, the univariate analysis revealed that the </p>

<p>corticosteroid approach for the enhanced nerve root, the proportion of the proximal flow, and the contrast 
dispersion of epidurography are respectively statistically significant relative to the other factors. Lastly, the 
multiple logistic regression analysis showed a significant association between the corticosteroid approach and the 
enhanced nerve root in the favorable VAS group. 
Conclusion Among the variables, MRI showed that the corticosteroid approach for the enhanced target root is the </p>

<p>most important prognostic factor in the predicting of the clinical parameters of the favorable TFESIs group. </p>

<p>Low back pain (LBP) is extremely common, whereby 
a lifetime prevalence as high as 80% has been recorded 
[1-3]. In some patients, the pain associated with an initial 
acute episode does not resolve and persists for more than 
3 months, leading to the development of chronic LBP [4]. 
Most chronic LBP patients do not respond to medication 
or physical therapy, with complaints of continuous LBP, 
and it is eventually the cause of muscle weakness in the 
low back area that is secondary to a lack of exercise. 
The use of lumbosacral transforaminal epidural steroid 
injections (TFESIs), which are an alternative diagnostic 
and therapeutic spinal intervention for LBP, radicular 
pain, and spinal stenosis, have increased over the past 
few years [5]. Even though a great amount of debate has 
occurred regarding the evidence of lumbosacral TFESIs, 
lumbosacral TFESIs are a helpful treatment for lumbosa-
cral radicular pain [3,6,7]. 
Most patients can benefit from lumbosacral TFESIs, but 
not all patients receive the benefits from such methods. 
Because a lot of factors contribute to the effectiveness 
of TFESIs, some researchers have studied the predictors 
of the effectiveness of TFESIs [8,9]. One study revealed 
clinical data such as an initially higher results for the vi-
sual analogue scale (VAS) and the McGill Pain Inventory, 
a lack of worsening pain during walking, and a positive 
femoral stretch test for the prediction of the pain reduc-
tion after TFESIs [8]. The other study showed low-grade 
nerve root compression with a prognostic value after the 
administration of TFESIs using magnetic resonance im-
aging (MRI) [9]. 
So far, only a few studies have used radiological param-
eters including MRI and clinical parameters to predict 
the effectiveness of TFESIs in terms of lumbosacral radi-
ating pain. Also, the radiological factors for the predicting 
of successful TFESI outcomes has not been well investi-
gated. To the best of the authors' knowledge, the relation-
ships between TFESIs and radiological factors, including 
contrast-enhanced MRI and fluoroscopic findings, have 
never been investigated. 
The aim of the present study is a determination of the 
favorable-outcome predictive value for radiological fac-
tors such as MRI or fluoroscopic variables in terms of 
lumbosacral radiating pain. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>This study is a retrospective study conducted from Jan-
uary 2011 to December 2012. A total of 67 patients who 
had been complaining of LBP with radiating pain are in-
cluded in this analysis. 
The patient-inclusion criteria were as follows: (1) those 
with a diagnosed herniated nucleus pulposus or spinal 
stenosis from a physical examination and imaging stud-
ies; (2) those who received spinal MRI with/without an 
enhancement; and (3) those who had been given first 
time TFESIs. The exclusion criteria were as follows: (1) 
patient's refusal of spinal MRI study; (2) patient who 
had not received TFESIs; (3) patient who had an allergic 
response to steroids or lidocaine; (4) follow-up loss; (5) 
patient who had been given physical therapy; (6) patient 
who had received a surgical operation; and (7) individu-
als with previous or current respiratory, cardiovascular, 
neurological, or psychological diseases. The study proto-
col was approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB 
No. BD2014-081), and all of the participants were pro-
vided the purpose of the study on the written informed 
consent. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The medical records of the patients who met the inclu-
sion and exclusion criteria were reviewed, and the clini-
cal and radiological parameters were subsequently set. </p>

<p>Radiological variables 
The authors assessed the radiological features includ-
ing MRI to arrange the level of the herniated nucleus 
pulposus (HNP), the type of HNP, the grade of the fo-
raminal stenosis, the location of the herniated interver-
tebral disc, the existence of the contrast-enhanced nerve 
root, and the block level of the nerve root. The 1.5T MRI 
was used, and it included sagittal and axial T1-and T2-
weighted gadolinium-enhanced images. The types of 
HNP were categorized as bulging, protrusion, extrusion, 
and sequestration [10]. There are four grades accord-
ing to Wildermuth's MRI grading system for the lumbar 
spine foraminal stenosis, as follows: (1) grade 0 (normal), 
normal dorsolateral border of the intervertebral disc and 
normal form at the foraminal epidural fat; (2) grade 1 
(slight foraminal stenosis), deformity of the epidural fat, </p>

<p>Predictive Parameters of TFESIs for Lumbosacral Radiating Pain </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>with the remaining fat still completely surrounding the 
exiting nerve; (3) grade 2 (marked foraminal stenosis), 
epidural fat only partially surrounding the nerve root; 
and (4) grade 3 (advanced foraminal stenosis), oblitera-
tion of the epidural fat [11-13]. An enhancement of a 
nerve root in the MRI was firstly evaluated by one of the 
authors, who was a physician trained in musculoskeletal 
pain and intervention, from an analysis of the pre-and 
post-contrast images stored at the same level settings. 
And then, the nerve root and the epidural enhancement 
were investigated by comparing the same nerve root of 
the pre-contrast images with the unaffected side or the </p>

<p>newly detected root or epidural enhancement in the post-
contrast images, which was differentiated from the oppo-
site nerve root of the same level (Figs. 1, 2). This is similar 
to the method of the previously described literature [14]. 
According to the patient's clinical presentation with the 
MRI studies, the authors decided the suitable injection 
level. When the patient had multilevel HNP, the authors 
determined the single target root level depending on 
the severity. According to the presence of the nerve root 
enhancement in the MRI, two groups were formed as fol-
lows: enhancement and non-enhancement. The authors 
injected an enhanced nerve root level in the enhance-</p>

<p>C 
A 
B </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The epidural enhancement of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans. (A) Sagittal T2-weighted images of 
L4/5 herniated disc, (B) L2/3 normal disc, and (C) L4/5 herniated disc with epidural enhancement (arrow) in axial T1-
weighted gadolinium-enhanced images. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Presence of the enhance-
ment of the nerve root (arrow) in 
a comparison between the mag-
netic resonance imaging (MRI) 
axial T2-weighted (A) and axial 
T1-weighted (B) gadolinium-en-
hanced images. </p>

<p>Yun Suk Jung, et al. </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>ment group. In the case of the non-enhancement group, 
the patients were given an injection according to the se-
verity of their symptoms and the imaging correlation. 
In addition to the MRI findings, the fluoroscopic find-
ings such as the contrast dispersion of the epidurography 
was defined in the previous study [15,16], the proportion 
of the proximal-flow pattern, the number of the flow level 
distribution, and the drug for the enhanced nerve root 
found in the MRI were also evaluated. The contrast dis-
tribution of the epidurographic findings were categorized 
into three distinct types, as defined by Pfirrmann et al. 
[16], as follows: intraepineural, extraepineural, and para-
neural patterns (Fig. 3). These three contrast patterns 
are as follows: (1) the intraepineural pattern appears to 
be a tubular outline of the nerve root or within the nerve 
root sheath, (2) the extraepineural pattern was defined 
as a contrast filling around the nerve root sheath that 
was like a tubular filling defect, and (3) the paraneural 
pattern is explained by a cloudlike appearance, which is 
located beneath the pedicle in the lateral neural foramen </p>

<p>and was not delineated by the contrast. The contrast flow 
patterns were evaluated among the groups according to 
whether the extent of the proximal was greater than 75%, 
75% to 25%, or less than 25%, based on the final needle-
tip position in the anterior-posterior fluoroscopic view; 
that is, the authors evaluated the fluoroscopic images for 
the spreading of the injectate to either the superior and/ 
or inferior level after the needle was placed. Before the 
corticosteroid was administered to the target, the con-
trast material was injected for the epidural flow pattern. 
In this article, a volume of 0.5 mL was first injected, and 
an additional 0.5 mL contrast was injected as a second 
injection for the checking of the number of the distrib-
uted levels. It was confirmed whether the reach of the 
injected contrast material is more proximal to the target 
nerve root under fluoroscopy when the patients had the 
enhanced nerve root lesion in the contrast-enhanced 
MRI. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Illustration of the three 
contrast-dispersion patterns in 
comparison with the fluorosco-
pic epidurography. (A) Type 1, 
intraepineural pattern; type 2, 
extraepineural pattern; and type 
3, paraneural pattern (modified 
from Pfirrmann et al. [16] with 
permission of the Radiological 
Society of North America). (B-D) 
Fluoroscopic-epidurography im-
ages are in sequence: (B) intraepi-
neural, (C) extraepineural, and 
(D) paraneural patterns. </p>

<p>Type 1 </p>

<p>Type 2 </p>

<p>Type 3 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Predictive Parameters of TFESIs for Lumbosacral Radiating Pain </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>Clinical variables 
The clinical parameters were as follows: (1) duration 
of LBP, (2) duration of radiating pain, (3) intensity of low 
back and radiating pains, and (4) presence of sensory and 
motor abnormalities. The VAS, a scale from 0 (no pain) 
to 10 (worst pain imaginable), was used to evaluate the 
pain at the time of the initial visit and again 2 weeks af-
ter the intervention according to the back and leg pains, 
respectively. Because of the minimal therapeutic effect 
of the TFESIs, the pain intensity was evaluated 2 weeks 
after the injection [16]. The collected patient data were 
classified into two groups according to the VAS change 
before and at 2 weeks after the intervention. According to 
the back-or leg-pain severity change from the VAS, the 
patients were divided into the 'favorable-VAS back or leg 
TFESIs group' and the 'non-favorable-VAS back or leg 
TFESIs group,' respectively. The favorable TFESIs group 
represents a VAS decline of at least 50% at 2 weeks after 
the intervention. </p>

<p>TFESIs technique 
All of the patients were given TFESIs using fluoroscopic 
guidance. The patient was positioned on a fluoroscopic 
table with a cushion under the lower abdomen in a C-
arm room. The level of interest was prepped in a sterile 
manner, and the C-arm was tilted obliquely and rotated 
into an arrangement to identify the target root. After a 
22-gauge, 3.5-in-length spinal needle was placed at the 
appropriate level, the needle was advanced toward the 
target nerve root. The needle position was confirmed us-
ing the axial and lateral fluoroscopic views. Before the 
corticosteroid injection, 0.5 mL of the contrast dye was 
injected initially, and the X-ray image was stored. After 
the 0.5 mL of contrast dye (a total dose of 1.0 mL) was 
administered, the image was stored consecutively to 
check for the epidural flow distribution. Lastly, all of the 
patients were given unilateral single level procedures and 
20 mg (40 mg/mL) of triamcinolone and 1.5 mL of 1% 
lidocaine with 1,500 IU of hyaluronidase H-lase for each 
treatment. And there were no acute complications after 
the TFESIs in this study. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Primary comparisons were performed between the 
favorable and non-favorable groups. The data were ex-
pressed as the mean±standard deviation or as percentag-</p>

<p>es. The categorical variables were compared using the χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>and the Fisher exact test. The continuous variables were 
compared using the two-tailed unpaired Student t-test 
for the variables with normal distributions, and the two-
tailed Mann-Whitney U test was used for the variables 
with non-normal distributions. The multivariate logistic 
regression analysis was then performed. The logistic re-
gression coefficients were used to assess the odds ratios 
for each independent variable. The entire statistical anal-
ysis was performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 19</rs> for Windows 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM SPSS Inc.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA). A p-value smaller 
than 0.05 indicates a statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Demographic characteristics, and clinical and radiological 
parameters </p>

<p>Of the total of 67 patients, 51 patients met the inclu-
sion criteria (the excluded patients comprise 7 follow-up 
loss, 4 incomplete-MRI study, and 5 repeated TFESIs). 
Of these patients, 19 were men and the other 32 were 
women. The subjects are all Korean people with a mean 
age of 53.10 years±16.54 years (range, 16-83 years). The 
mean durations of the back and leg pains are 15.09±52.18 
and 15.00±52.20, respectively. The numbers of patients 
with sensory and motor abnormalities were 38 (74.5%) 
and 48 (94.1%), respectively. All of the interventions were 
executed at the L4 level in 20 subjects (39.2%), the L5 
level in 25 subjects (49.0%), and the S1 level in 6 subjects 
(11.8%). The initial VAS score is 7.42±2.12, and the VAS 
score 2 weeks after the intervention is 3.13±2.51. 
In the radiological data, 23 patients had the unilevel 
HNP and the other 28 had the multilevel HNP. None of 
the patients had the L2-3 HNP, one (2.0%) had the L3-4, 
28 (54.9%) had the L4-5, and 22 (43.1%) had the L5-S1. 
Depending on the HNP severity, 7 patients (13.7%) had 
disc bulging, 16 (31.4%) had a disc protrusion, 21 (41.2%) 
had a disc extrusion, and 7 (13.7%) had sequestration. 
Most of the patients had grade 0 or 2 foraminal stenosis 
(41.2% and 31.4%, respectively). According to the loca-
tion of the HNP, most of the patients (49.0%) had a cen-
tral protrusion. The enhancement of a nerve root in the 
MRI was shown in 44 (86.3%) of the patients. During the 
TFESIs, the corticosteroid reached the enhanced nerve 
root in 35 (68.6%) cases. On the epidurographic contrast 
dispersion findings, 7 (13.7%) were intraepineural, 32 </p>

<p>Yun Suk Jung, et al. </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>Table 1. Univariate analysis of the possible predictive factors for the effectiveness of TFESIs </p>

<p>Variable 
Favorable group 
(n=36) </p>

<p>Non-favorable group 
(n=15) 
p-value </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
50.69±16.88 
58.87±14.61 
0.090 
Sex (%) 
0.360 
Men 
15 
4 
Women 
21 
11 
Clinical parameter 
Duration of back pain (mo) 
17.89±60.74 
7.30±6.38 
0.152 
Duration of leg pain (mo) 
17.78±60.77 
7.30±6.38 
0.111 
Sensory abnormality 
1.000 
Yes 
27 
11 
No 
9 
4 
Motor abnormality 
1.000 
Yes 
34 
14 
No 
2 
1 
VAS 
Before intervention 
7.69±2.14 
6.93±2.09 
0.299 
2 weeks after intervention 
2.01±1.71 
6.20±1.78 
0.000 
Radiological parameter 
MRI parameter 
HNP level 
0.372 
L3-4 
0 
1 
L4-5 
21 
7 
L5-S1 
15 
7 
HNP grade 
0.305 
Bulging 
4 
3 
Protrusion 
14 
2 
Extrusion 
13 
8 
Sequestration 
5 
2 
Foraminal stenosis grade 
0.563 
Grade 0 
17 
4 
Grade 1 
3 
2 
Grade 2 
10 
6 
Grade 3 
6 
3 
Location of HNP 
0.515 
Central 
17 
8 
Right/left central 
5 
0 
Subarticular 
8 
5 
Foraminal 
6 
2 
Extraforaminal 
0 
0 
Fluoroscopic parameter 
Block level 
1.000 
L4 
14 
6 
L5 
18 
7 
S1 
4 </p>

<p>
Predictive Parameters of TFESIs for Lumbosacral Radiating Pain </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>(62.7%) were extraepineural, and 12 (23.5%) were para-
neural. The proximal flow patterns from immediately 
after the injection of the corticosteroid were recorded in 
this study, depending on the proportion, and 31 (60.8%) 
cases approached a proximal of more than 75 %. The oth-
er 18 (35.3%) cases were between the proximals of 75% 
and 25 %, and the other three (3.9 %) cases were smaller 
than a proximal of 25%. The 0.5 mL volume of the con-
trast reached only the 1 level, while 19 (37.3 %) cases cov-
ered the 2 level when 1 mL of the contrast was infused. </p>

<p>Relationships between effective TFESIs and radiological 
factors </p>

<p>A significant correlation was observed between several 
of the predictive parameters and the favorable TFESIs. 
The results of the univariate analysis are listed in Table 1. 
By using the univariate analysis, the injected material ap-
proach for the enhancement of the nerve root, the distri-
bution of the contrast pattern, and the proportion of the 
proximal flow pattern are significantly associated with 
the favorable VAS group. Otherwise, the clinical factors 
such as age, sex, duration of LBP, duration of radiating </p>

<p>pain, and the presence of a neurological deficit, and the 
radiological factors such as the degrees of the HNP and 
the foraminal stenosis, the type of herniated interverte-
bral disc, the block level, and the number of flow levels 
did not show significant differences. 
Multiple logistic regression models were used to con-
trol for the confounding variables that were significant 
from the univariate analysis, and the results are sum-
marized in Table 2. Due to a multicollinearity among the </p>

<p>Table 1. Continued </p>

<p>Variable 
Favorable group 
(n=36) </p>

<p>Non-favorable group 
(n=15) 
p-value </p>

<p>Presence of enhancement 
1.000 
Yes 
31 
13 
No 
5 
2 
Approach of drug to enhanced root 
0.001** 
Yes 
30 
5 
No 
6 
10 
Contrast dispersion of epidurography 
0.014* 
Intraepineural 
3 
4 
Extraepineural 
27 
5 
Paraneural 
6 
6 
Proportion of proximal flow pattern (%) 
0.011* 
&gt;75 
26 
5 
25-75 
10 
8 
&lt;25 
0 
2 
Flow level 1.0 mL 
0.455 
1 level 
12 
7 
2 level 
11 
3 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation or number or %. 
TFESI, transforaminal epidural steroid injection; MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; HNP, herniated nucleus pulpo-
sus. 
*p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01. </p>

<p>Table 2. Multivariate analysis of the possible predictive 
factors for the effectiveness of TFESIs in back VAS group 
Variable 
Exp (B) 
95% CI 
p-value 
Approach of drug 
to enhanced root </p>

<p>8.403 
1.916-36.850 0.005** </p>

<p>Epidurography 
Intraepineural 
-
-
0.109 
Extraepineural 
1.018 
0.118-8.762 
0.987 
Paraneural 
4.839 
0.919-25.477 0.063 </p>

<p>TFESI, transforaminal epidural steroid injection; VAS, vi-
sual analogue scale; CI, confidence interval. 
**p&lt;0.01. </p>

<p>Yun Suk Jung, et al. </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>independent variables, the proportion of the proximal 
flow pattern was excluded from the multiple logistic re-
gression analysis. The corticosteroid approach for the 
enhanced nerve root was the only significant outcome 
prognostic factor that was associated with the favorable 
TFESIs group (odds ratio, 8.403; 95% confidence interval, 
1.916-36.850; p=0.005). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This retrospective study was designed to elucidate the 
meaningful clinical and radiological parameters of suc-
cessful TFESIs in lumbosacral radicular pain patients. 
The univariate analysis results demonstrated three sig-
nificant different variables, including the corticosteroid 
approach for the enhanced nerve root, the contrast 
dispersion pattern, and the pattern of the proximal flow 
between the favorable VAS group and the non-favorable 
VAS group after the intervention. After the multiple logis-
tic regression analysis was conducted, this study revealed 
that the corticosteroid approach for the enhanced nerve 
root found in MRI is the most important prognostic factor 
of TFESIs; that is, the nearer that the administered cor-
ticosteroid is to the target nerve root, the more effective 
the pain reduction will be. 
The contrast-enhanced spine MRI can display the in-
flammatory nerve pathology, and it is a useful method 
for diagnosing the herniated nucleus pulposus associ-
ated with radiculitis and the pain related to neural in-
flammation [17-19]; that is, the nerve root enhancement 
on the contrast spine MRI suggests neurological deficits 
because it is related to granulation-tissue accumulation, 
endoneurial capillary interruption, and inflammatory 
cytokines [20-22]. So, the nature of the TFESIs, which is 
a procedure for the distribution of a corticosteroid to the 
area of the target nerve root, enables the formulation of 
an explanation regarding the reduced radiating pain of 
the patients [23]. Also, for the effective TFESIs, an iden-
tification of the precise target nerve with the use of the 
contrast material and the injecting of the corticosteroid 
into the superior portion could be helpful [16]. This find-
ing is in accordance with the univariate analysis results of 
this study, but the enhanced spine MRI was also reviewed 
to find the precise target nerve root that was causing the 
radicular pain. The findings of Tak et al. [24] resemble 
the results of this study, in that they found improvements </p>

<p>of the NRS and the ODI in the nerve root enhancement 
groups from the contrast-enhanced MRI; however, they 
did not evaluate the effectiveness at the L5-S1 HNP level 
and other factors such as the clinical or the radiological 
factors that are included in this study. 
In the favorable VAS TFESIs group, the extraepineural 
dispersion was observed in 32 (62.7%) patients in this 
study. The association between the contrast distributed 
pattern and a clinical improvement after TFESIs is the 
focus of a number of studies [15,16,25], and one study 
showed results that are similar to those of this study. Lee 
et al. [25] revealed that the extraepineural injection may 
be a factor in the achievement of improved results for 
the radicular symptom after TFESIs. They hypothesized 
that an extraepineural injection was a more successful 
outcome because the corticosteroid was delivered adja-
cent to the inflammatory epineurium of the nerve root. 
In contrast, Paidin et al. [15] revealed that the intraepi-
neural and paraneural patterns were beneficial for the 
relieving of pain. Also, Pfirrmann et al. [16] reported no 
significant differences according to the contrast pattern, 
but they suggested that the intraepineural type would 
be a more effective response compared with the oth-
ers. But, the intraepineural pattern should be avoided 
because it may cause more pain to the patients during 
the intervention [26]. Although they anticipated that the 
paraneural and extraepineural patterns would produce 
a similar result if the drug enters into the epidural space, 
the extraepineural pattern did not show a significant pain 
reduction. The results of these two studies are in contrast 
to the results of the present study, as this study revealed 
that the extraepineural pattern was significantly differ-
ent from the others. Although both the extraepineural 
and paraneural patterns enable the entrance of the drug 
into the epidural space, the extraepineural pattern more 
precisely encircles the sheath of the target nerve root ac-
cording to the classification of Pfirrmann et al. [16]. It is 
therefore possible to infer that the extraepineural pattern 
is more effective than the paraneural pattern because the 
injected material can be more adjacent to the nerve in 
accordance with the overall results of the present study. 
In this study, the authors not only evaluated the contrast 
dispersion pattern, but other prognostic factors such as 
the proximal flow pattern under fluoroscopy and specific 
inflamed neural structures under an enhanced MRI were 
also examined. </p>

<p>Predictive Parameters of TFESIs for Lumbosacral Radiating Pain </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>In general, radicular pains are the result of an inflam-
matory response within the proximal area of a nerve root 
[27]. In this study, the proportion of the proximal flow af-
ter the injection was another predictive value of success-
ful TFESIs; that is, the more available the administered 
corticosteroid is regarding the proximal reach, the more 
effective the outcome will be. For the sake of a proximal 
injection, it would be more favorable to position the 
needle more adjacent to the target nerve, to administer a 
sufficient volume, and to apply force during the injection 
of the drug materials. 
In lumbar spine foraminal stenosis patients, TFESIs are 
not always beneficial because the administered mate-
rial cannot reach the target nerve due to perineural and 
epineural adhesions; therefore, the degree of the spine 
foraminal stenosis was considered for the investigation of 
this study. According to this study's results, a significant 
difference of the therapeutic effect owing to the degree of 
the spine foraminal stenosis was not found. The results 
of the present study correspond well with those of the 
earlier research regarding scoliosis patients [28]. In [28], 
the degree of the lateral canal stenosis in the MRI did not 
correlate with the initial TFESI-induced pain relief of the 
patients with the degenerative lumbar scoliosis stenosis. 
Likewise, a number of articles discuss the effectiveness of 
TFESIs in patients with spinal stenosis [29-32]; according 
to these articles, there is a dearth of evidence regarding 
the effectiveness of TFESIs for the radicular pain that is 
caused by the spinal stenosis. In addition, in a previous 
study, the severity of the spinal stenosis is not significant-
ly different for the patients with the improvement com-
pared with the patients without the improvement [33]. 
The findings of the present study are distinguished from 
those of other research in that the meaningful prognostic 
factors are different. Choi et al. [9] evaluated the prog-
nostic parameters of TFESIs according to the location of 
the HNP and the degree of the nerve root compression. 
They concluded that the centrally or extraforaminally 
herniated discs and the low-grade nerve root compres-
sion were different between the responder and non-
responder groups. Another study investigated the clinical 
and radiological factors like the present research [8]. In 
their study, only the presence of the HNP, central steno-
sis, foraminal stenosis and spondylolisthesis was checked 
for in the radiological findings; among these, there were 
no significant predictive factors. Instead, they found </p>

<p>meaningful clinical predictive factors including higher 
baseline scores for tools such as the VAS and the McGill 
Pain Inventory, a positive femoral stretch test, and a re-
duction of the worsening of the pain during walking. By 
inferring from an incorporation of the previous findings 
with those of the present study, the best way to achieve 
favorable TFESIs could be a precise administration of a 
corticosteroid to the target nerve root that is found in an 
enhanced spine MRI. 
The limitations of the present study are as follows. First, 
this study was a retrospective research undertaking, and 
therefore, a selection bias may exist. Second, the small 
sample size is another limitation, and a larger sample 
size may clarify significant prognostic factors; therefore, 
future research is required to confirm the results of this 
study. Third, a relatively short-term follow-up period was 
the other limitation of this study. The follow-up period of 
the 2 weeks after the intervention was selected to achieve 
a corticosteroid effect according to the previously de-
scribed articles [16,34]. The follow-up was so brief that 
the mid-or long-term therapeutic effects could not be 
evaluated sufficiently. 
To the authors' knowledge, this is the first research 
study wherein a simultaneous investigation of enhanced-
MRI and fluoroscopic parameters, including the lumbar 
foraminal stenosis according to the degree shown in MRI, 
has been conducted for the prediction of the effective-
ness of TFESIs. 
In summary, the results of this study could provide 
practitioners with useful pain-management information. 
When TFESIs are administered, the patients with lum-
bosacral radiating pain will experience a more-favorable 
outcome if the corticosteroid is injected more proximally, 
if the corticosteroid reaches the targeted enhanced nerve 
root, and if the extraepineural pattern is distributed. 
Above all, the corticosteroid approach regarding the tar-
get enhanced nerve shown in MRI is the most predictive 
of a favorable post-TFESI outcome. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>

<p>Yun Suk Jung, et al. </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank the Medical Research Collaborating 
Center at Seoul National University Bundang Hospital for 
statistical analyses. </p>



<p>Predictive Parameters of TFESIs for Lumbosacral Radiating Pain </p>





</text></tei>