<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5299485" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Aims: Since 2005, several glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonists (GLP-1 RAs) have been </p>

<p>approved to treat people with type 2 diabetes. These agents are considered for use at the same </p>

<p>point in the treatment paradigm as basal insulins. A comprehensive comparison of these drug </p>

<p>classes, therefore, can help inform treatment decisions. This systematic review and meta-</p>

<p>analysis assessed the clinical efficacy and safety of GLP-1 RAs compared with basal insulins. </p>

<p>Materials and methods: MEDLINE, EMBASE, CENTRAL and PubMed databases were searched. </p>

<p>Randomized clinical trials (RCTs) of ≥16 weeks' duration comparing GLP-1 RAs vs basal insulins </p>

<p>in adults with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled with oral antihyperglycemic drugs were </p>

<p>included. Data on the change from baseline to 26 weeks (AE10 weeks) of treatment in hemoglo-</p>

<p>bin A1c (HbA1c) and weight, as well as the proportion of patients experiencing hypoglycaemia, </p>

<p>were extracted. Fixed-effect pairwise meta-analyses were conducted where data were availa-</p>

<p>ble from ≥2 studies. </p>

<p>Results: Fifteen RCTs were identified and 11 were meta-analysed. The once-weekly GLP-1 </p>

<p>RAs, exenatide long acting release (LAR) and dulaglutide, led to greater, statistically significant </p>

<p>mean HbA1c reductions vs basal insulins (exenatide: −0.31% [95% confidence interval −0.42, </p>

<p>−0.19], dulaglutide: −0.39% [−0.49, −0.29]) whilst once-daily liraglutide and twice-daily exena-</p>

<p>tide did not (liraglutide: 0.06% [−0.06, 0.18], exenatide: 0.01% [−0.11, 0.13]). Mean weight </p>

<p>reduction was seen with all GLP-1 RAs while mean weight gain was seen with basal insulins. </p>

<p>Interpretation of the analysis of hypoglycaemia was limited by inconsistent definitions and </p>

<p>reporting. Because of the limited number of available studies sensitivity analyses to explore </p>

<p>heterogeneity could not be conducted. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Although weight reduction is seen with all GLP-1 RA's, only the once-weekly </p>

<p>agents, exenatide LAR and dulaglutide, demonstrate significant HbA1c reductions when com-</p>

<p>pared to basal insulins. </p>

<p>K E Y W O R D S </p>

<p>basal insulin, GLP-1 RAs, glycaemic control, meta-analysis, systematic review, type 2 diabetes </p>

<p>The clinical effectiveness and safety of GLP-1 RAs compared to </p>

<p>each other and to oral antihyperglycemic drugs (OAD) have been </p>

<p>assessed in several meta-analyses. 
9-11 However, the positioning of </p>

<p>GLP-1 RAs within the treatment paradigm is at the point when the </p>

<p>use of basal insulin might also be considered; therefore, there is an </p>

<p>increasing desire to understand the similarities and differences </p>

<p>between GLP-1 RAs and basal insulins. Although such comparisons </p>

<p>have been published, 
11-16 they all have limitations to consider. Wang </p>

<p>et al. 
15 do not include the two new agents (dulaglutide and albiglu-</p>

<p>tide) and, although Karagiannis et al. 
10 do include the new treat-</p>

<p>ments, their analysis is limited to only once-weekly GLP-1 RAs. Liu </p>

<p>et al. 
13 on the other hand, pooled all GLP-1 RAs together when com-</p>

<p>paring to insulin glargine. Such pooling assumes, a priori, that all GLP-</p>

<p>1 RAs are similar in efficacy and pharmacodynamic profile, which is </p>

<p>not the case as demonstrated in head-to-head studies. 
17,18 More </p>

<p>recently, Zaccardi et al. 
16 conducted an analysis where GLP-1 RAs </p>

<p>were considered independently, but basal insulins were pooled, again </p>

<p>making an a priori assumption that all basal insulins have the same </p>

<p>efficacy and pharmaocodynamic profile. Pooling also discounts the </p>

<p>heterogeneity between GLP-1 RA trials regarding background ther-</p>

<p>apy and drug dosage; as such, it is imperative that heterogeneity </p>

<p>using appropriate measures is assessed prior to combining treatments </p>

<p>for analytical purposes. To this end, to evaluate the clinical efficacy of </p>

<p>GLP-1 RAs, by type, vs basal insulins, we conducted a systematic </p>

<p>review of the literature and a series of paired meta-analyses to assess </p>

<p>the differences in glycaemic control, weight change and the risk of </p>

<p>hypoglycaemia in adults with type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>2 | MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>2.1 | Data sources and searches </p>

<p>MEDLINE (including Epub ahead of print and In-process citations), </p>

<p>EMBASE and the Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials </p>

<p>(CENTRAL) databases were searched from database inception to </p>

<p>September 9, 2016. The searches were limited to peer-reviewed </p>

<p>studies in the English language. Separate search strategies were </p>

<p>designed for each database (MEDLINE strategy is included in Appen-</p>

<p>dix S1, Supporting Information). Each search strategy included free-</p>

<p>text, MeSH and EMTREE terms, where appropriate, for type 2 diabe-</p>

<p>tes and GLP-1 RAs, and a randomized controlled trial (RCT) study </p>

<p>design filter in MEDLINE and EMBASE. </p>

<p>2.2 | Study selection </p>

<p>Included RCTs were selected based on predefined eligibility criteria </p>

<p>using the population, intervention, comparators, outcomes and study </p>

<p>design (PICOS) framework. Eligibility criteria included: (1) adults with </p>

<p>type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled by OADs; (2) treatment of </p>

<p>the majority of subjects with US approved dosages of GLP-1 RA (exe-</p>

<p>natide 10 μg twice daily, liraglutide 1.2 or 1.8 mg once daily, exena-</p>

<p>tide 2 mg once weekly (long acting release [LAR]), lixisenatide 20 μg </p>

<p>once daily, albiglutide 30 or 50 mg once weekly, and dulaglutide 0.75 </p>

<p>or 1.5 mg once weekly plus at least one OAD; (3) comparator arm of </p>

<p>basal insulin (ie, insulin detemir, insulin glargine, insulin degludec, neu-</p>

<p>tral protamine hagedorn [NPH] insulin) plus at least one OAD; and </p>

<p>(4) RCT duration of at least 16 weeks. Trials performed in treatment-</p>

<p>naïve patients with type 2 diabetes, or samples that recruited only </p>

<p>patients with comorbidities including renal failure or cardiovascular </p>

<p>comorbidities, were excluded. Two reviewers independently deter-</p>

<p>mined whether the RCTs met eligibility criteria. Each reviewer first </p>

<p>reviewed the titles and abstracts; full-text articles were reviewed </p>

<p>where eligibility could not be determined from the title and abstract </p>

<p>review alone. Discrepancies between reviewers were resolved by </p>

<p>consensus, or adjudicated by a third reviewer. </p>

<p>2.3 | Data extraction and quality assessment </p>

<p>Data extraction was performed by a single experienced data extractor </p>

<p>into a customized spreadsheet; key fields were validated by a second </p>

<p>extractor. Discrepancies were resolved as described previously for </p>

<p>study selection. The extraction form was designed to collect data </p>

<p>reporting study design features, baseline patient demographics and </p>

<p>clinical characteristics, treatment arm details, efficacy (glycated hemo-</p>

<p>globin [HbA1c], weight) and safety outcomes (hypoglycemia, gastroin-</p>

<p>testinal adverse events). </p>

<p>Endpoints at week 26 (AE10 weeks) were extracted and reported. </p>

<p>If data at week 26 were unavailable, the data closest to week </p>

<p>26 between weeks 16 and 36 were included. For trials that presented </p>

<p>endpoints in graph format only, values were derived by digitizing the </p>

<p>graph, using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">WebPlotDigitizer</rs> program available online (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://arohatgi.info/WebPlotDigitizer/app/</rs>/). This was necessary for </p>

<p>4 studies. 
19-22 A risk assessment of bias was performed for each </p>

<p>included RCT using the Cochrane Collaboration's tool. 
23 Two </p>

<p>reviewers independently assessed the quality of each included RCT. </p>

<p>2.4 | Data synthesis and statistical analysis </p>

<p>Mean values and associated measures of variability (variance, stand-</p>

<p>ard deviation [SD], standard error [SE] or confidence interval [CI]) for </p>

<p>continuous endpoints, and counts and proportions for categorical </p>

<p>endpoints were extracted. For the purposes of the meta-analyses, if </p>

<p>SINGH ET AL. </p>

<p>
SD was not reported, it was imputed from other available information </p>

<p>(eg, SE or 95% CI), using the prognostic method described by Ma </p>

<p>et al. 
24 Where sample sizes for HbA1c and weight outcomes were </p>

<p>not reported, the intention-to-treat (ITT) population was assumed. </p>

<p>Where sample sizes for hypoglycaemia endpoints were not reported, </p>

<p>if available, the safety population was assumed; otherwise the ITT </p>

<p>population was assumed. </p>

<p>The meta-analyses were conducted using the "meta" statistical </p>

<p>package in R version 3.1.3. 
25 To understand the difference between </p>

<p>GLP-1 RAs and basal insulins by drug, fixed-effect pairwise meta-</p>

<p>analyses using the frequentist approach were conducted for the </p>

<p>changes in HbA1c and weight, and the occurrence of hypoglycaemia </p>

<p>outcomes. Random effects analysis were considered where apprecia-</p>

<p>ble statistical heterogeneity was observed. However, when a small </p>

<p>number of studies are available for analysis, as was the case for this </p>

<p>analysis, random effects analysis shows poor precision of between-</p>

<p>study variance, and are therefore not appropriate. 
26 In keeping with </p>

<p>the Cochrane handbook, meta-analyses were conducted where data </p>

<p>were available for at least 2 separate trials with the same treat-</p>

<p>ments. 
27 If data for a treatment were identified in only 1 trial, meta-</p>

<p>analysis was not conducted; however, the trial results are shown. </p>

<p>"Hypoglycaemia" outcomes included all attributions of hypoglycaemia </p>

<p>in a publication (irrespective of blood glucose value), including severe </p>

<p>hypoglycaemia. The "severe hypoglycaemia" category included publi-</p>

<p>cation attribution as severe or major hypoglycaemia or definition of </p>

<p>"requiring third-party assistance." However, meta-analysis for severe </p>

<p>hypoglycaemia could not be conducted because of low event rates; </p>

<p>as such, only the proportion of patients experiencing severe hypogly-</p>

<p>caemia events in GLP-1 RA groups vs basal insulins were extracted </p>

<p>and presented. To calculate the weight contribution by individual </p>

<p>trials to the overall effect estimate, the inverse variance method for </p>

<p>continuous outcomes and the Mantel-Haenszel for categorical out-</p>

<p>comes were used. </p>

<p>Statistical tests of heterogeneity were conducted to understand </p>

<p>the extent to which the results of trials included in the meta-analysis </p>

<p>were consistent. The main measure of heterogeneity used for evalua-</p>

<p>tion was I 
2 value. 
27 Sub-group sensitivity analysis was conducted by </p>

<p>excluding one study to understand the impact of non-standard dosing </p>

<p>used in a minority (37.9%) of patients. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Each model was coded, analysed and summarized using forest </p>

<p>plots. The forest plots summarize effect estimates from all included </p>

<p>trials to provide a comprehensive view of available evidence, as well </p>

<p>as a pooled effect size from meta-analysis. For change in HbA1c and </p>

<p>weight, a mean difference &lt;0 signifies the result favouring the GLP-1 </p>

<p>RA arm compared to the basal insulin arm, ie, a greater reduction in </p>

<p>HbA1c or weight compared to basal insulin. For hypoglycaemia, an </p>

<p>odds ratio &lt;1 indicates lower odds in the GLP-1 RA arm compared to </p>

<p>basal insulin. Where meta-analyses were conducted (ie, 2 or more </p>

<p>trials were available for a treatment and comparator), I 
2 value was </p>

<p>also reported. Codes designed for meta-analyses and their outputs </p>

<p>were validated by a second analyst. </p>

<p>3 | RESULTS </p>

<p>The Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-</p>

<p>Analyses (PRISMA) flow diagram documenting the RCT selection </p>

<p>process is provided in Figure 1. A total of 2694 articles were identi-</p>

<p>fied, of which 19 articles describing 15 RCTs were eligible for inclu-</p>

<p>sion in the systematic literature review. Key study and baseline </p>

<p>characteristics, including background therapy, are presented in </p>

<p>Table 1. The eligible RCTs included comparisons of exenatide 10 μg </p>

<p>INCLUDED </p>

<p>SCREENING </p>

<p>IDENTIFICATION </p>

<p>ELIGIBILITY </p>

<p>Database inception -October 2015 
2,255 records identified by database searching: </p>

<p>• MEDLINE (inc. In-process) (n=792) 
• EMBASE (n=887) 
• Cochrane (n=567) 
• PubMed (Epub ahead of print) (n=9) </p>

<p>1,378 records after duplicates removed </p>

<p>62 full-text articles assessed for eligibility </p>

<p>19 articles included in systematic literature 
review (describing 15 RCTs) </p>

<p>1,817 records screened for eligibility 
1,755 records excluded </p>

<p>43 full-text articles excluded due to: 
Inappropriate study design (n=27) 
Inappropriate intervention (n=6) 
Inappropriate outcome (n=4) 
Not English language (n=2) 
Duplicates (n=4) </p>

<p>01 January 2015 -September 2016 
776 records identified by database 
searching: </p>

<p>• MEDLINE (inc. Epub ahead of </p>

<p>print and In-process) (n=314) </p>

<p>• EMBASE (n=250) </p>

<p>Cochrane (n=212) </p>

<p>439 records after duplicates removed </p>

<p>11 RCTs included in the meta-analyses </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 Study PRISMA diagram. 
Abbreviations: RCT, randomized clinical 
trial. </p>

<p> 
SINGH ET AL. </p>

<p>TABLE 1 Study population baseline characteristics, background therapies, and presence of key three endpoints </p>

<p>Trial name and author </p>

<p>Study 
duration 
(weeks) </p>

<p>Intervention 
Mean age (SD), 
years </p>

<p>Female, </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>White, </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>Mean disease 
duration (SD), 
years </p>

<p>Mean 
HbA1c 
(SD), % </p>

<p>Mean HbA1c 
(mmol/mol) </p>

<p>Mean 
bodyweight </p>

<p>(SD), kg </p>

<p>Mean BMI 
(SD), kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Background therapy, % </p>

<p>Exenatide 10 
μg twice daily vs insulin glargine </p>

<p>Bunck 2009 </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>Exenatide </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>58.4 (−) </p>

<p>36.1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>5.7 (−) </p>

<p>7.6 (−) </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>90.6 (−) </p>

<p>30.9 (−) </p>

<p>MET (100%) </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>58.3 (−) </p>

<p>33.3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>4.0 (−) </p>

<p>7.4 (−) </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>92.4 (−) </p>

<p>30.1 (−) </p>

<p>HEELA (Davies 2009) </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>Exenatide </p>

<p>56.8 (10.2) </p>

<p>29.7 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>9.0 (4.6) </p>

<p>8.7 (0.7) </p>

<p>72 </p>

<p>101.4 (19.8) </p>

<p>34.6 (5.7) </p>

<p>Double/triple therapy </p>

<p>MET 
AE SU 
AE TZD </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>56.2 (7.9) </p>

<p>33.6 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>8.4 (4.4) </p>

<p>8.5 (0.7) </p>

<p>69 </p>

<p>97.6 (16.4) </p>

<p>33.7 (4.9) </p>

<p>Heine 2005 </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>Exenatide </p>

<p>59.8 (8.8) </p>

<p>45.0 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>9.9 (6.0) </p>

<p>8.2 (1.0) </p>

<p>66 </p>

<p>87.5 (16.9) </p>

<p>31.4 (4.4) 
MET + SU (100%) </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>58.0 (9.5) </p>

<p>43.4 </p>

<p>81 </p>

<p>9.2 (5.7) </p>

<p>8.3 (1.0) </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>88.3 (17.9) </p>

<p>31.3 (4.6) </p>

<p>Gurkan 2014 </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>Exenatide </p>

<p>52.2 (7.3) </p>

<p>70.0 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>6.9 (3.3) </p>

<p>8.0 (0.8) </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>94.3 (11.8) </p>

<p>35.9 (3.7) </p>

<p>MET (100%) </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>53.1 (7.0) </p>

<p>58.8 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>7.6 (4.3) </p>

<p>8.1 (0.8) </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>90.5 (14.3) </p>

<p>33.2 (4.5) </p>

<p>Barnett 2007 </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>Exenatide </p>

<p>54.5 (−) </p>

<p>51.5 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>6.6 (−) </p>

<p>8.9 (−) </p>

<p>74 </p>

<p>85.6 (−) </p>

<p>31.3 (−) 
MET (55%-56%) or 
SU (44%-46%) </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>55.3 (−) </p>

<p>54.3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>8.3 (−) </p>

<p>9.0 (−) </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>84.0 (−) </p>

<p>30.9 (−) </p>

<p>Exenatide 2 mg once weekly vs insulin glargine 
DURATION-3 
(Diamant 2010, 2014) </p>

<p>156 </p>

<p>Exenatide </p>

<p>58.0 (10.0) </p>

<p>48.0 </p>

<p>82 </p>

<p>8.0 (6.0) </p>

<p>8.3 (1.1) </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>91.2 (18.6) </p>

<p>32.3 (5.4) </p>

<p>MET (70%) </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>58.0 (9.0) </p>

<p>45.0 </p>

<p>85 </p>

<p>7.8 (6.0) </p>

<p>8.3 (1.0) </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>90.6 (16.4) </p>

<p>32.3 (4.8) </p>

<p>Inagaki 2012 </p>

<p>62 </p>

<p>Exenatide </p>

<p>57.1 (10.4) </p>

<p>34.0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>8.9 (6.1) </p>

<p>8.5 (0.8) </p>

<p>69 </p>

<p>70.0 (13.3) </p>

<p>26.1 (4.03) 
MET (67%), BG + TZD (33%) </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>56.4 (11.2) </p>

<p>30.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>9.2 (6.0) </p>

<p>8.5 (0.8) </p>

<p>69 </p>

<p>71.0 (13.9) </p>

<p>26.2 (3.8) </p>

<p>Exenatide 2 mg once weekly vs insulin detemir 
Davies 2013 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Exenatide </p>

<p>59.0 (10.0) </p>

<p>36.0 </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>8.0 (6.0) </p>

<p>8.4 (0.9) </p>

<p>68 </p>

<p>96.7 (17.0) </p>

<p>33.7 (4.7) 
MET (100%) + SU (70%-72%) </p>

<p>Detemir </p>

<p>58.0 (10.0) </p>

<p>31.0 </p>

<p>97 </p>

<p>7.0 (5.0) </p>

<p>8.4 (0.9) </p>

<p>68 </p>

<p>97.9 (15.8) </p>

<p>33.7 (4.7) </p>

<p>Liraglutide 1.8 mg once daily vs insulin glargine 
EAGLE (D'Alessio 2015) </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Liraglutide </p>

<p>57.4 (8.9) </p>

<p>44.0 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>9.1 (1.1) </p>

<p>76 </p>

<p>90.1 (16.7) </p>

<p>31.8 (4.1) </p>

<p>MET + SU </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>57.1 (8.8) </p>

<p>47.3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>9.0 (1.0) </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>90.8 (16.6) </p>

<p>32.0 (4.2) </p>

<p>LEAD-5 (Russell-Jones 2009) 26 </p>

<p>Liraglutide </p>

<p>57.6 (9.5) </p>

<p>43.0 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>9.2 (5.8) </p>

<p>8.3 (0.9) </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>85.5 (19.4) </p>

<p>30.4 (5.3) 
MET + SU (94%-95%) </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>57.5 (10.5) </p>

<p>40.0 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>9.7 (6.4) </p>

<p>8.2 (0.9) </p>

<p>66 </p>

<p>85.0 (17.9) </p>

<p>30.3 (5.3) </p>

<p>Liraglutide 1.8 mg once daily vs insulin degludec 
DUAL-I (Gough 2014, 2015) </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>Liraglutide </p>

<p>55.0 (10.2) </p>

<p>50.0 </p>

<p>62 </p>

<p>7.2 (6.1) </p>

<p>8.3 (0.9) </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>87.4 (18.0) </p>

<p>31.3 (4.8) </p>

<p>MET (82%-83%), 
MET + TZD (17%-18%) </p>

<p>Degludec </p>

<p>54.9 (9.7) </p>

<p>52.0 </p>

<p>62 </p>

<p>7.0 (5.3) </p>

<p>8.3 (1.0) </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>87.4 (19.2) </p>

<p>31.2 (5.3) </p>

<p>Albiglutide 30 mg once weekly vs insulin glargine 
HARMONY4 
(Weissman 2014) </p>

<p>156 </p>

<p>Albiglutide </p>

<p>55.8 (9.3) </p>

<p>43.3 </p>

<p>69 </p>

<p>8.9 (6.5) </p>

<p>8.3 (0.9) </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>95.1 (19.7) </p>

<p>33.2 (5.6) </p>

<p>MET + SU (82%) </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>54.7 (9.8) </p>

<p>45.2 </p>

<p>66 </p>

<p>8.4 (5.7) </p>

<p>8.4 (1.0) </p>

<p>68 </p>

<p>94.6 (19.1) </p>

<p>33.0 (5.4) </p>

<p>SINGH ET AL. </p>

<p>
TABLE 1 Continued </p>

<p>Trial name and author </p>

<p>Study 
duration 
(weeks) </p>

<p>Intervention 
Mean age (SD), 
years </p>

<p>Female, </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>White, </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>Mean disease 
duration (SD), 
years </p>

<p>Mean 
HbA1c 
(SD), % </p>

<p>Mean HbA1c 
(mmol/mol) </p>

<p>Mean 
bodyweight </p>

<p>(SD), kg </p>

<p>Mean BMI 
(SD), kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Background therapy, % </p>

<p>Dulaglutide once weekly vs insulin glargine 
AWARD-2 (Giorgino 2015) </p>

<p>78 </p>

<p>Dulaglutide </p>

<p>0.75 mg </p>

<p>57.0 (9.0) </p>

<p>50.0 </p>

<p>71 </p>

<p>9.0 (6.0) </p>

<p>8.1 (1.0) </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>86.0 (18.0) </p>

<p>32.0 (5.0) 
MET + SU (65%-68%) </p>

<p>Dulaglutide </p>

<p>1.5 mg </p>

<p>56.0 (10.0) </p>

<p>47.0 </p>

<p>71 </p>

<p>9.0 (6.0) </p>

<p>8.2 (1.0) </p>

<p>66 </p>

<p>85.0 (18.0) </p>

<p>31.0 (5.0) </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>57.0 (9.0) </p>

<p>49.0 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>9.0 (6.0) </p>

<p>8.1 (1.0) </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>88.0 (20.0) </p>

<p>32.0 (6.0) </p>

<p>Araki 2015 </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>Dulaglutide </p>

<p>0.75 mg </p>

<p>57.5 (10.5) </p>

<p>31.0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>8.9 (6.7) </p>

<p>8.1 (0.8) </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>70.9 (13.7) </p>

<p>26.1 (3.6) </p>

<p>MET 
AE SU </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>56.1 (11.3) </p>

<p>26.0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>8.8 (6.1) </p>

<p>8.0 (0.9) </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>71.1 (13.8) </p>

<p>25.9 (3.9) </p>

<p>Lixisenatide versus insulin glargine 
LixiLan-O (Rosenstock 2016) </p>

<p>Lixisenatide </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>μg </p>

<p>58.7 (8.7) </p>

<p>43.2 </p>

<p>92.3 </p>

<p>8.9 (6.3) </p>

<p>8.1 (0.7) </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>90.8 (16.3) </p>

<p>32.0 (4.4) </p>

<p>MET </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Glargine </p>

<p>58.3 (9.4) </p>

<p>49.3 </p>

<p>90.1 </p>

<p>8.7 (5.6) </p>

<p>8.1 (0.7) </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>89.8 (16.3) </p>

<p>31.7 (4.5) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BG, biguanine; BMI, body mass index; HbA1c, glycated hemoglobin; MET, metformin; SD, standard deviation; SU, sulfonylurea; TZD, thiazolidinedione. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>The majority of participants received exenatide 10 </p>

<p>μg twice daily. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Trial conducted in a Japanese population. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Insulin glargine arm: MET = 99.6%, SU = 67.5%, SUs taken by 60% of participants at baseline and reduced to 49% at 24 weeks, liraglutide arm: MET = 99.8%, SU = 68.3%, SUs taken by 63% of participants at base-
line and reduced to 48% at 24 weeks. SUs were reduced or discontinued at investigators discretion. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Dulaglutide arm: SU monotherapy (19%), MET monotherapy (35%), SU + MET (46%). Insulin glargine arm: SU monotherapy (18%), MET monotherapy (37%), SU + MET (45%). </p>

<p> 
SINGH ET AL. </p>

<p>or 2 mg, liraglutide 1.8 mg, albiglutide 30 mg (uptitrated to 50 mg as </p>

<p>needed), dulaglutide 0.75 or 1.5 mg or lixisenatide 20 μg with insulin </p>

<p>detemir, glargine or degludec. Eligible studies reporting NPH insulin </p>

<p>were not identified. Study endpoints were reported at 16, 24, 26, 28, </p>

<p>52, 78, 156 and 168 weeks. Fifteen RCTs reported HbA1c and body-</p>

<p>weight change from baseline, 9 reported hypoglycemic episodes and </p>

<p>11 reported severe hypoglycemic episodes. As data for the dulaglu-</p>

<p>tide 1.5 mg dose, albiglutide 30 and 50 mg doses and lixisentatide </p>

<p>20 μg were identified in only 1 study each, meta-analysis could not </p>

<p>be performed for these doses. The insulin titration algorithms and </p>

<p>fasting plasma glucose (FPG) targets are shown in Table S1, Support-</p>

<p>ing Information. HbA1c, weight and FPG change from baseline are </p>

<p>shown in Tables S2 to S4, Supporting Information respectively. </p>

<p>Mean patient age in the included studies ranged from 52.2 to </p>

<p>59.8 years and mean disease duration ranged from 4.0 to 9.9 years. </p>

<p>Slightly more males were represented in the study populations. Mean </p>

<p>baseline HbA1c levels ranged from 7.4% to 9.1% (57-76 mmol/mol); the </p>

<p>median across trials was 8.2%. Mean bodyweight ranged from 69.95 to </p>

<p>101.40 kg and mean body mass index (BMI) ranged from 25.90 to </p>

<p>35.89 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Mean fasting glucose values at baseline varied from 8.6 to </p>

<p>12.2 mmol/L (Table S4, Supporting Information). Two trials were con-</p>

<p>ducted in Asian populations 
28,29 and the other trials that reported ethnic-</p>

<p>ity were conducted in mostly white populations. </p>

<p>21,22,30-35 </p>

<p>3.1 | Risk of bias </p>

<p>The risk of bias for all trials included is presented in Figure S1, Sup-</p>

<p>porting Information. Selection bias was assessed as unclear in </p>

<p>7 trials 
20,22,31,36-39 for random sequence generation and in </p>

<p>4 trials 
20,36-38 for allocation concealment. Absence of reporting was </p>

<p>the main reason for the decision to assign an RCT as presenting </p>

<p>unclear risk of bias. All trials were open label. Attrition bias (see </p>

<p>incomplete outcome data) was assessed to be low in </p>

<p>12 trials 
19-22,28-31,33-35,38 (percentage of patients lost to follow-up </p>

<p>reported as 0%-3% in all arms) and was unclear in 3. 
36,37,39 Two trials </p>

<p>were deemed to have an unclear risk with regard to reporting. </p>

<p>36,37 </p>

<p>3.2 | Efficacy outcomes </p>

<p>3.2.1 | Glycemic control </p>

<p>Of the 15 RCTs identified by the systematic review, 11 studies </p>

<p>reported change in HbA1c at 26 weeks (AE10 weeks) and had compa-</p>

<p>rable data from at least 2 studies to allow for a pairwise meta-analy-</p>

<p>sis. These included 5 trials of exenatide 10 μg vs insulin </p>

<p>glargine 
19,20,34,37,38 ; 2 trials of exenatide 2 mg LAR vs insulin glar-</p>

<p>gine 
29,33 ; 2 trials of liraglutide 1.8 mg vs insulin glargine 
36,39 ; and </p>

<p>2 trials of dulaglutide 0.75 mg vs insulin glargine. 
21,28 Four studies </p>

<p>could not be included in the pair-wise meta-analysis as the require-</p>

<p>ment of comparable data for the same dose or comparator insulin </p>

<p>from 2 studies was not met. These studies compared exenatide 2 mg </p>

<p>LAR vs insulin detemir, 
30 liraglutide 1.8 mg vs insulin degludec, 
31 albi-</p>

<p>glutide 30 mg titrated to 50 mg (as required) vs insulin glargine 
22 and </p>

<p>lixisentatide 20 μg vs insulin glargine. 
35 In addition, although 2 studies </p>

<p>were available for a pair-wise meta-analysis of the 0.75 mg dose of </p>

<p>dulaglutide 
21,28 to be performed, only 1 study reported both doses of </p>

<p>dulaglutide (0.75 and 1.5 mg). 
21 In the absence of another study with </p>

<p>the 1.5 mg dose, a pair-wise analysis for this dose could not be per-</p>

<p>formed. A summary of all evidence identified by the systematic </p>

<p>review and the results of the pairwise meta-analyses are presented in </p>

<p>Figure 2A. Mean HbA1c changes from baseline as well as the per-</p>

<p>centage of patients achieving HbA1c &lt; 7% (53 mmol/L) are pre-</p>

<p>sented in Table S2, Supporting Information. </p>

<p>Compared with insulin glargine, the mean difference in HbA1c </p>

<p>change was +0.01% (95% CI, −0.11, 0.13; I 
2 = 0%) (+0.01 mmol/L </p>

<p>[95% CI, −1.2, 1.4]) with exenatide 10 μg, −0.31% (95% CI, −0.42, </p>

<p>−0.19; I 
2 = 75%) (−3.4 mmol/L [95% CI, −4.6, −2.1]) with exenatide </p>

<p>2 mg LAR, +0.06%, (95% CI, −0.06, 0.18; I 
2 = 86.1%) (+0.7 mmol/L </p>

<p>[95% CI, −0.7, 2.0]) with liraglutide 1.8 mg and −0.39% (95% CI, </p>

<p>−0.49, −0.29; I 
2 = 88.6%) (−0.43 mmol/L [95% CI, −5.4, −3.2]) with </p>

<p>dulaglutide 0.75 mg (Figure 2A). </p>

<p>The RCT conducted by Bunck et al.20 included 5 different doses </p>

<p>of exenatide: 10 μg BID (62.1% of participants), 15 μg BID (3.4%), </p>

<p>10 μg 3 times daily (TID) (6.9%), 15 μg TID (3.4%) and 20 μg TID </p>

<p>(17.2%). This RCT was included in the systematic literature review </p>

<p>because the majority of participants (62.1%) received a licensed dose </p>

<p>of exenatide (10 μg BID). However, because of the different doses of </p>

<p>exenatide administered to patients as compared to other exenatide </p>

<p>10 μg BID trials, sensitivity analyses for HbA1c and weight were con-</p>

<p>ducted to understand the impact of this trial on the overall pooled </p>

<p>estimate and heterogeneity. This sensitivity analysis showed no </p>

<p>impact on the overall effect estimate or heterogeneity measure for </p>

<p>exenatide 10 μg BID vs insulin glargine with a pooled mean HbA1c </p>

<p>change of +0.01% (95% CI, −0.11, 0.13; I 
2 = 0%), (+3.2 mmol/L [95% </p>

<p>CI, −1.2, 1.4]), which is the same as the pooled estimates when </p>

<p>including the Bunck et al. trial. </p>

<p>3.2.2 | Body weight </p>

<p>A summary of all evidence for bodyweight, as well as the pairwise </p>

<p>meta-analyses at 26 weeks, are presented in Figure 2B. Compared </p>

<p>with insulin glargine, the mean difference in bodyweight was −4.31 kg </p>

<p>(95% CI, −4.71, −3.90; I 
2 = 76%) with exenatide 10 μg, −2.85 kg (95% </p>

<p>CI, −3.20, −2.49; I 
2 = 96.5%) with exenatide 2 mg LAR, −4.65 kg (95% </p>

<p>CI, −5.08, −4.22; I 
2 = 89.1%) with liraglutide 1.8 mg, and −1.98 kg </p>

<p>(95% CI, −2.32, −1.64, I 
2 = 91%) with dulaglutide 0.75 mg. Removing </p>

<p>the RCT conducted by Bunck et al. 
20 minimally changed the overall </p>

<p>effect estimate for exenatide 10 μg to −4.35 kg (95% CI, −4.77, −3.93; </p>

<p>I 
2 = 81.5%). Mean bodyweight and BMI change from baseline are pre-</p>

<p>sented in Table S3, Supporting Information. </p>

<p>3.3 | Safety outcomes </p>

<p>3.3.1 | Hypoglycaemia </p>

<p>A summary of all evidence for hypoglycaemia as well as the pairwise </p>

<p>meta-analyses at 26 weeks are presented in Figure 3A. Compared to </p>

<p>insulin glargine, the odds ratio for a hypoglycaemic episode was 0.32 </p>

<p>(95% CI, 0.22, 0.47; I 
2 = 33.2%) with exenatide 2 mg LAR and 0.40 </p>

<p>(95% CI, 0.32, 0.51; I 
2 = 96%) with liraglutide 1.8 mg. A summary of </p>

<p>the evidence related to the proportion of patients experiencing a </p>

<p>hypoglycaemic episode and the background therapy is presented in </p>

<p>Figure 3B. </p>

<p>SINGH ET AL. </p>

<p>
Out of the 15 studies that reported data at week 26 (AE10 weeks), </p>

<p>11 RCTs reported data for severe hypoglycaemia. Meta-analyses of </p>

<p>severe hypoglycaemia were not conducted because of the limited </p>

<p>events observed; 3 studies reported no events in both arms 
28-30 and </p>

<p>5 studies reported no events in one arm. 
19,31,35,36,39 The numbers </p>

<p>and proportions of patients experiencing an episode of hypoglycae-</p>

<p>mia or an episode of severe hypoglycaemia, and the definitions of </p>

<p>hypoglycaemia and severe hypoglycaemia as described by the </p>

<p>authors are presented in Table S5, Supporting Information. </p>

<p>3.3.2 | Gastrointestinal events </p>

<p>Meta-analyses of gastrointestinal events were not conducted as </p>

<p>reporting across studies was insufficient to allow meaningful analyses </p>

<p>(data not shown). </p>

<p>4 | DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The meta-analyses show statistically significant reductions in HbA1c </p>

<p>with once-weekly exenatide 2 mg LAR and once-weekly dulaglutide </p>

<p>0.75 mg, compared to insulin glargine at 6 months, a reduction in </p>

<p>HbA1c of 0.3% (3.3 mmol/L) and 0.4% (4.4 mmol/L), respectively. In </p>

<p>contrast, once-daily liraglutide and twice-daily exenatide 10 μg did </p>

<p>not show a statistically significant difference from insulin glargine. </p>

<p>This difference between weekly and daily GLP-1 RAs may be attribu-</p>

<p>ted to the potential impact of the weekly agents on both FPG and </p>

<p>postprandial plasma glucose (PPG), compared to the daily agents that </p>

<p>may predominantly regulate PPG. </p>

<p>The systematic review identified 15 trials reporting results at </p>

<p>26 weeks (AE10 weeks). Eleven trials were included in pair-wise meta-</p>

<p>analyses: 5 trials of exenatide 10 μg vs insulin glargine 
19,20,34,37,38 ; </p>

<p>2 trials of exenatide 2 mg LAR vs insulin glargine 
29,33 ; 2 trials of lira-</p>

<p>glutide 1.8 mg vs insulin glargine 
36,39 ; and 2 trials of dulaglutide </p>

<p>0.75 mg vs insulin glargine. 
21,28 Although it was not possible to incor-</p>

<p>porate data for dulaglutide 1.5 mg, lixisenatide or albiglutide into the </p>

<p>analyses, as only 1 study for each met the inclusion criteria and at </p>

<p>least 2 studies are required for meta-analysis, it should be considered </p>

<p>that the 3-armed trial identified by the systematic review that </p>

<p>included the 1.5 mg dulaglutide dose (vs dulaglutide 0.75 mg and </p>

<p>insulin glargine) indicated that the higher dose led to a greater reduc-</p>

<p>tion in HbA1c and bodyweight compared to both dulaglutide </p>

<p>0.75 mg and insulin glargine (Figure 2). 
21 With lixisenatide, a weight </p>

<p>reduction was observed compared to insulin glarine, but HbA1c </p>

<p>reduction was greater with glargine (Figure 2). 
35 With albiglutide, </p>

<p>although there was weight reduction when compared with insulin </p>

<p>glargine, HbA1c reduction was not different from insulin glargine </p>

<p>(Figure 2). 
22 This finding is not unexpected, however, as albiglutide </p>

<p>was inferior in glycaemic lowering efficacy when compared to liraglu-</p>

<p>tide, which in this meta-analysis also did not have a statistically signif-</p>

<p>icant HbA1c reduction when compared to insulin glargine. 
18 Analyses </p>

<p>conducted for weight change from baseline demonstrated statistically </p>

<p>significant weight loss with all GLP-1 RAs compared to weight gain </p>

<p>with basal insulins: −4.65 kg (95% CI −5.08, −4.22) for liraglutide </p>

<p>1.8 mg, −4.31 kg (95% CI −4.71, −3.90) for exenatide 10 μg, </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 Effect of GLP-1 RA compared to basal insulin at week 
26 (AE10 weeks). Change in HbA1c (%) (A), and change in bodyweight 
(kg) (B). Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; GLP-1 RA, glucagon-
like peptide-1 receptor agonist; MD, mean difference; SD, standard 
deviation. *Twice daily; **once weekly. </p>

<p> 
SINGH ET AL. </p>

<p>−2.85 kg (95% CI −3.20 to −2.49) for exenatide 2 mg LAR, and </p>

<p>−1.98 kg (95% CI −2.32, −1.64) for dulaglutide 0.75 mg. </p>

<p>The results of the 2 pairwise meta-analyses indicated that there </p>

<p>is a lower risk of hypoglycaemia with liraglutide 1.8 mg once daily </p>

<p>compared to insulin glargine and also with once-weekly exenatide </p>

<p>2 mg LAR compared to insulin glargine. However, these results </p>

<p>should be interpreted with caution because of the variability in defini-</p>

<p>tions of hypoglycaemia in different studies, a challenge that has been </p>

<p>identified by the American Diabetes Association. 
40 Moreover, there </p>

<p>were only limited data available for severe hypoglycaemia, and where </p>

<p>FIGURE 3 Effect of GLP-1 RA compared to basal 
insulin at 26 weeks (AE10 weeks) on hypoglycemia, 
odds ratio (A), and proportion (%) (B). 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; GLP-1 RA, 
glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonist; OR, 
odds ratio; prop, proportion. *Twice daily; **once 
weekly.  †At baseline, the majority of patients in 
each treatment group (exenatide 84.7%; insulin 
glargine 86.2%) were taking SUs.  † †At baseline, 
70.0% and 30.0% of patients in both arms were 
receiving MET and MET + SU, respectively. One 
in four patients had a reduction in SU dose.  ‡SU 
dosage was reduced or discontinued at the 
physician's discretion. SUs were initially taken by 
60.0% of those receiving insulin glargine and by 
63.0% receiving liraglutide. At 24 weeks, 49.0% 
and 48.0%, respectively, were still taking them. 
 ‡ ‡At baseline, 94.0% in the liraglutide arm and 
95.0% in the insulin glargine arm were receiving 
SU.  ‡ ‡ ‡The majority of the patients in the 
dulaglutide group (65.0%) and insulin glargine 
group (63.0%) received SU at baseline. In the 
dulaglutide and insulin glargine groups, 13/117 
(11.1%) and 11/114 (9.6%) patients, respectively, 
decreased their concomitant SU dose from 
baseline as a result of hypoglycemia. 
 §Figure includes only insulin glargine trials to 
highlight the differences in proportions of patients 
experiencing hypoglycemic events between trials, 
which may be due to variations in insulin titration 
and background therapies. </p>

<p>SINGH ET AL. </p>

<p>
data were present, the event rates were too low to yield clinically </p>

<p>meaningful interpretation; as such, a meta-analysis for severe hypo-</p>

<p>glycaemia was not conducted. However, it is important to note that </p>

<p>the outcome "hypoglycaemia" reported in this article also included </p>

<p>"severe hypoglycaemia". </p>

<p>It is pertinent that we acknowledge the effect that insulin titra-</p>

<p>tion may have had on the results for hypoglycaemia. The impact of </p>

<p>insulin titration was most apparent in the RCT conducted by D'Ales-</p>

<p>sio et al. 
36 which compared once-daily liraglutide 1.8 mg and insulin </p>

<p>glargine with an aggressive up-titration of insulin glargine that </p>

<p>resulted in a mean insulin dose of 52 units/d at study end (Table S1, </p>

<p>Supporting Information) coupled with the down-titration of back-</p>

<p>ground SU. The result of the meta-analyses for this comparison show </p>

<p>glycaemic control in favour of insulin glargine, a greater increase in </p>

<p>weight from baseline and an increased risk of hypoglycaemia which </p>

<p>may be a result of aggressive insulin titration. In contrast, the mean </p>

<p>doses of insulin glargine in the once-weekly exenatide 2 mg LAR </p>

<p>studies used in the pairwise meta-analysis for hypoglycaemia were </p>

<p>only 16 to 31 insulin units (Table S1, Supporting Information), which </p>

<p>may have been responsible for, not only the lower risk of hypoglycae-</p>

<p>mia, but also the lesser weight gain and lower HbA1c drop with insu-</p>

<p>lin glargine. 
33 It is important to point out that the titration of basal </p>

<p>insulin, even in the setting of clinical trials designed around insulin </p>

<p>titration, is often suboptimal. For example, in the treat-to-target trial </p>

<p>comparing once-daily insulin glargine with NPH insulin, the average </p>

<p>dose of insulin was 47.2 IU (SD = 1.3) for glargine and 41.8 IU </p>

<p>(SD = 1.3) for NPH. 
41 Inadequate insulin dosing could also have </p>

<p>implications for a real-world setting, where basal insulin titration </p>

<p>might not always occur as it should. As such, GLP-1RAs, some of </p>

<p>which do not require any dose titration, could offer a reasonable </p>

<p>alternative to basal insulin. </p>

<p>Although our analysis attempted to minimize heterogeneity among </p>

<p>studies by ensuring that treatment regimens and outcome time points </p>

<p>were consistent, and the systematic review eligibility criteria specifying </p>

<p>that background therapy must be received concurrently with study </p>

<p>medication, any OAD was allowed as background therapy. However, </p>

<p>because of the limited evidence base, heterogeneity was observed </p>

<p>among studies, leading to uncertainty concerning the estimates. Table 1 </p>

<p>clearly indicates that background therapy varied among the included </p>

<p>studies, which could also have impacted the results. Whilst MET is </p>

<p>largely weight neutral and has a low risk of hypoglycaemia associated </p>

<p>with it, both SU and TZD treatments are associated with weight gain, </p>

<p>which should be considered when interpreting results. In addition, SUs </p>

<p>carry a moderate risk of hypoglycaemia, which is of particular impor-</p>

<p>tance because basal insulin is also associated with weight gain and an </p>

<p>increased risk of hypoglycaemia. 
42 Although sensitivity analyses can be </p>

<p>conducted to assess the impact of differing background therapies, it </p>

<p>was not possible in this study because most meta-analyses included </p>

<p>only 2 trials, a number insufficient for a meaningful sensitivity analysis. </p>

<p>As the analyses for the present study were being conducted, a </p>

<p>systematic review and meta-analysis of once-weekly GLP-1 RAs was </p>

<p>published. 
10 However, the current study has several important differ-</p>

<p>ences from that study and other previously published analyses. Our </p>

<p>research question was more specific than that posed by previous ana-</p>

<p>lyses. First, we considered only head-to-head comparisons with basal </p>

<p>insulins rather than with any antihyperglycemic treatment, which </p>

<p>offers more comprehensive evidence for clinicians regarding choice </p>

<p>between the two injectable options in the treatment pathway. Sec-</p>

<p>ond, rather than being restricted to once-weekly GLP-1 Ras, our anal-</p>

<p>ysis considered all licensed dosages of all GLP-1 RAs currently being </p>

<p>used in clinical practice. And finally, our analysis did not pool drugs </p>

<p>according to class; thus, each drug and dosage was considered inde-</p>

<p>pendently and we pooled only outcome data from studies within </p>

<p>the time frame of 16 to 36 weeks of treatment. Although these </p>

<p>restrictions meant that some treatments were not included in the </p>

<p>meta-analysis, notably albiglutide 30 mg (uptitrated to 50 mg as </p>

<p>needed), dulaglutide 1.5 mg (where only one study comparing it to </p>

<p>basal insulin at this dose was available) and lixisenatide 20 μg, it </p>

<p>was not thought appropriate to conduct an analysis pooling the </p>

<p>drugs, dosages or different time frames because head-to-head </p>

<p>trials of GLP-1 RAs have demonstrated differences within the </p>

<p>class. 
43 Another recently published pairwise and network meta-</p>

<p>analysis sought to understand the benefits and harms of once-</p>

<p>weekly GLP-1 RAs. 
16 However, that analysis considered only </p>

<p>once-weekly GLP-1 RAs and was conducted primarily to assess </p>

<p>the cardiometabolic efficacy and adverse effects of GLP-1 RAs and </p>

<p>not the comparison to basal insulin in the treatment paradigm, </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>as we did in our study. </p>

<p>There are several limitations in the current systematic literature </p>

<p>review and meta-analysis that should be acknowledged. One limita-</p>

<p>tion is that only English-language articles were searched and included. </p>

<p>Although we do not envision the number of included articles to sub-</p>

<p>stantially increase if the scope of the search was expanded to include </p>

<p>non-English articles, we cannot be certain of the impact of an </p>

<p>expanded scope on the results of the meta-analysis. In addition, we </p>

<p>combined the results of trials at 26 weeks (AE10 weeks) and therefore </p>

<p>are unable to draw conclusions about the long-term efficacy and </p>

<p>safety of GLP-1 RAs compared to basal insulin; future studies should </p>

<p>explore this area. Further, a priori, we developed a protocol to ana-</p>

<p>lyse the results of the systematic review by meta-analysis. As future </p>

<p>studies are published, expanding the evidence base for GLP-1 RAs </p>

<p>compared to basal insulin, consideration of conducting an analysis </p>

<p>including both direct and indirect data by network meta-analysis may </p>

<p>be warranted. </p>

<p>The meta-analysis conducted for hypoglycemia should be inter-</p>

<p>preted with caution because of high heterogeneity in defining hypo-</p>

<p>glycaemic events, an inherent problem when conducting meta-</p>

<p>analyses in diabetes. 
40 Of the 15 studies identified by the systematic </p>

<p>review, the definitions of hypoglycaemia varied considerably </p>

<p>(Table S5, Supporting Information). With the exception of the study </p>

<p>by Davies et al. 
30 which required only the presence of symptoms for </p>

<p>a hypoglycaemic event to be reported, the remaining studies did </p>

<p>define a hypoglycaemic event using a blood glucose target, but this </p>

<p>target varied between 3.0 and 4.0 mmol/L depending on the study. </p>

<p>Interpretation of findings from the meta-analysis of hypoglycaemia </p>

<p>was further complicated by heterogeneity among studies with regard </p>

<p>to background therapies and insulin titration; as such, future trials </p>

<p>with similar background therapies, insulin titration algorithms and </p>

<p>standardized definitions of hypoglycaemia are warranted for compa-</p>

<p>rability of studies. </p>

<p> 
SINGH ET AL. </p>

<p>In conclusion, the current analysis indicates that once-weekly </p>

<p>GLP-1 Ras, exenatide LAR and dulaglutide, demonstrate a greater </p>

<p>reduction in HbA1c compared to basal insulin after 26 weeks of treat-</p>

<p>ment. Once-or twice-daily GLP-1 RAs, liraglutide and exenatide, also </p>

<p>demonstrate a reduction in HbA1c, but these changes were similar to </p>

<p>those seen with basal insulin. Treatment with all GLP-1 RAs results in </p>

<p>significant reduction in bodyweight as compared to basal insulins. </p>

<p>However, clarity and consistency is required in defining hypoglycae-</p>

<p>mia in clinical trials, to allow meaningful conclusions to be inferred for </p>

<p>this outcome when comparing GLP-1 RAs with basal insulin. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank James Eaton for study planning and Sarah Goring (both of </p>

<p>ICON Plc) for analysis validation and manuscript editing. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>S. S. has served previously on the Advisory Board of Eli Lilly and was </p>

<p>compensated for his time. E. E. W. has served previously on a speak-</p>

<p>er's bureau for Eli Lilly, Boehringer Ingelheim and Abbott Diabetes </p>

<p>Care, on advisory boards for Eli Lilly, Boehringer Ingelheim, Abbott </p>

<p>Diabetes Care, Amgen and Voluntis, and as a consultant for Eli Lilly, </p>

<p>Boehringer Ingelheim, Abbott Diabetes Care and Amgen, and has </p>

<p>received grants from Abbott Diabetes Care. A. K. and R. J. are </p>

<p>employees of Lilly USA, LLC and are Lilly stock holders. M. Y. is an </p>

<p>employee of Eli Lilly Canada Inc. and is a Lilly stock holder. J. T., I. S., </p>

<p>E. K. and N. W. are employees of the consultancy group of ICON plc, </p>

<p>which received compensation for the completion of the analysis. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>S. S. participated in the conception, design, analysis, and interpreta-</p>

<p>tion of drafting the results of the manuscript. He did not receive any </p>

<p>compensation for his participation in the study. E. E. W. participated </p>

<p>in the original study design, analysis of the data, and review and edit-</p>

<p>ing of the manuscript. He did not receive any compensation for his </p>

<p>participation in the study. A. K., and R. J. contributed to the design of </p>

<p>the study, analysis of the data and review and editing of the paper. </p>

<p>M. Y. contributed to the design of the study, analysis of the data and </p>

<p>review and editing of the paper. J. T., I. S., E. K. and N. W. partici-</p>

<p>pated in the conception, design, interpretation and writing of the </p>

<p>manuscript. </p>



<p>SINGH ET AL. </p>



<p>
 
SINGH ET AL. </p>

</text></tei>