<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5084721" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Antibiotic allergy labels that reflect either immune-and/or 
nonimmune-mediated adverse drug reactions are prevalent in 
10%-30% of hospitalized patients. Whilst often inaccurate, 
they are also associated with inappropriate antimicrobial pre-
scribing, microbiological resistance, higher antimicrobial 
costs, and suboptimal patient outcomes [1-4]. Inappropriate la-
beling of drug side effects, suboptimal allergy history taking, in-
correct antibiotic allergy recording in electronic medical 
records, and poor clinician understanding have previously 
been identified as contributing factors [5-7]. 
The Infectious Diseases Society of America (IDSA) antimi-
crobial stewardship guidelines highlight the burden of antibiotic </p>

<p>allergy and propose the incorporation of antibiotic allergy as-
sessment into stewardship progams [8]. Antibiotic allergy de-
labeling programs have been shown to effectively remove 
&gt;90% of patient labels, and hence such programs could aid 
stewardship measures [9-12]. We distributed a survey to mem-
bers of the Emerging Infections Network (EIN) of IDSA to as-
certain current availability of antibiotic allergy services and the 
receptiveness for incorporating antibiotic allergy testing (AAT) 
strategies into stewardship programs. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>The EIN is a provider-based network of practicing adult and 
pediatric infectious diseases (ID) physicians from all 50 states, 
the District of Columbia, and Canada [13]. A 10-item survey 
(Appendix 1) to evaluate current practices and knowledge was 
developed in consultation with ID physicians, hospital pharma-
cists, immunologists, and key stakeholders of the EIN. The 
survey was piloted amongst staff of the EIN. The EIN distribu-
ted the survey and study objectives between September 15 and 
October 13, 2015. An opt-out option and 2 e-mail reminders at 
1-week intervals were provided. Demographic information was 
available for each EIN respondent. 
Survey responses were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 13</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp</rs>, College Station, TX) using the χ 2 test for categorical 
variables and paired t test or Wilcoxon signed-rank tests for 
continuous variables. A P value of &lt;.05 was deemed statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Characteristics of Participants </p>

<p>In this study, 736 of 1545 (48%) respondents were active EIN 
members: 75% (558 of 736) were adult physicians, 20% (154 
of 736) were pediatricians, and 3.2% (24 of 736) were both. 
Further baseline characteristics of respondents and nonrespon-
dents are provided (see Supplementary Table 1). </p>

<p>Antibiotic Allergy Prevalence and Availability of Allergy Testing </p>

<p>Most repsondents estimated penicillin allergy prevalence to be 
between 5% and 20% of the their patients (68%, 500 of 736). 
Although 43% (317 of 736) of the physicians had a skin prick 
test (SPT) or intradermal test (IDT) available to them, only 27% 
(204 of 736) had SPT/IDT combined with oral challenge, which 
is the gold standard (Table 1). Twenty-three percent (171 of 
736) of respondents did not have access to any form of testing, 
including oral challenge or desensitization (Table 1). Penicillin 
remained the most commonly used allergy-testing reagent 
(59%, 271 of 460) (Figure 1). Of those who did have AAT </p>

<p>services available, 40% (182 of 460) were unaware of the specific 
nature of available testing. 
AAT was most frequently performed in outpatient facilities 
(63%, 274 of 432). However, a significant proportion of respon-
dents also offered testing either in inpatient units (47%, 202 of 
432) and/or intensive care units (50%, 218 of 432). Only 3% (12 
of 460) of respondents performed SPT/IDT themselves, and 8% 
(39 of 460) performed oral challenge. Although years of experi-
ence did not impact upon a respondent's likelihood of self-per-
forming SPT/IDT (P = .47), those with &gt;15 years clinical </p>

<p>experience were more likely to perform oral challenges (8% 
[27 of 361] vs 3% [12 of 375]; P = .01). 
Extended β-lactam testing that involved more than just pen-
icillins was less infrequently used (Figure 1), and it was more 
likely to be offered by federal institutions (19%, 6 of 31) than 
private practice (4%, 7 of 183) (P = .01). Skin prick test/IDT 
and oral challenge for non-β-lactams was available to 13% (60 
of 460) and 30% (141 of 460) of respondents, respectively. </p>

<p>Perceived Value of Allergy Testing </p>

<p>Most respondents believed that it was worthwhile to refer pa-
tients for AAT (93%, 410 of 442), and they believed that testing 
would serve to remove the antibiotic allergy label (78%, 336 of 
432). Respondents with &lt;15 year's experience were more likely 
than those with ≥15 year's experience to believe in the effective-
ness of antibiotic testing to remove the antibiotic allergy label 
(82% [198 of 241] vs 63% [138 of 219]; P = .0001). The presence 
of an immediate/accelerated antibiotic allergy would prompt 
antibiotic allergy testing by 67% of respondents (294 of 442) 
(Table 1), and this was not affected by experience (&lt;15 or 
≥15 years; P = .23). </p>

<p>Knowledge and Current Practices Regarding Management of Antibiotic 
Allergies </p>

<p>In patients with a remote history of penicillin allergy and where 
penicillin is the preferred therapy (scenario 1), respondents indi-
cated that in their practice, the single preferred treatment strategy 
for acute management would be as follows: (1) point-of-care test-
ing (40%, 177 of 442); (2) use of an alternative non-β-lactam 
antibiotic, even if inferior (13%, 57 of 442); (3) desensitization 
with maintenance of penicillin allergy label (8%, 37 of 442); or 
(4) desensitization then allergy clinic referral for penicillin allergy 
testing (7%, 30 of 442). For a patient with a history of penicillin 
anaphylaxis within the last 6 months (scenario 2), respondents </p>

<p>Table 1. Antibiotic Allergy Testing: Availability and Potential Benefits </p>

<p>Antibiotic Allergy Testing 
Responses, n (%) </p>

<p>Antibiotic allergy services available (n = 736) </p>

<p>Desensitization to ≥1 antibiotic 
417 (57%) </p>

<p>Traditional testing (skin prick, intradermal) 
316 (43%) </p>

<p>Oral challenge 
297 (40%) </p>

<p>None of the above 
171 (23%) </p>

<p>Not sure 
55 (7%) </p>

<p>Allergy phenotypes were allergy testing preferred (n = 442) </p>

<p>Immediate/accelerated reactions 
294 (67%) </p>

<p>Mild delayed reactions 
182 (41%) </p>

<p>Severe delayed reactions 
124 (28%) </p>

<p>Any/all reactions 
77 (17%) </p>

<p>None 
5 (1%) </p>

<p>Potential benefits of antibiotic allergy "label" removal (n = 446) </p>

<p>Better antibiotic selection 
422 (95%) </p>

<p>Improved antibiotic appropriateness 
411 (92%) </p>

<p>Improved antibiotic stewardship services 
365 (82%) </p>

<p>Safer administration of antibiotics 
332 (74%) </p>

<p>Unclear if any measurable improvement 
10 (2%) </p>

<p>None 
2 (0.4%) </p>

<p>Other 
6 (1%) </p>

<p>Note: Respondents were able to select more than 1 response. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Antibiotic allergy testing procedures available to respondents (n = 460). (Note: 182 of 460 (40%) selected "do not know the specifics of available testing". 278 of 
460 (60%) selected at least one of the options available.) </p>

<p>2 • OFID • BRIEF REPORT </p>

<p>favored using an alternative non-β-lactam antibiotic, even if 
inferior (51%, 222 of 439), or desensitization with maintenance 
of penicillin allergy label (28%, 121 of 439). Delabeling approach-
es such as desensitization then allergy clinic referral for penicillin 
allergy testing (8%, 36 of 439), point-of-care testing (5%, 22 of 
439), and other strategies (6%, 26 of 439) were infrequently 
used. Experience (&lt;15 or ≥15 years) did not impact upon respon-
dent approaches to scenario 1 (P = .16) or scenario 2 (P = .46). </p>

<p>Evaluation of Models of Care Including AAT </p>

<p>Most physicians (62%, 277 of 446) thought that antibiotic aller-
gy delabeling would improve clinical practice by enhancing the 
following: (1) antibiotic appropriateness, (2) safer administra-
tion of antimicrobials, and (3) improved antimicrobial steward-
ship (Table 1). Sixty-eight percent (305 of 449) of respondents 
agreed that AAT should be incorporated into antimicrobial 
stewardship programs, and incorporation of AAT into antimi-
crobial stewardship programs received greater support from 
those with &lt;15 years' versus those with ≥15 years experience 
(72% [173 of 241] vs 60% [132 of 219]; P = .01). Employment 
type (federal, military, university, hospital/clinic, or private 
practice) did not impact upon respondent desire to incorporate 
AAT into antimicrobial stewardship programs (P = .3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Contemporary studies suggest that both outpatient and inpa-
tient AAT programs comprising combinations of SPT/IDT 
and oral challenge are both cost saving and effective at delabel-
ing patients of antibiotic allergy [1, 14, 15]. Most antibiotic 
allergy "labels" are inaccurate, because almost 90% of patients 
with a penicillin allergy history are able tolerate a β-lactam 
after formal allergy testing [9]. In our survey, antibiotic allergy 
services were perceived as desirable, particularly in their poten-
tial capacity to aid antimicrobial stewardship. However, a mi-
nority (43%) of respondents had testing available. The relative 
inexperience of ID physicians with AAT services and their con-
fidence in these services are juxtaposed against a high perceived </p>

<p>burden of antibiotic allergy labels and knowledge gaps centered 
around antibiotic safety in those with penicillin allergy histories. 
To our surprise, we found that the overall experience of the ID 
physician respondents seemed to be negatively correlated with 
perceived utility and effectiveness of AAT. This finding supports 
previous studies that illustrated significant inconsistencies in the 
availability of specialized and standardized AAT services over 
time. Furthermore, a recent survey of practices amongst Allergy 
and Immunology specialists in the United States also supports 
this inconsistency [16]. 
Although testing may be limited by consistent access to spe-
cialty clinics and services [7], simple measures such as direct 
oral challenge in very low-risk patients and desensitization by 
published protocols should be available to all ID physicians 
[17, 18]. Key knowledge gaps were identified via clinicians' </p>

<p>responses to common clinical scenarios, irrespective of experi-
ence, that could negatively impact on the ability to successfully 
manage antibiotic allergy. Very few respondents were willing 
to use, or had access to, point-of-care AAT or follow-up delab-
eling strategies in patients with a history of recent or remote im-
mediate hypersensitivity, and these respondents also preferred 
to use inferior antibiotic therapies. Evidence supports &lt;1% 
cross-reactivity among penicillin, third-generation cephalospo-
rins, and carbapenems [15] and predictable cross-reactivity 
dependent on β-lactam side chains [15, 19]. Although not 
addressed in this survey, applying this evidence into clinical 
practice may help effect change in these common clinicial 
scenarios [18]. More encouragingly, Blumenthal et al [6] dem-
onstrated that clinician practices could be altered with decision 
support and a guided education program. 
More than 80% of respondents, spanning all areas of clinical 
practice, believed that AAT would aid antibiotic selection, anti-
biotic appropriateness, and antimicrobial stewardship. Recent 
studies have highlighted increased use of restricted antibiotics 
and inappropriate prescriptions in those with antibiotic allergy 
labels [2]. The engagement of hospital pharmacists is essential; 
programs using direct allergy referrals from pharmacy depart-
ments have aided delabeling initiatives [12, 20]. A multidisci-
plinary model involving allergists, immunologists, ID physicians, 
and pharmacists is most likely to engage clinicians and deliver an 
effective service [21]. Strategies to manage antibiotic allergy and 
AAT could be incorporated into existing antimicrobial steward-
ship programs, even in areas of low antimicrobial resistance 
[22, 23]. 
This study does have limitations. Although key stakeholders 
were surveyed and targeted toward clinicians of teaching hospi-
tals, other members of broader antimicrobial stewardship pro-
grams were not. Furthermore, immunologists and allergists 
were not surveyed, and they form a key role in the provision 
of antibiotic allergy practices [16]. As with all voluntary surveys, 
there is a potential for selection bias because those interested in 
AAT may be more likely to respond. In assessing knowledge 
gaps, respondents were questioned about their own approaches 
to clinical antibiotic allergy scenarios, which may in part be im-
pacted by the absence of allergy services. Despite these limita-
tions, the majority of respondents (68%) support the call for 
AAT to be incorporated into antimicrobial stewardship pro-
grams [21, 24]. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>These findings demonstrate an urgent need to address both the 
lack of availability of AAT services and the educational gaps 
surrounding antibiotic use in labeled patients. Incorporation 
of allergy teaching into ID training programs and undergradu-
ate medical teaching and the application of clinical guidelines 
for management of remote allergies are likely to have significant 
impacts on prescribing in those with antibiotic allergy labels. It </p>

<p>BRIEF REPORT • OFID • 3 </p>

<p>is essential to ensure that allergy labels in the electronic medical 
record reflect the true nature of the adverse drug reactions, if 
any attempt at addressing allergy labels is to be successful. To 
support the feasibility of access to AAT, delabeling services, 
and incorporation of these into antimicrobial stewardship pro-
grams, greater collaboration is needed between allergy service 
providers and ID physicians as well as between pharmacists 
who can further contribute to and direct the antibiotic delabel-
ing and stewardship cause. Reorganization of current healthcare 
services and physician training may be required to foster this 
collaboration. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments 
Financial support. This work was supported by the National Institute 
Health (NIH) (grant 1P50GM115305-01, 1R01AI103348-01 to E. J. P.); 
NIH-funded Tennessee Center for AIDS Research (P30 AI110527 to E. J. P.); 
and National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) and Austra-
lian Centre for HIV and Hepatitis Virology Research (to E. J. P.). J. A. T. is 
supported by an NHMRC postgraduate scholarship. 
Potential conflicts of interest. All authors: No reported conflicts. All au-
thors have submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential Conflicts 
of Interest. </p>

<p>Supplementary Data </p>

<p>Supplementary material is available online at Open Forum Infectious Diseases 
online (http://OpenForumInfectiousDiseases.oxfordjournals.org/). </p>



<p>4 • OFID • BRIEF REPORT </p>

</text></tei>