<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5387955" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background: Corticosteroids are a potential risk factor </p>

<p>for mortality in patients with perforated diverticular 
disease, due to blinding of disease severity, hampered 
wound healing or adrenal insufficiency. We examined 
mortality in corticosteroid users and non-users among 
patients with perforated diverticular disease. </p>

<p>Methods: A cohort study based on medical databases </p>

<p>including all patients ≥18 years in Denmark (source 
population 5 289 261 inhabitants) admitted to a 
hospital with incident perforated diverticular disease 
between 2005 and 2013. 7-day, 1-month, 3-month 
and 1-year mortality risks in corticosteroid users and 
non-users were calculated using the Kaplan-Meier 
method, and compared with Cox proportional hazard 
regression adjusted for age, sex and comorbidities. </p>

<p>is ∼10-25%, 3 which is known to present with 
perforation. 4 5 The incidence of perforated 
diverticular disease is ∼4 per 100 000 persons 
each year, reported in hospital records in the 
UK of Great Britain and Northern Ireland 
and the USA. 6 Mortality after perforated 
diverticular disease requiring operative inter-
vention has been reported to be as high as </p>

<p>Summary box </p>

<p>What is already known about this subject? </p>

<p>▸ Perforation is a well-known complication of 
diverticulitis. 
▸ The incidence of perforated diverticular disease 
is ∼4 per 100 000 persons each year. 
▸ Mortality risk after perforated diverticular 
disease requiring operative intervention has 
been reported to be 12-36% in small cohort 
studies. 
▸ Use of corticosteroids is a potential risk factor 
affecting mortality in patients with perforated 
diverticular disease. </p>

<p>What are the new findings? </p>

<p>▸ Mortality risk was twice as high for current corti-
costeroids users compared with non-users. 
▸ This is the first large cohort study comparing 
mortality risks between corticosteroid users and 
non-users among patients with perforated diver-
ticular disease. We found that corticosteroid use 
is a strong indicator for 1-year mortality, with an 
absolute risk of about 50%. 
▸ Our study did not indicate a relation between 
corticosteroid dose and mortality risk. </p>

<p>How might it impact on clinical practice in 
the foreseeable future? </p>

<p>▸ Use of systemic corticosteroids should be 
regarded as an important risk marker for mortal-
ity in patients with perforated diverticular 
disease. Further multiangled evidence is needed 
to determine whether the association between 
corticosteroid use and mortality risk is causal. </p>

<p>Broersen LHA, Horváth-Puhó E, Pereira AM, et al. BMJ Open Gastro 2017;4:e000136. doi:10.1136/bmjgast-2017-000136 </p>



<p>Epidemiology </p>

<p>12-36% in small cohort studies (78-121 cases). 7 8 Given 
this high mortality risk, a better understanding of prog-
nostic factors associated with mortality is clearly needed. 
Use of corticosteroids is a potential prognostic factor 
affecting mortality in patients with perforated diverticu-
lar disease. Corticosteroids are widely prescribed for 
inflammatory diseases, malignancies and after organ 
transplantation, in order to inhibit an inflammatory 
response. 9-11 At the same time, corticosteroids have 
been associated with bowel perforation in patients with 
diverticular disease. Three case-control studies reported 
increased ORs of 1.7 to 28.3 and one cohort study 
reported a relative risk of 2.2. 12-15 A recent meta-analysis 
showed ORs for perforation of diverticular disease after 
use of corticosteroids of 2.17 to 31.90. 16 
There are several reasons why mortality may be 
increased in patients with perforated diverticular disease 
who use corticosteroids. Disease severity might be 
masked by use of corticosteroids, 17 leading to incorrect 
staging of disease severity and, consequently, inadequate 
treatment. 6 Corticosteroid use might hamper wound 
healing as well through its anti-inflammatory effects, by 
suppressing cellular wound responses and by inducing 
diabetes, and thus increasing the risk of wound infec-
tion. 18 A systematic review also showed that corticoster-
oid use may increase the risk of anastomotic leakage 
after colorectal surgery. 19 Use of corticosteroids is asso-
ciated with an increased risk of venous thromboembol-
ism. 20 In perforated diverticulitis, undiagnosed and 
untreated adrenal insufficiency may lead to an 
Addisonian crisis, which increases mortality risk in 
affected patients. 21 </p>

<p>Study aims 
The primary aim of this study was to examine absolute 
mortality risks and compare 7-day, 1-month, 3-month 
and 1-year mortality rates in patients with perforated 
diverticular disease who were corticosteroid users versus 
non-users. The secondary aim was to examine mortality 
rates in patients with perforated diverticular disease who 
used corticosteroids administered in different forms and 
with different cumulative doses. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Source population 
The source population for this study was the entire 
population of Denmark (5 289 261 inhabitants) between 
2005 and 2013. The study period began in 2005 because 
a full record of medications sold at community pharma-
cies and hospital-based outpatient pharmacies became 
available starting in 2004 in the National Health Service 
Prescription Database. 22 The study was based on data from 
the Danish National Patient Registry, which has recorded 
all acute care hospital discharges since 1977 and all out-
patient specialist clinic and emergency room visits since 
1995. 23 Data from the Danish Civil Registration System were 
used to determine vital status. 24 </p>

<p>Study population and follow-up 
The study included all adult patients (≥18 years), with 
and without use of corticosteroids, hospitalised with 
incident perforated diverticular disease between 
2005 and 2013. Identification of perforated and 
non-perforated diverticular disease was based on 
International Classification of Diseases (ICD) codes (see 
online supplementary appendix 1 for specification of the 
codes). The codes used for perforated diverticular 
disease have a positive predictive value ranging from 0.73 
to 0.75. 25 There were no restrictions in corticosteroid 
dose or treatment duration. Patients diagnosed during an 
emergency room visit were excluded because of the low 
predictive value of emergency room diagnoses; diagnostic 
accuracy improves with more extensive diagnostic proce-
dures. 26 The year 2005 as start of follow-up was chosen in 
order to provide a 1-year prediagnosis period in which 
exposure to corticosteroids could be assessed similarly in 
all patients. Patient follow-up began on the hospital 
admission date for perforated diverticular disease and 
ended on death, emigration or end of follow-up on 30 
November 2013, whichever came first. </p>

<p>Classification of corticosteroid use and surgical 
procedures 
Corticosteroid use was categorised as follows, based on 
the National Health Service Prescription Database: 22 
I. Non-users: patients not prescribed corticosteroids 
during the year prior to hospital admission. 
II. Current users: patients using corticosteroids at time of 
admission, that is, the last prescription for corticoster-
oids was filled during the 90 days before admission. The 
group of current users was subdivided into new users, 
defined as patients who filled their first prescription 
≤90 days before admission, and chronic users, which 
included all other current users. 
III. Recent users: patients who used corticosteroids until 
shortly before admission, that is, their last corticosteroid 
prescription was filled between 91 and 365 days before 
admission. 
Analyses were performed separately for patients using 
systemic corticosteroids regardless of use of other forms 
of corticosteroids, for patients using systemic corticoster-
oids only, for patients using inhaled corticosteroids only, 
and for patients using intestinal acting corticosteroids 
only. There was one patient using both inhaled and 
intestinal acting corticosteroids. 
The analysis of cumulative dose was based on categor-
ising the 1-year cumulative dose of systemic corticoster-
oids among current users, calculated using prednisone 
dose equivalents. The cumulative dose cut-offs were 
≤625, &gt;625 to 2000, &gt;2000 to 3500 and &gt;3500 mg, to 
provide four groups of approximately equal size. 
Surgical procedures related to diverticular perfor-
ation (including a 30-day period around date of admis-
sion for diverticular disease) were categorised as 
explorative surgery including lavage; stoma with or 
without resection; and resections with primary </p>



<p>Broersen LHA, Horváth-Puhó E, Pereira AM, et al. BMJ Open Gastro 2017;4:e000136. doi:10.1136/bmjgast-2017-000136 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>anastomosis (see online supplementary appendix 2 for 
surgical codes). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Descriptive contingency tables were prepared, showing 
demographic characteristics and medical history (age, sex, 
calendar year of perforated diverticular disease diagnosis, 
comorbidities) of corticosteroid users and non-users. 
For time-to-event analyses, the Kaplan-Meier method 
and Cox regression were used. Absolute mortality risks 
in corticosteroid users and non-users were calculated 
using the Kaplan-Meier method. Cox proportional 
hazard regression was used to compare mortality rates 
among the predefined categories of corticosteroid users, 
providing HRs for 7-day, 1-month, 3-month and 1-year 
mortality. Stratified analyses were performed according 
to type of surgery within 30 days before or after diagno-
sis of perforated diverticular disease. 
Subgroup analyses were performed to compare mortal-
ity risks among patients taking different forms of corticos-
teroids (inhaled only, intestinal only and systemic only) 
and with different 1-year cumulative doses of systemic cor-
ticosteroid use. Also, sensitivity analyses were performed 
after excluding patients with malignancies, patients with 
inflammatory bowel disease, patients with a previous 
code for diverticular disease and patients with rheumatic 
diseases including mixed connective tissue disease. 
In addition to crude analyses, we performed adjusted 
analyses including the following potential confounders: 
age, sex, use of cardiovascular medications (anticoagulants, 
non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, ACE/angiotensin 2 
receptor (A2R) inhibitors, statins, β blockers, calcium 
channel blockers, diuretics, selective serotonin reuptake 
inhibitors (SSRIs) and nitrates) 16 during the 90 days 
before admission, hypertension, chronic obstructive 
pulmonary disease (COPD; as a proxy for smoking), liver 
disease or chronic pancreatitis, alcoholism-related diseases 
other than those affecting the liver or pancreas, inflamma-
tory bowel disease, rheumatoid arthritis, connective 
tissue disease, malignancies and modified Charlson 
Comorbidity Index score (see online supplementary 
appendix 1 for specification of the codes). The modified 
Charlson Comorbidity Index score was calculated after 
exclusion of COPD, liver diseases, connective tissue disease 
and malignancies. These characteristics and conditions are 
associated with corticosteroid use and constitute potential 
risk factors for mortality. 
We used <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, North 
Carolina, USA) for our statistical analyses. Permission 
from the Danish Data Protection Board was granted. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Study population 
A total of 4640 patients with perforated diverticular 
disease were included in the study. Of these, 3743 
(80.7%) had not used corticosteroids in the year before 
hospital admission (table 1). Of the 897 patients using </p>

<p>corticosteroids in the prior year, 725 (80.8%) were 
exposed to systemic corticosteroid treatment (current 
and recent users combined). Of systemic corticosteroid 
users, 88.8% used prednisone or prednisolone, 6.9% 
methylprednisolone, 13.4% β-methasone, 1.5% triamci-
nolone and 1.0% hydrocortisone. Since the number of 
patients using only intestinal acting corticosteroids was 
small (n=28), this patient group was not analysed 
further. Corticosteroid users were on average older than 
non-users and more often female than non-users (64.8% 
vs 54.2%). Patients using systemic corticosteroids were 
more often hypertensive, more often had COPD, 
chronic bronchitis, emphysema or asthma, and more 
often had malignancies, rheumatoid arthritis, connective 
tissue disease or inflammatory bowel disease. Almost all 
patients using only inhaled corticosteroids had a diagno-
sis of COPD, chronic bronchitis, emphysema or asthma, 
but were otherwise comparable to non-users. Charlson 
Comorbidity Index scores were higher for all groups of 
corticosteroid users compared with non-users. </p>

<p>Mortality risk in patients with perforated colonic 
diverticular disease 
A total of 889 patients (19.2%) with perforated diverticu-
litis died within 1 year following their diagnosis (table 2). 
Mortality risk in non-users of corticosteroids was 4.4% 
after 7 days, 8.8% after 30 days, 11.9% after 90 days and 
15.6% after 1 year. This risk was doubled for current 
users of corticosteroids (adjusted HRs ranging from 1.96 
(30-day mortality) to 2.10 (7-day mortality)), with mortal-
ity risks reaching 14.2% after 7 days and 47.6% after 
1 year (figure 1). Mortality risk was even higher for new 
corticosteroid users, increasing from 15.7% 7 days post-
diagnosis to 52.5% after 1 year. Among chronic cortico-
steroid users, mortality risks also were almost doubled, 
with adjusted HRs of 1.89 after 7 days and 1.74 after 
1 year, and absolute mortality risks reaching 13.7% after 
7 days and 45.9% after 1 year. </p>

<p>Mortality risk according to 1-year cumulative dose 
In our study population, 124 patients had a 1-year cumu-
lative dose ≤625 mg, 144 patients had a 1-year cumula-
tive dose &gt;625-2000 mg, 140 patients had a 1-year 
cumulative dose &gt;2000-3500 mg and 86 patients had a 
1-year cumulative dose &gt;3500 mg (table 3). A higher 
1-year cumulative dose was not clearly associated with 
higher mortality risk in patients with perforated diver-
ticular disease. </p>

<p>Abdominal surgical procedures 
In total, 2497 (53.8%) of 4640 patients had a 
diverticulitis-related surgical procedure (table 1). The 
percentage of patients with surgery within 30 days before 
or after incident perforated diverticular disease was 
higher among systemic corticosteroid users (62.9%) 
compared with users of inhalation corticosteroids only 
(56.6%) and non-users (52.1%). Patients using systemic 
corticosteroids had a surgical procedure resulting in a </p>

<p>Broersen LHA, Horváth-Puhó E, Pereira AM, et al. BMJ Open Gastro 2017;4:e000136. doi:10.1136/bmjgast-2017-000136 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>stoma (33.8%) more often than patients not using corti-
costeroids (22.6%). 
Within categories of surgery (explorative surgery 
including lavage, stoma, resection with primary anasto-
mosis), mortality risk was increased when comparing 
current users to non-users. After explorative surgery, 
mortality risk after 1 year was 14.8% for non-users and 
43.5% for current users (adjusted HR 1.12 (95% CI 0.69 
to 1.83)). For patients who received a stoma, mortality 
risk after 1 year was 26.5% for non-users and 48.8% 
for current users (adjusted HR 1.37 (95% CI 1.03 to 
1.82)). After a resection with primary anastomosis, 
mortality risk after 1 year was 15.2% for non-users 
and 54.1% for current users (adjusted HR 2.88 (95% 
CI 1.57 to 5.28)). </p>

<p>Subgroup and sensitivity analyses 
The mortality risk among patients currently using sys-
temic corticosteroids only (13.9% after 7 days and 48.0% 
after 1 year) was comparable to that among patients 
using systemic corticosteroids regardless of other cortico-
steroid use (figure 2). Compared with non-users, 
patients who currently used only inhaled corticosteroids 
also had an increased mortality risk (6.2% after 7 days 
and 22.3% after 1 year), with an adjusted HR ranging 
from 1.44 to 1.85 (table 4). 
When we excluded patients with malignancies, inflam-
matory bowel disease, a previous code for diverticular 
disease, or rheumatic diseases including mixed connect-
ive tissue disease, the results of the analysis of current 
users of systemic corticosteroids regardless of use of </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline characteristics of corticosteroid users and non-users among patients with perforated diverticular disease </p>

<p>Non-use </p>

<p>Systemic use 
regardless of 
other uses </p>

<p>Systemic use 
only </p>

<p>Inhaled use 
only 
N 
Per cent 
N 
Per cent 
N 
Per cent 
N 
Per cent </p>

<p>Total 
3743 
100.0 
725 
100.0 
656 
100.0 
145 
100.0 
Current use 
− 
− 
494 
68.1 
446 
68.0 
81 
55.9 
New use 
− 
− 
121 
16.7 
109 
16.6 
7 
4.8 
Chronic use 
− 
− 
373 
51.4 
337 
51.4 
74 
51.1 
Recent use 
− 
− 
231 
31.9 
210 
32.0 
64 
44.1 
Age, years 
18-59 
1431 
38.2 
119 
16.4 
113 
17.2 
42 
29.0 
60-69 
860 
23.0 
146 
20.1 
133 
20.3 
37 
25.5 
70-79 
777 
20.8 
239 
33.0 
213 
32.5 
41 
28.3 
80+ 
675 
18.0 
221 
30.5 
197 
30.0 
25 
17.2 
Gender (male) 
1713 
45.8 
256 
35.3 
232 
35.4 
56 
38.6 
Calendar year of perforated diverticular disease diagnosis 
2005-2008 
1556 
41.6 
328 
45.2 
294 
44.8 
60 
41.4 
2009-2013 
2187 
58.4 
397 
54.8 
362 
55.2 
85 
58.6 
Comorbidities 
Diverticular disease of the colon without 
perforation </p>

<p>897 
24.0 
173 
23.9 
151 
23.0 
36 
24.8 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
844 
22.5 
263 
36.3 
247 
37.7 
39 
26.9 
COPD, chronic bronchitis, emphysema 
and asthma </p>

<p>682 
18.2 
334 
46.1 
278 
42.4 
137 
94.5 </p>

<p>Liver disease and/or chronic pancreatitis 
111 
3.0 
25 
3.4 
24 
3.7 
5 
3.4 
Alcoholism-related diseases other than 
those affecting the liver or pancreas </p>

<p>310 
8.3 
42 
5.8 
38 
5.8 
13 
9.0 </p>

<p>Cancer 
503 
13.4 
201 
27.7 
189 
28.8 
19 
13.1 
Rheumatoid arthritis/connective tissue 
disease </p>

<p>138 
3.7 
200 
27.6 
186 
28.4 
4 
2.8 </p>

<p>Inflammatory bowel disease 
71 
1.9 
40 
5.5 
32 
4.9 
4 
2.8 
Charlson Comorbidity Index score 
0 
2659 
71.0 
371 
51.2 
334 
50.9 
99 
68.3 
1-2 
888 
23.7 
261 
36.0 
241 
36.7 
36 
24.8 
≥3 
196 
5.2 
93 
12.8 
81 
12.3 
10 
6.9 
Surgery within 30 days before or after 
diagnosis of diverticulitis (total) </p>

<p>1949 
52.1 
456 
62.9 
425 
64.8 
82 
56.6 </p>

<p>Explorative surgery including lavage 
616 
16.5 
115 
15.9 
108 
16.5 
24 
16.6 
Stoma 
845 
22.6 
245 
33.8 
228 
34.8 
38 
26.2 
Resection with primary anastomosis 
488 
13.0 
96 
13.2 
89 
13.6 
20 
13.8 </p>

<p>COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. </p>



<p>Broersen LHA, Horváth-Puhó E, Pereira AM, et al. BMJ Open Gastro 2017;4:e000136. doi:10.1136/bmjgast-2017-000136 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>other corticosteroids did not materially change for mor-
tality risk after 7, 30, 90 days or 1 year. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
We examined mortality risks between corticosteroid 
users and non-users among patients with perforated </p>

<p>diverticular disease. One-year mortality risk for current 
users of corticosteroids was 47.6%, double that of 
non-users after adjustment for confounders. One-year 
mortality risk was even higher for new corticosteroid 
users: 52.5%. Thus, corticosteroid use was clearly asso-
ciated with an increased mortality risk for patients with 
perforated diverticular disease, continuing until at least 
1 year after diagnosis, regardless of corticosteroid dose. 
This is the first large cohort study comparing mortality 
risks between corticosteroid users and non-users among 
patients with perforated diverticular disease. The advan-
tage of the cohort approach is the ability to calculate 
absolute mortality risks, which can inform clinical prac-
tice. Our study showed that corticosteroid use is a strong 
indicator for 1-year mortality. An earlier study of patients 
with perforated peptic ulcer disease reported a 30-day 
mortality ratio of 2.1 after corticosteroid use. 27 This is in 
line with the increased mortality risk (adjusted HR of 
1.96 for 30-day mortality) that we found among current 
users of systemic corticosteroids in the present study. 
The following study limitations need to be taken into 
account in interpreting our results. Determination of 
exposure was based on redeemed prescriptions, which 
may not always coincide completely with medication 
taken by patients. 28 We also did not consider use of cor-
ticosteroids for longer than a year before hospital admis-
sion. Also, since prednisolone and prednisone were the 
most frequently used systemic steroids (89%), the results 
in first line apply to this patient category; whether our </p>

<p>Table 2 Mortality among patients with systemic corticosteroid use, regardless of use of intestinal acting or inhaled 
corticosteroids compared with non-use </p>

<p>Corticosteroid use 
Period </p>

<p>Absolute risk 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Rate per 1000 PYRs 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Crude HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Adjusted HR* 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Non-use 
7 days 
4.4 (3.8 to 5.1) 
6.46 (5.47 to 7.44) 
30 days 
8.8 (7.9 to 9.7) 
3.12 (2.78 to 3.45) 
90 days 
11.9 (10.9 to 12.9) 
1.46 (1.33 to 1.60) 
1 year 
15.6 (14.4 to 16.8) 
0.51 (0.47 to 0.55) 
Current use 
7 days 
14.2 (11.4 to 17.6) 
21.81 (16.70 to 26.92) 
3.38 (2.56 to 4.47) 
2.10 (1.52 to 2.90) 
30 days 
27.9 (24.2 to 32.1) 
11.53 (9.60 to 13.45) 
3.56 (2.92 to 4.35) 
1.96 (1.56 to 2.47) 
90 days 
36.6 (32.5 to 41.0) 
5.71 (4.87 to 6.54) 
3.59 (3.02 to 4.27) 
1.97 (1.62 to 2.41) 
1 year 
47.6 (43.2 to 52.1) 
2.22 (1.93 to 2.50) 
3.75 (3.22 to 4.38) 
2.05 (1.72 to 2.45) 
New use 
7 days 
15.7 (10.3 to 23.5) 
24.20 (13.32 to 35.09) 
3.75 (2.33 to 6.03) 
2.88 (1.77 to 4.70) 
30 days 
31.4 (23.9 to 40.5) 
13.46 (9.18 to 17.73) 
4.09 (2.92 to 5.73) 
2.72 (1.92 to 3.85) 
90 days 
46.3 (37.9 to 55.6) 
7.87 (5.81 to 9.93) 
4.75 (3.60 to 6.28) 
3.06 (2.29 to 4.09) 
1 year 
52.5 (43.9 to 61.7) 
2.83 (2.13 to 3.53) 
4.43 (3.41 to 5.75) 
2.89 (2.21 to 3.79) 
Chronic use 
7 days 
13.7 (10.6 to 17.6) 
21.04 (15.27 to 26.81) 
3.26 (2.38 to 4.46) 
1.89 (1.30 to 2.74) 
30 days 
26.8 (22.6 to 31.6) 
10.93 (8.79 to 13.07) 
3.40 (2.71 to 4.25) 
1.68 (1.29 to 2.19) 
90 days 
33.4 (28.8 to 38.4) 
5.08 (4.18 to 5.97) 
3.23 (2.65 to 3.94) 
1.58 (1.25 to 2.00) 
1 year 
45.9 (40.9 to 51.2) 
2.05 (1.74 to 2.36) 
3.54 (2.98 to 4.21) 
1.74 (1.42 to 2.14) 
Recent use 
7 days 
6.1 (3.6 to 10.0) 
8.97 (4.27 to 13.67) 
1.39 (0.81 to 2.40) 
1.11 (0.63 to 1.95) 
30 days 
13.9 (10.0 to 19.1) 
5.12 (3.34 to 6.89) 
1.63 (1.13 to 2.34) 
1.15 (0.79 to 1.68) 
90 days 
19.2 (14.7 to 24.9) 
2.53 (1.78 to 3.28) 
1.68 (1.24 to 2.30) 
1.17 (0.84 to 1.61) 
1 year 
26.3 (21.0 to 32.6) 
0.95 (0.71 to 1.20) 
1.78 (1.36 to 2.33) 
1.23 (0.93 to 1.63) </p>

<p>*HR adjusted for age, sex, use of cardiovascular medication, hypertension, COPD, liver disease or chronic pancreatitis, alcoholism-related 
diseases other than those affecting the liver or pancreas, inflammatory bowel disease, rheumatoid arthritis, connective tissue disease, 
malignancies and modified Charlson Comorbidity Index score. 
COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; PYR, person year. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Cumulative mortality in patients with systemic 
corticosteroid use, regardless of other use. </p>

<p>Broersen LHA, Horváth-Puhó E, Pereira AM, et al. BMJ Open Gastro 2017;4:e000136. doi:10.1136/bmjgast-2017-000136 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>results also apply to patients using steroids with high first 
pass metabolism needs further study. Finally, perforated 
diverticular disease may be misclassified, 6 17 as the sensi-
tivity of relevant ICD codes is not 100% accurate. Since </p>

<p>misclassification is probably more likely in corticosteroid 
users (due to blinding of symptoms and severity of the 
condition), mortality risk is potentially overestimated if 
less severe cases in corticosteroid users go undetected. 25 
However, in analyses stratified by type of surgery, which 
most likely harmonises the diagnostic category, a similar 
increased risk was found. 
The central causal question is whether increased mor-
tality risk in corticosteroid users is actually caused by cor-
ticosteroid use prior to diagnosis. Clinical arguments 
underlying the rationale for a causal association are 
masked disease severity, 17 impaired wound healing and 
increased infection risk, 18 increased risk of venous 
thromboembolism 20 and unrecognised adrenal insuffi-
ciency. 29 The risk was doubled for corticosteroid users in 
our fully adjusted statistical model, but residual con-
founding (no perfectly valid data on actual disease 
severity status) might still be an issue. For instance, high 
mortality among patients using corticosteroids may be 
explained partially by the underlying diseases for which 
corticosteroids were prescribed. However, our subgroup 
analyses showed no clear differences when high-risk sub-
groups were excluded. Regardless of the causal question, 
our study indicated that corticosteroid use was an 
important prognostic factor for mortality. 
Two explanations are possible for the lack of an associ-
ation observed between mortality risk and dose. First, 
the risk may be associated with corticosteroid use per se, </p>

<p>Table 3 Mortality among patients with current use of systemic corticosteroids, regardless of other corticosteroid use, 
according to 1-year cumulative dose compared with non-use </p>

<p>Cumulative dose of 
corticosteroids* 
Period </p>

<p>Absolute risk 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Rate per 1000 PYRs 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Crude HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Adjusted HR † 
(95% CI) </p>



<p>Figure 2 Cumulative mortality in patients with systemic use 
of corticosteroids only. </p>



<p>Broersen LHA, Horváth-Puhó E, Pereira AM, et al. BMJ Open Gastro 2017;4:e000136. doi:10.1136/bmjgast-2017-000136 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>so that the maximum increase in risk is already reached 
at a low (but still supraphysiological) dose. Second, our 
classification did not distinguish between short-term, 
high-dose corticosteroid use and long-term, low-dose 
use, because the prescription database used does not 
provide certainty whether a drug is prescribed in high 
doses for short-term use, or in lower doses for longer 
duration. Although clinically short-term, high-dose cor-
ticosteroid use and long-term, low-dose corticosteroid 
use are very heterogeneous groups of patients, in our 
analysis according to dose, both translate into the same 
1-year cumulative dose. 
In conclusion, this study demonstrated that corticoster-
oid use was associated with increased mortality risk after 
diagnosis of perforated diverticular disease. Clinically, 
use of systemic corticosteroids should be regarded as an 
important risk marker for mortality among patients with 
this disease. </p>

<p>Contributors All authors contributed to the development of the study protocol 
and read and approved the final manuscript. EH-P extracted the data from the 
National Health Service Prescription Database and the Danish National Patient 
Registry, and performed the statistical analyses. LHAB first analysed the rough 
data from the statistical analyses and summarised their implications in this 
article. AMP related the implications to the endocrinology practice, whereas 
RE did the same for the gastroenterology practice. OMD paid attention to the 
epidemiological correctness of the implications that were made. HTS 
managed the entire research process and checked the final version of the 
article for completeness. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>

<p>Table 4 Mortality among current corticosteroid users: subgroup and sensitivity analyses compared with non-use </p>

<p>Restrictions 
Period </p>

<p>Absolute risk 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Rate per 1000 PYRs 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Crude HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Adjusted HR* 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Non-use 
7 days 4.4 (3.8 to 5.1) 
6.46 (5.47 to 7.44) 
30 days 8.8 (7.9 to 9.7) 
3.12 (2.78 to 3.45) 
90 days 11.9 (10.9 to 12.9) 
1.46 (1.33 to 1.60) 
1 year 15.6 (14.4 to 16.8) 
0.51 (0.47 to 0.55) 
Inhaled only 
7 days 6.2 (2.6 to 14.2) 
9.16 (1.13 to 17.18) 
1.42 (0.58 to 3.45) 1.55 (0.60 to 3.97) 
30 days 17.3 (10.6 to 27.4) 
6.46 (3.08 to 9.84) 
2.04 (1.20 to 3.49) 1.85 (1.04 to 3.27) 
90 days 21.0 (13.6 to 31.6) 
2.83 (1.48 to 4.17) 
1.87 (1.15 to 3.04) 1.72 (1.03 to 2.89) 
1 year 22.3 (14.7 to 33.0) 
0.79 (0.43 to 1.16) 
1.54 (0.96 to 2.46) 1.44 (0.88 to 2.37) 
Systemic use only 
7 days 13.9 (11.0 to 17.5) 21.30 (16.00 to 26.60) 3.30 (2.47 to 4.42) 2.02 (1.44 to 2.82) 
30 days 28.0 (24.1 to 32.5) 11.53 (9.51 to 13.55) 
3.56 (2.90 to 4.38) 1.96 (1.55 to 2.48) 
90 days 36.0 (31.7 to 40.7) 
5.60 (4.73 to 6.47) 
3.52 (2.94 to 4.22) 1.92 (1.56 to 2.36) 
1 year 48.0 (43.4 to 52.8) 
2.23 (1.93 to 2.53) 
3.77 (3.22 to 4.42) 2.04 (1.70 to 2.45) 
Systemic use, regardless of 
other uses </p>

<p>7 days 14.2 (11.4 to 17.6) 21.81 (16.70 to 26.92) 3.38 (2.56 to 4.47) 2.10 (1.52 to 2.90) 
30 days 27.9 (24.2 to 32.1) 11.53 (9.60 to 13.45) 
3.56 (2.92 to 4.35) 1.96 (1.56 to 2.47) 
90 days 36.6 (32.5 to 41.0) 
5.71 (4.87 to 6.54) 
3.59 (3.02 to 4.27) 1.97 (1.62 to 2.41) 
1 year 47.6 (43.2 to 52.1) 
2.22 (1.93 to 2.50) 
3.75 (3.22 to 4.38) 2.05 (1.72 to 2.45) 
Excluding patients with 
malignancies </p>

<p>7 days 14.3 (11.1 to 18.4) 21.94 (15.92 to 27.97) 4.03 (2.91 to 5.59) 2.22 (1.50 to 3.28) 
30 days 26.3 (22.1 to 31.2) 10.80 (8.62 to 12.99) 
4.04 (3.18 to 5.13) 2.00 (1.50 to 2.67) 
90 days 32.9 (28.3 to 38.0) 
5.00 (4.10 to 5.91) 
3.87 (3.13 to 4.78) 1.93 (1.50 to 2.48) 
1 year 42.3 (37.3 to 47.7) 
1.85 (1.55 to 2.15) 
3.93 (3.26 to 4.74) 2.03 (1.62 to 2.55) 
Excluding patients with 
inflammatory bowel disease </p>

<p>7 days 14.3 (11.4 to 17.8) 21.91 (16.63 to 27.20) 3.35 (2.52 to 4.46) 2.03 (1.46 to 2.83) 
30 days 28.1 (24.2 to 32.4) 11.58 (9.59 to 13.57) 
3.54 (2.89 to 4.34) 1.89 (1.49 to 2.40) 
90 days 36.6 (32.4 to 41.2) 
5.72 (4.86 to 6.59) 
3.55 (2.97 to 4.24) 1.87 (1.52 to 2.29) 
1 year 48.1 (43.6 to 52.8) 
2.25 (1.95 to 2.54) 
3.76 (3.21 to 4.39) 1.96 (1.64 to 2.36) 
Excluding patients with a 
previous code for diverticular 
disease </p>

<p>7 days 15.7 (12.4 to 19.7) 24.47 (18.28 to 30.66) 3.43 (2.53 to 4.65) 2.06 (1.45 to 2.93) 
30 days 29.8 (25.5 to 34.6) 12.57 (10.26 to 14.88) 3.66 (2.94 to 4.56) 2.03 (1.58 to 2.63) 
90 days 38.5 (33.8 to 43.6) 
6.15 (5.16 to 7.15) 
3.67 (3.03 to 4.45) 2.01 (1.61 to 2.51) 
1 year 49.3 (44.4 to 54.5) 
2.35 (2.01 to 2.68) 
3.80 (3.20 to 4.51) 2.07 (1.70 to 2.53) 
Excluding patients with 
rheumatic diseases including 
mixed connective tissue 
disease </p>





<p>Open Access </p>





<p>Broersen LHA, Horváth-Puhó E, Pereira AM, et al. BMJ Open Gastro 2017;4:e000136. doi:10.1136/bmjgast-2017-000136 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>