<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5073050" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Aim: Maintenance of the blood and extracellular volume requires tight con-
trol of endothelial macromolecule permeability, which is regulated by cAMP 
signalling. This study probes the role of the cAMP mediators rap guanine 
nucleotide exchange factor 3 and 4 (Epac1 and Epac2) for in vivo control of 
microvascular macromolecule permeability under basal conditions. 
Methods: Epac1 
À/À and Epac2 
À/À C57BL/6J mice were produced and </p>

<p>compared with wild-type mice for transvascular flux of radio-labelled 
albumin in skin, adipose tissue, intestine, heart and skeletal muscle. The 
transvascular leakage was also studied by dynamic contrast-enhanced 
magnetic resonance imaging (DCE-MRI) using the MRI contrast agent 
Gadomer-17 as probe. 
as exposure to thrombin (Cullere et al. 2005). A role 
of Epac1 and its target, the small GTPase Rap, to 
modulate inflammation-associated endothelial hyper-
permeability has been confirmed in numerous in vitro 
studies and noted in some in situ perfusion studies of 
accessible microvessels, although the relative roles of 
PKA, cGMP-dependent protein kinase (PKG) and 
Epac in different organ vascular beds and under dif-
ferent experimental conditions still remain uncertain 
(for recent reviews, see Spindler et al. 2010, Surapi-
sitchat &amp; Beavo 2011, Kuhn 2012, Curry &amp; Adam-
son 2013). 
The role of Epac to maintain stable baseline perme-
ability in intact microvessels under non-inflammatory 
conditions is less well studied. A major reason is the 
lack of ways to reliably inhibit Epac and other cAMP-
dependent pathways pharmacologically in vivo (Spind-
ler &amp; Waschke 2011), in part due to rapid metabolism 
and renal clearance of cAMP analogues used to modu-
late Epac and PKA activity (Kleppe et al. 2015). 
In this study, Epac-deficient mice (Epac1 
À/À or </p>

<p>Epac2 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>) were generated to elucidate the potential 
in vivo role of Epac in regulation of baseline macro-
molecule flux across microvascular endothelium. 
Others have reported that Epac1 
À/À and Epac2 
À/À mice </p>

<p>have only subtle phenotypes. Epac2 
À/À mice have a </p>

<p>slightly perturbed pathway of pancreatic beta cell insu-
lin exocytosis (Shibasaki et al. 2007), while Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>mice have been reported to gain slightly more (Kai et al. 
2013) or slightly less (Yan et al. 2013) body weight on 
both low-and high-fat diets, and be less susceptible to 
rickettsial invasion (Gong et al. 2013). 
We report here an increased basal microvascular 
transvascular albumin flux in skin, skeletal muscle and 
intestines of Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>, but not Epac2 
À/À mice. </p>

<p>Dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imag-
ing (DCE-MRI) studies of the masseter muscle using 
Gadomer-17 demonstrated transvascular flux of the 
high molecular weight MR contrast agent, which con-
firmed that Epac1 
À/À mice had constitutively increased </p>

<p>microvascular permeability to macromolecules. Trans-
mission electron microscopy was used to compare the 
ultrastructure of the endothelial junctions in masseter 
muscle biopsies from basal state in Wt and Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>mice. They revealed decrease of junctional complex in 
the interendothelial slits from Epac1 
À/À mice. </p>

<p>To evaluate further whether Epac1 and/or Epac2 
contributed to the regulation of vascular permeability 
under physiological conditions, we tested the response 
of microvessels to the naturally circulating atrial natri-
uretic peptide (ANP) in Wt, Epac1 
À/À and Epac2 
À/À mice. </p>

<p>ANP is released when plasma volume is expanded and 
increases vascular permeability to albumin as part of 
the normal control of plasma volume. We and others 
have demonstrated this action in Wt mice (Curry </p>

<p>et al. 2010, Lin et al. 2011), and also shown that it is 
attenuated when cAMP is elevated, and proposed that 
ANP might increase permeability via decreased Epac 
activity (Lin et al. 2011). We show here that Epac1-
deficient mice, but not Epac2-deficient mice have an 
attenuated response to ANP. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Ethical approval </p>

<p>The animal experiments were approved by the Norwe-
gian Animal Research Authority and conducted accord-
ing to the European Convention for the Protection of 
Vertebrates Used for Scientific Purposes, Norway. </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>The anti-Epac1 antibody was kindly provided by 
J. Bos, University of Utrecht, the Netherlands. The 
anti-Epac2 antibody (5B1) was from Cell Signaling 
technology (www.cellsignal.com). The anti-CD31 anti-
body (DIA-310) was from Dianova, Hamburg, Ger-
many. ANP and rolipram were from Sigma-Aldrich 
(St. Louis, MO, USA). Gadomer-17 was from in vivo 
Contrast GmbH, Schering Pharma (Berlin, Germany). 
Human serum albumin (HSA) was labelled with </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>I 
or </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I (from Perkin Elmer, Waltham, MA, USA) by 
the iodogen method, as previously described (Curry 
et al. 2010). Any free iodide was removed by spinning 
twice on a 3-kDa cut-off column (Microcon filter; 
Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA) prior to experiments. 
The labelled HSA eluted like native HSA upon anionic 
exchange and high-resolution size exclusion chro-
matography with online gamma radiation detection in 
series with UV detector. Low molecular weight 
radioactivity accounted for &lt;0.3% of the total activity. </p>

<p>Generation of Epac1 
À/À and Epac2 
À/À knock-out </p>

<p>models. Epac1 
À/À and Epac2 
À/À mice were generated </p>

<p>by genomic deletion of exons 7-10 in Rapgef3 (encod-
ing Epac1) and exons 12-13 of Rapgef4 (encoding 
Epac2) encoding the cAMP-binding domains of both 
proteins (Fig. 1a,d) by use of the Cre-LoxP system. An 
additional frame shift codon was introduced in exon 
11 in Rapgef3 resulting in a stop codon at the start of 
exon 11 (Fig. 1a). Heterozygous floxed Rapgef3 and 
Rapgef4 mice were generated at the Mouse Clinical 
Institute, Strasbourg, France, and subsequently crossed 
with C57BL/6J mice expressing CRE recombinase 
from the CMV promoter resulting in global deletion of 
Epac1 and Epac 2 expression, as confirmed by 
immunoblotting and RT-PCR (Fig. 1b,c,e). C57BL/ 
6JBomTac mice from Taconic, Denmark, were used to 
backcross the recombined chimeric mice for at least 10 </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Acta Physiologica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of 
Scandinavian Physiological Society, doi: 10.1111/apha.12697 </p>

<p>442 </p>

<p>Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice · R K Kopperud et al. </p>

<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

<p>generations. The origin of the C57BL/6JBomTac mice 
is described at http://www.taconic.com/wmspage.cfm? 
parm1=764. </p>

<p>Genotyping </p>

<p>For genotyping, DNA was extracted from one 
1.5-mm-diameter ear punch according to Truett et al. </p>

<p>(2000). The deletion of exon 7-10 in Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>and exon 
12-13 in Epac2 
À/À was confirmed by PCR (Qiagen, </p>

<p>Hilden, Germany; Multiplex PCR Kit, Cat.No: 
206143) using primers P1-P3 and P4-P6 respectively. 
P1, CAC-AGA-CAG-TGC-TTA-GCA-CAG-TGC; P2, 
CAC-CTC-TCT-TCC-CAA-ACC-TAG-AGC-C; P3, 
GCC-CCA-AGG-CTG-CTG-ATC-CC; P4, TGA-AT 
T-ATG-GGG-GAA-CGC-ACT-TTC-C; P5, GTG-TGG </p>

<p>Figure 1 Generation of the Epac1 
À/À and Epac2 
À/À mouse strains. (a) The Epac1 (Rapgef3) gene targeting construct and dele-</p>

<p>tion strategy. (b) Anti-Epac1 immunoblots showing lack of Epac1 protein in Epac1 
À/À mouse tissue and decreased expression in </p>

<p>Epac1 
À/+ compared to Wt tissue. (c) PCR genotyping demonstrates the sizes of PCR products predicted for the Epac1 deletion </p>

<p>(see Methods for details; WAT is white adipose tissue). (d) The Epac2 (Rapgef4) gene targeting construct and the deletion strat-
egy. The deletion includes the functional cAMP-binding domain common for all known Epac2 isoforms. (e) Anti-Epac2 immu-
noblots showing lack of Epac2 protein in Epac2 
À/À mouse organs (brain, adrenal cortex) with high expression of Epac2. (f) </p>

<p>PCR genotyping validation of the deletion. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Acta Physiologica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of 
Scandinavian Physiological Society, doi: 10.1111/apha.12697 </p>

<p>443 </p>

<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

<p>R K Kopperud et al. · Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice </p>

<p>-TGC-TAT-GAA-ATT-GGT-TCC-GTT-G; P6, TGC-C 
TC-CAT-TGT-TCT-TCG-GG. 
The PCR was for 30 cycles of 94°C (each 30 s), 
63°C (Epac1) or 60°C (Epac2) for 90 s, 72°C for 
90 s, and finally 72°C for 10 min. For Epac1, the pre-
dicted size of the &lt;1000 bp PCR product is 525 bp for 
Wt and 315 bp for Epac1 
À/À tissue (P1-P3). For Epac2, </p>

<p>it is 495 bp for Wt and 332 for Epac2 
À/À tissue (P4-P6). </p>

<p>Immuno (Western) blotting </p>

<p>Immunoblotting was performed essentially as descri-
bed elsewhere (Gausdal et al. 2004). The membra-
nes were probed with either mouse monoclonal 
anti-Epac1 or mouse monoclonal anti-Epac2. Bands 
representing the proteins of interest were detected 
using alkaline phosphatase-conjugated secondary anti-
bodies and CDP-Star substrate (Tropix, Bedford, 
MA, USA) and band intensity determined in a Fuji 
LAS3000 (Fuji Photo Film, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Animal experiments </p>

<p>General. Artificial lighting was maintained on a 
12 : 12-h light-dark cycle. Room temperature was 
kept constant at 23°C, and the animals were provided 
with water and rodent chow ad libitum. The mice were 
12-16 weeks old when used for experiments, the ratio 
of female to male mice being about one (0.8-1.2). The 
weight range was 20-25 g for the female and 25-30 g 
for the male mice. All experimental procedures were 
performed while animals were anesthetized using 3.5% 
isoflurane (Isoba vet; Schering-Plough Animal Health, 
Uxbridge, UK) and maintained with 1.5-2% isoflurane 
in air. The anaesthesia was supplied via a nose cone. 
During anaesthesia, the body temperature, and in the 
case of MRI, also the respiration rate was monitored 
continuously and kept stable during the experiments. A 
single catheter was placed in a tail vein (MRI) or the 
jugular vein (two-tracer method) for infusions. </p>

<p>Determination of arterial blood pressure. Arterial 
blood pressure (BP) was measured in five Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>and six wild-type mice by the tail-cuff method follow-
ing the instructions of the manufacturer (CODA5; 
Kent Scientific, Torrington, CT, USA). Briefly, the 
mice were pre-warmed in an incubator at 32°C for 
30-45 min and then transferred to a tube for measur-
ing the BP. The tubes were placed on a heating pad to 
keep the mice warm. The warming prevents tail vessel 
vasoconstriction and ensures optimal vasodilation for 
the blood pressure determination. Measurement of 
blood pressure was performed in five cycles, each 
20 s. Each mouse was trained on day 1, and the blood 
pressure measured each of the two following days. </p>

<p>Determination plasma albumin and total protein con-
centration. Blood (20 lL) from the facial vein of live 
mice was drawn into syringes coated with acid-
citrate-dextrose solution. The blood was centrifuged 
at 150 g for 4 min, and the resulting platelet-rich 
plasma centrifuged at 1000 g for another 5 min. The 
plasma concentration of albumin and total plasma 
protein was compared in Wt and Epac 
À/À mice using </p>

<p>a label-free proteomic method as described elsewhere 
(Haslene-Hox et al. 2011). </p>

<p>The two-tracer method for determination of intact 
mouse tissue albumin clearance </p>

<p>The two-tracer method (Curry et al. 2010) was used to 
determine albumin clearance. The method depends on 
the sequential infusion of </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I-HSA and 
131 I-HSA. It </p>

<p>has been validated for determination of albumin leak-
age in Wt mice and explained in detail in (Curry et al. 
2010). In brief, 
125 I-HSA (0.1 MBq) was given i.v. over </p>

<p>30 s in 0.05 mL of saline. Thirty minutes thereafter, 
131 I-HSA (0.05 MBq) was injected (also i.v. in </p>

<p>0.05 mL of saline over 30 s). Five minutes thereafter, 
cardiac blood was withdrawn for plasma sampling, 
and the mice were killed by i.v. injection of saturated 
KCl. Tissue samples were rapidly dissected from back 
skin (four samples: left and right upper and lower 
quadrant), skeletal muscle (quadriceps), heart, small 
intestine (jejunum), large intestine (colon) and adipose 
tissue (inguinal white fat). The tissues and plasma sam-
ples were transferred to pre-weighed vials, which were 
sealed and immediately reweighed. After determination 
of radioactivity, the tissue samples were de-sealed and 
evaporated in a drying chamber at 60°C. The vials 
were weighed repeatedly until stable weight (normally 
after 2-3 weeks) was reached. The radioactivity was 
determined in a gamma-counting system (LKB Wallac 
1285, Turku, Finland). Spillover from 
131 I to 
125 I was </p>

<p>corrected automatically. Blood-to-tissue clearance was 
estimated as the extravascular plasma equivalent vol-
ume of 
125 I-HSA (counts min 
À1 per g dry tissue </p>

<p>weight)/(counts min 
À1 per mL plasma). The clearance </p>

<p>over 30 min is the difference between the plasma 
equivalent distribution volume of </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I-HSA at 35 min 
and that of </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>I-HSA at 5 min. All clearances were ref-
erenced to tissue dry weight. The clearance data were 
also normalized to clearance per unit blood volume by 
dividing clearance by the plasma volume in the sample 
to minimize effects of variable blood filling between the 
samples (see Curry &amp; Adamson 2010 for discussion). </p>

<p>DCE-MRI to determine Gadomer-17 microvascular 
clearance. Dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic reso-
nance imaging was performed to determine the clear-
ance of macromolecular tracers. The MR contrast </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Acta Physiologica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of 
Scandinavian Physiological Society, doi: 10.1111/apha.12697 </p>

<p>444 </p>

<p>Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice · R K Kopperud et al. </p>

<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

<p>agent Gadomer-17 has a molecular weight of 17 kDa, 
but due to its dendrimeric structure, its Stokes radius 
is as for globular proteins of molecular weight 
35 kDa (Misselwitz et al. 2001). The contrast agent 
was injected over 15 s during scanning through a 
catheter in the tail vein after acquisition of 30 baseline 
images. For the ANP study, 0.4 mmol Gadomer kg </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>(diluted 1 : 4 in saline) was injected. In the rolipram 
study, 0.2 mmol Gadomer kg 
À1 was injected. The </p>

<p>MRI was performed using a horizontal bore 7T small 
animal MRI instrument (PharmaScan; Bruker Corpo-
ration, Ettlingen, Germany), equipped with dedicated 
mouse bed and head coil. DCE-MRI data were 
obtained with a T1-weighted FLASH sequence (Fast 
Low Angle Shot) with a flip angle of 25°, repetition 
time and echo time of 13.77 and 2.52 ms respectively. 
A total of 600-1200 axial images through the mas-
seter muscle were acquired with a sampling interval of 
0.99 s, with a slice thickness of 1 mm, field of view of 
2.5 cm and acquisition matrix of 96 9 96. 
A separate group of animals (n = 9) was used to 
determine the signal over time in large supplying ves-
sels to the head to estimate the arterial input function 
(AIF). An oblique sagittal slice was positioned over 
the carotid arteries, and 1200 T 1 -weighted (same 
acquisition parameters as above) with a sampling 
interval of 0.99 s were acquired. The signal intensity 
over time was acquired in a region of interest of the 
internal masseter muscle using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Nordic Image Control 
and Evaluation</rs> (nICE; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Nordic Imaging Lab AS</rs>, Ber-
gen, Norway). The data were further processed using </p>

<p><rs id="software-2" type="software">MATLAB</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">The Mathworks</rs>, Natick, MA, USA) to imple-
ment the step/slope model as previously described 
(Curry et al. 2010). The rate constant (0.0063 s </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>) 
for Gadomer-17 was equal for all animals based on 
the estimation of the AIF above. The rate constants 
were estimated using blind deconvolution as previ-
ously described (Taxt et al. 2012). </p>

<p>Investigation of the effect of ANP and rolipram on 
Gadomer-17 clearance-Three series of experiments 
were performed. In the first series, 20 Epac1 
À/À and 20 </p>

<p>Wt mice were used. Ten mice in each group received 
ANP and 10 received vehicle (PBS without potassium). 
ANP (500 ng (kg BW) 
À1 min 
À1 ) or vehicle was given </p>

<p>as a 30 min continuous infusion before the Gadomer-
17 injection. The DCE-MRI experiments were per-
formed as described above. In the second series, 20 
Epac2 
À/À and 20 Wt mice were used. Again, 10 mice </p>

<p>in each group received ANP and 10 received vehicle. 
Finally, for the rolipram study, 20 Epac1 
À/À and 20 Wt </p>

<p>mice were used. Ten of the mice in each group received 
8 mg kg 
À1 BW rolipram intraperitoneally and 10 </p>

<p>received vehicle just before the Gadomer-17 injection 
and start of MR image acquisition. </p>

<p>Investigation of the effect of ANP on albumin cleara-
nce-Atrial natriuretic peptide (500 ng (kg BW) 
À1 min </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>) 
or vehicle was given as a continuous infusion for 
30 min directly after the initial </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I-HSA injection (as 
described above) to either 20 Epac1 
À/À or 20 Wt mice. </p>

<p>Transmission electron microscopy. Tissue was dis-
sected from the mice immediately after euthanasia, 
sliced into 1 mm 
3 cubes, fixed for 24 h in 1.5% glu-</p>

<p>taraldehyde in 0.1 M Na-cacodylate buffer (pH 7.4) and 
post-fixed in 1% osmium tetroxide (OsO 4 ) for 60 min. 
Dehydration was in graded alcohol solutions. After 
embedding in Agar 100 resin, ultra-thin sections were 
cut and stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate. Sec-
tions were examined in a Jeol (Tokyo, Japan) JEM-1230 
electron microscope. The sections were cut perpendicu-
lar to the long axis of the muscle fibres and their accom-
panying microvessels. The transverse microvessel 
sections were scrutinized for presence of endothelial slits 
(junctions), which were counted. High-magnification 
digital micrographs of the junctions were analysed on a 
screen for the presence and length of dense junctional 
complexes. In addition, the slit length (including any 
curvatures) and calibre (the interendothelial cell distance 
not obstructed by electron-dense material) was deter-
mined. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical staining of endothelial CD31, 
estimation of capillary density. Sections (4 lm thick) 
of paraffin-embedded masseter muscle were dewaxed, 
microwave-treated with 10 mM citric acid, pH 6.0 and 
subsequently blocked for 10 min at 25°C with 5% 
BSA and 5% normal rabbit serum in 0.05 M Tris, pH 
7.4, 0.15 M NaCl (TBS) before being immunostained 
for 18 h with anti-CD31 antibody (1 : 20 in TBS with 
1% BSA) at 4°C. The sections were next treated with 
3% H 2 O 2 in PBS for 5 min before incubation with bio-
tin-labelled secondary antibody (Biotinylated anti-rat 
IgG; Vector BA-4001) for 45 min. The immunohisto-
chemical reactions were developed using the ABC Vec-
tastain Elite staining kit (Vector Laboratories, 
Burlingame, CA, USA), based on avidin-coupled perox-
idase. The sections were counterstained with haema-
toxylin. The number of capillaries per fibre was 
estimated based on counting 300-550 capillaries from 
13 photographs of random sections from two Wt and 
two Epac1 
À/À mice. </p>

<p>Statistical methods </p>

<p>Differences between groups were tested with one-way </p>

<p>ANOVA with subsequent post hoc testing using <rs id="software-3" type="software">GRAPHPAD</rs> 
INSTAT (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, La Jolla, CA, USA). Two-
tailed t-tests were used when comparing only two 
groups. When testing ANP-effects, one-tailed testing </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Acta Physiologica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of 
Scandinavian Physiological Society, doi: 10.1111/apha.12697 </p>



<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

<p>R K Kopperud et al. · Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice </p>

<p>was used as extensive studies by others and us have 
failed to demonstrate any case when ANP decreases 
endothelial permeability. The Mann-Whitney two-
tailed U-test (http://elegans.som.vcu.edu/~leon/stats/ 
utest.html) was used to assess whether endothelial slit 
calibre or the magnitude of endothelial junctional com-
plex differed significantly between samples from Wt 
and Epac1 
À/À mice, as such data are not normally dis-</p>

<p>tributed. Values are generally given as mean AE SEM. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Verification of the Epac deletions </p>

<p>The Rapgef3 gene coding for Epac1 was silenced by a 
deletion comprising the exon coding for the cAMP-
binding domain, removing the possibility of cAMP 
regulation of any product of the disrupted Rapgef3 
gene. The deletion introduced, in addition, a missense 
mutation to avoid translation of the C-terminal part 
active site containing part of the Epac1 molecule (see 
Fig. 1a for details). Epac1 was not detected by Wes-
tern blot analysis in any tested tissue from the 
Epac1 
À/À mice. Compared with Wt mice, the expres-</p>

<p>sion was lower in Epac1 
+/À mice (Fig. 1b). The dele-</p>

<p>tion was confirmed by PCR of genomic DNA 
(Fig. 1c). 
A similar strategy (deletion of the functional cAMP-
binding domain) was used for Rapgef4 (Fig. 1d). The 
Rapgef4 gene codes for 3 Epac2 size variants (a, b, c). 
Each variant has a separate promoter, whose methyla-
tion state decides which size variant is expressed (Ueno 
et al. 2001, Niimura et al. 2009, Hoivik et al. 2013). 
As the functional cAMP-binding domain is common 
for all size variants (Kawasaki et al. 1998, de Rooij 
et al. 1998), Epac2A (highly expressed in brain; 
Fig. 1e), Epac2B (highly expressed in adrenal cortex; 
Fig. 1e) and Epac2C (highly expressed in the parenchy-
mal hepatocytes of the liver; not shown) were absent in 
the Epac2 
À/À mouse. PCR of genomic DNA confirmed </p>

<p>the deletion of Epac2 (Fig. 1f). The Epac1 
À/À and </p>

<p>Epac2 
À/À mice were able to reproduce and had normal </p>

<p>life span. </p>

<p>Arterial blood pressure </p>

<p>The Epac1 
À/À mice have, like the Wt mice, normal </p>

<p>blood pressure. After 2 days of habituation to the pro-
cedure, the mean arterial pressure in Wt mice was 
101 AE 6.3 mmHg (systolic 122 AE 6.6 and diastolic 
98 AE 6.4) against 102 AE 4.9 mmHg (124 AE 4.9 and 
91 AE 5.2) in Epac1 
À/À mice. The first day after train-</p>

<p>ing, the mean pressure was slightly higher, but again 
near identical in Wt (108 AE 4.3) and Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>(108 AE 4.3) mice. We considered it therefore unlikely </p>

<p>that the basal state microvascular transendothelial flux 
could differ in Wt and Epac1 
À/À mice due to divergent </p>

<p>blood pressure. </p>

<p>Plasma albumin and total protein concentration </p>

<p>The albumin concentration and total plasma protein 
concentration were similar in Wt and Epac1 
À/À mice, </p>

<p>as determined by quantitative proteomic analysis (ar-
bitrary units). Serum albumin was 10.0 AE 1.0 and 
total protein 18.8 AE 0.8 in Wt, against 10.0 AE 0.2 
and 17.8 AE 1.4 in Epac1 
À/À mice. </p>

<p>Epac1 
À/À mice have constitutively increased 
microvascular albumin permeability in major organs </p>

<p>The movement of albumin from the vascular to the 
extravascular compartment was evaluated by the 
two-tracer method. The experiments were executed in 
two separate series (one for Epac1 
À/À and one for </p>

<p>Epac2 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>), each with Wt animals as control. The two 
Wt groups were tested against each other. As there was 
no difference between them, a combined group consist-
ing of all Wt animals was used for comparison with the 
Epac1 
À/À and Epac2 
À/À animals. </p>

<p>The local plasma volume of each tissue sample was 
determined from the content of </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>I-HSA, which was 
infused 5 min before euthanasia, and was similar in 
tissue samples from Wt, Epac1 
À/À and Epac2 
À/À ani-</p>

<p>mals (for details see legend to Fig. 2). The Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>mice had significantly increased albumin clearance 
(normalized to plasma volume) in skin, skeletal mus-
cle, adipose tissue and large intestine (Fig. 2). An 
increase in albumin clearance when expressed relative 
to local plasma volume is a strong indication of an 
actual change in vascular permeability, as it compen-
sates for differences in surface area for exchange. In 
contrast to Epac1 
À/À mice, the Epac2 
À/À mice had </p>

<p>albumin clearance similar to Wt mice in skin, skeletal 
muscle, adipose tissue and large intestine, but was 
increased in the small intestine (Fig. 2). Taken 
together, these results indicate that Epac1, but not 
Epac2, provided a significant contribution to the basal 
macromolecular endothelial permeability in most of 
the organs studied here. </p>

<p>The microvascular clearance of the MRI contrast agent 
Gadomer-17 is enhanced in the masseter muscle of 
Epac1 
À/À mice </p>

<p>To obtain further evidence for a role of Epac1 in 
macromolecule endothelial permeability and eliminate 
the (unlikely) possibility that increased albumin clear-
ances were due to an albumin-specific uptake mecha-
nism, additional studies were performed using the </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Acta Physiologica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of 
Scandinavian Physiological Society, doi: 10.1111/apha.12697 </p>

<p>446 </p>

<p>Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice · R K Kopperud et al. </p>

<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

<p>synthetic macromolecule Gadomer-17 in the immobi-
lized M. masseter skeletal muscle of Wt and Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>mice. The initial rapid rise of the MRI signal after 
intravenous Gadomer-17 injection seen in Figure 3a 
reflected blood vessel filling and was similar for Wt 
and Epac1 
À/À animals, suggesting near-identical vascu-</p>

<p>lar volumes. Thereafter, the MR signal intensity 
became higher in muscle from Epac1 
À/À mice than Wt </p>

<p>mice, indicating increased constitutive permeability in </p>

<p>Epac1 
À/À microvasculature. Apparently, the loss of </p>

<p>Epac1 affected a pathway for microvascular macro-
molecule exchange common for albumin and Gado-
mer-17 (Fig. 3b). We finally tested whether lack of 
Epac1 also could blunt the known permeability 
decreasing effect of the cAMP elevating PDE4 inhibi-
tor rolipram in the masseter muscle (Lin et al. 2011). 
Rolipram induced a lowering of Gadomer-17 perme-
ability that was blunted in Epac1 
À/À masseter </p>

<p>Figure 2 The normalized albumin clearance is increased in skin, skeletal muscle, adipose tissue and large intestine of Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>, 
but not Epac2 
À/À mice. The normalized clearance (NC) in tissue samples of back skin, skeletal muscle, white adipose tissue, </p>

<p>small and large intestine, and heart is shown mL g 
À1 dry weight (average AE SEM). The NC is the ratio of the clearance (based </p>

<p>on relative tissue sample content of </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I-HSA infused 35 min before euthanasia) and the local tissue plasma volume (relative 
content of </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>I-HSA, infused 5 min before euthanasia). P-values &lt; 0.05 (*) and &lt;0.001 (AE) are shown. The plasma volume 
(mL g 
À1 dry weight) was, with the exception of jejunum from the Epac2 
À/À mice, similar between Wt (n = 19), Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>(n = 9) and Epac2 
À/À (n = 9) mouse tissues: Skin: Wt: 0.023 AE 0.002, Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>: 0.020 AE 0.002, Epac2 
À/À : 0.027 AE 0.003; </p>

<p>quadriceps muscle (corresponding values): 0.022 AE 0.003, 0.014 AE 0.001, and 0.018 AE 0.002; inguinal fat: 0.024 AE 0.001, 
0.023 AE 0.002 and 0.028 AE 0.003; jejunum: 0.101 AE 0.008, 0.116 AE 0.017 and 0.064 AE 0.006; colon: 0.042 AE 0.004, 
0.033 AE 0.002 and 0.032 AE 0.003; heart: 0.229 AE 0.013, 0.215 AE 0.019, and 0.205 AE 0.015. HSA, human serum albumin. </p>

<p>Figure 3 The constitutive Gadomer-17 
clearance is increased in masseter muscle 
of Epac1 
À/À compared to Wt mice. (a) </p>

<p>Typical magnetic resonance imaging 
(MRI) signal intensity (SI) obtained upon 
continuous scanning of a masseter region 
from Epac1 
À/À (red) or Wt (green) </p>

<p>mouse before and after Gadomer (Gd)-
17 injection. The solid lines show fits 
based on the calculated permeability 
coefficient. (b) The Gd 17 permeability 
coefficient calculated from the scanning 
data obtained before and after infusion 
of vehicle or rolipram, each animal serv-
ing as its own control. P-values &lt; 0.05 
are shown (n = 10). (c-e) The endothe-
lium of transverse sections of M. mas-
seter from Epac1 
À/À (c) or Wt (e) mice </p>

<p>was visualized by anti-CD31 staining 
and the capillary/myofibre ratio deter-
mined (d). Error bars are SEM. 
P-values &lt; 0.05 (*) are shown. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Acta Physiologica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of 
Scandinavian Physiological Society, doi: 10.1111/apha.12697 </p>



<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

<p>R K Kopperud et al. · Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice </p>

<p>(Fig. 3b). The results could not be explained by 
decreased microvascularity in the Epac1 
À/À masseter </p>

<p>as its capillary density was similar to Wt masseter 
(Fig. 3c-e). We conclude that Epac1 
À/À masseter has </p>

<p>increased microvascular permeability both under basal 
and rolipram-stimulated conditions. </p>

<p>Comparison of the microvascular permeability enhancing 
effect of ANP in Wt and Epac1 
À/À mice </p>

<p>We and others have previously demonstrated that 
ANP increases the baseline microvascular permeability 
of Wt mice, particularly in skin and muscle (therefore, 
one-tailed t-testing was used). It is not known whether 
ANP acts through Epac1 inhibition or independently 
of Epac1. We reasoned that if ANP acted indepen-
dently of Epac or an Epac-induced pathway, it should 
enhance permeability to the same level in Wt and 
Epac1 
À/À mice. We failed to note any further ANP-</p>

<p>induced increase of permeability in the Epac1 
À/À mice </p>

<p>(Fig. 4a,b), unlike in the Epac2 
À/À mice (Fig. 4c). </p>

<p>Besides, the albumin permeability enhancing effect of 
ANP was, if anything, slightly lower in magnitude 
than the effect of deleting Epac1 (Fig. 4a). The above 
results are consistent with an action of ANP to reduce 
the effectiveness of an Epac1 pathway to maintain the 
constitutive vascular permeability. </p>

<p>A possible consequence of constitutively increased 
loss of albumin from the vascular to the extravascular 
compartment could be a slight increase of interstitial 
oncotic pressure accompanied by a slight water accu-
mulation. As the tissue samples to be analysed for 
albumin isotope content were weighed before and 
after drying (see the Experimental section for details), 
we could compare their water content (relative to dry 
weight). Only in skin was the water content high 
enough to produce experimentally reliable data. 
Epac1 
À/À back skin had about 2% higher water con-</p>

<p>tent than back skin from Wt mice (Fig. 5). Further, 
the magnitude of the increase in water content was 
similar whether or not they were treated with ANP. 
This is not unexpected due to the short exposure time 
to ANP and the modest albumin permeability rate of 
back skin under the experimental conditions. In con-
trast, the Epac1 
À/À mice have a constitutive opportu-</p>

<p>nity to retain fluid subsequent to the increased 
albumin permeability. </p>

<p>Epac1 
À/À microvessels have structurally less constricted 
interendothelial slits </p>

<p>We next studied whether the different Gadomer-17 
permeability observed between Wt and Epac1 
À/À mas-</p>

<p>seter muscle had structural microvascular correlates. </p>

<p>Figure 4 The effect of atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP) on macromolecule microvascular permeability in tissue from Wt, 
Epac1 
À/À and Epac2 
À/À mice. (a) The effect of ANP on the normalized albumin clearance is shown for tissues from Wt and </p>

<p>Epac1 
À/À mice. The mice were given vehicle or ANP 30 minutes before euthanasia, and the apparent plasma volume and albu-</p>

<p>min clearance determined by the [ </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>I]albumin/[ </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I]albumin method as for the experiment shown in Figure 2. (b) The effect of 
ANP on the microvascular permeability of Gadomer-17 is shown for masseter muscle from Wt and Epac1 
À/À mice. (c) The </p>

<p>effect of ANP on the normalized albumin clearance for tissues from Wt and Epac2 
À/À mice. Error bars are SEM (n = 10). P-</p>

<p>values &lt; 0.05 (*) and &lt;0.01 (+) are shown. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Acta Physiologica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of 
Scandinavian Physiological Society, doi: 10.1111/apha.12697 </p>

<p>448 </p>

<p>Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice · R K Kopperud et al. </p>

<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

<p>As already noted, the microvessel density did not 
differ between Epac1 
À/À and Wt masseter muscle </p>

<p>(Fig. 3c-e). We therefore investigated transverse 
sections of Epac1 
À/À masseter muscle microvessels </p>

<p>by electron microscopy for differences at the ultra-
structural level. These analyses revealed a trend 
towards shorter and wider junctions in Epac1 
À/À cap-</p>

<p>illaries (average length and width were 395 and 
13 nm in Epac1 
À/À against 483 and 11 in Wt; </p>

<p>P &gt; 0.05). More importantly, a highly significant </p>

<p>difference existed between Wt and Epac1 
À/À endothe-</p>

<p>lial slits regarding the extent and density of junctional 
complex material. On average, Wt clefts had 224 nm 
of strongly developed junctional complex against only 
97 nm for Epac1 
À/À clefts (Fig. 6a). Four of the 48 slit </p>

<p>sections scrutinized from Epac1 
À/À microvessels had </p>

<p>no constrictions &lt;6 nm and no areas with strong accu-
mulation of junctional complex material, against only 
one for the 57 studied slits from Wt mice. The most 
extreme examples of slit difference in distribution of 
electron-dense material are shown in Figure 6b-e. 
These observations demonstrated ultrastructural dif-
ferences between endothelial slits from Wt and 
Epac1 
À/À animals under basal conditions, consistent </p>

<p>with the finding that macromolecules such as Gado-
mer-17 and albumin have increased capillary perme-
ability in Epac1 
À/À compared with Wt tissues. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study demonstrates increased albumin 
clearance in several tissues of Epac1 
À/À mice under </p>

<p>basal in vivo conditions. The Epac1 
À/À animals have </p>

<p>normal plasma protein levels, normal blood pressure, 
and similar microvessel density and initial tissue blood 
filling of injected labelled albumin or Gadomer-17 as 
Wt animals. Enhanced transendothelial vesicle trans-
port of surface receptor bound albumin has been 
described in some ANP-stimulated specialized 
endothelia (Chen et al. 2012), but is unlikely to </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) 
(c) </p>

<p>(d) 
(e) </p>

<p>Figure 6 The endothelial junctional density of Epac1 
À/À and Wt capillaries. (a) The average length of each endothelial slit </p>

<p>found associated with strong junctional complex (JC) in Wt and Epac1 
À/À M. masseter. Error bars are SEM. The P-value for </p>

<p>the difference between Epac1 
À/À and Wt slits was &lt;0.00002 by the Mann-Whitney two-tailed U-test and &lt;0.0003 by the two-</p>

<p>tailed t-test. (b-e) Examples of junctions from Wt and Epac1 
À/À mice. The two Wt junctions shown (b, c) had more abundant </p>

<p>JC than found in any of the 48 Epac1 
À/À junctions studied. The two Epac1 
À/À junctions shown (d, e) had less abundant JC than </p>

<p>any of 57 Wt junctions studied. </p>

<p>Figure 5 The water content of back skin from Wt and 
Epac1 
À/À mice. The water content (mL g 
À1 dry weight) of </p>

<p>back skin from Epac1 
À/À mice and Wt mice injected with </p>

<p>vehicle or atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP) was determined in 
the tissue samples used for the experiments on albumin clear-
ance shown in Figures 2 and 4a, as described in the experi-
mental section. Error bars are SEM (n = 10). P-value &lt; 0.05 
(*) is shown. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Acta Physiologica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of 
Scandinavian Physiological Society, doi: 10.1111/apha.12697 </p>



<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

<p>R K Kopperud et al. · Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice </p>

<p>explain the enhanced albumin clearance of Epac1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>animals as they had increased clearance also of the 
artificial macromolecule Gadomer-17. Our results 
therefore conform to the hypothesis that tonic activity 
of Epac1-dependent pathways contributes to the main-
tenance of baseline vascular permeability, and loss of 
this activity leads to a sustained increase in baseline 
permeability. We ascribe this phenotype to enhanced 
permeability of the interendothelial junctions of 
Epac1 
À/À mouse microvessels. </p>

<p>A number of studies implicate PKA alone or PKA 
and Epac together as responsible for cAMP-induced 
endothelial barrier tightening (Rampersad et al. 2010, 
Surapisitchat &amp; Beavo 2011, Curry &amp; Adamson 2013). 
The present study does not exclude an action of PKA in 
maintaining the endothelial barrier in vivo, but suggests 
that Epac1 has a dominant role compared to PKA in 
intact microvessels as treatment with rolipram, which 
would increase cAMP and PKA activity, failed to over-
come the lack of Epac1 (Fig. 3). A similar dominant 
role of Epac1 was noted in arterial endothelial cells 
in vitro, where the junctional protein VE-cadherin colo-
calizes with PKA, a PDE4D/Epac1 complex, and the 
Epac target Rap1 in a 'signalosome' controlling the 
paracellular permeability (Rampersad et al. 2010). It is 
noted that these conclusions apply principally to the sit-
uation where the molecular complexes regulating 
cAMP are tethered close to the cell membrane. The 
tethering of PKA, Epac1 and their substrates close to 
sites of production of cAMP or cGMP and members of 
the cyclic nucleotide phoshodiesterase (PDE) family of 
cyclic nucleotide degrading enzymes is an important 
part of the regulatory scheme (Maurice 2011). Thus, 
lung endothelial cells responded to cAMP produced by 
a soluble bacterial adenylyl cyclase by interendothelial 
cell gap formation, facilitating bacterial invasion and 
oedema formation. The same cells showed restricted 
permeability, however, when cAMP was produced 
close to the surface membrane. In either case, the cAMP 
effect was attributed to PKA activation (Prasain et al. 
2009, Ochoa et al. 2012). 
Our observations provide new insight into mecha-
nisms that regulate vascular permeability. In particu-
lar, they imply that Epac1 activity exerts a tonic 
inhibition of microvessel permeability. One potential 
way to relieve the Epac1-dependent inhibition in the 
intact animal is by lowering the cAMP concentration 
close to the endothelial junction. In fact, this has been 
proposed as explanation for the ANP-enhanced 
microvessel permeability. The ability of ANP to 
enhance microvascular albumin clearance depends on 
its binding to the endothelial cGMP producing recep-
tor GC-A (Kuhn et al. 2009, Kuhn 2012). The result-
ing cGMP increase can (i) directly activate PKG, (ii) 
directly inhibit PDE3 degradation of cAMP and thus </p>

<p>indirectly activate PKA and Epac, or (iii) directly acti-
vate PDE2 to indirectly lower cAMP and thereby 
reduce PKA and Epac activity (Surapisitchat et al. 
2007, Birukova et al. 2008, Kuhn 2012). Epac1 does 
not bind cGMP at physiologically relevant concentra-
tions (Christensen et al. 2003), but as in (iii) above, a 
cGMP burst can inhibit Epac indirectly by stimulating 
PDE2 to degrade cAMP in an endothelial cell com-
partment close to Epac1 (Kraynik et al. 2013). This 
scenario is compatible with the present findings as the 
ANP effect was blunted or absent in the Epac1 
À/À ani-</p>

<p>mals (Fig. 4a) and that rolipram, a strong inhibitor of 
the cAMP-specific PDE4, easily overrides ANP-
induced hyperpermeability in vivo (Lin et al. 2011). 
Such overriding is less easily explained for purely 
cGMP-regulated putative ANP mediators like PKG 
(Schreier et al. 2008). Besides, the constitutive 
endothelial barrier resistance was lowered to at least a 
similar extent by Epac1 deficiency compared to expo-
sure to ANP, as expected if ANP acted to inhibit 
Epac1 through a moderate decrease of endothelial cell 
cAMP (Kraynik et al. 2013). 
As our animal models had global Epac deletion, the 
observed endothelial phenotype might in part be 
caused by deletion of Epac1 in non-endothelial cells. 
We considered therefore whether it could be related to 
constitutively increased aldosterone output from the 
adrenal cortex, where ANP decreases aldosterone pro-
duction through GC-A/cGMP/PDE2-dependent lower-
ing of cAMP (Tsai &amp; Beavo 2011). This is unlikely 
because the adrenocortical cells express Epac2 rather 
than Epac1 (Niimura et al. 2009, Hoivik et al. 2013, 
see also Fig. 1e), and our Epac2 
À/À animals responded </p>

<p>fully to ANP (Fig. 4c). Secondly, the ANP effect on 
microvascular permeability is abolished in mice with 
endothelial-specific deletion of the GC-A receptor for 
ANP (Curry et al. 2010). Thirdly, our Epac mice had 
normal blood pressure, arguing that their renin-an-
giotensin-aldosterone axis was unperturbed. The pre-
sent study supports therefore the notion that ANP may 
modulate endothelial permeability in vivo through 
lowering the cAMP concentration near Epac1. 
The ultrastructural analysis of the junctions between 
endothelial microvessel cells demonstrated less elec-
tron-dense junction complex material in Epac1 
À/À than </p>

<p>in Wt microvessels (Fig. 6). Thus, it is likely that 
microvessels in Epac1 
À/À mice have more discontinu-</p>

<p>ities in the band of tight junction material that effec-
tively seals the junctions to molecules the size of 
albumin and Gadomer-17. The effect of such disconti-
nuities on permeability depends on their three-dimen-
sional arrangement (Weinbaum &amp; Curry 1995, Michel 
&amp; Curry 1999). Assuming a similar arrangement in wt 
and Epac1 
À/À mice, our results are consistent with a </p>

<p>hyperpermeable state. The present study does not </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Acta Physiologica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of 
Scandinavian Physiological Society, doi: 10.1111/apha.12697 </p>

<p>450 </p>

<p>Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice · R K Kopperud et al. </p>

<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

<p>address whether the paucity of junction material in 
Epac1 
À/À slits is readily reversible, but it may be noted </p>

<p>that the forskolin/rolipram-induced endothelial barrier 
tightening of rat mesenteric post-capillary venules 
occurs rapidly in vivo (Spindler et al. 2011). 
An important question is the role of Epac1-depen-
dent pathways in relation to other signal mediators, 
such as sphingosine-1 phosphate (S1P) that also exerts 
a tonic control of vascular permeability (Curry &amp; 
Adamson 2013). As it is reasonable to assume that 
S1P was present at normal levels in our experiments, 
we conclude that reduced Epac1 activity can increase 
permeability at physiological levels of S1P. 
Our observations have potentially useful transla-
tional implications. Agents selectively targeting Epac1 
may be sufficient and more precise tools than general 
cAMP agonists to modulate the endothelial barrier 
in vivo. Cyclic nucleotide analogues, including those 
with potential as Epac1 modulators, so far have not 
been useful in intact mammals, mainly because they, 
like cAMP itself, are rapidly cleared through active 
renal excretion and metabolism by phosphodiesterases 
(for recent review see Kleppe et al. 2015). New inhibi-
tors of Epac that act outside the cyclic nucleotide bind-
ing site have been produced. So far, they are specific for 
Epac2 (Tsalkova et al. 2012, Chen et al. 2013), which 
appears not to be involved in the control of the endothe-
lial barrier. Nevertheless, this new inhibitor class indi-
cates a route to produce modulators of Epac1, which 
may become useful to control the endothelial barrier. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of 
interest. </p>

<p>Gerd Salvesen, Trude Skogstrand, Bodil Hansen, Reidar 
Myklebust, Anne Nyhaug, Nina Lied Larsen and Ingeborg 
Brønstad provided expert technical assistance. All MRI and 
TEM experiments were performed at the Molecular Imaging 
Center (MIC) at the University of Bergen, Norway. Funding 
was from the Research Council of Norway (NRC), The Wes-
tern Norway Health Authority (WNRH) and the Norwegian 
Cancer Association (DNK). FEC was supported by NIH 
grant HL028607-32. </p>



<p>© 2016 The Authors. Acta Physiologica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of 
Scandinavian Physiological Society, doi: 10.1111/apha.12697 </p>

<p>451 </p>

<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

<p>R K Kopperud et al. · Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice </p>





<p>Microvessel permeability in Epac1KO mice · R K Kopperud et al. </p>

<p>Acta Physiol 2017, 219, 441-452 </p>

</text></tei>