<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5467422" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to investigate the ability of worker's compensation (WC) patients to return to 
work without restrictions after hip arthroscopy. Twenty-nine WC patients along with age and gender matched 
controls who underwent hip arthroscopy were retrospectively reviewed after achieving maximum medical im-
provement (MMI) status at minimum 1 year postoperatively. Patient demographic factors were evaluated, along 
with the Hip Outcome Score Activities of Daily Living and Sports-Specific subscales, and the modified Harris Hip 
Score (mHHS). The majority of WC patients were able to return to work without restrictions after reaching 
MMI (20/29, 69.0%). WC patients who failed to return to work without restrictions had a prolonged time from 
injury to surgery (3.01 6 2.16 months versus 6.36 6 4.16 months; P ¼ 0.0079), more concomitant orthopedic 
injuries (4/20, 20.0% versus 9/9, 100%; P ¼ 0.0001), and higher body mass index (BMI) (26.61 6 3.52 versus 
29.54 6 3.43; P ¼ 0.047) than those who returned to work without restrictions. the WC population exist in the literature, but there is a 
paucity of information examining this patient population in 
the context of hip arthroscopy [2-9]. However, Lee et al. 
[10] recently performed one of the larger reviews, examin-
ing 268 cases of arthroscopic labral debridement and iden-
tified workers compensation status as one of five 
predictors of a longer recovery time in patients undergoing 
hip arthroscopy. 
Hip arthroscopy is believed to be a common, effective 
and safe method of treating pathologic hip conditions such </p>

<p>V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, 
please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>



<p>30 </p>

<p>Journal of Hip Preservation Surgery Vol. 4, No. 1, pp. 30-38 
doi: 10.1093/jhps/hnw037 
Advance Access Publication 27 October 2016 
Research article </p>

<p>as femoroacetabular impingement (FAI) and labral tears 
[11-16]. Although it has been shown that patients in gen-
eral perform well after hip arthroscopy, the subset of WC 
patients may be susceptible to worse outcomes. Recently, 
Stake et al. [17] performed a comparative analysis 
between WC and control patients, showing that WC 
patients undergoing arthroscopic hip surgery presented 
with lower pre-operative patient-reported outcome scores 
as compared with their non-WC counterparts. However, 
these patients still attained significant improvement from 
arthroscopic hip surgery. Salvo et al. [18] returned to work 
an average of 6.8 months after surgery with only 58% of 
patients currently working at time of most recent follow-
up. They also demonstrated that WC patients had a signifi-
cantly higher Hip Outcome Score compared with controls. 
Gigi et al. [19] also recently showed that patients undergo-
ing hip arthroscopy for work-related injuries with active 
work claims had significantly lower patient reported 
outcomes scores at most recent follow-up compared with 
patients with sports related injuries, but interestingly not 
significantly higher than a group of non-sports-related inju-
ries without pending active work claims. However, the 
work-related injuries were again able to demonstrate sig-
nificant improvements in outcomes scores compared with 
baseline. 
Interestingly, WC patients have typically been analysed 
as a single group in the orthopedic literature. Comparative 
differences within the differential outcome groups in this 
population after hip arthroscopy have not yet been 
explored. The purpose of this study was to investigate 
the ability of WC patients to return to work without 
restrictions after hip arthroscopy and factors associated 
with failure to return to work without restrictions </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study design 
Institutional review board approval was obtained for this 
study (IRB: 120221080). Prospective data on all workers' 
compensation patients undergoing hip arthroscopy with la-
bral repair, acetabular rim-trimming and/or femoral osteo-
chondroplasty by a single fellowship-trained surgeon from 
January 2010 to May 2012 was analysed. Inclusion criteria 
encompassed WC patients with age greater than eighteen, 
diagnosis of unilateral symptomatic labral tear in the set-
ting of FAI who had failed non-surgical treatment, patients 
who had reached maximum medical improvement (MMI) 
at a minimum 1-year after hip arthroscopy. Exclusion 
criteria encompassed patients who had previous hip path-
ology, as well as those who had not yet reached MMI. A </p>

<p>control group was also created matched by age-(63 years) 
and gender to the WC patients, and used for comparison. 
Patients who met the study criteria completed a pre-
operative questionnaire that included relevant demo-
graphic information including age, gender, body mass 
index (BMI), side of operative extremity, past surgical his-
tory, concomitant orthopedic issues (prior lower extremity 
or spine surgery) and smoking and alcohol consumption. 
Mechanism of hip injury was recorded. Intraoperative data 
included both diagnostic information as well as procedures 
performed including acetabular rim trimming, labral refixa-
tion, femoral osteochondroplasty, iliopsoas lengthening, 
type of capsular repair, trochanteric bursectomy and ilioti-
bial band lengthening. </p>

<p>Functional outcome evaluation 
WC patients and controls completed hip-specific outcome 
instruments including the Hip Outcome Score Activity of 
Daily Living (HOS-ADL) and Sport-Specific Subscales 
(HOS-SS) [20, 21], and the modified Harris Hip Score 
(mHHS) [22, 23] at baseline and at least one year follow-
ing surgery. All complications were also recorded. Primary 
outcome measures included ability to return to work with-
out restrictions, US Department of Labor Dictionary of 
Occupational Titles physical exertion requirements classifi-
cation work level at MMI (light, medium, heavy) [24], and 
need for revision hip arthroscopy. </p>

<p>Radiographic analysis 
Plain radiographs were performed at baseline and at final 
recent follow-up and read by the senior author. All patients 
had a standard anteroposterior radiographs for the pelvis, 
false profile view, and oblique lateral (Dunn) view with the 
patient in a supine position. All radiographs were per-
formed with the coccyx positioned midline, approximately 
one centimeter above the pubic symphysis (neutral tilt) 
and the obturator foramina and the trochanters symmetric 
(neutral rotation) [25]. The lateral center edge angle of 
Wiberg and alpha angle were measured on plain radio-
graphs using a digital picture archiving and communication 
system [25, 26]. </p>

<p>Surgical technique 
All patients underwent hip arthroscopy under general anes-
thesia using a previously described technique [9, 27]. 
Patients were placed in the supine position on a traction 
table with a well-padded perineal post. Axial traction was 
then applied [28-30], and the time onset of hip distraction 
was marked by the circulating nursing staff to assure safe 
duration of traction time. </p>

<p>Return to work in workers compensation following hip arthroscopy 31 </p>

<p>An anterolateral (AL) portal was first established. Prior 
to fluid introduction, needle-localized placement of an an-
terior portal was performed. After cannulation and intro-
duction of the arthroscope through the AL portal, the AL 
portal was established under direct spinal needle localiza-
tion. A transverse interportal capsulotomy measuring 
4 cm in length was performed from 12 to 2 o'clock about 
5-8 mm from the labrum. The capsule adjacent to the 
acetabulum was then reflected to expose the superior ace-
tabular rim from the indirect head of the rectus femoris in-
sertion (12 o'clock position) laterally to the iliopsoas 
tendon (3 o'clock position) anteriorly. Acetabular rim 
trimming and labral refixation with suture anchors was 
then performed as appropriate [29] using a distal anterolat-
eral accessory (DALA) portal. Next, the traction was 
released and the hip was flexed roughly 30 
. A T-capsulot-
omy was then performed using an arthroscopic scalpel 
through a 5.0-mm cannula in the DALA portal at the inter-
val between the iliocapsularis and the gluteus minimus. 
The T-capsulotomy was performed perpendicular to the 
prior transverse capsulotomy along the length of the fem-
oral neck distally to the capsular reflection at the intertro-
chanteric line in order to access the femoral head-neck 
junction in the peripheral compartment. All indicated pro-
cedures, including femoral osteochondroplasty between 12 
and 6 o'clock, were then performed and the hip was taken 
through a dynamic fluoroscopic examination. The capsule 
then was closed arthroscopically and the portals were 
approximated in a layered fashion. </p>

<p>Rehabilitation 
Post-operatively, all patients took part in a standardized 
physical rehabilitation protocol. A hip orthosis was worn 
for the first 3 weeks to limit flexion to 90 degrees, abduc-
tion to 30 degrees, extension to 0 degrees and internal/ex-
ternal rotation to 20 degrees. They were also restricted to 
a crutch-assisted gait with 20 pounds foot flat for the first 3 
weeks and a continuous passive motion machine is utilized 
during this period to assist with hip range of motion. 
Physical therapy starts with passive range of motion exer-
cises along with isometrics and progresses the patient to 
full weigh bearing as tolerated with active range of motion 
and strengthening by 6 weeks. Over the next 6 weeks, the 
patients progress to performing all community ambulation 
unassisted while progressing with closed-chain kinetic 
strengthening. The next four weeks of therapy are spent 
performing work-specific activities before returning to 
work. Patients considered to be at medium or heavy level 
work duties underwent a one month period of work condi-
tioning prior to return to work. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
A power analysis was performed to ensure adequate power to 
detect differences between the WC patients who returned to 
work without restrictions and those who failed to do so. WC 
patients who returned to work without restrictions were com-
pared with those who failed to do so. WC patients were also 
compared with controls. Comparative statistical analysis of 
continuous variables was performed utilizing independent 
samples paired and unpaired t-tests. An analysis of covariance 
was subsequently performed on post-operative outcome 
scores to ensure that the observed statistical effect was not 
influenced by pre-operative baseline values. Contingency ana-
lysis was carried out with chi-squared or Fisher's exact test for 
nominal variables. A P values of less than 0.05 was considered 
to be statistically significant (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 21</rs>, Chicago, IL). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Ability to return to work without restrictions 
Twenty-nine WC patients were available for analysis after 
reaching MMI at minimum 1-year post-operative following 
hip arthroscopy. There were no reoperations and no com-
plications. Twenty WC patients were able to return to 
work without restrictions (69.0%), while 9 were not able 
to return to work or returned to work with permanent 
restrictions (31.0%). Factors associated with failure of WC 
patients to return to work without restrictions were longer 
time from injury to surgical intervention (3.01 6 2.16 ver-
sus 6.36 6 4.16 months; P ¼ 0.0079), higher incidence of 
concomitant orthopedic injuries (4/20, 20.0% versus 9/9, 
100%; P ¼ 0.0001), and higher BMI (26.61 6 3.52 versus 
29.54 6 3.43; P ¼ 0.047). There were no other differences 
in patient demographics or radiographic measurements 
between those who returned to work without restrictions 
and those who failed to do so (Table I). 
Mechanism of injury and US Department of Labor 
Dictionary of Occupational Titles physical exertion requirem 
ents classification for each WC patient were recorded 
(Table II) [23]. Of patients who were able to return to work 
without restrictions, five patient occupations were classified as 
'Heavy' (25%), eight as 'Medium' (40%) and seven as 'Light' 
(35%) work levels. The WR group had four patient occupa-
tions classified as 'Heavy' (44%), three as 'Medium' (33%) and 
two as 'Light' (22%) work levels. Work level classifications 
were not significantly different statistically between patients 
who were able to return to work without restrictions and those 
who failed to do so (P ¼ 0.684). </p>

<p>Comparison of WC patients to controls 
The 29 WC patients and 29 age-and gender-matched con-
trols were compared (Table III), revealing that WC </p>



<p>patients had higher BMI (Control: 24.96 6 3.86; WC: 
27.52 6 3.70; P ¼ 0.012), higher incidence of concomitant 
orthopaedic injuries (Control: 4/29, 13.8%; WC: 13/29, 
44.8%; P ¼ 0.020), and were more likely to smoke 
(Control: 1/29, 3.4%; WC: 6/29, 20.7%; P ¼ 0.037). 
There were no significant differences in the specific pro-
cedures each group underwent (Table III). There were 
also no other differences in patient demographics or radio-
graphic parameters. </p>

<p>Functional outcome score assessment 
All patient-reported outcome scores at most recent 
follow-up were significantly improved as compared with 
preoperative baseline levels for WC patients and matched 
controls (P &lt; 0.0001). WC patients had significantly lower 
scores on the HOS-ADL, HOS-SS, and mHHS as 
compared with controls both preoperatively (P &lt; 0.0001, 
P ¼ 0.025, P ¼ 0.001, respectively) and at most recent </p>

<p>follow-up (P &lt; 0.0001, P ¼ 0.001, P ¼ 0.011, respectively) 
(Table IV). 
WC patients who returned to work without restrictions 
and those who failed to do so both exhibited significant im-
provements in outcome scores following hip arthroscopy 
(P &lt; 0.0001). WC patients who returned to work without 
restrictions achieved higher post-operative scores in all 
three patient reported outcomes as compared with those 
who failed to do so (HOD-ADL: P &lt; 0.0001; HOS-SS: 
P ¼ 0.004; mHHS: P ¼ 0.009) (Table V). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
This study examines the ability of WC patients to return to 
work without restrictions after reaching MMI following hip 
arthroscopy and factors associated with failure to return to 
work without restrictions. We find that the majority 
(69.0%) of WC patients are able to return to work without 
restrictions after reaching MMI a minimum of 1-year fol-
lowing hip arthroscopy. The patients who were unable to </p>

<p>Table I. Demographic characteristics of the Workers' Compensation patients who returned to work without restric-
tions (Returned) and those who failed to do so (Failed) </p>

<p>Returned (n ¼ 20) 
Failed (n ¼ 9) 
P-values </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
10 
4 </p>

<p>Female 
10 
5 </p>

<p>Mean age at surgery 
37.3 6 10.8 years 
42.9 6 6.85 years </p>

<p>CEA 
36.1 6 8.77 
42.7 6 7.02 </p>

<p>AA 
58.7 6 6.73 
58.2 6 8.10 </p>

<p>Surgical side </p>

<p>Left 
9 
3 </p>

<p>Right 
11 
6 </p>

<p>Time in between: </p>

<p>Presentation-surgery 
3.01 6 2.16 months 
6.36 6 4.16 months 
(P ¼ 0.0079) </p>

<p>Injury-presentation 
11.74 6 11.6 months 
14.48 6 12.3 months </p>

<p>Injury-surgery 
14.75 6 11.3 months 
20.83 6 14.05 months </p>

<p>Associated injuries 
4 
9 
(P ¼ 0.0001) </p>

<p>Smoker 
4 
2 </p>

<p>Drinker 
8 
2 </p>

<p>BMI 
26.61 6 3.52 
29.54 6 3.43 
(P ¼ 0.047) </p>

<p>CEA, Center Edge Angle; AA, Alpha Angle; MMI, Maximum Medical Improvement; BMI, Body Mass Index. </p>

<p>Return to work in workers compensation following hip arthroscopy 33 </p>

<p>Table II. Age, gender, US Department of Labor Dictionary of Occupational Titles physical exertion requirements 
classification and mechanism of injury for Workers' Compensation patients </p>

<p>Age 
Gender 
Work classification 
Mechanism of injury </p>

<p>24 
F 
Light 
Fall </p>

<p>25 
F 
Light 
Fall </p>

<p>29 
M 
Heavy 
Fall </p>

<p>29 
F 
Medium 
Kickboxing accident </p>

<p>29 
M 
Medium 
Fall </p>

<p>29 
M 
Medium 
Fall </p>

<p>29 
M 
Medium 
Injured with pivot motion while dancing </p>

<p>30 
F 
Light 
Lifting a heavy object </p>

<p>30 
F 
Light 
Altered hip biomechanics after foot accident </p>

<p>30 
M 
Heavy 
Lifting a heavy object </p>

<p>32 
F 
Light 
Fall </p>

<p>33 
M 
Heavy 
Hip was hyperflexed and twisted </p>

<p>33 
M 
Heavy 
Fall </p>

<p>38 
M 
Light 
Over abduction and internal rotation </p>

<p>38 
F 
Medium 
Twisting and external rotation injury while dancing </p>

<p>39 
M 
Heavy 
Lifting and throwing heavy objects </p>

<p>39 
F 
Heavy 
Fall </p>

<p>40 
F 
Light 
Motor vehicle accident </p>

<p>42 
F 
Light 
Fall </p>

<p>43 
F 
Medium 
Twisting injury during a slip on the stairs </p>

<p>44 
F 
Medium 
Insidious onset </p>

<p>47 
F 
Heavy 
Motor vehicle accident </p>

<p>47 
M 
Medium 
Fall </p>

<p>47 
M 
Medium 
Fall </p>

<p>48 
M 
Heavy 
Direct trauma </p>

<p>50 
F 
Medium 
Motor vehicle accident </p>

<p>55 
F 
Light 
Fall </p>

<p>57 
M 
Heavy 
Fall </p>

<p>60 
M 
Medium 
Fall </p>



<p>return to work without restrictions had higher BMI, higher 
rate of concurrent orthopaedic injuries, and longer time 
from injury to surgery. WC patients exhibit significant im-
provement in patient reported outcomes regardless of abil-
ity to return to work without restrictions, but scores 
remained lower than age and gender matched controls. 
The results of this study not only provide clinicians valu-
able information on the results of hip arthroscopy in WC 
patients compared with matched controls, but also identi-
fies factors associated with failure to return to work with-
out restrictions. 
WC status has been associated with inferior outcomes 
after orthopedic surgery in general and specifically for hip </p>

<p>arthroscopy as well [1, 10, 31]. Potter et al. [3] followed a 
military cohort receiving arthroscopic acetabular labral de-
bridement and showed that patients with disability status 
exhibited significantly lower post-operative mean mHHS 
(P &lt; 0.0001), lower Short Form-36 subscale scores 
(P &lt; 0.02), and lower satisfaction rates (P &lt; 0.04) as 
compared with non-disability patients. Conversely, Byrd 
showed that successful outcomes could be achieved in a 
small number of workers' compensation patients undergo-
ing hip arthroscopy, finding no significant differences in 
the Harris Hip Scale between WC patients and non-WC 
patients [32] Stake et al. [17] performed a case-control 
study and found that workers' compensation patients had </p>

<p>Table III. Demographic characteristics of the workers compensation cohort and the age-gender matched controls </p>

<p>WC (n ¼ 29) 
Control (n ¼ 29) 
P-values </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
14 
14 </p>

<p>Female 
15 
15 </p>

<p>Mean age at surgery 
39.1 6 9.94 years 
40.4 6 9.97 years </p>

<p>CEA 
38.2 6 8.67 
35.1 6 7.23 </p>

<p>AA 
58.6 6 6.97 
59.3 6 11.1 </p>

<p>Surgical side </p>

<p>Left 
12 
11 </p>

<p>Right 
17 
18 </p>

<p>Time in between: </p>

<p>Presentation-surgery 
4.05 6 3.26 months 
3.31 6 3.43 months </p>

<p>Follow-up (months) 
24.5 6 11.9 
22.8 6 5.33 </p>

<p>Associated injuries 
13 
4 
(P ¼ 0.020) </p>

<p>Smoker 
6 
1 
(P ¼ 0.037) </p>

<p>Drinker 
10 
9 </p>

<p>BMI 
27.52 6 3.70 
24.96 6 3.86 
(P ¼ 0.012) </p>

<p>Combined acetabular rim trimming and 
femoral osteochondroplasty </p>

<p>25 
22 </p>

<p>Femoral osteochondroplasty only 
4 
7 </p>

<p>Iliopsoas lengthening 
11 
8 </p>

<p>Trochanteric bursectomy 
8 
6 </p>

<p>Iliotibial band lengthening 
4 
6 </p>

<p>WC, Workers' Compensation; CEA, Center Edge Angle; AA, Alpha Angle; BMI, Body Mass Index. </p>

<p>Return to work in workers compensation following hip arthroscopy 35 </p>

<p>lower pre-and post-operative patient-reported outcome 
scores than their non-WC counterparts, but experienced 
the same magnitude of improvement in outcome scores 
with surgery. 
Comparable outcomes have been achieved in shoulder 
surgery for WC patients. Nicholson studied a cohort of 40 
WC patients undergoing arthroscopic acromioplasty and </p>

<p>found that post-operative American Shoulder and Elbow 
Surgeons scores (ASES), Simple Shoulder Test scores 
(SST) and Visual Analog Scale (VAS) pain scores were 
not significantly different as compared with non-WC pa-
tients [9]. However, WC patients had a significantly longer 
average time period prior to returning to full-duty work 
(P ¼ 0.0001) [9]. Bhatia et al. [27] found that 88.5% in a 
cohort of 69 WC patients returned to their preoperative 
level of work at a mean time to MMI of 7.6 months after 
arthroscopic rotator cuff repair. These patients demon-
strated improved outcomes using validated scoring scales 
at the time of follow-up, but outcomes remained inferior 
to non-WC patients as compared with a historical control 
group [27]. Cuff et al. [6] also found significantly lower 
ASES scores, SST scores, and VAS pain scores in a cohort 
of 50 WC patients undergoing arthroscopic rotator cuff re-
pair as compared with non-WC patients (P &lt; 0.0001). 
Interestingly, this study also stratified and analysed WC pa-
tients based on differential outcomes, showing that those 
who were compliant with the prescribed post-operative re-
habilitation protocol performed better on the ASES, SST 
and VAS pain score as compared with non-compliant pa-
tients (P &lt; 0.0001) at follow-up [6]. These results re-
inforce the findings presented in our study, emphasizing 
that a spectrum of outcomes exist within the WC 
population. 
In accordance with the literature, our WC cohort also 
shows lower pre-operative and post-operative outcomes 
scores compared with matched-controls. Nevertheless, we 
found that WC patients had significantly improved out-
come scores following hip arthroscopy regardless of ability 
to return to work without restrictions. Even though WC 
patients started at lower baseline outcome scores and 
ended up having lower post-operative outcome scores, 
their magnitude of improvement was similar to the 
matched-controls. This may indicate that since WC pa-
tients start at a lower baseline, the expectations regarding 
their ultimate outcomes would need to be adjusted 
accordingly. 
The current study demonstrates a significantly larger 
BMI in WC patients as compared with matched controls 
as well as a significantly larger BMI in WC patients who 
failed to return to work without restrictions after hip arth-
roscopy as compared with WC patients who failed to do 
so. BMI has been shown in other studies to be an inde-
pendent predictor of post-operative complications and 
inferior clinical outcomes. Gupta et al. [33] performed a 
retrospective review of 119 primary reverse total shoulder 
arthroplasties and determined that BMI was the only sig-
nificant determinant of overall complication rates and med-
ical complication rates (P &lt; 0.05). Similar conclusions </p>

<p>Table IV. Comparison of pre-operative and post-op-
erative patient-reported outcome scores for the WC 
patients and the matched controls </p>

<p>WC 
Controls 
P-values </p>

<p>All WC (n ¼ 29) </p>

<p>Preoperative </p>

<p>HOS-ADL 
46.5 6 16.9 69.2 6 19.6 (P &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>HOS-SS 
25.4 6 26.3 43.6 6 27.9 (P ¼ 0.025) </p>

<p>mHHS 
43.0 6 17.5 61.2 6 15.9 (P ¼ 0.001) </p>

<p>Post-operative </p>

<p>HOS-ADL 
76.8 6 12.5 89.9 6 6.76 (P &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>HOS-SS 
64.7 6 14.5 79.2 6 13.4 (P ¼ 0.001) </p>

<p>mHHS 
69.3 6 11.2 78.6 6 8.31 (P ¼ 0.011) </p>

<p>NR, NR Outcomes; WR, Poor Outcomes; HOS-ADL, Hip Outcome Score-
Activities of Daily Living; HOS-SS, Hip Outcome Score-Sports Specific 
Subscale; mHHS, Modified Harris Hip Scale. </p>

<p>Table V. Comparison of pre-and post-operative patient-
reported outcome scores for theWC patients who re-
turned to work without restrictions and those who failed 
to do so </p>

<p>Returned 
Failed 
P-values </p>

<p>Preoperative </p>

<p>HOS-ADL 
50.9 6 16.2 37.2 6 15.5 (P ¼ 0.059) </p>

<p>HOS-SS 
29.4 6 30.8 18.6 6 15.3 (P ¼ 0.367) </p>

<p>mHHS 
49.5 6 13.9 28.7 6 16.8 (P ¼ 0.011) </p>

<p>Post-operative </p>

<p>HOS-ADL 
82.0 6 8.82 65.3 6 12.0 (P &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>HOS-SS 
69.6 6 10.9 53.7 6 16.2 (P ¼ 0.004) </p>

<p>mHHS 
74.0 6 6.29 59.0 6 13.1 (P ¼ 0.009) </p>

<p>HOS-ADL, Hip Outcome Score-Activities of Daily Living; HOS-SS, Hip 
Outcome Score-Sports Specific Subscale; mHHS, Modified Harris Hip Scale. </p>



<p>have been found in studies on total shoulder arthroplasty, 
total knee arthroplasty and total hip arthroplasty [34-38]. 
Although the limited evidence exploring obesity in hip 
arthroscopy has not suggested significant impact on out-
comes, Collins et al. argued that obesity significantly in-
creases the risk of post-operative complications such as 
deep venous thrombosis and worsened hip pain [38, 39]. 
The potential interaction of a higher BMI in an already 
vulnerable group, such as WC patients, may represent an 
additional barrier to satisfactory outcomes. Identification 
of these patients preoperatively may be of benefit to the 
surgeon, allowing them to either adjust the expectations of 
the patient or to potentially apply weight loss interventions 
before surgery if appropriate. 
WC patients who failed to return to work without re-
strictions after hip arthroscopy had higher rate of associ-
ated orthopaedic injuries and a longer time period between 
initial injury and hip arthroscopy. The reason for associ-
ation of longer time from injury to surgery with failure to 
return to work without restrictions is not clear, but could 
potentially relate to deconditioning from longer timeframe 
of hip pain and dysfunction. Additionally, patients with 
associated injuries might have undergone workup and 
treatment for these injuries prior to addressing their hip 
pathology, which would represent a confounding variable. 
The WC patients who failed to return to work without 
restrictions had a 100% rate of concurrent orthopaedic 
conditions, as opposed to 20% in the patients who re-
turned to work without restrictions. In addition to a slowed 
recovery from hip arthroscopy, the management of these 
injuries may actually potentiate the pain experienced in the 
hip. The presence of associated injuries should alert the 
surgeon to adjust expectations for the patient, informing 
them of a potentially slower recovery period. </p>

<p>Limitations 
Our study is limited by the fact that our cohort reflects the 
patient population of only one tertiary care center in a 
major metropolitan area of one state. The findings based 
on this case mix may therefore not be generalizable. 
Differing worker's compensation (WC) regulations in dif-
ferent states may affect outcomes as well and may be con-
founded by conflicting issues such as potential secondary 
gain. Additionally, the study is retrospective in nature using 
a prospectively collected database and may potentially be 
underpowered as there were a limited number of eligible 
WC patients that met our inclusion criteria to be included 
in the analysis. Our sample size only allowed for matching 
on a limited number of variables, potentially not taking 
into account other important confounding variables. The 
patients' psychological state was also another potential </p>

<p>contributor to patient outcomes that was not explored in 
the current study. The addition of an outcomes survey 
with a psychological component such as the SF-12 or SF-
36 would have been able to examine this component. 
Patients had follow-up for at a minimum of 1-year post-op-
erative and until they obtained MMI status. This timeframe 
is relevant for treatment of a WC patient population re-
garding ability to return to work without restrictions and 
short-term patient reported outcomes, but longer follow-
up would also provide valuable information about the dur-
ability of hip arthroscopy results in the WC patient 
population. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS 
The majority of WC patients are able to return to work 
without restrictions when they reach MMI status following 
hip arthroscopy. WC patients exhibit significant improve-
ment in patient reported outcomes regardless of ability to 
return to work without restrictions, but scores remained 
lower than age and gender matched controls. Factors asso-
ciated with failure to return to work without restrictions in-
clude prolonged time course between injury and surgical 
treatment, concomitant orthopaedic injuries, and a higher 
BMI. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT 
None declared. </p>



<p>Return to work in workers compensation following hip arthroscopy 37 </p>





</text></tei>