<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5266189" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>To investigate the value of quantitative analysis in dual energy spectral computed tomography (DESCT) for differentiating malignant 
gastric mucosal lesions from benign gastric mucosal lesions (including gastric inflammation [GI] and normal gastric mucosa [NGM]). 
This study was approved by the ethics committee, and all patients provided written informed consent. A total of 161 consecutive 
patients (63 with gastric cancer [GC], 48 with GI, and 50 with NGM) who underwent dual-phase contrast enhanced DESCT scans in 
the arterial phase (AP) and portal venous phase (PVP) were included in this study. Iodine concentration (IC) in lesions was derived from 
the iodine-based material-decomposition images and normalized to that in the aorta to obtain normalized IC (nIC). The ratios of IC 
and nIC between the AP and PVP were calculated. Diagnostic confidence for GC and GI was evaluated with reviewing the features 
including gastric wall thickness, focal, and eccentric on the conventional polychromatic images. All statistical analyses were 
performed by using statistical software <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> (SPSS, Chicago, IL). IC and nIC in GC differed significantly from those in GI and 
NGM, except for nIC AP in comparing GC with GI. Mean nIC values of GC (0.18 ± 0.06 in AP and 0.62 ± 0.16 in PVP) were significantly 
higher than that of NGM (0.12 ± 0.03 in AP and 0.37 ± 0.08 in PVP) (all P &lt; 0.05). There was also significant difference for IC values in 
GC, GI, and NGM (24.19 ± 8.27, 19.07 ± 5.82, and 13.61 ± 2.52 mg/mL, respectively, in AP and 28.00 ± 7.01, 24.66 ± 6.55, and 
16.94 ± 3.06 mg/mL, respectively, in PVP). Based on Receiver Operating Characteristic Curve analysis, nIC and IC in PVP had high 
sensitivities of 88.89% and 90.48%, respectively, in differentiating GC from NGM, while the sensitivities were 71.43% and 88.89% 
during AP. Ratios IC and nIC ratios did not provide adequate diagnostic accuracy with their area under curves less than 0.65. With the 
conventional features, the diagnostic accuracies for GC and GI were 75.0% and 98.0%, respectively. Quantitative analysis of DESCT 
imaging parameters for gastric mucosa, such as nIC and IC, is useful for differentiating malignant from benign gastric mucosal lesions. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: AP = arterial phase, DESCT = dual energy spectral computed tomography, GC = gastric cancer, GI = gastric 
inflammation, GSI = gemstone spectral imaging, IC = iodine concentration, NGM = normal gastric mucosa, nIC = normalized IC, PVP 
= portal venous phase. </p>

<p>Gastric cancer (GC) is the fourth most common cancer and the 
second deadly cancer in the world, and the majority occurs in the 
developing countries and in East Asian countries, especially in </p>

<p>Japan, Korea, and China. 
[1,2] During the past 3 decades, the 
survival rate of GC has increased dramatically due to the early 
diagnosis. 
[3] Among the early GC patients whose lesions are 
limited to the gastric mucosa and submucosa, 95% patients will 
survive more than 5 years. 
[4] Consequently, early diagnosis for 
malignant gastric mucosal lesions is of great importance since 
the outcome is dependent on the initial stages. 
The standard method for diagnosing GC and distinguishing it 
from benign gastric condition was digestive endoscopy, com-
bined with biopsy and histopathological evaluation, which shows 
high diagnostic accuracy. 
[5] However, this method also has some 
shortcomings due its invasiveness. In addition, some early GCs 
with little contrast with the surrounding mucosa can even be 
missed during the routine endoscopic examination. 
[5,6] Also, 
endoscopy cannot evaluate the depth of gastric wall invasion and 
the distant metastatic lesions. 
Multidetector computed tomography (MDCT) has in recent 
years become a powerful and noninvasive tool for identifying 
gastric wall invasion and perigastric extent in GC patients, 
combined with multiple planar reconstruction and virtual 
endoscopy, the detection rates achieved 44% to 93.5%. </p>

<p>[7-10] </p>

<p>However, with conventional MDCT, the averaging attenuation 
effect and beam-hardening artifacts would reduce the ability to 
reliably detect lesions, especially the small lesions, such as gastric </p>

<p>Editor: Feng Yang. </p>

<p>Funding/support: Contract grant sponsor-National Natural Science Foundation 
of China; contract grant number: 81271529; Contract grant number-81371524. </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>a Department of Radiology, Tongji Hospital, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong 
University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, 
b Department of Radiology, The 
Central Hospital of Enshi Autonomous Prefecture, Enshi, Hubei, China. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Correspondence: Zhen Li, Department of Radiology, Tongji Hospital, Tongji 
Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan 
430030, China (e-mail: doclizhen@hotmail.com) </p>

<p>Copyright © 2017 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC), where it is 
permissible to download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided 
it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially without permission 
from the journal. </p>

<p>Medicine (2017) 96:2(e5878) </p>

<p>Received: 21 April 2016 / Received in final form: 19 December 2016 / Accepted: 
20 December 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000005878 </p>

<p>Diagnostic Accuracy Study </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>OPEN </p>



<p>mucosa lesions. 
[11] On the other hand, since the introduction in the 
late-2000, dual energy spectral computed tomography (DESCT) 
imaging, which is based on the rapid switching between 80 and 
140 kVp, has gained its popularity in angiography, cancer 
detection, characterization, and differentiation. 
[12-15] The gem-
stone spectral imaging (GSI) mode allows the reconstruction 
of monochromatic images with photon energy levels from 40 to 
140 keV and generates accurate material decomposition images, 
such as water-and iodine-based material-decomposition images. 
Material-decomposition images represent the amount or the 
density of different materials. The iodine concentration (IC) 
measurement in the iodine-based material decomposition image 
may be used to reflect the different contrast uptakes in gastric 
mucosa and GC, and the use of monochromatic X-ray beam in 
DESCT would eliminate the beam-hardening artifacts and average 
attenuation effects. 
[11,14,16,17] DESCT has demonstrated its value 
in gastric imaging to improve the N staging accuracy and to 
differentiate tumor histopathology type and lymph nodes. </p>

<p>[16] </p>

<p>However, the use of DESCT imaging in gastric mucosa has not 
been reported. The aim of this study was to introduce a 
quantitative analysis method in DESCT to differentiate GC from 
benign gastric mucosal condition, including gastric inflammation 
(GI) and normal gastric mucosa (NGM). </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Patients cohort </p>

<p>This retrospective study was approved by our Hospital Ethics 
Committee (Tongji Hospital, Wuhan), and all patients provided 
written informed consent before the CT examinations. We 
retrospectively analyzed the imaging information of 161 patients 
who underwent dual-phase contrast enhanced CT scanning 
successfully with GSI mode on a Discovery CT750HD scanner 
(GE Medical System; Milwaukee, WI) from February 2012 to 
January 2013 for detecting the presence of gastric, renal, or liver 
lesion. 
The inclusion criteria of our study were patients with GC or 
inflammation were histopathologically proved by surgery or by 
gastrointestinal endoscopy biopsy, patients had no contraindica-
tion for nonionic iodine contrast media, and patients with no 
chemotherapy or surgery. The interval between CT examination 
and biopsy or surgery was less than 1 week in GC and GI patients. 
Patients without any gastric symptom (such as stomach pain, 
nausea, abdominal distension, belching, and acid reflux, etc.), 
infectious diseases (such as cholecystitis and pancreatitis), or 
tumor history were confirmed as having NGM. 
A total of 165 consecutive patients were included for CT 
scanning, 4 patients were excluded from the study group after the 
CT scanning due to heavy artifacts caused by breathing. Among 
the 161 patients (M:F = 75:86; age range 16-77 years with mean 
age 50.02 ± 15.20 years), 63 patients (M:F = 29:34) had GC (19 
with early GC and 44 with advanced GC) confirmed by surgery 
or endoscopy, 48 patients (M:F = 26:22) had GI (21 with 
superficial gastritis and 27 with atrophic gastritis) confirmed by 
endoscopy, and 50 (M:F = 20:30) had NGM (shown in Fig. 1). </p>

<p>2.2. CT examinations </p>

<p>CT examinations were performed for all patients on a Discovery 
CT750HD scanner (GE Healthcare; Waukesha, WI). Before 
CT scanning, each patient orally took 800 to 1000 mL warm 
water in 15 to 20 minutes to achieve gastric pouch distention, 
then received 10 mg of butylscopolamine bromide (Buscopan, </p>

<p>Boehringer Ingelheim; Ingelheim, Germany) intravenously 
through an antecubital vein to minimize bowel peristalsis and 
to facilitate hypotonia. Scanning covered the entire stomach 
region (from the top of the diaphragm to the pelvis) during a 
single breath-hold with patients in the supine position. Nonionic 
contrast material (iopromide, Ultravist 370; Schering, Berlin, 
Germany) was injected through an 18-gauge angiographic 
catheter inserted into an antecubital vein at a rate of 3 to 4 
mL/s by using an automatic power injector (Stellant; Medrad, 
Indianola, PA), with a total dosage ranging between 60 and 100 
mL (1.0 mL/kg of body weight). After the contrast material 
injection, 20 mL normal saline solution was injected to flush 
contrast material in catheter and in blood vessel. 
The arterial phase (AP) scanning was performed at 30 seconds 
after the beginning of contrast material injection, and the portal 
venous phase (PVP) scan was performed at a delay of 20 seconds 
after finishing AP scanning. The dual-phase scanning was 
performed in the GSI mode with fast tube voltage switching 
between 80 and 140 kVp on adjacent views during a single 
rotation. Other scanning parameters were display field of view of 
40 cm, reconstruction matrix size 512 Â 512, collimation of 40 
mm, slice thickness and interval for axial images of 5 mm/5 mm, 
tube current of 600 mA, rotation speed of 0.6 seconds, helical 
pitch of 0.983, and with a fixed volumetric CT dose index of 21.8 
mGy for each phase. Images were reconstructed by using 
projection-based material-decomposition software and a stan-
dard reconstruction kernel. Two types of images were recon-
structed from the single spectral CT acquisition for analysis: 
iodine-based material decomposition images and monochromat-
ic images obtained at energies ranging from 40 to 140 keV. All 
images were reconstructed to 0.625 mm for quantitative analysis. </p>

<p>2.3. Imaging analysis </p>

<p>All DESCT data were transferred to an Advantage Workstation 
4.5 (ADW 4.5) (GE Healthcare) for image analysis and data 
measurement. 
Two experienced abdominal radiologists (5 and 9 years in 
abdominal imaging) manually placed circular regions of interest 
(ROIs) on gastric mucosa in axial 70-keV monochromatic images 
(slice thickness 0.625 mm) independently. Suitable ROIs were set 
for covering the mucosa with an area of about 1.81 mm 
2 , 
avoiding cystic, necrosis, and hemorrhage, to measure imaging </p>

<p>Figure 1. Flowchart of patient selection. DESCT = dual energy spectral 
computed tomography. </p>

<p>Meng et al. Medicine (2017) 96:2 
Medicine </p>



<p>parameters of mucosa. All ROIs were automatically propagated 
to monochromatic images of all energy levels (40-140 keV) and 
water-and iodine-based material decomposition images. CT 
attenuation values were measured from the monochromatic 
image sets to generate a spectral hounsfield unit curve (CT 
number as function of photon energy), and the ICs were also 
calculated automatically. 
Each reader placed the ROIs in 3 neighboring areas on mucosa, 
the average of the 2 readers was the final value. To minimize the 
variations between patients, the IC of mucosa was normalized to 
the IC of aorta both for AP and PVP with a suitable ROI as large 
as possible in the same level to derive a normalized IC (nIC) with 
formula: nIC = IC lesion /IC aorta . IC and nIC ratios were calculated 
with the formulas: IC ratio = IC PVP /IC AP , nIC ratio = nIC PVP / 
nIC AP (IC PVP and IC AP values were IC in PVP and AP, 
respectively, and nIC PVP and nIC AP were nIC values in PVP 
and AP, respectively). 
Four experienced abdominal radiologists (above 5 years) 
reviewed the GC and GI conventional polychromatic images at 
the workstation. They were blinded to the diagnosis of the 
lesions, patient's information, and symptom. The readers 
measured the gastric wall thickness on the balanced lesions 
and reviewed the following features including the gastric wall 
thickness, eccentric, and focal on the conventional polychromatic 
images. According to the features above, the images were scored 
as levels 1-carcinoma, 0-unidentified, and À1-inflammation 
both for GC and GI groups. When the view was inconsistent, the 
decision was made with discussion by these 4 radiologists. </p>

<p>2.4. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">17.0</rs> (SPSS, 
Chicago, IL) statistical software for Windows. All quantitative 
data were presented as mean ± standard deviation. The one-way 
analysis of variance test with post hoc Bonferroni correction was 
performed to compare the parameters IC, nIC, IC ratio, and nIC 
ratio between GC and GI, GC and NGM, and GI and NGM both 
in AP and PVP, with P &lt; 0.05 indicating statistical significance. 
Receiver operating characteristic curve (ROC) analysis was 
performed to calculate the diagnostic accuracy of IC, nIC, IC 
ratio, and nIC ratio and to establish the optimal threshold values 
to discriminating GC from NGM and GI. Area under curve 
(AUC) for the ROC curve, sensitivity, specificity, and cutoff value 
were calculated. The null hypothesis tested was that the AUC was 
0.5, and the alternative was that the AUC was greater than 0.5. 
Diagnostic accuracy was analyzed with the diagnostic 
confidence and the clinical results (including pathological and 
endoscopic results). The interobserver agreement for the gastric </p>

<p>lesions and aorta IC measurement was calculated with the 
interclass correlation coefficient (ICC). The interobserver 
agreement was defined as almost perfect (0.81-1.00), substantial 
(0.61-0.80), moderate (0.41-0.60), fair (0.21-0.40), slight 
(0.00-0.20), and poor (&lt;0.00). </p>

<p>[18] </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>Values of nIC, IC, IC ratio, and nIC ratio for GC, GI, and NGM 
in both AP and PVP for the spectral CT quantitative assessment 
are listed in Table 1. The quantitative parameters for the 3 groups 
were compared with each other. IC and nIC values in patients 
with GC were significantly different from those in patients with 
GI and NGM, except for nIC AP in comparing GC with GI. Mean 
nIC of GC in AP (0.18 ± 0.06) was higher than that of GI (0.16 ± 
0.05) without significant difference while was significantly higher 
than that of NGM (0.12 ± 0.03), and nIC of GC in PVP (0.62 ± 
0.16) was significantly higher than that of GI (0.54 ± 0.15) and 
NGM (0.37 ± 0.08) (P &lt; 0.01). There was also significant 
difference for IC values in GC, GI, and NGM (24.19 ± 8.27, 
19.07 ± 5.82, and 13.61 ± 2.52 mg/mL, respectively, in AP and 
28.00 ± 7.0182, 24.66 ± 6.5582, and 16.94 ± 3.0682 mg/mL, 
respectively, in PVP). The nIC ratio of GC (3.72 ± 1.23) and 
GI (3.69 ± 1.35) was higher than that of NGM (3.20 ± 1.08), but 
there was no difference between each other. For IC ratio, there 
was no significant difference among GC, GI, and NGM (P &gt; 
0.05) (showed in Figs. 2-4). 
The ROC curves for different parameters in DESCT in 
differentiating GC from GI and NGM during AP and PVP are 
shown in Fig. 5. The parameter cutoff values required to optimize 
both the sensitivity and specificity for distinguishing the 2 types of 
mucosa are also listed. Based on the ROC analysis, nIC and IC in 
PVP had high sensitivity of 88.89% and 90.48% in differentiat-
ing GC from NGM, respectively, and the values were 71.43% 
and 88.89% during AP. For differentiating GI from NGM, using 
a threshold of 0.45 for nIC in PVP would provide sensitivity of 
72.92% and specificity of 86.00% with AUC of 0.86, while using 
a threshold of 22.25 mg/mL for IC in PVP would provide 
sensitivity of 68.75% and specificity of 96.00% with AUC of 
0.86. However, both the IC and nIC ratios did not show strong 
evidence for diagnosing the gastric mucosa lesions, with all of the 
AUCs less than 0.65 (showed in Table 2). 
The thickness of gastric carcinoma (11.83 ± 4.32 mm) was 
significantly higher than that of gastritis (6.65 ± 2.33 mm) (P &lt; 
0.01). In gastric carcinoma, the occurrence rate of focal and 
eccentric sign was higher than that of gastritis. With the features 
on the conventional polychromatic images, the diagnostic 
accuracies for GC and GI were 75% (47/63) and 98% (47/ </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Spectral computed tomography quantitative assessment of GC and gastric inflammation in gastric mucosa and normal gastric mucosa. </p>

<p>Value and index 
F 
P </p>

<p>ANOVA test  *  (P) </p>

<p>GC 
GI 
NGM 
GC vs GI 
GC vs NGM 
GI vs NGM </p>

<p>nIC AP 
0.18 ± 0.06 
0.16 ± 0.05 
0.12 ± 0.03 
17.75 
0.00 
0.116 
0.000 
0.001 
nIC PVP 
0.62 ± 0.16 
0.54 ± 0.15 
0.37 ± 0.08 
45.78 
0.00 
0.010 
0.000 
0.000 
IC AP 
24.19 ± 8.27 
19.07 ± 5.82 
13.61 ± 2.52 
40.19 
0.00 
0.000 
0.000 
0.000 
IC PVP 
28.00 ± 7.01 
24.66 ± 6.55 
16.94 ± 3.06 
49.99 
0.00 
0.011 
0.000 
0.000 
nIC ratio 
3.72 ± 1.23 
3.69 ± 1.35 
3.20 ± 1.08 
3.07 
0.49 
-
-
-
IC ratio 
1.23 ± 0.37 
1.35 ± 0.34 
1.26 ± 0.20 
1.75 
0.18 
-
-
-</p>

<p>ICs were cited in milligrams per milliliter (mg/mL); data were mean value ± standard deviation, P &lt; 0.05 indicated statistically difference between GC and GI, GC and NGM, and GI and NGM. AP = arterial phase, IC 
ratio = IC PVP /IC AP , IC = iodine concentration, nIC (normalized IC) = IC lesion /IC aorta , nIC ratio = nIC PVP /nIC AP , GC = gastric cancer, GI = gastric inflammation, NGM = normal gastric mucosa PVP = portal venous 
phase. ANOVA test was calculated with post hoc Bonferroni correction. </p>

<p>Meng et al. Medicine (2017) 96:2 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>Figure 2. Contrast enhanced images of a 60-year-old man with a right renal cyst show the iodine concentration (IC), regions of interests (ROIs), computed 
tomography attenuation, and spectral curve with normal gastric mucosa. (A) Iodine-based material-decomposition image at 70 keV with ROI setting on partial 
enlarged views during portal venous phase (PVP) and showed that IC of NGM was 13 mg/mL and normalized IC was 0.272. (B) Graph showed spectral HU curves 
of aorta (blue) and NGM (the other 3 colors) during PVP. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Contrast enhanced gemstone spectral imaging images of a 61-year-old man with early gastric adenocarcinoma (staged T1) demonstrated focal 
thickening and focalized mucosa absent in the gastric cardia during portal venous phase (PVP). (A and B) Monochromatic image at 70 keV in PVP showed the 
focalized mucosa absent and location of the regions of interests. (C) Iodine-based material-decomposition image showed that iodine concentration of gastric 
cancer mucosa was 29.1 mg/mL and normalized iodine concentration was 0.67. (D) Graph showed spectral HU curves of aorta (blue) and the mucosa of gastric 
cancer mucosa (the other 3 colors) during the PVP. </p>

<p>Meng et al. Medicine (2017) 96:2 
Medicine </p>



<p>Figure 4. Contrast enhanced gemstone spectral imaging images from a 59-year-old man with undifferentiated adenocarcinoma staged T4 in the lesser curvature 
of gastric in portal venous phase (PVP). (A) Monochromatic image at 70 keV during PVP showed the thickened gastric wall. (B) Iodine-based material-
decomposition image showed that the iodine concentration of gastric cancer mucosa was 21.6 mg/mL, and the normalized iodine concentration was 0.55. (C) 
Water-based material-decomposition image. (D) Graph showed spectral HU curves of aorta (blue) and the mucosa of gastric cancer mucosa (the other 3 colors) 
during PVP. </p>

<p>Figure 5. ROC curves for spectral computed tomography parameters (included iodine concentration [IC], normalized IC [nIC], IC ratio, and nIC ratio) during arterial 
phase and portal venous phase of the gastric mucosa in distinguishing (A) gastric cancer (GC) from gastric inflammation (GI), (B) GC from normal gastric mucosa 
(NGM), (C) GI from NGM, and (D) GC from benign gastric mucosa (GI and NGM included). </p>

<p>Meng et al. Medicine (2017) 96:2 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>48), respectively (showed in Table 3). The interobserver 
agreement for the IC measurement between these 4 readers 
was almost perfect with all ICCs above 0.9. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we investigated the use of nontraditional CT 
quantitative parameters (such as IC) in DESCT for differentiating 
malignant gastric mucosal lesions from benign gastric mucosal 
lesions (including GI and NGM). For medical diagnostic imaging 
with GSI scanning mode, water and iodine were often selected as 
the basis material pairs for material-decomposition image 
presentation because their atomic numbers span the range of 
atomic numbers for materials generally found in medical imaging 
and approximate those of soft tissue and iodinated contrast 
material to result in material-attenuation images that were 
intuitive to interpret. 
[11,14] For GC and GI in the mucosa and 
NGM, their IC values were derived from the iodine-based 
material decomposition images. 
The quantitative parameter IC could be used to effectively 
reflect the degree of enhancement and the blood supply of 
lesions. 
[14] Our result showed that IC of GC was significantly 
higher than that of NGM both in AP and PVP. The increased IC 
value in GC would indicate the increased angiogenesis in the 
development of tumors, since the angiogenesis is the fundamental 
process and the growth formation would determine their 
enhancement in CT. 
[19] ROC analysis in this study indicated 
that IC had high sensitivity and specificity for discriminating GC 
from NGM. In PVP, a threshold of 21.17 mg/mL for IC in PVP 
would yield a sensitivity of 90.48% and specificity of 92.0% 
for differentiating GC from NGM. On the other hand, the 
inflammatory lesions are also associated with increased angio-
genesis, which will result in similar effects to tumor-associated 
neovascularization. 
[19] Our study revealed that even though there </p>

<p>was no statistically significant difference in the IC value between 
GC and GI, and the AUC values were not high enough to provide 
clinically meaningful diagnostic power to differentiate GC from 
GI. On the other hand, using IC in PVP, we were able to obtain 
AUC of 0.86 with sensitivity of 68.75% and specificity of 96% 
for the differentiation of GI from NGM. 
Since simple measurements of IC within tissues might be 
influenced by patient variations in height, weight, cardiac output, 
and central blood volume, we also calculated the nIC, which uses 
the IC of aorta as the reference parameter to minimize the 
variations in patients. 
[11,20] The nICs during the PVP provided 
high sensitivity for diagnosing GC from NGM. In PVP, nIC of 
GC was significantly higher than that of NGM, and a threshold 
for nIC of 0.48 yielded a high sensitivity of 88.89% and 
specificity of 96.00% for differentiating GC from NGM, and the 
AUC reached 0.94. Our results are consistent with many other 
clinical applications in that the quantitative nIC measurement 
was proven to be valuable, such as differentiating hepatic lesions, 
evaluating lymph nodes in rectal cancer and papillary thyroid 
cancer, and distinguishing between differentiated and undiffer-
entiated GCs. 
[11,14,16,18,21] On the other hand, results indicated 
that the nIC ratio (including IC ratio) had no diagnostic value for 
discriminating GC from GI and NGM. 
In general, we found that values in PVP provided higher 
diagnostic power than that in AP. Using nIC in AP, the sensitivity 
and specificity were only 71.43% and 80.00%, respectively, with 
an AUC of 0.80 for differentiating GC from NGM. The AUCs in 
PVP were higher than in AP for other group pairs. Some 
authors 
[11,15] reported that measuring ICs in PVP could increase 
the accuracy for distinguishing small hepatocellular carcinoma 
from other hepatic lesions than in AP, due to the fact that contrast 
could effectively disperse in the liver and tissue in PVP. Combing 
the conventional size criterion, the nIC of lymph nodes during the 
PVP would improve the diagnostic accuracy for distinguishing 
metastatic from nonmetastatic lymph nodes in rectal cancer due 
to the contrast media both in intrasvasular and extravascular 
space with the leakage to the extravascular space. </p>

<p>[18] </p>

<p>In this study, the nIC of GC was higher than that of GI with a 
high sensitivity, while with a low specificity (41.67%). Gastric 
carcinoma originated from the mucosa and the sequence was 
from chronic nonatrophic gastritis that progressed to chronic 
atrophic gastritis, which might lead to intestinal metaplasia, 
dysplasia, and finally adenocarcinoma. 
[4] In addition, there is 
increasing evidence that the inflammation seems to play a critical 
role in the development and progression of numerous can-
cers. 
[22,23] The main reaction of inflammation is the increased 
blood flow secondary to vasodilation and increased vascular 
permeability, which would lead to more IC in the gastric mucosa </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Diagnostic performance of spectral computed tomography quantitative parameters for discriminating GC from GI and NGM. </p>

<p>GC vs GI 
GC vs NGM 
GI vs NGM 
GC vs (GI and NGM) </p>

<p>AUC Cutoff Sensitivity Specificity AUC Cutoff Sensitivity Specificity AUC Cutoff Sensitivity Specificity AUC Cutoff Sensitivity Specificity </p>

<p>nIC AP 
0.61 0.17 
53.90 
70.83 
0.80 0.14 
71.43 
80.00 
0.71 0.16 
50.00 
88.00 
0.71 0.17 
53.97 
81.63 
nIC PVP 0.67 0.48 
88.89 
41.67 
0.94 0.48 
88.89 
96.00 
0.86 0.45 
72.92 
86.00 
0.80 0.48 
88.89 
69.39 
IC AP 
0.70 21.91 
60.32 
75.00 
0.92 15.92 
88.89 
90.00 
0.82 15.42 
68.75 
86.00 
0.81 18.92 
77.78 
75.51 
IC PVP 
0.64 24.58 
71.43 
74.92 
0.94 21.17 
90.48 
92.00 
0.86 22.25 
68.75 
96.00 
0.79 21.17 
90.48 
61.22 
nIC ratio 0.52 2.55 
90.48 
22.92 
0.64 4.04 
36.51 
90.00 
0.63 0.36 
56.25 
78.00 
0.58 4.01 
38.10 
79.59 
IC ratio 0.39 1.05 
38.10 
85.42 
0.42 1.06 
39.68 
92.00 
0.57 1.58 
22.92 
94.00 
0.41 1.05 
38.10 
88.78 </p>

<p>ICs were cited in milligrams per milliliter (mg/mL); AUC = area under curve of the receiver operating characteristic curve; sensitivity and specificity were cited as percentages. AP = arterial phase, IC ratio = IC PVP / 
IC AP , IC = iodine concentration, nIC (normalized IC) = IC lesion /IC aorta , nIC ratio = nIC PVP /nIC AP , GC = gastric cancer, GI = gastric inflammation, NGM = normal gastric mucosa PVP = portal venous phase. </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Features on the conventional images and diagnostic accuracy for 
GC and GI. </p>

<p>Features 
GC 
GI </p>

<p>Thickness 
(mm) 
11.83 ± 4.32 
6.65 ± 2.33 
Focal 
(yes or no) 
89%(56/63) 
21%(10/48) 
Eccentric 
(yes or no) 
82%(52/63) 
2%(1/48) 
Diagnostic 
confidence </p>

<p>1, carcinoma 
47 
0 </p>

<p>0, unidentified 
14 
1 
À1, gastritis 
2 
47 
Accuracy 
75%(47/63) 
98%(47/48) </p>

<p>Meng et al. Medicine (2017) 96:2 
Medicine </p>



<p>in enhanced CT. 
[14,19,22] Insko et al 
[24] summarized taking 
advantage of the gastric wall thickness was 1 cm or greater, 
focal, eccentric, and gastric wall enhanced almost would reach a 
92% specificity for indicating malignant lesions, while with a low 
sensitivity. So taking these features into account, the diagnostic 
accuracy for GI has reached 98%. In the clinical study, combing 
the quantitative analysis and conventional features would 
provide more diagnostic information. 
Our study did have some limitations. First, the patients of 
NGM group were confirmed by clinical information, and not all 
NGM patients were confirmed by pathological or endoscopy, the 
normal group might have slight gastritis which may lead to some 
bias in the study. Second, in this study, we focused our attention 
on the quantitative analysis of the IC of gastric mucosa without 
the evaluation of N staging. The use of optimal monochromatic 
images in spectral CT imaging could improve the N staging 
accuracy for GCs which was the key for choosing accurate 
therapy. 
[16] Third, in this study, few patients of early GC had 
lesion localized in mucosa layer, the result should be verified in 
large-scale clinical study. Fourth, we did not divide the GC 
patients into different pathological pattern groups. In the 
following study, we will consider the diversity outcome from 
different mucosa pathological patterns. Finally, the thickness of 
gastric mucosa was just 2 to 3 mm, which made it difficult to place 
ROIs. 
In conclusion, quantitative analysis of spectral CT parameters 
may be used to improve the sensitivity and specificity for 
differentiating malignant mucosa from benign gastric mucosa 
with DESCT, especially in PVP. </p>





</text></tei>