<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5066857" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To assess those published cases of yellow fever (YF) vaccine-associated viscerotropic 
disease that meet the Brighton Collaboration criteria and to assess the safety of YF vaccine with 
respect to viscerotropic disease. 
Literature search: Ten electronic databases were searched with no restriction of date or 
language and reference lists of retrieved articles. 
Methods: All abstracts and titles were independently read by two reviewers and data indepen-
dently entered by two reviewers. 
Results: All serious adverse events that met the Brighton Classification criteria were associated 
with first YF vaccinations. Sixty-two published cases (35 died) met the Brighton Collaboration 
viscerotropic criteria, with 32 from the US, six from Brazil, five from Peru, three from Spain, 
two from the People's Republic of China, one each from YF is caused by a flavivirus endemic in the tropical areas of 31 African and ten Latin 
American countries (refer to the maps by Monath and Vasconcelos). 
1 The yellow fever 
virus (YFV) is transmitted in forests and jungles in Africa by Aedes africanus mosqui-
toes and in South America by Haemagogus and Sabethes species, with monkeys as the 
primary host and infecting forest dwellers and visitors such as construction workers 
or loggers. In African savannah areas, Aedes species transmit the virus to monkeys or 
humans as the intermediate hosts, and in urban areas Aedes aegyptii (which breeds in 
water containers in or near dwellings) transmits infection between humans (refer to the 
transmission diagram by Quaresma et al). 
1,2 Because of the greater intensity of urban </p>

<p>Correspondence: Roger e Thomas 
Department of Family Medicine, Faculty 
of Medicine, University of Calgary, 
Research Office, G012, Health Sciences 
Centre, 3330 Hospital Drive Nw, 
Calgary T2N 4N1, AB, Canada 
Tel +1 403 210 9208 
Fax +1 403 270 4329 
email rthomas@ucalgary.ca </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Drug Design, Development and Therapy 
12 October 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3346 </p>

<p>Thomas </p>

<p>populations, large epidemics are more likely in urban areas. </p>

<p>1   There has been an intense YFV circulation in Brazil since 
1997 and also in Peru, Colombia, Argentina, and Paraguay. 
In Africa, large epidemics occur in West Africa (irregularly 
every 5-20 years) and East Africa (at longer intervals such 
as 45 years), and there have been sustained epidemics in 
Nigeria, Ghana, and Guinea in the past 30 years. 
1 An outbreak 
in Angola began in December 2015. Deforestation increases 
biting by canopy-dwelling vectors at ground level, and 
colonization of new areas in endemic zones (eg, migration 
of unvaccinated coastal dwellers into the hinterland in Peru) 
resulted in an increase in YF cases. 
1 Current risk areas for 
YF are described in the publications by Jentes et al, 
3 Hill, </p>

<p>4   and Rogers et al. 
5 One estimate is that in Africa since 2008 
only 1%-2% of the cases suspected on clinical grounds had 
laboratory proof. Mortality from YF in Africa is ~20% and 
40%-60% in Latin America. 
1 The incubation period after a 
mosquito bite is 3-6 days, and then the patient experiences 
headaches, fever, muscle and joint aching, poor appetite, 
and vomiting. Then, there is a 3-to 4-day period of remis-
sion with fewer clinical symptoms, and the patient either 
recovers or goes into the intoxication stage of high fever, 
abdominal pain, a lowered state of consciousness, and nau-
sea and vomiting. The patient is likely to be jaundiced and 
have multiple sources of bleeding (hematemesis, melena, 
petechiae, and ecchymoses) and go into multiorgan failure 
due to hypotension, fluid loss, capillary fragility, hepatitis, 
and renal failure. 
2,6 There is rapid viral replication in lymph 
nodes and then systemic spread to the bone marrow, liver, 
and spleen. A characteristic pathological sign in the liver 
is midzonal hepatocellular degeneration with eosinophilic 
Councilman bodies, and Councilman bodies are also seen 
in the kidneys and myocardium. 
6 The immune responses 
involve the proinflammatory cytokine interleukin-6, CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>helper lymphocytes, CD8 
+ cytotoxic lymphocytes, and natu-
ral killer cells. The main cause of cellular death is apoptosis 
due to transforming growth factor beta. 
1,2 (refer Figure 5 in 
Quaresma et al </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). The seven YFV genotypes (five African and 
two South American) form a single serotype, and evolution-
ary rates in all genotypes are similar at 2-5×10 
−4 substitutions/ 
site/year (less than other flaviviruses such as dengue). 
The South American genotypes I and II differ by up to 16% 
at the nucleotide level from the African genotypes, and each 
subtype contains clades. 
6 Immunity to other flaviviruses con-
fers some immunity to YF. 
1 The signs and symptoms of YF 
are similar to those of viral hepatitis, malaria, leptospirosis, 
typhus, Ebola, and other hemorrhagic fevers. An outbreak of 
YF can go undetected because health workers in remote areas </p>

<p>may find it difficult to make a definitive diagnosis based on 
the signs and symptoms alone, and in mild cases, the patient 
may be treated at home and not seek health care. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>YF vaccines </p>

<p>Strain 17DD is used to manufacture vaccine in Brazil and 
17D-204 by the other five manufacturers, with no significant 
differences in immunogenicity or safety. 
1 The vaccine 
replicates initially in lymphoid and reticuloendothelial tissues 
and is found in the blood in the first week and may persist 
into the second week. Vaccines based on 17D and using 
the substrains 17DD and 17D-204 have very low interlot 
variability and high genetic stability levels. 
8,9 Risk factors 
for vaccination include thymic disease, a thymectomy, 
and autoimmune suppression. A review concluded that the 
evidence for risk for the elderly remains limited, and vac-
cination should be based on a risk-benefit analysis. </p>

<p>10   effectiveness of YF vaccines </p>

<p>YF vaccination results in an exceptionally strong and 
lifelong immune response. The log neutralization index to 
neutralize virus after vaccination averages 2.2, which is 
30 times greater than that needed for protection. The effect 
is due to a wide-ranging immune response: the production 
of neutralizing antibodies to highly conserved confor-
mational epitopes in the envelope glycoprotein and to 
robust T-cell responses (CD4 
+ , CD8 
+ , and central memory 
CD45RA 
+ ), increases in natural killer cells, interferons, 
activation of multiple genes by interferons, the complement 
system, and innate immune sensors (Toll-like receptors), 
and proinflammatory cytokines (interleukin-6 and -2, 
tumor necrosis factor, IP-10, MCP-1, and RANTES). 
1 The 
neutralizing antibodies are found in 90% of recipients by 
day 10 (and then the vaccination certificate is valid) and 
in nearly 100% by day 30, 
1 are thus highly immunogenic 
(91%-100%), 
8,9 and provide an estimated .40 years of 
protection. The Global Vaccine Action Plan Alliance 
(Global Alliance for Vaccines and Immunization) plans to 
reduce the number of YF deaths from epidemic YF by the 
planned vaccination of 174 million individuals in Africa 
and Latin America between 2011 and 2020. From a 1993 
Nigerian study, they estimated that one epidemic death 
would be averted for each 5,000 persons vaccinated. They 
also estimated that the average interval between epidemics 
is 17 years, and 4 million persons in the target populations 
on average would be affected per epidemic with 20% 
epidemic incidence and a 20% proportional case fatality 
ratio. They assumed 95% vaccine effectiveness against </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3347 </p>

<p>Yellow fever vaccine-associated viscerotropic disease </p>

<p>YF death and lifetime immunity and that if population 
immunity of .60% could be achieved, epidemic trans-
mission could be prevented. Based on these assumptions, 
they computed that vaccinating 174 million individuals 
between 2011 and 2020 will avert 34,849 deaths in Africa 
and Latin America. 
8 Travelers from developed countries 
have shorter exposures and accommodations more pro-
tected from mosquitoes, and it is estimated that the risk 
of disease for an unvaccinated traveler during endemic 
periods is one in 267 and of death is one in 1,333 in an 
African country in which YF is endemic, with levels ten 
times lower in South America. </p>

<p>11   Serious adverse events after YF 
vaccination </p>

<p>The World Health Organization (WHO) defines serious 
adverse events after YF vaccination as: </p>

<p>An Adverse Event Following Immunization (AEFI) will be </p>

<p>considered serious if it results in death, is life-threatening, </p>

<p>requires in-patient hospitalization or prolongation of existing </p>

<p>hospitalization, results in persistent or significant disability/ </p>

<p>incapacity, is a congenital anomaly/birth defect, or required </p>

<p>intervention to prevent permanent impairment or damage. </p>

<p>12   Serious adverse events include anaphylaxis, neurologic, and 
viscerotropic events. </p>

<p>12   The Brighton Collaboration case 
definitions and levels of diagnostic 
certainty of viscerotropic disease </p>

<p>The key definition of viscerotropic disease as a serious 
post-YFV adverse event is the Brighton Collaboration 
definition (which builds on the initial definition of the 
US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention working 
group). The collaboration provides detailed case definitions 
and diagnostic methods for these serious events reported 
after YF vaccination: anaphylaxis, neurologic syndromes 
(encephalitis, myelitis, acute disseminated encephalo-
myelitis [ADEM], and Guillain-Barré syndrome), and 
viscerotropic disease (multiorgan failure). The Brighton 
Collaboration case definitions yield three diagnostic cer-
tainty levels: Level 1 (most specific), Level 2, and Level 
3 (least specificity and greatest sensitivity). The viscero-
topic disease definition provides two classifications: the 
viscerotropic disease classification is based on seven major 
and six minor criteria of laboratory evidence of major 
organ dysfunction and provides three levels of evidence: 
Level 1 (three major criteria), Level 2 (two major or one </p>

<p>major + two or more minor), and Level 3 (jaundice and 
two or more other minor or three or more minor, or one 
major and one minor). Viscerotropic disease also provides 
a second level of classification: an YF vaccine-associated 
viscerotropic disease (YEL-AVD) classification with 
suspected, probable, and confirmed levels with the con-
firmed level based on laboratory confirmation of YF vac-
cine virus detection. 
13 A patient with post-YF vaccination 
viscerotropic disease will experience similar symptoms 
to those of a patient who has wild-type disease. Because 
many other diseases in YF areas can mimic aspects of 
viscerotropic disease, the definitions strongly emphasize 
laboratory confirmation, and clinical symptoms are only 
assessed as minor criteria. Table 1 lists the major and minor 
criteria: clinical symptoms and signs occur only as minor 
criteria for viscerotropic disease and then only as five of 
seven criteria. The Brighton Collaboration reviewed the 
clinical symptoms and signs of 36 cases of YEL-AVD and 
specifically excluded fever, bradycardia, and tachycardia 
and rated laboratory proof as major criteria (eg, elevated 
bilirubin) and jaundice as a minor criterion. </p>

<p>13   Purpose of the review and update </p>

<p>After five deaths occurred in Peru in 2007 following YF 
vaccination, 
14 the Global Alliance for Vaccines and Immu-
nization commissioned the WHO to organize a systematic 
review of the safety of YF vaccine. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Literature search </p>

<p>For the initial review for the WHO, the Cochrane Library 
(including the Cochrane CENTRAL Register of Controlled 
Trials, the Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews, and 
the NHS Database of Abstracts of Reviews of Effects), 
MEDLINE, EMBASE, BIOSIS Previews, Global Health, 
CAB Abstracts, and the Lilacs Database of Latin American 
and Caribbean literature were searched for individual studies 
and systematic reviews through July 10, 2013, with no 
language or date limits. Reference lists of included articles 
were searched for additional studies. </p>

<p>Search update </p>

<p>On May 12, 2016, PubMed and MEDLINE were searched 
using the terms viscerotropic and (yellow fever vaccine) 
and (adverse events). Although the original searches 
were conducted through July 10, 2013, the new search in 
MEDLINE was conducted in 2011-2016 to avoid missing 
any publications. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3348 </p>

<p>Thomas </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The data were entered into a specially designed database in 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">ACCESS</rs>. 
15 For the initial review, all abstracts and 
full-text articles were independently read by two reviewers 
(RET, Wendy Spragins) to determine relevance, with any dis-
agreements resolved by a third reviewer (Diane Lorenzetti). 
To maximize sensitivity in detecting cases, we assessed any 
report whose title, abstract, or text proposed that a patient had 
suffered one of the abovementioned serious adverse events 
after YF vaccination. The systematic review was conducted 
according to Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic 
Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) 
16 guidelines. </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>For each case, these data were independently entered by two 
authors (RET, WS). 1) Age, sex, country, vaccine type, batch 
number, days till first symptoms, and if the patient died; 
2) Brighton Collaboration major and minor criteria and level 
of diagnostic certainty for each of anaphylaxis, encephalitis, 
myelitis, acute disseminated meningoencephalitis, Guillain-
Barré syndrome, viscerotropic disease, and YEL-AVD 
vaccine-associated causality; 3) laboratory tests for YF and 
other infectious diseases; 4) other laboratory tests; 5) other 
findings (past medical history, vaccines, current medica-
tions); 6) decisions, with five criteria: i) Is the method by 
which the authors selected the case clearly described? Did 
the authors assess probable confounders in the past medical 
history? Did the authors address probable confounders from 
medications, vaccines, or other interventions? ii) Are there 
complete clinical data for the case? iii) Is there complete </p>

<p>detection of adverse event following immunization due to 
YF vaccination with sensitive, specific, and valid outcome 
measures? iv) Is there complete assessment of probable con-
founders: other infections, illnesses? v) What is the judgment 
on this case: does the case meet the Brighton Collaboration 
criteria and at what level? vi) A Decision Flow Sheet. The 
principal classification of a case was according to the higher 
level of evidence reached (eg, if a case met both Encepha-
litis 2 and ADEM 3 criteria, the principal classification was 
Encephalitis 2 and the secondary classification ADEM 3). 
For the update, four new viscerotropic cases discovered by 
the new literature search were entered. Some cases were 
published in a series without citation from the original 
author, and we compared the clinical and laboratory details 
of all cases to ensure no duplicate cases were included in 
this systematic review. </p>

<p>Results 
Literature search </p>

<p>Electronic and other database searching identified 4,498 
abstracts and 66 from other sources, with 2,888 records after 
removal of duplicates. Of these, 745 articles were selected for 
full-text retrieval and 93 articles reporting individual cases or 
series were included in this review (Figure 1). The findings of 
systematic reviews of pharmacovigilance databases, 
17 active 
and passive surveillance systems, 
18 and groups regarded at 
high risk 
19 (children, pregnant females, HIV+ individuals, 
older persons, patients with malignancy, immunosuppressed 
or taking immunosuppressive medications) are incorporated 
into this review. </p>

<p>Table 1 Major and minor criteria for the case definition of viscerotropic disease </p>

<p>Major criteria 
Laboratory or clinical data 
Hepatic 
Total bilirubin $1.5× ULN or $1.5× patient's Bv or ALT or AST $3× ULN or $3× patient's Bv 
Renal 
Creatinine $1.5× ULN or $1.5× patient's Bv 
Musculoskeletal 
CPK $5× ULN 
Respiratory 
Oxygen saturation #88% on room air or requirement for mechanical ventilation 
Platelet disorder 
Platelets ,100,000/μL 
Hypotension 
Requirement for vasopressor drugs to maintain systolic BP 
Coagulopathy 
iNR $1.5 or prothrombin time $1.5× ULN or activated partial thromboplastin time $1.5× ULN or elevated 
fibrin degradation products or hemorrhage from more than one site 
Minor criteria 
Hepatic 
Jaundice 
Renal 
Urine output ,500 mL urine/24 hours for adults; ,0.5 mL/kg/h for children 
Musculoskeletal 
Positive urine dipstick test for blood with a negative urine microscopy examination for red blood cells 
Respiratory 
Increased respiratory rate for age 
Platelet disorder 
Petechiae or purpura present 
Hypotension 
Systolic BP ,90 mmHg for adults; ,fifth percentile for age in children ,16 years 
Coagulopathy 
Clinically evident hemorrhage (one of): epistaxis, hematemesis, melena, hematochezia, hemoptysis, 
metrorrhagia or menorrhagia, gingival hemorrhage, persistent bleeding from needle puncture sites </p>

<p>Notes: Symptoms and physical signs are indicated in bold. Adapted from Vaccine, 30(33), Gershman MD, Staples Je, Bentsi-enchill AD, et al, viscerotropic dis ease: case 
definition and guidelines for collection, analysis, and presen tation of immunization safety data, 5038-5058, Copyright 2012, with permission from Elsevier. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ULN, upper limit of normal; Bv, baseline value; h, hour; BP, blood pressure; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; iNR, 
International Normalized Ratio; CPK, creatinine phosphokinase. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3349 </p>

<p>Yellow fever vaccine-associated viscerotropic disease </p>

<p>Search update </p>

<p>On May 12, 2016, PubMed was searched using the term 
viscerotropic and 105 citations were retrieved and using the 
terms (YF vaccine) and (adverse events), 141 citations were 
retrieved. MEDLINE was searched with same terms, and 67 
and 37 citations were retrieved. Four new AVD cases were 
identified. </p>

<p>20-23 </p>

<p>Cases that met both neurologic and 
viscerotropic Brighton Collaboration 
criteria </p>

<p>One case 
24 met both encephalitis level 1 and viscerotropic 
level 1 criteria, and the other case, 
25 encephalitis level 2 and 
viscerotropic level 3 criteria. </p>

<p>viscerotropic disease: cases that met 
Brighton Collaboration criteria </p>

<p>An important result is that all serious adverse events we 
identified that met Brighton Classification criteria were 
associated with first YF vaccinations. Sixty-two cases 
(35 died) met Brighton Collaboration viscerotropic criteria, 
with 32 from the US, six from Brazil, five from Peru, three 
from Spain, two from the People's Republic of China, one 
each from Argentina, Australia, Belgium, Ecuador, France, 
Germany, Ireland, New Zealand, Portugal, and the UK, and 
four no country stated. 
14,20-45 Some cases met both viscero-
tropic and YEL-AVD criteria and some only viscerotropic </p>

<p>or YEL-AVD criteria (Table 2). Two cases met both 
viscerotropic and YF vaccine-associated neurologic disease 
criteria. 
24,25 The new search identified four new viscerotropic 
cases for the database. Case 43 from Biscayart's Argentina 
report 
20 did not provide enough information to meet any 
viscerotropic criteria but met YEL-AVD confirmed; the 
case from Oregon 
21 met viscerotropic level 1 and YEL-AVD 
confirmed criteria; the case from Hong Kong 
22 met level 2 
diagnostic certainty and YEL-AVD confirmed criteria, and 
the case from New Zealand 
23 met both level 1 certainty and 
confirmed criteria. 
The full data are available in Supplementary materials or 
from the author. The viscerotropic disease cases are numbers 
1-5, 23-28, 33, 42-45, 47, 49, 52, 53, 56-61, 66-69, 85, 87, 
93-104, 106, 133, 202-212, 217, 227, and 230-233. </p>

<p>viscerotropic disease: cases that did not 
meet Brighton Collaboration criteria </p>

<p>Seventy cases (37 died) proposed by authors as viscerotropic 
disease did not meet Brighton Collaboration criteria (Table 2). 
There were 26 individual cases 
41,46-52 presented by authors as 
viscerotropic disease but which provided insufficient evi-
dence to meet either any viscerotropic level of diagnostic 
certainty or any YEL-AVD causality criteria. In Brazil, a 
National System for Surveillance of Adverse Events follow-
ing Immunization was established in 1998, with reports from 
30,000 health centers country-wide. Cases were classified </p>

<p>Figure 1 Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) flow diagram. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3350 </p>

<p>Thomas </p>

<p>according to CDC criteria, and a Guideline for Investigation 
of Serious Adverse Events was developed. There is also a 
compulsory and immediate reporting system for icterohe-
morrhagic febrile syndrome for hospitals. 
53 The Brazilian 
Ministry of Health, 
54-56 Martins et al, 
53 and Romano et al </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>provide reports for overlapping periods during 2000-2009. 
The Ministry reports 
54-56 are dated 2009, Martins et al 2010, </p>

<p>53 </p>

<p>and Romano et al 2014, 
57 and (to avoid double counting) the 
minimum estimate is 28 viscerotropic cases (24 deaths) in 
Brazil due to AVD. No clinical or laboratory data were pro-
vided for individual cases and thus could not be assessed with 
Brighton Collaboration criteria. An analysis of the Australian 
databases (Lawrence et al </p>

<p>58,59   ) identified one viscerotropic 
case and the US Vaccine Adverse Events Reporting System 
(VAERS) database 13 cases (Khromava et al 
60 seven and </p>

<p>Lindsey et al 
61 six), which did not provide enough data to 
meet Brighton Collaboration criteria (Table 2). </p>

<p>Cases proposed by authors as 
viscerotropic cases but excluded </p>

<p>Thirty-seven proposed cases from three sources were 
excluded. The US Vaccine Safety Datalink 1991-2006 </p>

<p>62   reported International Classification of Diseases (ICD-9) 
codes for potential adverse events after vaccination. They did 
not have access to laboratory or imaging studies and could not 
apply the Brighton criteria. Instead, they applied ICD-9 cri-
teria and created the definition of "visceral" events after YF 
vaccination and noted one each of cardiac disease, hypoten-
sion, and lung disease. The US Department of Defense 
Database reported adverse events for vaccine-exposed </p>

<p>Table 2 Cases of viscerotropic adverse events that meet and do not meet Brighton Collaboration diagnostic and causality criteria </p>

<p>Met Brighton Collaboration Viscerotropic or YEL-AVD criteria or both </p>

<p>Viscerotropic level 
YEL-AVD classification 
Total </p>

<p>Confirmed 
Probable 
Suspect 
Did not meet any 
YEL-AVD criteria </p>

<p>Level 1 
12 
3 
5 
20 </p>

<p>Level 2 
3 
1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Level 3 
2 </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Did not meet any level criteria 
1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>62 (35 died) </p>

<p>Did not meet Brighton Collaboration Viscerotropic or YEL-AVD criteria </p>

<p>Cases in individual journal articles 
n=28 (6 deaths) </p>

<p>Australia (Lawrence 2003, 
58 2004 
59 ) 
n=1 (no deaths) </p>

<p>Brazil: (For overlapping dates): 
(1) Martins (2010) 
56 for 1999-2008; reported 26 AVD cases; 21 from Brazil and 
5 from other Latin American countries;19 confirmed, 4 probable, 3 suspect; 24 died; 
For none of the Brazilian databases are clinical and laboratory details provided for 
individual cases (2) Brazilian Ministry of Health for 1999-2008 
54-56 reported 28 AVD 
cases (3) Romano (2014) 
57 6 AvD (2 in the state of Rio Grande do Sul, 3 in the state 
of Sao Paulo, 1 in Santa Caterina), all 6 died </p>

<p>n=28 (24 deaths) </p>

<p>USA vAeRS: (Khromava; 
60 n=7 AvD with 5 deaths), (Lindsey; 
61 n=6 AvD with 
2 deaths) </p>

<p>n=13 (7 deaths) </p>

<p>Total Viscerotropic adverse events (both met and did not meet 
Brighton criteria) </p>

<p>132 
(72 deaths) 
"serious adverse events" (not further defined, which could include some 
viscerotropic events: Monath (2005) 
66 (n=34); Schumacher (2010) 
67 (n=3) </p>

<p>Unknown number 
of YeL-AvD cases </p>

<p>Notes: To avoid double counting in the different Brazilian reports for the same time, a conservative estimate is 28 cases and 24 deaths. There are three analyses of the US 
vAeRS database with overlapping time periods. Khromava et al for 1990-2002 and Lindsey et al for 2000-2006 divided cases into neurologic or viscerotropic. Martin et al </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>only presented four cases. However, Martin et al 
68 for the US vAeRS database 1990-1998 reported 26 "systemic adverse events (multisystemic or neurologic)" but did not 
classify them further. His time period overlaps those of Khromava et al and Lindsey et al, and thus, only their analyses are included. Schumacher et al 
67 for the Swiss database 
reported "seven serious AEFI including four neurologic reactions" (four were assigned to the neurologic total, and the other three undefined cases are recorded as undefined 
SAes). The systematic review of studies using active surveillance (Thomas et al </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>) did not find any SAEs. A systematic review of mortality following YF vaccination of troops and 
civilians during the 1930s and WWII identified an upper limit of 82 military and 24 civilian deaths, but it was difficult to assess the cause of death, and in the troops, it was most 
likely due to contamination by hepatitis viruses (Thomas et al </p>

<p>69 </p>

<p>). The summary of the literature (1989-2010) by Monath et al 
70 estimated a world total of 113 cases of serious 
adverse reactions, but clinical and laboratory details of cases are not presented, and it is not possible to cross-check this estimate with the cases in this review. Cases from 
Monath et al's earlier edition of their chapter are included if sufficient data were presented. Seligman's review reported nine AVD cases already reported in the literature and 
already included in this review. 
71 Miyaji et al's study of 906 persons 60 years or older who received YFV was able to follow-up 700, and no serious YF AEFIs were identified. </p>

<p>72 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: YeL-AvD, yellow fever vaccine-associated viscerotropic disease; US vAeRS, US vaccine Adverse events Reporting System; AeFi, adverse event following 
immunization; SAEs, serious adverse events; WWII, World War II; YF, yellow fever; YFV, yellow fever virus. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3351 </p>

<p>Yellow fever vaccine-associated viscerotropic disease </p>

<p>military personnel 1999-2007. 
62 There was again no access 
to laboratory, imaging, or chart data. Thirty-six "visceral" 
events were identified (not further specified). These cases 
did not meet Brighton criteria because of the imprecision 
of the ICD-9 codes in classifying adverse vaccine events, a 
task for which they were not designed. The "visceral" event 
classification cannot be related in any way to the Brigh-
ton Collaboration, and so these events are not included in 
this review, except for one death already documented and 
included in this review. A case from the Netherlands did not 
meet any Brighton criteria. </p>

<p>63 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The WHO advises vaccination for all individuals $9 months 
living in countries or areas at risk, except infants 6-8 months 
or pregnant females or breastfeeding mothers who may be 
vaccinated during epidemics or if unavoidably traveling to 
high-risk areas. Similarly, the WHO advises that individuals 
60 years and older are at risk for severe adverse events after 
vaccination, and the risk and benefits need to be weighed. </p>

<p>64   The US Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices 
(ACIP) indicates that YF vaccine is contraindicated in those 
with sensitivity to eggs or chicken, infants ,6 months, indi-
viduals with thymus disorders or who have had a thymectomy, 
individuals with HIV and AIDS, and individuals on immuno-
suppressive therapies. The ACIP advises precaution in vac-
cinating infants aged 6-8 months, those aged $60 years, and 
individuals with asymptomatic HIV infection and moderate 
immune suppression (CD4 count 200-499 per mm 
3 for per-
sons $6 years, or 15%-24% of total lymphocytes for children 
,6 years), pregnancy, and breastfeeding. The ACIP notes the 
limited database for these recommendations. 
65 The published 
cases of vaccine-associated viscerotropic disease presented 
here include only developed countries. These cases probably 
accurately represent the number of cases of viscerotropic dis-
ease in these developed countries because patients become so 
ill they promptly seek care and the initial clinical and labora-
tory presentations are unusual enough that extensive inves-
tigations are likely to be launched. However, an unknown 
proportion of patients in developing countries with endemic 
YF are likely exposed to wild-type virus and may not have 
the same incidence of viscerotropic disease postvaccination 
as individuals from developed countries. Individuals in devel-
oping countries with severe adverse events after vaccination 
may not reach health care and may not be investigated and 
published, and thus, the numbers in low-income countries are 
unknown. The strengths of this review are that the search was 
conducted from 1930 to July 10, 2013, in multiple databases, </p>

<p>with no limitations of language and updated on May 12, 2016. 
All papers not in English were translated. Titles, abstracts, 
and full-text articles were assessed independently by two 
authors. The Brighton Collaboration criteria are specifically 
designed to assess serious adverse effects after YF vaccination 
and cases were assessed and data entered independently by 
two reviewers. The limitations are that only published reports 
or reports published by manufacturers are included and for 
many cases insufficient information was provided to assess 
if they met Brighton criteria. The rates of published viscero-
tropic disease can be estimated for individual databases. The 
three analyses of the YEL-AVD cases in the US VAERS 
database included partly overlapping periods (Khromava 
et al 
60 for 1990-2002, Lindsey et al 
61 for 2000-2006, and 
Martin et al 
38 reported only four cases) and provide an esti-
mate of 3.1 per million YEL-AVD and a slightly higher one 
of 3.9 per million. 
60,61 The Brazilian databases provide a low 
estimate of 0.19 per million YEL-AVD, 
53-57 and the Australian 
database of 5 per million. 
58,59 A systematic review that com-
pared active and passive surveillance of post YF vaccination 
(2,660,929) reported no YEL-AVD cases. 
18 This review 
identified 62 cases (35 deaths) that met Brighton Collabora-
tion criteria and 70 cases (37 deaths) that did not provide 
enough information to be assessed with Brighton Collabora-
tion criteria. An overall rate for the current review cannot be 
computed because the denominators for all the studies are not 
known. Thus, YF vaccine is a very safe vaccine with a very 
low rate of YEL-AVD per million, and the findings of this 
review provide additional support for the abovementioned 
recommendations of the WHO 
64 and ACIP. </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The author reports no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/drug-design-development-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal that spans the spectrum of drug design 
and development through to clinical applications. Clinical outcomes, 
patient safety, and programs for the development and effective, safe, 
and sustained use of medicines are the features of the journal, which </p>

<p>has also been accepted for indexing on PubMed Central. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>





</text></tei>