<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5210339" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.4</rs></p>

<p>Risk Prediction for AKI in ADHF Patients 
Zhou et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>was developed in a cohort of ADHF patients whose clinical 
characteristics and risk exposure were different from those of 
the patients with heart surgery. The c statistic of the proposed 
score for predicting acute CRS reached 0.859, demonstrating 
excellent performance of our risk score in ADHF patients. 
Sensitivity analysis showed that the 2 incomplete mea-
sures had little influence on the risk model. Furthermore, we 
have kept age, sex, NT-proBNP, and serum albumin in the final 
risk model, although they were not statistically significant. 
Age and sex were given factors for controlling potential 
patients' heterogeneity. NT-proBNP and serum albumin were 
also found significantly associated with the development of 
AKI in univariate analysis and by other researchers. 45,46 We 
also developed a clinical score that reached acceptable 
performance. Clinicians could choose the one that fits their 
clinical practice best. </p>

<p>Strengths and Limitations of This Study </p>

<p>Our study has several strengths. First, our risk score was 
derived for early detection of patients at high risk of 
developing AKI incorporating, for the first time, both baseline 
characteristics and novel biomarkers recorded on the first day 
of admission before a clinically significant change in serum 
creatinine. Second, the risk score possesses high discrimina-
tive power as well as high stability and reproducibility, as 
shown by concordance between internal and external valida-
tion. Third, to develop a prediction tool for early detection of 
patients who would develop AKI during hospitalization, 
researchers should exclude those who already have AKI on 
admission. In our study we excluded those having AKI on 
admission based on preadmission measurements of serum 
creatinine, but we did not use this information in developing 
the risk score; thus, the use of the developed predicting tool is 
not limited by the need for preadmission serum creatinine. 
Last, our article closely follows the TRIPOD statement. 
The study also has limitations. First, AKI diagnosed by an 
increase in serum creatinine may introduce the dilemma of 
using a surrogate outcome to assess the performance of 
novel models. 47 Evidence of AKI on renal biopsy would be the 
gold standard but was not feasible in our large cohort. As is 
the case in most AKI studies, we did not use urine output 
criteria (ie, &lt;0.5 mL/kg per hour for &gt;6 hours) for AKI 
diagnosis because urine output as the diagnostic criterion for 
AKI has been questioned recently for its limited sensitivity 
when diuretics are administered, reduced specificity in the 
presence of dehydration, and lack of practicality when an 
indwelling urinary catheter is not present (as in our setting). 15 
Second, our findings remain to be confirmed by other 
independent studies. The question of whether the model 
predicts AKI in the special setting of ADHF versus AKI from 
other causes remains to be addressed. Third, although the </p>

<p>study participants were recruited from 6 hospitals located in 5 
cities in China, generalizability of the risk score to other 
populations still needs to be validated. In addition, the 
bootstrap procedure to estimate the overoptimism was 
conducted based on the developed risk score, which did not 
include the model selection step. The estimate of the 
overoptimism could be substantially biased under this 
circumstance. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>We developed and validated a novel risk score by incorporat-
ing both major clinical risk factors and effective urine 
biomarkers to predict AKI in ADHF patients early. Individual 
risk prediction, as well as risk stratification based on the risk 
score, may assist clinicians to assess the risk of AKI in ADHF 
patients, which, in turn, would help them to plan and initiate 
the most appropriate disease management for patients in 
time. </p>

<p>The authors have followed the STROBE checklist in collecting and 
reporting their data and the TRIPOD checklist in reporting the 
prediction model. Elements of the checklist are incorporated into the 
manuscript. Further details of any particular checklist item are 
available on request from the corresponding authors. </p>

<p>Sources of Funding </p>

<p>This study was supported by the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (no. 81273191/81673270) granted to 
Prof Chen and the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China (no. 81430016) to Dr Hou. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>None. </p>





<p>Risk Prediction for AKI in ADHF Patients 
Zhou et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>





<p>Risk Prediction for AKI in ADHF Patients 
Zhou et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>



<p>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL </p>



<p>Data S1. </p>

<p>Supplemental Methods </p>

<p>Study Design. The study is a prospective, multi-center, observational study. All patients </p>

<p>provided informed written consent for the procedure(s) and the study was approved by the </p>

<p>Institutional Review Board. </p>

<p>Study Population. A total of 676 consecutive participants, aged 18-80 years old, were </p>

<p>prospectively enrolled between September 2011 and August 2014 from six regional central </p>

<p>hospitals located in five cities in China. Among the participants, 169 were excluded </p>

<p>according to exclusion criteria (Figure 1), and the remaining 507 participants formed our </p>

<p>study population. </p>

<p>The inclusion criteria were patients with ADHF 1) who were admitted to the six </p>

<p>participating hospitals, and 2) who had at least three measurements of serum creatinine over a </p>

<p>six-month period before admission. Exclusion criteria were 1) exposing to nephrotoxins, such </p>

<p>as contrast media, aminoglycoside antibiotics, vancomycin, and/or non-steroidal </p>

<p>anti-inflammatory drugs except aspirin, within 4 weeks before admission or during hospital </p>

<p>stay, 2) pre-existing advanced chronic kidney disease (CKD) (chronic dialysis or </p>

<p>pre-admission estimated glomerular filtration rate [Egfr] &lt;30 ml/min/1•73m 2 ), 3) urinary </p>

<p>tract infection or obstruction, cancer, a concurrent diagnosis of an acute coronary syndrome, </p>

<p>cardiogenic shock or need for inotropes, 4) heart failure following cardiac surgery, and 5) </p>

<p>having AKI on admission (i.e., those with a 50% increase in serum creatinine from </p>

<p>preadmission level on the day of hospitalization). </p>

<p>Laboratory measurements </p>

<p>Urine and blood samples were measured in a central laboratory with standard protocol. A </p>

<p>sandwich ELISA kit (Immuno-Biologic Laboratories Co. Ltd, Japan) was used for </p>



<p>quantifying AGT in urine, and further confirmed by western blot analyses. uNGAL was </p>

<p>measured with an ELISA kit (Antibody Shop, Denmark). Urine albumin to creatinine ratio </p>

<p>(UACR) was measured using an automatic analyzer (Siemens BNPro Spec, Germany). All </p>

<p>urine biomarkers were normalized based on the level of urinary creatinine. Estimated </p>

<p>glomerular filtration rate (GRF) was determined by Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology </p>

<p>Collaboration (CKD-EPI) equation (1). </p>

<p>Candidate predictors </p>

<p>Candidate predictors included clinical variables such as sex, age (years), hypertension, </p>

<p>diabetes mellitus, pre-existing CKD indicated from medical records, or reported by patients, </p>

<p>or diagnosed by doctor, prior hospitalization for heart failure, left ventricular ejection </p>

<p>fraction, severity of breathlessness by the New York Heart Association (NYHA) </p>

<p>classification, NT-proBNP (pg/ml), systolic and diastolic blood pressure (mmHg), serum </p>

<p>albumin (g/L), serum creatinine (μmol/L), hemoglobin (g/L), use of renin-angiotensin system </p>

<p>blockersand/or diuretic, and urine biomarkers such as urine albumin to creatinine ratio </p>

<p>(UACR, mg/g Cr), uNGAL (μg/g Cr) and uAGT (μg/g Cr). All these variables were assessed </p>

<p>and recorded on admission. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>We took two steps to develop a risk model based on the development cohort. The first was </p>

<p>to select meaningful clinical risk factors (non-urine markers) by logistic regression with </p>

<p>backward elimination. Clinical candidate predictors significant at P&lt;0.1 in univariate logistic </p>

<p>regression models were considered for backward elimination. In this step, a clinical model </p>

<p>with clinical factors was developed. Then, urine biomarkers (UACR, uNGAL and uAGT) </p>

<p>were evaluated sequentially based on this clinical model. The likelihood ratio χ 2 test (2) was </p>

<p>used to evaluate the significance of the added urine biomarkers, and net-reclassification index </p>



<p>(NRI) and integrated discrimination improvement (IDI) (3) were used to quantify the </p>

<p>additional contribution of these urine biomarkers to risk reclassification. </p>

<p>To develop the risk score, the scoring method similar to Sullivan et al's (4) was employed </p>

<p>based on the developed risk model. Continuous variables were divided into categories in </p>

<p>terms of clinical significance except for NT-proBNP, for which the cut-off of 5578 pg/ml was </p>

<p>chosen to yield good sensitivity and specificity. Mid-point value was defined as the reference </p>

<p>value of each category. For the first and last categories of each variable, we used the 1 st and </p>

<p>the 99 th percentiles to minimize the influence of extreme values. For each risk factor, the </p>

<p>lowest risk category was chosen as the base category, and the distance of other categories </p>

<p>from the base category was calculated as the difference of reference values between </p>

<p>corresponding categories and base category multiplied by the regression coefficient of </p>

<p>corresponding variable in the generated risk model. One point of the risk score system was </p>

<p>defined as a constant of 0.141 which means the increase of risk associated with a 10-year </p>

<p>increase in age, that is 0.0141×10. The score of each base category was set at 0, and that of </p>

<p>other categories were computed by dividing corresponding distance from the base category </p>

<p>by the constant of 0.141 and then rounded to the nearest integer. The total risk score for an </p>

<p>individual patient is obtained by summing up the score of each predictive variable. </p>

<p>The predictive accuracy of the risk model and the risk score model was assessed by both </p>

<p>discrimination measured by C-statistic (5) and calibration evaluated by Hosmer-Lemeshow </p>

<p>χ² statistic (6) and calibration plot, a plot of observed proportions versus predicted </p>

<p>probabilities. Bootstrapping technique (7) was used to adjust for over-fitting and </p>

<p>over-optimistic model performance. </p>

<p>The natural logarithmic transformation of NT-proBNP and all urine biomarkers was </p>

<p>made because of their extreme positive skewness. Generalized additive model (GAM) (8) </p>

<p>was used to explore the potential nonlinear relationship between those continuous variables </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>and the outcome. The clinical meaningful interactions between predictors were also </p>

<p>examined. Continuous variables were expressed as mean (SD) or median (1 st Quarter-3 rd </p>

<p>Quarter). Categorical variables were expressed as percentages. Sensitivity analysis was </p>

<p>conducted to assess the influence of the two incomplete measures by leaving the </p>

<p>corresponding two cases out. Further, we also applied the risk score to the whole </p>

<p>participants as sensitivity analysis. All analyses were done with <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., </p>

<p>Cary, NC, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 9.4</rs>). A two-sided P&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>



<p>Table S1: Baseline characteristics outlining those who developed versus not developed AKI. </p>

<p>Values are numbers (percentages) unless stated otherwise. </p>

<p>Non-AKI 
(n=339) </p>

<p>AKI 
(n=168) </p>

<p>P 
value 
Demographics 
mean (SD) age (years) 
63.0(15.3) 
69.6(13.1) 
&lt;.001 
Sex, Male 
211(62.2) 
109(64.9) 
0.562 
Pre-existing clinical conditions 
Hypertension 
146(43.1) 
107(63.7) 
&lt;.001 
Diabetes 
68(20.1) 
61(36.3) 
&lt;.001 
Pre-CKD 
55(16.2) 
78(46.4) 
&lt;.001 
Prior hospitalization for HF 
170(50.1) 
91(54.2) 
0.394 
Primary causes of heart failure 
Ischemic heart disease 
178(52.5) 
93(55.4) 
0.545 
Hypertension 
43(12.7) 
22(13.1) 
0.896 
Rheumatic heart disease 
47(13.9) 
23(13.7) 
0.957 
Cardiomyopathy 
48(14.2) 
14(8.3) 
0.059 
Other 
23(6.8) 
16(9.5) 
0.276 
Characteristics on admission 
LVEF&lt;45% 
153(45.1) 
81(48.2) 
0.512 
NYHA, class IV 
144(42.5) 
99(58.9) 
&lt;.001 
Median (IQR) NT-proBNP (pg/ml) 
4181.0(1942.0-8463.0) 7088.5(3699.3-9000.0) &lt;.001 
Mean (SD) SBP (mmHg) 
126.2(24.0) 
129.3(24.8) 
0.173 
Mean (SD) DBP (mmHg) 
75.6(16.1) 
74.8(14.4) 
0.591 
Mean (SD) Serum creatinine (μmol/L) 
98.5(40.0) 
128.8(59.1) 
&lt;.001 
Mean (SD) Serum albumin (g/L) 
34.8(5.8) 
30.8(5.9) 
&lt;.001 
Mean (SD) Hemoglobin (g/L) 
128.1(23.1) 
115.8(26.3) 
&lt;.001 
Treatment before Admission 
Use ACEI/ARB pre-admission 
90(26.5) 
54(32.1) 
0.189 
Mean (SD) Drug index of ACEI/ARBc 
4.3(1.1) 
4.1(1.2) 
0.283 
Use spironolactone 
103(30.4) 
60(35.7) 
0.226 
Mean (SD) Drug index of spironolactonec 
1.1(0.3) 
1.1(0.3) 
0.314 
Mean (SD) Drug score of RAAS blockerc 
5.4(1.1) 
5.2(1.4) 
0.476 
Use diuretic pre-admission 
117(34.5) 
66(39.3) 
0.292 
Use of high-dose diuretic 
5(1.5) 
5(3.0) 
0.253 
Biomarker measurement 
Median (IQR) UACR (mg/g Cr) 
51.2(16.2-182.4) 
180.4(63.7-491.5) 
0.012 
Median (IQR) uNGAL (μg/g Cr) 
29.7(14.9-78.3) 
114.2(39.1-417.2) 
&lt;.001 </p>







<p>Table S2. C-statistic, NRI and IDI for different models </p>

<p>Models 
VS 
LR χ 2 
P 
C-statistic(95%CI) 
NRI 
IDI </p>

<p>Clinical model (M1)* 
0.767(0.714-0.820) </p>

<p>M1 + uAGT (M2) 
M1 
64.923 &lt;0.001 0.861(0.820-0.925) # 
0.809 
（p&lt;0.001） </p>

<p>0.169 
（p&lt;0.001） </p>

<p>M1 +uAGT+ uNGAL (M3) M2 
8.737 
&lt;0.013 0.874(0.835-0.913) #&amp; 0.293 
（p=0.012） </p>

<p>0.023 
（p=0.011） 
M1 +uAGT+ 
uNGAL+UACR (M4) 
M3 
1.582 
0.208 
0.875(0.836-0.914) 
0.105 
(p=0.369) </p>

<p>0.004 
(p=0.214) </p>

<p>* Clinical model included age, sex, pre-existing CKD, ALB and NT-proBNP. </p>

<p># VS M1, DeLong's test, P &lt; 0.001 
# VS M2, DeLong's test, P = 0.035 </p>



<p>Table S3. Predicted risk of AKI in patients with ADHF based on the risk score model. 
Total risk 
score </p>

<p>Predicted 
risk (%) </p>

<p>Total risk 
score </p>

<p>Predicted 
risk (%) </p>

<p>Total risk 
score </p>

<p>Predicted 
risk (%) 
0 
1.8 
19 
13.7 
38 
58.5 
1 
2.0 
20 
15.1 
39 
61.3 
2 
2.2 
21 
16.6 
40 
63.9 
3 
2.5 
22 
18.3 
41 
66.6 
4 
2.7 
23 
20.1 
42 
69.1 
5 
3.1 
24 
22.0 
43 
71.5 
6 
3.4 
25 
24.0 
44 
73.7 
7 
3.8 
26 
26.2 
45 
75.9 
8 
4.3 
27 
28.5 
46 
78.0 
9 
4.8 
28 
30.9 
47 
79.9 
10 
5.3 
29 
33.4 
48 
81.7 
11 
5.9 
30 
36.0 
49 
83.3 
12 
6.6 
31 
38.7 
50 
84.9 
13 
7.4 
32 
41.4 
51 
86.3 
14 
8.2 
33 
44.2 
52 
87.6 
15 
9.1 
34 
47.1 
53 
88.8 
16 
10.1 
35 
50.0 
54 
89.9 
17 
11.2 
36 
52.8 
55 
90.9 
18 
12.4 
37 
55.7 </p>



<p>Table S4. Risk score for single risk factors associated with developing AKI for clinical </p>

<p>score model in ADHF patients. </p>

<p>Risk Factor 
Score 
C-statistic for single 
variable 
Age (year) 
0.638 (0.574-0.701) 
≤55 
0 
56-65 
2 
66-75 
3 
76 and older 
5 
Sex 
0.514 (0.460-0.568) 
Male 
1 
Female 
0 
Pre-CKD 
0.680 (0.627-0.732) 
Yes 
5 
No 
0 
Serum albumin (mmol/L) 
0.640 (0.576-0.704) 
≤35 
4 
&gt;35 
0 
NT-proBNP (pg/ml)  † 
0.635 (0.572-0.698) 
＜5578 
0 
≥5578 
3 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Table S5. Sensitivity analysis of model performance of models with different included variables. 
Included variables 
Development dataset 
Validation dataset </p>

<p>C-statistic 
-2 Log L 
AIC 
C-statistic </p>

<p>Age / Sex / pre-CKD / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin 
345.736 
357.736 
0.767 
0.807 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / pre-CKD / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uNGAL 
314.196 
328.196 
0.819 
0.823 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / pre-CKD / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uAGT 
280.813 
294.813 
0.861 
0.888 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / pre-CKD / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uNGAL / ln-uAGT 
272.076 
288.076 
0.874 
0.890 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / eGFR / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin 
355.295 
367.295 
0.751 
0.825 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / eGFR / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uNGAL 
320.421 
334.421 
0.812 
0.841 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / eGFR / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uAGT 
288.065 
302.065 
0.854 
0.898 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / eGFR / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uNGAL / ln-uAGT 
277.847 
293.847 
0.867 
0.903 </p>



<p>Figure S1. Flow of enrollment of the study participants. </p>



<p>Figure S2. Boxplot showing the risk score across different AKI stage of the patients. 
Significant difference in average risk score of different AKI stage was found, with 
higher risk score in patients with higher stage of AKI (P value by one-way ANOVA 
analysis, &lt;0.001). </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Figure S3. Receiver Operator Characteristic Curves showing the discriminatory 
power of the risk score for predicting death during hospitalization. </p>



<p>Figure S4. Receiver Operator Characteristic Curves showing Area Under the Curve 
of clinical model and clinical score for AKI in ADHF patients. </p>



<p>Figure S5. Calibration plot as well as the Hosmer-Lemeshow χ² statistic for the risk 
score in both development and validation cohorts. The points and circles indicate the 
observed frequencies by decile of predicted probability. </p>



<p>Figure S6. Risk levels according to the risk score in development and validation 
cohorts. Risks were categorized into low-risk (0-4 points), moderate-risk (5-9 points), 
high-risk (10-14 points), very high-risk (15-18 points). Higher points means higher 
risk of developing AKI in patients with ADHF, P for trend&lt;0.001. </p>

<p>Supplemental risk calculator AKI risk calculator. </p>





</text></tei>