<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5040012" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Diabetes mellitus (DM) remains a major health problem worldwide. Several clinical trials have shown the superiority of 
the Traditional Chinese Medicine in delaying or reversing the development and progression of DM. This study aimed to evaluate the 
efficacy of Jinlida (JLD) granule, a Chinese herbal recipe, in the treatment of impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) and its effect on the 
prevention of DM. 
Methods: Sixty-five IGT patients were randomized to receive one bag of JLD granules three times daily (JLD group, n = 34) or no drug 
intervention (control group, n = 31) for 12 weeks. Oral glucose tolerance test, glycated hemoglobin A 1c (HbA 1c ), body mass index, blood 
lipids levels, fasting insulin, and insulin resistance calculated using homeostatic model assessment (HOMA-IR) of all the patients were 
observed and compared before and after the treatment. 
Results: Sixty-one participants completed the trial (32 in JLD group and 29 in the control group). There were statistically significant 
decreases in HbA 1c (P &lt; 0.001), 2-h plasma glucose (P &lt; 0.001), and HOMA-IR (P = 0.029) in JLD group compared with the control group 
after 12 weeks of treatment. After 12 weeks of treatment, two (6.9%) patients returned to normal blood glucose, and five (17.2%) patients 
turned into DM in control group, while in the JLD group, 14 (43.8%) returned to normal blood glucose and 2 (6.2%) turned into DM. There 
was a significant difference in the number of subjects who had normal glucose at the end of the study between two groups (P = 0.001). 
Conclusions: JLD granule effectively improved glucose control, increased the conversion of IGT to normal glucose, and improved the 
insulin resistance in patients with IGT. This Chinese herbal medicine may have a clinical value for IGT. </p>

<p>Key words: Clinical Observation; Diabetes Mellitus; Impaired Glucose Tolerance; Jinlida Granule </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Dr. Shu-Yu Yang, 
Xiamen Diabetes Institute, The First Affiliated Hospital of Xiamen 
University, 55 Zhenhai Road, Xiamen, Fujian 361003, China 
E-Mail: xmyangshuyu@126.com </p>

<p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, 
tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited 
and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms. </p>

<p>For reprints contact: reprints@medknow.com </p>

<p>© 2016 Chinese Medical Journal ¦ Produced by Wolters Kluwer -Medknow </p>

<p>Received: 13-06-2016 Edited by: Xin Chen 
How to cite this article: Shi YL, Liu WJ, Zhang XF, Su WJ, Chen NN, 
Lu SH, Wang LY, Shi XL, Li ZB, Yang SY. Effect of Chinese Herbal 
Medicine Jinlida Granule in Treatment of Patients with Impaired Glucose 
Tolerance. Chin Med J 2016;129:2281-6. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ October 5, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 19 </p>

<p>
research has shown the superiority of the Traditional Chinese 
Medicine (TCM) in this field. 
[11-13] Jinlida (JLD) granule, 
a TCM, is an herbal formula developed under the theory 
that Pi (Spleen)-deficiency appears in the onset of DM. By 
nourishing Pi and regulating body fluid of DM subjects, JLD 
granule was used for diabetes management with positive data 
from the animal and human studies. 
[14-18] However, the efficacy 
of JLD granule in the treatment of IGT patients and its effect 
on the prevention of DM have never been observed. This study 
therefore was designed to evaluate the efficacy and safety of 
JLD granule for the IGT treatment and prevention of DM. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study design </p>

<p>The research procedures were performed in abidance 
with standards of quality control in Chinese clinical trial 
and in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. The 
study was approved by the Medical Ethical Committee of 
The First Affiliated Hospital of Xiamen University (No. 
KYZ-2014-004), and the written informed consent was 
obtained from all the participants. </p>

<p>The overall design of the study consisted of a screening 
visit and a 12-week treatment period. After the initial 
screening, 65 eligible participants from Department of 
Endocrinology and Diabetes, The First Affiliated Hospital 
of Xiamen University, between April 2014 and October 
2014 were randomly assigned to the JLD group (n = 34) 
and control group (n = 31) based on the random block 
procedure produced by the Random Allocation Software 
(version 1.0; Isfahan, Iran) [Figure 1]. Participants in JLD 
group orally took one bag of JLD granules (9 g) three times 
daily with 120-150 ml warm water after each meal and 
participants in the control group received no drug treatment. 
All the participants engaged in standard diet control and 
exercise therapy. Smoking and alcohol consumption were 
controlled. During treatment, the use of other TCM that 
shares similar functional components with JLD granule 
was prohibited. </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria were as follows: (1) patients with IGT, 
which was defined as fasting plasma glucose (FPG) 
concentration &lt;7.0 mmol/L and 2-h plasma glucose (2-h PG) 
concentration ≥7.8 mmol/L and &lt;11.1 mmol/L, according to 
the World Health Organization criteria, 
[19] and diagnosis will 
have been made after undertaking an oral glucose tolerance 
test (OGTT); (2) age between 20 years and 80 years; and (3) 
body mass index (BMI) of 18-30 kg/m 
2 . </p>

<p>Exclusion criteria were as follows: (1) Type 1 DM and type 2 
DM (T2DM), gestational DM, secondary diabetics, and 
other special types of DM; (2) ketoacidosis or hyperosmotic 
coma within 12 weeks; (3) previous history or treatment for 
type 2 diabetes; (4) serious hepatic and renal function; (5) 
complicated with severe cardiovascular diseases, severe 
gastrointestinal disease, or psychiatric diseases; (6) former 
use of antidiabetic or lipid-lowering drugs; (7) concomitant 
medication known to interfere with glucose metabolism, 
such as systemic corticosteroids glucocorticoid within 
8 weeks of start date of this study; (8) previous use of 
growth hormones within 6 months of start date of this 
study; (9) pregnancy, lactation, or being prepared pregnant 
women; (10) participated in other clinical trial within the last 
2 weeks; or (11) refusing to provide consent for the study. </p>

<p>Study medication </p>

<p>The JLD granules were provided by Shijiazhuang 
Yiling Pharmaceutical Company (Hebei, China). This 
herbal drug, prepared in small granules, is dark brown 
in color and has a bitter taste. The JLD granule contain 
over a dozen Chinese medicinal herbs, including 
ginseng (Renshen), puerarin (Gegen), pale white atractylodes 
rhizome (Cangbaizhu), Coptis chinensis (Huanglian), poria 
cocos (Fuling), radix polygonati officinalis (Yuzhu), and so 
on. The quality of these herbs and decoction preparation 
was in accordance with the requirement of Chinese 
Pharmacopoeia (2005 edition). </p>

<p>Study assessments </p>

<p>Participants meeting preliminary criteria were invited to 
attend a clinic visit by a physician to confirm eligibility </p>

<p>Patients were assessed for 
eligibility and randomized (n = 65) </p>

<p>JLD group (n = 34) 
Control group (n = 31) </p>

<p>One patient lost to follow-up 
One patient violated protocol </p>

<p>One patient lost to follow-up 
One patient refused </p>

<p>Patients completed study in 
JLD group (n = 32) </p>

<p>Patients completed study in 
control group (n = 29) </p>

<p>Figure 1: Flow diagram of the participants of this study. JLD: Jinlida. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ October 5, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 19 </p>



<p>and have signed an informed consent before any study 
assessments. All the participants received diabetic 
education and an exercise program formulated according 
to age and gender. The following clinical data were 
collected: demographic data (i.e., gender, age and family 
history of diabetes), medical history, body weight, height, 
waist circumference, hip circumference, vital signs, PG, 
plasma insulin, glycated hemoglobin A 1c (HbA 1c ), total 
cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein (HDL), low-density 
lipoprotein (LDL), cholesterol triglycerides (TG), and liver 
and kidney function. </p>

<p>During this 12-week period, the study assessments were 
performed at 0, 4, 8, and 12 weeks. Participants received 
frequent reminders on healthy lifestyle principles. FPG 
was checked at each visit. At 0 and 12 weeks, OGTT, 
HbA 1c , routine laboratory tests, serum lipids, and physical 
examination (body weight, BMI, waist circumference and hip 
circumference, etc.) were checked, plasma insulin levels were 
measured, and the homeostatic model assessment (HOMA) 
was performed to quantify insulin resistance (HOMA-IR). </p>

<p>Body weight will be measured in participants wearing 
light clothes without shoes using a digital scale to the 
nearest 0.1 kg. Height will be measured using a portable 
stadiometer to the nearest 0.1 cm. Waist circumference and 
hip circumference were measured at the first visit and final 
visit, as well as BMI. The waist circumference measurement 
was taken at the midpoint between the lower rib margin and 
the iliac crest in centimeters to the nearest 0.1 cm, and hip 
circumference was measured at the most prominent area of 
hip in centimeter to the nearest 0.1 cm. </p>

<p>PG and insulin levels were tested by OGTT. We collected 
venous blood samples at fasting, 30 min and 2 h after 75 g 
glucose ingestion. Blood samples collected by venipuncture 
for metabolic parameters (i.e., FPG, total cholesterol, 
LDL-cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, and TGs) were obtained 
in the early morning after an 8 h fast and were analyzed by 
Hitachi Automatic Analyzer (Hitachi, Japan). The HbA 1c 
level was measured using a Bio-Rad D10 Automated HbA 1c 
Analyzer (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). Patients having 
symptoms such as polyuria and polydipsia suggesting 
DM during the study visits would have a random PG 
measurement taken by a blood glucose monitor (Contour 
Plus Blood Glucose Monitoring System, Bayer, Germany). 
A glucose measurement ≥ 11.1 mmol/L was followed up 
using a venipuncture PG sample for the patient's safety. </p>

<p>HOMA was used to calculate insulin resistance. The 
calculation was based on FPG and insulin. In general, a high 
PG level indicates insulin resistance despite hyperinsulinemia. 
HOMA-IR was calculated as FPG (mmol/L) × fasting 
insulin (μU/ml)/22.5. </p>

<p>[20,21] </p>

<p>Efficacy evaluation </p>

<p>The primary outcome was the changes in HbA 1c , FPG, and 2-h 
PG levels. The secondary outcome included the conversion 
of IGT to normal blood glucose, the conversion of IGT to 
T2DM, and changes in insulin resistance (HOMA-IR). </p>

<p>Safety evaluation </p>

<p>The safety evaluations included routine blood tests, liver 
function, kidney function, and adverse events (AEs) 
during the therapeutic period. Subjects were interviewed 
monthly to record adherence and query about AEs. Any 
AEs were assessed for severity and possible relationship 
to study drugs and were followed until they either being 
resolved or no clinical significance determined by the 
investigators. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>We calculated the sample size required to detect an effect size 
of 0.6 (i.e., mean change in the outcome variable over time 
differs by at least 0.6 standard deviations (SDs) between the 
two groups) and thirty patients were required in each group 
to obtain an alpha of 0.05 and a beta of 0.80. We sought to 
enroll 35 participants per group to allow for 10% withdrawal 
and noncompliance. These calculations were based on the 
changes found in an earlier study of JLD granule. </p>

<p>[18] </p>

<p>The statistical analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
Statistics (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 16.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). 
Data are expressed as mean ± SD or median (Q1, Q3) for 
continuous variables and frequencies (percentages) for 
categorical variables. For between-group comparisons, 
Student's t-test was performed on variables with normal 
distributions, Chi-square test for categorical data, and Mann-
Whitney's U-test for variables with nonnormal distributions. 
For in-group comparisons, Paired t-test or Wilcoxon test was 
performed. Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) was used to 
model outcome at 12 weeks by treatment group corrected for 
baseline level of the outcome variable. All statistical tests 
were two-sided and assumed to be statistically significant 
at a level of P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>Subject characteristics </p>

<p>A total of 65 patients were enrolled in the study, and 
61 (93.8%) patients completed this study. Of these 
61 patients, 32 (52.5%) were in the JLD group and 
29 (47.5%) in the control group. There were no statistically 
significant differences between groups in gender, age, BMI, 
and laboratory data (all P &gt;0.05) [Table 1]. No participants 
were prescribed other diabetes medications during the study. 
As the test drug could be taken conveniently, the compliance 
of patients was generally pretty good. </p>

<p>Comparisons of blood glucose and glycated hemoglobin 
A 1c </p>

<p>After 12 weeks of treatment, 2-h PG was significantly decreased 
in JLD group (t = 2.180, P = 0.037) and not significantly 
changed in control group (t = −2.030, P = 0.052), compared with 
baseline. An ANCOVA found that 2-h PG showed a statistically 
significant difference between JLD group and control group 
after 12 weeks of treatment (F = 14.425, P &lt; 0.001). HbA 1c was 
very significantly decreased in JLD group (t = 4.107, P &lt; 0.001) 
and not significantly changed in control group (t = −0.946, 
P = 0.352), compared with baseline. The ANCOVA showed </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ October 5, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 19 </p>

<p>
a statistically significant difference in HbA 1c between two 
groups after 12 weeks of treatment (F = 23.340, P &lt; 0.001). 
FPG was significantly decreased in both groups compared 
with baseline (t = 4.828, P &lt; 0.001 for JLD group; t = 3.720, 
P = 0.001 for control group), but the difference between </p>

<p>two groups after 12 weeks of treatment was not statistically 
significant (F = 1.874, P = 0.176) [Table 2]. </p>

<p>Comparison of insulin resistance index of homeostatic 
model assessment </p>

<p>After 12 weeks of treatment, HOMA-IR was significantly 
lower in JLD group (Z = −2.412, P = 0.015) and significantly 
higher in control group (Z = −3.104, P = 0.001), compared 
with baseline. There was a statistically significant difference 
in HOMA-IR between two groups after 12 weeks of 
treatment (Z = −2.181, P = 0.029) [Table 2]. </p>

<p>Comparisons of weight, body mass index, waist/hip 
ratio, and total cholesterol </p>

<p>After 12 weeks of treatment, significant reduction in weight, 
BMI, and total cholesterol were observed in both groups 
compared with baseline (JLD group: t = 4.238, P &lt; 0.001 for 
weight, t = 4.268, P &lt; 0.001 for BMI, t = 3.207, P = 0.003 
for total cholesterol; control group: t = 3.228, P = 0.003 for 
weight, t = 3.274, P = 0.003 for BMI, t = 3.915, P = 0.001 
for total cholesterol); but no significant changes in waist/hip 
ratio were observed between baseline and after 12 weeks 
of treatment in both groups (all P &gt;0.05). After 12 weeks 
of treatment, the differences in weight, BMI, waist /hip 
ratio, and total cholesterol between two groups were not 
significantly different (all P &gt;0.05) [Table 2]. </p>

<p>Comparison of the conversion of impaired glucose 
tolerance </p>

<p>After 12 weeks of treatment, 2 (6.9%) patients returned to 
normal blood glucose, 22 (75.9%) patients remained in IGT, 
and 5 (17.2%) patients developed DM in control group, while 
in the JLD group, 14 patients (43.8%) returned to normal 
blood glucose, 16 (50.0%) patients remained in IGT, and 
2 (6.2%) patients developed DM. There was a significant </p>

<p>Table 1: Patient demographic and clinical 
characteristics of JLD and control groups at baseline </p>

<p>Characteristics 
JLD group 
(n = 32) </p>

<p>Control group 
(n = 29) </p>

<p>t 
P </p>

<p>Age (years) 
47.1 ± 7.1 
49.9 ± 7.2 
−1.527 0.132 
Male 
17 (53.1) 
14 (48.3) 
0.143 0.800 
Weight (kg) 
61.7 ± 9.0 
62.7 ± 8.2 
−0.453 0.652 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
22.9 ± 2.5 
23.6 ± 2.7 
0.945 0.280 
Waist (cm) 
83.4 ± 9.1 
81.5 ± 5.4 
0.960 0.341 
Waist/hip ratio 
0.9 ± 0.1 
0.9 ± 0.1 
0.957 0.343 
FPG (mmol/L) 
6.2 ± 0.5 
6.3 ± 0.6 
−0.956 0.343 
2-h PG (mmol/L) 
8.5 ± 2.1 
9.4 ± 1.6 
−1.841 0.071 
HbA 1c (%) 
6.5 ± 0.7 
6.5 ± 0.5 
0.007 0.994 
Fasting insulin 
(μU/ml) </p>

<p>9.2 (7.0, 15.3) 9.0 (8.1, 10.7) −0.159 0.874 </p>

<p>HOMA-IR 
2.4 (2.0, 4.0) 
2.5 (2.1, 3.0) 
−0.116 0.908 
Triglycerides 
(mg/L) </p>

<p>15.3 ± 7.8 
15.4 ± 7.9 
−0.026 0.979 </p>

<p>Total cholesterol 
(mg/L) </p>

<p>56.1 ± 10.5 
55.5 ± 9.1 
0.244 0.808 </p>

<p>HDL-C (mg/L) 
13.5 ± 3.1 
14.2 ± 2.7 
−0.905 0.369 
LDL-C (mg/L) 
33.8 ± 6.2 
32.4 ± 8.3 
0.740 0.462 
Data are shown as mean ± SD, n (%), or median (Q1, Q3). The 
difference between groups was nonsignificant at the level P&gt;0.05 at 
baseline tested by Student's t-test or Chi-square test. BMI: Body mass 
index; FPG: Fasting plasma glucose; 2-h PG: 2-h plasma glucose; 
HbA 1c : Glycated hemoglobin A 1c ; HOMA-IR: Insulin resistance index 
of homeostasis model assessment; HDL-C: High-density lipoprotein 
cholesterol; LDL-C: Low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; JLD: Jinlida; 
SD: Standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 2: Clinical variables at baseline and after 12 weeks treatment in JLD and control groups </p>

<p>Variables 
JLD group (n = 32) 
Control group (n = 29) 
After 12 weeks treatment, 
JLD group versus control 
group </p>

<p>Baseline 
After 12 weeks 
Baseline 
After 12 weeks 
Statistical 
values </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>FPG (mmol/L) 
6.2 ± 0.5 
5.8 ± 0.6* 
6.3 ± 0.55 
6.0 ± 0.6* 
1.874 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.176 
2-h PG (mmol/L) 
8.5 ± 2.1 
7.7 ± 2.0 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>9.4 ± 1.6 
10.3 ± 2.5 
14.425 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
HbA 1c (%) 
6.5 ± 0.7 
6.0 ± 0.6* 
6.5 ± 0.5 
6.5 ± 0.5 
23.340 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
Fasting insulin (μU/ml) 
9.2 (7.0, 15.3) 
9.5 (6.5, 11.9) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>9.0 (8.1, 10.7) 
11.4 (8.3, 12.4)* 
-1.813 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>0.070 
HOMA-IR 
2.4 (2.0, 4.0) 
2.41 (1.7, 3.9) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>2.5 (2.1, 3.0) 
3.0 (2.1, 3.3)* 
-2.181 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>0.029 
Weight (kg) 
61.7 ± 9.0 
60.2 ± 9.6* 
62.7 ± 8.2 
61.1 ± 7.6* 
0.005 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.944 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
22.9 ± 2.5 
22.3 ± 2.4* 
23.6 ± 2.7 
23.0 ± 2.2* 
0.271 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.605 
Waist (cm) 
83.4 ± 9.1 
82.6 ± 9.4 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>81.5 ± 5.4 
80.9 ± 4.5 
0.002 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.965 
Waist/hip ratio 
0.9 ± 0.1 
0.9 ± 0.1 
0.9 ± 0.1 
0.9 ± 0.0 
0.135 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.715 
Triglycerides (mg/L) 
15.3 ± 7.8 
15.0 ± 7.1 
15.4 ± 7.9 
13.4 ± 5.4 
3.289 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.075 
Total cholesterol (mg/L) 
56.1 ± 10.5 
52.4 ± 10.1* 
55.5 ± 9.1 
49.7 ± 5.6* 
2.362 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.130 
HDL-C (mg/L) 
13.5 ± 3.1 
13.1 ± 2.7 
14.2 ± 2.7 
13.3 ± 2.4 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.268 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.606 
LDL-C (mg/L) 
33.8 ± 6.2 
32.6 ± 6.1 
32.4 ± 8.3 
31.2 ± 5.9 
0.267 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.607 
Data are shown as mean ± SD, or median (Q1, Q3). *P&lt;0.01, 
 † P&lt;0.05, compared with baseline in the same group using paired 
t-test or Wilcoxon test. 
 ‡ Analysis of covariance; </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney's U-test. BMI: Body mass index; FPG: Fasting plasma glucose; 
2-h PG: 2-h plasma glucose; HbA 1c : Glycated hemoglobin A 1c ; HOMA-IR: Insulin resistance index of homeostasis model assessment; 
HDL: High-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL: Low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; JLD: Jinlida; SD: Standard deviation. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ October 5, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 19 </p>



<p>difference in the number of subjects who had normal glucose 
at the end of the study between JLD group and control 
group (χ 
2 = 10.678, P = 0.001). The Chi-square test showed 
no significant difference in comparison of the incidence of 
DM between the two groups (χ 
2 = 1.809, P = 0.173). </p>

<p>Adverse reactions </p>

<p>Results of liver and kidney function in both groups examined 
before and after treatment were all in the normal range. 
Following the treatment for 12 weeks, AEs were noted in two 
patients. All reported AEs were gastrointestinal reactions and 
mild to moderate in severity. One patient in the JLD group 
experienced diarrhea and one subject in the control group 
had nausea. No patients were withdrawn from the study due 
to these AEs. No hypoglycemia or other serious AEs were 
reported during the study period. </p>

<p>dIscussIon </p>

<p>Several large-scale intervention trials have demonstrated 
that lifestyle changes (including dieting and exercising) </p>

<p>[22-24] </p>

<p>and pharmacological interventions 
[25-30] (acarbose, voglibose, 
metformin, thiazolidinediones, etc.) were effective in 
preventing T2DM. However, lifestyle intervention is 
impractical to some extent as it could hardly be carried out 
by patients to achieve satisfactory improvement. There are 
also many disadvantages of the Western medicine listed 
above, such as costly price and AEs. In this field, TCM has 
been used in the prevention of diabetes and showed certain 
superiority. </p>

<p>[11,12,31-34] </p>

<p>Several clinical trials have revealed that JLD granule can 
control blood glucose levels and have systemic benefits in 
patients with diabetes. 
[14-18] In an early clinical observational 
study of 186 patients with T2DM ineffectively managed by 
metformin monotherapy, 12 weeks of JLD granule treatment 
as add-on medication decreased HbA 1c by 0.92 ±1.09% and 
reduced FPG and 2-h PG levels. 
[18] Elevated HbA 1c levels 
that integrated PG overtime was now validated as another 
indicator of IGT. 
[5] Our study showed that patients in JLD 
group had significantly reduced FPG, 2-h PG, and HbA 1c 
after 12 weeks of treatment, and the levels of 2-h PG and 
HbA 1c were very significantly different between two groups 
after 12 weeks of treatment. Our data indicated that JLD 
granule had a good hypoglycemic effect, in accord with the 
result of the previous clinical study on JLD granule. </p>

<p>Chinese herbal medicine is often used in the prevention 
of different diseases. To date, no clinical trials have been 
conducted to evaluate whether JLD granule is effective in 
treating IGT. IGT can be observed as an intermediate stage 
in diabetes. 
[19] In this study, the JLD granule effectively 
enhanced the conversion of IGR to normal blood glucose, 
and the incidence of DM showed a decreased tendency in 
JLD group compared with control group. </p>

<p>IGT is associated with the insulin resistance syndrome. 
Insulin resistance syndrome, which is also known 
as the metabolic syndrome, is characterized by the 
presence of insulin resistance, dyslipidemia, increased </p>

<p>weight circumference (abdominal obesity), dysglycemia, 
hypertension, etc. 
[35] The clinical characters listed above 
are risk factors that increase the risk of type 2 diabetes, 
cardiovascular disease, and all-cause mortality. 
[36] Our data 
showed that insulin resistance, which directly involved in the 
pathogenesis of T2DM, was significantly decreased in JLD 
group after 12 weeks of treatment, compared with baseline. 
Both JLD and control groups showed lowered weight, 
BMI, and total cholesterol after 12 weeks of treatment, 
indicating that our subjects may benefit from standard diet 
control and exercise therapy. Noticing that mean waist 
circumference of JLD group was reduced after 12 weeks of 
treatment (P = 0.037) while no changes were observed in the 
control group, which implied that patients with abdominal 
obesity might benefit from JLD granule. </p>

<p>JLD granule is composed of seventeen Chinese medical herbs. 
Many components of JLD granule, such as ginsenosides, 
puerarin, and C. chinensis, have been demonstrated to have 
a hypoglycemic effect. 
[37-39] Besides, Wang et al. 
[40] supposed 
that the mechanism underlying the antihyperglycemic effect 
of JLD granule might be associated with its protection of 
pancreatic β-cells through AMP-activated protein kinase 
activation. In the current study, no obvious AEs occurred, 
which suggested that this herbal drug was safe to use. 
Although the results of our study need to be confirmed by 
larger and longer clinical trials in the future, JLD granule 
had promising potential as an effective means in slowing 
the progression of IGT to T2DM. </p>

<p>Our study had some limitations, such as relatively short 
study period and small sample size. Given the limitation of 
this study, the conversion of IGT to T2DM did not reach the 
significant level based on statistical analysis. In the future, 
further interventional studies with longer length of treatment 
and follow-up and larger sample size are needed to verify it. </p>

<p>In summary, the JLD granule effectively improved glucose 
control, increased the conversion of IGT to normal glucose, 
and improved the insulin resistance in individuals with IGT. 
For IGT individuals who are at high risk of developing T2DM, 
this Chinese herbal medicine may help to prevent diabetes. </p>

<p>Financial support and sponsorship </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant from the Xiamen 
Systems Biology Research Program for Metabolic Disease 
(No. 3502Z20100001). </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>There are no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>references </p>



<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ October 5, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 19 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>