<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5238813" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: The effects of different formulations and manufacturing process conditions on the 
physical properties of a solid dosage form are of importance to the pharmaceutical industry. It is 
vital to have in-depth understanding of the material properties and governing parameters of its 
processes in response to different formulations. Understanding the mentioned aspects will allow 
tighter control of the process, leading to implementation of quality-by-design (QbD) practices. 
Computational intelligence (CI) offers an opportunity to create empirical models that can be 
used to describe the system and predict future outcomes in silico. CI models can help explore 
the behavior of input parameters, unlocking deeper understanding of the system. This research 
endeavor presents CI models to predict the porosity of tablets created by roll-compacted binary 
mixtures, which were milled and compacted under systematically varying conditions. CI models 
were created using tree-based methods, artificial neural networks (ANNs), and symbolic regres-
sion trained on an experimental data set and screened using root-mean-square error (RMSE) 
scores. The experimental data were composed of proportion of microcrystalline cellulose (MCC) 
(in percentage), granule size fraction (in micrometers), and die compaction force (in kilonewtons) 
as inputs and porosity as an output. The resulting models show impressive generalization abil-
ity, with ANNs (normalized root-mean-square error [NRMSE] =1%) and symbolic regression 
(NRMSE =4%) as the best-performing methods, also exhibiting reliable predictive behavior when 
presented with a challenging external validation data set (best achieved symbolic regression: 
NRMSE =3%). Symbolic regression demonstrates the transition from the black box modeling 
paradigm to more transparent predictive models. Predictive performance and feature selection 
behavior of CI models hints at the most important variables within this factor space. 
Pharmaceutical companies rely on solid dosage forms, which constitute a majority of 
the total manufactured and marketed product. Powder characteristics, manufacturing 
process parameters, and various other tangible entities have profound effects on the 
quality of a solid dosage form in a complex way. The quality of a solid dosage form, 
among other factors, can be assessed based on its hardness and porosity, which can 
be used as indirect measurements of its capability and rate to dissolve. 
1 In most cases, 
the complexity of relationships among the possible material parameters and upstream 
processes diminishes the understanding of the system as a whole. 
Porosity, known as the ratio of volume of void space to the bulk volume and gen-
erally represented as a percentage, is an important property that controls the micro-
structure of the tablet during compression. It can assist in the understanding of the 
dispersion mechanism, behavior after ingestion, moisture penetration, and with certain </p>

<p>correspondence: Mohammad 
hassan Khalid 
Department of Pharmaceutical 
Technology and Biopharmaceutics, 
Faculty of Pharmacy, Jagiellonian 
University-Medical college, 
Medyczna 9, Krakow 30-688, Poland 
Tel +48 73 306 5594 
email hassankhalid101@gmail.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Drug Design, Development and Therapy 
12 January 2017 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>194 </p>

<p>Khalid et al </p>

<p>prerequisites, even bioavailability. Porosity measurements 
are also known to be relevant indicators of drug stability. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>The effect of shape and porosity of granules has been stud-
ied by Johansson and Alderborn, 
3 suggesting that stronger 
tablets are formed when granules with irregular porosity are 
compressed. Theoretically, the porosity of a tablet can be a 
predictor of its dissolution behavior as well. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Previous works on this topic have revealed that porosity 
influences tablet strength; lactose tablets with larger pores 
were weak 
5-7 and similar relationships were observed with 
other excipients such as glucose and mannitol. 
7,8 The impor-
tance of porosity as an indirect measurement of dissolution 
was demonstrated using rate of water uptake, and solvent 
penetration was studied in microcrystalline cellulose (MCC) 
tablets with different porosities. Results showed that tablets 
with 10% and 15% porosity take up water much faster (30 s) 
and expand by up to 50% of original thickness, while tablets 
with 5% porosity are much slower in water uptake behavior 
(148 s), in addition to showing less expansion. 
9 The corre-
lation of porosity with die compaction force has been well 
studied in the past. 
10,11 It was explained that tablets made from 
pharmaceutical powders do not exhibit the quasi-exponential 
trend proposed by Heckel 
12 for evolution of porosity against 
pressure. Pharmaceutical powders exhibit plastic deformation 
properties, while Heckel's model works well with metal-
lic powders. 
11 Tablet brittleness has been described as an 
exponential growth function of porosity using a diverse set 
of pharmaceutical tablets by Gong et al. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Data-driven empirical models established using compu-
tational intelligence (CI) methods can be used as surrogates 
to run in silico experiments to predict porosity. Use of CI 
offers reduction in experiments, leading to cost and time sav-
ings and broader understanding of the system. CI tools have 
been used in works addressing the pharmaceutical industry's 
various problems, including tensile strength, porosity, and 
dissolution problems. </p>

<p>14-18 </p>

<p>Generally, modeling and simulation (M-and-S) is a huge 
area of science, in which various paradigms of modeling are 
used, mostly based on well-established theory. In pharma-
ceutical sciences, a broad area of molecular modeling, using 
ab initio techniques such as molecular docking offers profound 
examples of such an approach. 
19-21 However, when no such 
theory is present, only empirical modeling is a suitable alterna-
tive, in particular with data-driven modeling in focus. 
The aim of this work is to create data-driven intelligent 
models using well-known and established approaches to 
compute the porosity of tablets based on average granule size, 
proportion of MCC, and die compaction force. Furthermore, </p>

<p>it aims to show that CI models can be represented in the 
form of an equation as a result of modeling through sym-
bolic regression -a shift from the black box paradigm to 
transparency. Last, this work attempts to dissect CI models 
to ascertain which of the input variables are more important 
to predict porosity. The models are based on experimental 
data generated by Perez-Gandarillas et al. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
ethics </p>

<p>Since this study is conducted purely in silico, no ethics review 
was sought or granted here. </p>

<p>Training data </p>

<p>The experimental data set contains records of binary tablets 
made from MCC and lactose. Powder mixtures were roll 
compacted under constant conditions. Ribbons were milled to 
produce granules of three different size ranges (315-500; 630-
800, and 800-1,000 μm). In continuation of the process, the 
feed powders (binary mixtures) and their granules from each 
size range were die compacted using six different die compac-
tion forces. The experiments were done in triplicates. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>The tablets were characterized through the porosity. 
Therefore, the porosity is an outcome (Table 1A). After 
ejection, the tablet dimensions (diameter and thickness) were 
measured with a digital micrometer (Mitutoyo, Takatsu-ku, 
Japan), and tablet mass was weighed with an electronic bal-
ance (CP224S). These data were used to calculate the relative 
density (ρ r ) of each tablet, as follows: </p>

<p>ρ 
ρ </p>

<p>r 
t </p>

<p>= 
4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>m 
hD 
π 
(1) </p>

<p>where m is the mass, h is the tablet thickness, D is the tablet 
diameter, and ρ t is the true density of each binary mixture. 
Once the relative density is obtained, the porosity (ε) is 
calculated as follows: </p>

<p>ε 
ρ 
= − 
1 r 
(2) </p>

<p>Validation data </p>

<p>An additional data set from single-powder tableting experiments 
was used to validate the CI models. The data set is explained in 
Perez-Gandarillas et al. 
23 The validation set is composed of data 
generated by varying roll compaction over two sets of tooling 
(cheek plates and sealed rim rolls) and two roll compaction 
forces (4 kN/cm and 8 kN/cm). The ribbons were milled under 
constant settings and granules were compacted under seven </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>195 </p>

<p>computational intelligence models to predict porosity of tablets </p>

<p>different die compaction forces (Table 1B). Variation in roll 
compactor tooling and roll compaction/die compaction forces 
introduces a challenge to trained CI models. </p>

<p>Model training </p>

<p>The models were built using three different approaches: 
1. Tree-based predictive models 
i. Decision trees (<rs type="software">Cubist</rs>) 
ii. Random forests (<rs type="software">randomForest</rs>) 
2. Artificial neural networks (ANNs) (<rs type="software">monmlp</rs>) 
3. Symbolic regression (<rs type="software">rgp</rs>). 
Extensive combinations of algorithm parameters in all 
the approaches were tried. The data set was divided into 
10 folds, where nine of the folds were used for training and 
one for testing. Tenfold cross-validation (10cv) is a renowned 
method to create a "real-world" depiction of a problem from 
the data representing it. 
24 Models were selected based on their 
RMSE values calculated according to Equation 1. The RMSE 
values are a measure of the differences between the predicted 
and the observed values and are completely independent of 
the modeling technique. Hence, they are reliable and widely 
accepted measures for evaluating a model. R statistical envi-
ronment was used to create the models. </p>

<p>RMSE 
pred obs 
= 
∑ 
− 
 
  </p>

<p> 
  </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>n 
( 
) 
(3) </p>

<p>where "pred" is the predicted value from the models, "obs" 
is the observed value from the experiments, and "n" is the 
total number of test cases. 
The RMSE values were normalized using Equation 2. </p>

<p>NRMSE 
RMSE 
= 
− 
× 
X 
X </p>

<p>max 
min </p>

<p>100 
(4) </p>

<p>where RMSE was calculated in Equation 1, X max and X min are 
the highest and the lowest observed values for the outcome 
in the data set, respectively. </p>

<p>CI methods 
Decision trees -<rs type="software">cubist</rs> </p>

<p><rs type="software">Cubist</rs> is a tree-based modeling approach wherein a linear 
model is fit iteratively, resulting in a set of linear models at 
each node starting from the root to the last node of the tree. 
<rs type="software">Cubist</rs> is an ensemble-based technique. All variables that are 
covered by a linear function at a single node are then dis-
carded from the future iterations for that particular tree. This 
process is recursively continued until all the input variables 
have been covered by a single or a set of rules in a tree. This 
is also known as the separate-and-conquer approach. At every 
step, the response of the model is analyzed and adjusted to 
be used by the next model, until the final model is achieved. 
The final prediction is a simple average of the predictions 
from each tree in the ensemble. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>random forest </p>

<p>Random forests are well known tree-based models. One 
model is shaped by numerous trees in the collection. Indepen-
dent trees are generated based on sample data randomly taken 
out of the training data set. Errors exhibited by individual 
trees are collectively representative of the generalization 
error of the <rs type="software">randomForest</rs> model. 
26 An extensive search for 
the best architecture was carried out using a 10cv scheme, 
followed by training of the best-performing architecture on 
the full data set. </p>

<p>anns -<rs type="software">monmlp</rs> </p>

<p><rs type="software">Monmlp</rs> is the implementation of ANN in <rs type="software">R</rs>. ANNs with 
<rs type="software">monmlp</rs> are generalized feed-forward ANNs that work in a 
monotone fashion using the backpropagation (BP) algorithm </p>

<p>Table 1 characteristics of Mcc tablets and the various compaction conditions </p>

<p>Statistical 
parameters </p>

<p>Die compaction 
force (KN) </p>

<p>MCC proportion (%) 
Average granule 
range (μm) </p>

<p>Roll compaction 
force (kN/cm) </p>

<p>Porosity (%) </p>

<p>(a) experimental parameters for training data 
Minimum 
2 
25 
80 
Fixed at 11.02; 
not used in the 
training models </p>

<p>0.17 
Maximum 
14 
100 
900 
0.46 
Median 
6 
50 
408 
0.26 
Mean 
6.84 
54 
481.9 
0.27 
(B) experimental parameters for external validation data 
Minimum 
2 
Fixed at 100% 
80 
0 
0.14 
Maximum 
15 
350 
8 
0.47 
Median 
8 
350 
4 
0.21 
Mean 
8.14 
296 
4.8 
0.24 </p>

<p>Abbreviation: Mcc, microcrystalline cellulose. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>196 </p>

<p>Khalid et al </p>

<p>enhanced by the nonlinear minimization algorithm (nlm) for 
training. Neural networks imitate the structure of the human 
brain, whereby information is passed on between neurons 
in the form of synapses. <rs type="software">Monmlp</rs> allows two hidden layers 
of neurons, with hyperbolic tangent and linear activation as 
transfer functions. 
27 In <rs type="software">monmlp</rs>, signals move forward from 
the input layer through sigmoid neurons before reaching the 
linear output layer. 
Neurons in each layer consist of N inputs (X i ), which 
multiplies by the proper generated weight element (W i,j ) for 
the layer named j. Summation of the weighted inputs plus bias 
(b j ) produces the input (n j ) for the activation function, using 
which the output of each neuron (y i ) can be calculated. 
Moreover, different activation functions, such as hyper-
bolic tangent sigmoid (TAN-SIG) transfer function, loga-
rithm sigmoid (LOGSIG) transfer function, and pure linear 
(PURELIN) transfer function, are the potential transfer 
functions that can be used in each layer. 
28 The neural net-
work package <rs type="software">monmlp</rs> was run extensively to find the best-
performing network architecture with 10cv. The whole data 
set was used to retrain the model on the best architecture. </p>

<p>symbolic regression by <rs type="software">rgp</rs> </p>

<p>Genetic programming (GP) is a bioinspired algorithm based 
on evolution principles to solve complex problems. A com-
plex problem is broken down into smaller, simpler problems 
with random solutions. These solutions are then evolved 
through the biologically mimicked process of variation and 
selection until the end condition is reached or a workable 
solution is generated. Thus, <rs type="software">rgp</rs> is an implementation of GP 
methods in the R environment. 
29 Package <rs type="software">rgp</rs> results are 
simple representations of the problem without being exposed 
to a priori information. <rs type="software">rgp</rs> offers various options for initial-
ization, variation, and selection procedures inherent in GP. 
GP implements a tree structure representation to show the 
mathematical equations. The tree structure is composed of 
two parts: function set (nodes) and a terminal set (leaves). </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>The function set can be chosen through the operators {+, -, 
*, /, sin, cos, log, abs}, mathematical functions, conditional 
statements, or even the user-defined operators. In addition, 
the terminal set includes constants and model variables. </p>

<p>31,32 </p>

<p>To find the best solution, different runs were conducted 
by iterating over GP tuning parameters. The most important 
tuning parameters are maximum size of the chromosome, 
the number of generations, and population size. 
30 The size 
of the chromosome, which governs the maximum length of 
the equation, was varied from 5 to 100. The population size 
was set to 1,000, and the number of generations was set to 
500 million evolution steps divided into 100 stages. 
These equations can be optimized by different strategies. </p>

<p>33,34 </p>

<p>For this experiment, equations were created on the whole 
data set, and then selected ones were optimized using the 
simulated annealing (SANN) algorithm, followed by a quasi-
Newton (Broyden-Fletcher-Goldfarb-Shanno [BFGS]) 
method. </p>

<p>35,36 </p>

<p>independent feature selection by <rs type="software">fscaret</rs> </p>

<p>The package <rs type="software">fscaret</rs> allows semiautomatic feature selection, 
working as a wrapper for the caret package in R. <rs type="software">Fscaret</rs> 
is specialized for in silico feature selection experiments, 
whereby approximately 120 different packages are used to 
fit models. 
37 Input feature ranking is extracted from trained 
models by using weighted averages. Sum of squared errors 
(SSE), mean squared errors (MSEs), and RMSEs are used to 
evaluate models. <rs type="software">fscaret</rs> has been successfully implemented 
in recent studies. </p>

<p>38,39 </p>

<p>Results and discussion </p>

<p>Approximately 10,000 models with different architectures 
were developed using the CI methods mentioned herein. 
External validation of the models was done using a data 
set on tableting with MCC under different roll compaction 
conditions. </p>

<p>Model performance </p>

<p>Results for best models from all the different CI methods are 
shown in Table 2. All CI methods perform well on the data 
sets. The multiple linear regression (MLR) model, shown 
in Table 3, does not represent the process adequately (15% 
error), suggesting that nonlinearity needs to be addressed 
with a robust method. Figure 1 shows the predicted vs 
observed graph for the MLR model. Hence, to find a suitable </p>

<p>Table 2 nrMse for 10cv and external validation tests for all ci methods </p>

<p>Data set 
Multivariate linear 
regression (lm) </p>

<p><rs type="software">Cubist</rs> 
(Cubist) </p>

<p>RF 
(<rs type="software">randomForest</rs>) </p>

<p><rs type="software">Monmlp</rs> 
(monmlp) </p>

<p>Symbolic 
regression (<rs type="software">rgp</rs>) </p>

<p>average of 10cv 
15 
3 
3 
1 
4 
external (unknown to models) 
-
3 
7 
6 
3 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: 10cv, tenfold cross-validation; ci, computational intelligence; nrMse, normalized root-mean-square error; rF, random forest. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>197 </p>

<p>computational intelligence models to predict porosity of tablets </p>

<p>model, decision trees, ANNs, and GP algorithms were used. 
<rs type="software">RGP</rs> was performed as an early-stage experiment at this 
point. Nonetheless, <rs type="software">RGP</rs> shows results comparable to those 
from other methods, which is evidence that evolutionary 
computational methods are quite robust and can fit complex 
data well. </p>

<p>ann model </p>

<p>ANNs show best 10cv generalization results among all the 
experiments conducted, although they fail to maintain the 
performance on the external data set. A simple network of 
two hidden layers of 13 and 11 nodes, respectively, with 
10 ensembles and 100 iterations was found out to be the 
best-performing architecture. Hyperbolic tangent was used 
as the transfer function within the ANN (Figure 2). 
Recent works 
39,40 demonstrate the ANN as a much coveted 
CI modeling tool. ANNs show plausible results in super-
vised learning, a behavior that can be attributed to the high 
generalization ability of the ANNs. Moreover, 10cv ANN 
models exhibit a meager 1% normalized root-mean-square 
error (NRMSE) (Table 1). Although ANNs are robust, are 
widely used, and have great generalization capabilities, they 
are generally black-box models. The resulting ANN models 
cannot be dissected with certainty to establish how different </p>

<p>input features are interacting with each other to predict 
porosity. Furthermore, ANN models are unstable where 
retraining could lead to a slightly different understanding 
of the system. The source of instability and inconsistency 
lies within the design and strategy used to train an ANN. 
Weights in the ANN are generated at random to expedite 
the learning process while the process of learning itself 
is deterministic. Hence, the randomness introduced while 
generating the weights could lead to a completely different 
model after retraining. </p>

<p>symbolic regression </p>

<p>GP is a stable, a transparent method that can offer structural 
insights into the models. Symbolic regression exhibits a good 
model fit (4% 10cv error, 3% external). The advantage of 
symbolic regression is that the result can be represented in 
the form of a mathematical formula. 
41 The model for poros-
ity can be represented as in Equation 4. A regression plot is 
shown in Figure 3. </p>

<p>Table 3 Mlr model statistical parameters </p>

<p>Intercept 
Die compaction force (kN) 
MCC proportion 
Granule fraction range </p>

<p>estimate 
3.486e-01 
-2.041e-02 
1.242e-01 
-1.094e-05 </p>

<p>standard error 
8.743e-03 
8.284e-04 
1.289e-02 
8.426e-06 
t-value 
39.874 
-24.634 
9.633 
-1.299 </p>

<p>P-value 
2e-16 
2e-16 
1.22e-14 
0.198 </p>

<p>Note: adjusted R-squared: 0.8899. 
Abbreviations: Mcc, microcrystalline cellulose; Mlr, multiple linear regression. </p>

<p>⋅ </p>

<p>Figure 1 Predicted vs observed graph for Mlr. 
Abbreviation: Mlr, multiple linear regression. </p>

<p>⋅ </p>

<p>Figure 2 Predicted vs observed graph for ann. 
Abbreviation: ANN, artificial neural network. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>198 </p>

<p>Khalid et al </p>

<p>The model represents the outcome of porosity with high 
accuracy (4% 10cv error). </p>

<p>Porosity In 
In In 
= 
− 
− 
+ + </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C X 
X 
X C </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 
2 
2 
1 
3 </p>

<p>2 
 
( 
) 
(5) </p>

<p>where C 1 =1.52888, C 2 =2.415892, C 3 =7.28763, X 1 is the 
die compaction force (in kilonewtons), and X 2 is the MCC 
proportion (as fraction). </p>

<p>external validation </p>

<p>Data from additional tableting experiments was used to 
test the trained models. Tablets were made with MCC. The 
external data set was particularly challenging for the models 
because roll compaction conditions were kept constant in 
the training data set while being systematically changed in 
the external data set. Table 1 shows the results of external 
validation. The models were able to predict porosity with 
substantial accuracy using unseen input data. The external 
data set is composed of experiments with two different roll 
compactor tooling (cheek plates and rim rolls) and two dif-
ferent roll compaction forces (4 kN and 8 kN) for each. The 
variety of roll compactor settings introduces variance in the 
external data set unknown to the trained models. Although 
CI systems are not known for their extrapolation abilities, </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>the models presented herein are able to extrapolate success-
fully in a small range. Regardless of the complexity in the 
external data set, the <rs type="software">rgp</rs> model represented by Equation 4 
makes accurate predictions of the test cases from all different </p>

<p>tooling and force conditions (Figure 4). Table 4 shows the 
levels of accuracy of prediction for the external validation 
data set. Non-roll-compacted powder is predicted with the 
most accuracy (NRMSE: 7%), followed by prediction of roll 
compaction using rim rolls at 4 kN (NRMSE: 9%). </p>

<p>Model description </p>

<p>Further analysis of trained CI models gives interesting 
insights into the governing parameters within this tableting 
experiment. </p>

<p>Feature selection by gP </p>

<p>Symbolic regression model exhibits feature selection 
behavior. The resulting model represents two inputs in the 
equation as compared to the original three inputs presented 
to it while training. Feature selection process discards the 
input variables which are not contributing decisively toward 
the outcome; in this case, the average granule fraction size. 
Considering granule fraction range as a disposable input 
characteristic for the outcome of porosity is contrary to pre-
vious works, 
43 but justified within the range of this training 
data set. 
22 A comparison between the GP model and the ANN 
model shows that the average granule fraction size does not 
exercise significant effect on the outcome (Figure 5), also 
supported by MLR (Table 3). ANN model does not perform 
feature selection on its own and is bound to use all three 
inputs in the final model. Therefore, GP model discarding 
the average granule fraction size makes it less complex and 
improves performance on the external data set (Table 2). 
Further RSM analysis based on the GP equation shows 
that variation in the amount of MCC does not have a profound 
effect on the porosity of the tablet, while an increase in the 
die compaction force considerably reduces the porosity of 
tablets (Figure 6), a behavior that can be attributed to particle 
rearrangement followed by plastic deformation during the 
compression stage. </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>Feature selection on the external data set to 
establish the surplus of discarded variables </p>

<p>Plausible performance of the trained CI models on a signifi-
cantly different external data set could be an occurrence of 
chance. To study this in detail, important features from both 
the data sets were compared. Feature selection experiments 
using fscaret were run independently on the external data set. 
Confirmatory models were developed with a variation of 
input vectors using the tree-based learning method <rs type="software">Cubist</rs>. 
The resulting top features of the external data set are in agree-
ment with the features used to train the models. The results 
confirm that the die compaction force is the most important 
variable, with roll compaction force, roll compaction tooling, </p>

<p>Figure 3 Predicted vs observed graph for <rs type="software">rgp</rs> (nrMse: 4%). 
Abbreviations: nrMse, normalized root-mean-square error; <rs type="software">rgp</rs>, r-genetic 
programming. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>199 </p>

<p>computational intelligence models to predict porosity of tablets </p>

<p>Figure 4 Model performance on external data set. </p>

<p>percentage of material in the formulation, and granule frac-
tion range displaying much lower ranking. Models developed 
without the information of roll compaction force, roll com-
paction tooling, and granule fraction range predict porosity of 
tablets accurately (Table 5: experiments with two and three 
inputs). The successful modeling shows that these variables </p>

<p>do not contribute to the outcome within this design space. 
The results strongly suggest redundancies in the original 
data set, which, once removed, do not affect the prediction 
of porosity within the factor space. Correlation analysis of 
the original data set reveals that porosity is highly correlated 
to die compaction force (Figure 7). </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>Khalid et al </p>

<p>Table 4 rMse and nrMse for external validation data set using 
<rs type="software">rgp</rs> model </p>

<p>System 
RMSE 
NRMSE </p>

<p>cheekplates (4 kn) 
0.0314 
10 
cheekplates (8 kn) 
0.0401 
14 
rim rolls (4 kn) 
0.0309 
9 
rim rolls (8 kn) 
0.0387 
13 
Feed powder 
0.0254 
7 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: nrMse, normalized root-mean-square error; rMse, root-mean-
square error. </p>

<p>Figure 5 Surface plot showing the influence of average granule fraction size on 
porosity based on the <rs type="software">monmlp</rs> model. 
Abbreviation: <rs type="software">monmlp</rs>, Monotone Multi-layer Perception neural network. </p>

<p>Figure 6 Surface plot showing the influence of MCC and die compaction force on 
porosity based on <rs type="software">rgp</rs> model. 
Abbreviations: Mcc, microcrystalline cellulose; <rs type="software">rgp</rs>, r-genetic programming. </p>

<p>Table 5 Performance metrics for different input combinations of 
training and test data sets </p>

<p>Data set and input numbers 
MLR </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Decision trees </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Training data with three inputs 
8% (0.89) 
3.4% (0.97) 
Training data with two inputs 
8% (0.89) 
3.4% (0.96) 
Test data with five inputs 
11% (0.90) 
1% (0.99) 
Test data with three inputs 
10% (0.90) 
1% (0.99) 
Test data with two inputs 
11.7% (0.78) 
5.2% (0.95) </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>nrMse and R 
2 are presented. all experiments were done in 10cv mode 
of data representation. Mlr and decision trees were implemented in r using lm 
command and <rs type="software">cubist</rs> package, respectively. 
Abbreviations: 10cv, tenfold cross-validation; Mlr, multiple linear regression; 
nrMse, normalized root-mean-square error. </p>

<p>Figure 7 correlation plots for (A) training and (B) test data. 
Abbreviations: avg, average; Mcc, microcrystalline cellulose. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>201 </p>

<p>computational intelligence models to predict porosity of tablets </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>CI models for MCC-based tablets are presented herein. The 
models have been rigorously tested internally using 10cv and 
then externally validated by using a challenging data set. The 
models exhibit reliable prediction behavior, with the best 
achieved 10cv-NRMSE of 1% on using ANNs. The models 
also exhibit understanding of the tableting process within the 
design space. The equation for porosity is presented as the 
result of symbolic regression models with 10cv-NRMSE of 
4% and external validation NRMSE of 3%. Presentation of 
CI models in the form of an equation makes them transpar-
ent to scrutiny and shows how the input variables interact 
with each other plus contribute toward the specific outcome 
of porosity. Contrary to common knowledge, roll compac-
tion parameters such as tooling and compression force do 
not influence the porosity of tablets. Such conclusions are 
confined to the local design space and cannot be treated as 
general rules governing the tableting process. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the IPROCOM Marie Curie 
Initial Training Network, funded through the People Pro-
gramme (Marie Curie Actions) of the European Union's 
Seventh Framework Programme FP7/2007-2013/under REA 
grant agreement number 316555. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/drug-design-development-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal that spans the spectrum of drug design 
and development through to clinical applications. Clinical outcomes, 
patient safety, and programs for the development and effective, safe, 
and sustained use of medicines are the features of the journal, which </p>

<p>has also been accepted for indexing on PubMed Central. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>202 </p>

<p>Khalid et al </p>



</text></tei>