<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5099213" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective To explore the intersection of tobacco, 
legalised marijuana and electronic vaporiser use among 
young adults in the 'natural laboratory' of Colorado, the 
first state with legalised retail marijuana. 
Methods We conducted semistructured interviews with 
32 young adults (18-26 years old) in Denver, Colorado, 
in 2015 to understand the beliefs and practices related 
to the use of tobacco, marijuana and vaporisers. 
The legal landscape around marijuana in the USA is 
changing rapidly. Currently, medical marijuana is 
legal in 25 states and Washington DC, with retail 
('recreational') marijuana legalised in four states 
and Washington DC. On 1 January 2014, 
Colorado became the first state to legally sell retail 
marijuana to people 21 years or older. Shifting reg-
ulations have been accompanied by technological 
innovations, including electronic vaporisers for 
tobacco and marijuana. These developments are 
likely to transform use of these substances, espe-
cially among young adults. 
Nationally, young adults have the highest rates of 
current ( past 30 days) marijuana use, with 18.9% 
aged 18-25 years using in 2013, compared to 7.1% 
aged 12-17 years and 5.5% aged ≥26 years. </p>

<p>1   According to 2014 data, almost 30% of young 
adults in Colorado reported current marijuana 
use. 
2 Young adults also have the highest current </p>

<p>rates of tobacco smoking (37%). 
3 More young 
adults have ever tried e-cigarettes (21.6%) com-
pared to other age groups. 
4 Rates of dual and poly 
use are also high: in 2013, among US young adults 
who smoked cigarettes in the past 30 days (16% of 
the sample), 47% were current marijuana users. </p>

<p>5   Given high rates of co-use of tobacco and mari-
juana among young adults, 
6-9 as well as transfor-
mations in the realm of policy and technology, 
tobacco, marijuana and vaporisers are most effect-
ively studied in relationship to one another. </p>

<p>10   Referred to as 'the triangulum' (Latin for triangle), 
this approach reflects interest in the intersection of 
tobacco, marijuana and electronic vaporiser use, 
with implications for surveillance (eg, evaluating 
tobacco and marijuana use, product taxonomies), 
policy (eg, smoke-free policies related to marijuana 
and e-cigarettes) 
11 12 and treatment (eg, effects of 
dual use on cessation). 
13 Several quantitative 
studies examined some aspects of the triangulum, 
including co-use of combustible tobacco and mari-
juana, 
14 perceptions of comparative harm of 
tobacco and marijuana, 
15 prevalence of vaporiser 
use among marijuana users 
16 17 and reasons for use 
of marijuana vaporisers. 
17 18 Two qualitative 
studies examined the intersection of tobacco and 
marijuana by interviewing youth in Scotland. </p>

<p>13 19   The data in the studies, however, were collected 
over a decade ago and do not reflect changing legal 
and normative environments around marijuana or 
the proliferation of vaporising devices. Several 
quantitative studies have addressed marijuana 
vaporisers use by adults, including Lee et al 
17 and 
Etter, 
18 but neither was designed to explore in 
depth why users choose to vaporise marijuana, or 
the social or policy contexts shaping vaporiser use. 
To the best of our knowledge, this is the first 
in-depth, qualitative investigation of the triangulum 
in the 'natural laboratory' of Colorado. We inter-
viewed young adults in Colorado to understand 
how they use, perceive and ascribe meaning to 
various tobacco, marijuana and vaporiser products. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Collaboration </p>

<p>As part of the State and Community Tobacco 
Control (SCTC) research initiative (http://www. 
sctcresearch.org), this project was developed in stra-
tegic partnership with Denver Public Health and 
Jefferson County Public Health departments in 
Colorado. Beginning in early 2014, we worked 
with local agencies to identify research questions 
that would advance policy solutions and practice. 
These questions were further refined iteratively </p>

<p> 
McDonald EA, et al. Tob Control 2016;25:i96-i102. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2016-053091 </p>

<p>Research paper </p>

<p>throughout the data collection period. Local agencies provided 
staff to recruit participants, assisted with interviewing, provided 
space for interviews and engaged key stakeholders in reviewing 
early findings. </p>

<p>Study recruitment </p>

<p>Participants were recruited using flyers placed in marijuana dis-
pensaries, vape shops, cafes, stores and on bulletin boards at 
community colleges in the Denver Metro area. Online recruit-
ment was conducted through Craigslist and posting on 
Facebook. Inclusion criteria included being 18-26 years old and 
current use ( past month) of at least one of the three products 
(marijuana, tobacco or electronic vaporisers). Prospective parti-
cipants were screened and enrolled in the study via telephone 
by trained research staff. We attempted to interview all 32 
enrolled participants twice, in order to allow conversations to 
develop more deeply. Twenty-four completed both interviews. 
Participants were compensated $35 for the first interview and 
$65 for the second. Each participant gave written consent. All 
study protocols were approved by the Committee on Human 
Research at the University of California, San Francisco. </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>Semistructured interviews were conducted between January and 
August 2015 by six trained interviewers (three PhDs, one 
MD and two MPHs), following a standard interview guide. 
Interviews were conducted individually (one participant with 
one or more interviewers) in public places (coffee shops, librar-
ies) or in meeting rooms in local health departments. Before 
each interview, participants completed brief questionnaires with 
demographic information and past tobacco and marijuana use 
history. Discussion topics included definitions of smoking, 
experiences with tobacco, e-cigarettes, marijuana, marijuana 
vaporisers and other products, perceived benefits and risks of 
products and experiences with marijuana legalisation in Denver. 
Interviews lasted between 60 and 90 min, and were audio 
recorded. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>Audio recordings were professionally transcribed. Data were 
coded using <rs type="software">Dedoose</rs> software. Researchers McDonald and 
Popova independently blind-coded a subset of transcripts, which 
were then compared to develop coding guidelines. Researchers 
created code definitions and developed a consistent coding 
scheme to ensure that codes were applied consistently. The 
larger set of transcripts was divided and coded independently. 
Themes were generated iteratively during review of coded tran-
scripts. Memos summarising each theme with illustrative quotes 
were reviewed by authors and discussed iteratively to reach con-
sensus and theme saturation. Pseudonyms are used for all parti-
cipants quoted in this article and no real names have been used. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Sample characteristics </p>

<p>Participants were 32 young adults with a mean age of 23 
(SD=2.36) years; 43.8% were women, 34% were Hispanic, 
31% non-Hispanic white, 19% non-Hispanic black and 13% 
more than one race, non-Hispanic. The majority (19 partici-
pants or 59%) were not currently enrolled in or attending 
school, five participants were in community college, four in 
high school, two in a 4-year college or university, one in a tech-
nical or trade school and one in a professional (law or medical) 
school. </p>

<p>Ninety-one per cent of participants had ever smoked a 
tobacco cigarette; 56% smoked 100 cigarettes or more; 97% 
ever smoked marijuana and 44% were daily marijuana smokers. 
Table 1 shows rates of use of each product as collected in our 
intake questionnaire. Three-quarters (75%) of participants 
reported dual use of tobacco and marijuana in the past 30 days, 
while 19% reported only marijuana use and 6% only tobacco 
use in the past 30 days. Sixty-nine per cent of participants had 
used all three products-combustible tobacco, marijuana and 
vaporisers (for nicotine or marijuana)-in the past 30 days. </p>

<p>Themes </p>

<p>Participants highlighted fluidity between use of tobacco, mari-
juana and vaporisers. Reflecting this fluidity, the terms 'smoke' 
and to be a 'smoker' were used to describe either tobacco or 
marijuana use in ways that left unclear which substance was 
referred to. While dual and poly use was our primary focus, 
some participants also reported co-use through merging pro-
ducts, including use of tobacco wraps (blunts) or little cigars/ 
cigarillos to smoke marijuana and the use of tobacco cigarettes 
to 'extend' the effects of marijuana. Vaporising devices were 
used to consume either nicotine or marijuana concentrates, 
with such devices nearly indistinguishable in appearance. 
Participants remarked upon the increasing popularity of 
'vaping', expanded interest in vaporisers for nicotine and mari-
juana products and the convenience of vaporisers for use in 
public spaces. 
In some contexts, participants clearly distinguished between 
tobacco, marijuana and vaping, as they did when discussing the 
risks of secondhand smoke. Participants viewed secondhand 
tobacco smoke as potentially dangerous, often limiting or prohi-
biting use of combustible tobacco in homes or cars. Marijuana 
secondhand smoke, in sharp contrast, was widely considered 
safer and more pleasant smelling than tobacco smoke, with few 
participants restricting combustible marijuana indoors. </p>

<p>Do you smoke? </p>

<p>Our question 'Do you smoke?' was frequently met with the 
question: 'smoke what?' The term 'smoking' was used inter-
changeably to refer to the use of marijuana or tobacco, with this 
ambiguity only uncovered through conversation: when a 
researcher asked 'Ethan', 22, 'In terms of your social circle in 
Colorado, do many people smoke?' 'Ethan' responded, '[e] 
veryone that I work with under the age of 30 smokes. I have 
five roommates and they all smoke. Just about everyone I know 
in Denver smokes. I have one friend that doesn't, just because 
he gets panic attacks'. When the researcher asked whether these 
friends were regular or occasional smokers, 'Ethan' responded, 
'Much more regular marijuana smokers…[ pause] are we still 
talking about tobacco smoking? When I hear "smoking" now, I 
associate it more with marijuana than tobacco smoking'. 'Ethan' 
clarified that among his friends, only five were regular tobacco 
smokers, whereas the majority smoke marijuana. In Colorado, 
he elaborated, the term 'smoke' primarily indicates use of mari-
juana, but added, 'If I go back to Texas, and somebody says, 
"I'm going to go for a smoke," I know [they mean] cigarettes-
tobacco'. 
When asked if he ever smoked while drinking, 'Owen', 20, 
commented, 'Yeah… if I have one drink I'll probably be 
smoking before, you know?' When the researcher asked him to 
clarify whether he meant smoking marijuana or tobacco, he 
responded, 'Marijuana. I don't really smoke tobacco products 
like that. The only reason why I put 20 times [of tobacco use 
per month on the questionnaire] is because [of ] Swisher Sweets </p>

<p>McDonald EA, et al. Tob Control 2016;25:i96-i102. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2016-053091 
i97 </p>

<p>Research paper </p>

<p>[cigarillos]. I'd have to get a Swisher Sweet to roll up the mari-
juana, you know?'. He added that he would not smoke cigarillos 
'straight', but only as a wrap for marijuana. </p>

<p>Blunts: bringing together marijuana and tobacco </p>

<p>Participants frequently discussed smoking marijuana using 
blunts (the emptied shell of a tobacco cigarillo or a tobacco 
wrap filled with marijuana). However, many of these partici-
pants did not report using blunts as a form of tobacco use. 
Some participants seemed unsure whether to categorise the 
use of blunt wraps or cigarillos for marijuana as a form of 
tobacco use. 'Daniela', 22, states, 'I've never smoked a cigar… 
the blunt wrap, I don't know if it should even be considered 
[tobacco] just because it's its own [ product]… it's just a paper… 
it's not like you can get addicted to blunt wraps'. 
Other participants recognised the effects of nicotine in blunt 
wraps when compared to other methods of consuming mari-
juana. 'Nia', 19, commented she could 'feel' the nicotine in 
blunt wraps and elected to use 'papers' rather than blunt wraps, 
'because the papers don't have any nicotine'. </p>

<p>Traditional surveys may fail to record tobacco wrap use. 
When asked about his response of using tobacco products on 3 
of the past 30 days, 'Andre', 22, clarified: </p>

<p>Interviewer: You're smoking a tobacco product three days out of 
the month? </p>

<p>'Andre': Yeah. </p>

<p>Interviewer: How often are you using wraps for marijuana, 
tobacco wraps? </p>

<p>'Andre': Oh, tobacco wraps? Definitely every day. Definitely 
every day. </p>

<p>Interviewer: Okay. How many times per day are you using blunt 
wraps? </p>

<p>'Andre': I'd say three, four blunts a day maybe. </p>

<p>Interviewer: Walk me through the timing of those during your 
day. </p>

<p>Table 1 Participants' use of tobacco and marijuana products (N=32) </p>

<p>Product 
Ever use (%) 
Past 30 days (%) 
Daily user (%) </p>

<p>Days used in past 
30, median (IQR) </p>

<p>Tobacco cigarettes 
90.6 
43.8 
15.6 
0 (0-10) </p>

<p>Little cigars or cigarillos 
78.1 
43.8 
9.4 
0.5 (0-9.3) </p>

<p>Electronic cigarettes 
78.1 
46.9 
9.4 
0.5 (0-10) </p>

<p>Hookah 
81.3 
34.4 
3.1 
0 (0-1) </p>

<p>Moist snuff 
25.0 
0 
0 
0 ( 0 -0) </p>

<p>Snus 
18.8 
0 
0 
0 ( 0 -0) </p>

<p>Smoked marijuana 
96.9 
93.8 
43.8 
28 (15-30) </p>

<p>Marijuana vaporisers 
90.6 
81.3 
6.3 
2 (1-10) </p>

<p>Marijuana edibles 
93.8 
68.8 
3.1 
1 (0-3.8) </p>

<p> 
McDonald EA, et al. Tob Control 2016;25:i96-i102. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2016-053091 </p>

<p>Research paper </p>

<p>'Andre': Let's start with 8:00 and I'll usually finish that whole 
blunt. That would be one gone. And then by noon or 1:00 at 
least. After lunch usually, that's when I have my second one. And 
then depending how tired I am, after my day is done, it's my 
winding down. Sometimes it takes one, sometimes it takes two. 
So, that's what I mean…three or four. </p>

<p>One reason participants used cigarillos to consume marijuana 
was enjoyment of flavours. 'Andre' commented that while he 
had smoked joints (marijuana rolled in paper), he preferred 
blunt wrap flavours: </p>

<p>I love wraps way more. It might be the tobacco, but there's some-
thing about smoking weed in the wraps that's different from 
blunt papers to me. When you inhale it, you get that flavor some-
times of whatever flavor wrap you choose…I just love fruit 
flavors…they put out new flavors all the time too. I tried a 
chicken and waffle wrap flavor the other day. It tasted like syrup 
mainly, but that's what I'm saying. I didn't know they could do 
stuff like that so I'm like, 'I've got to try it!' It's just kind of fun 
to me. I do it with my brothers and we'll just chill-we'll have a 
good time. </p>

<p>Another reason participants reported choosing blunts over 
other forms of marijuana consumption was the social nature of 
sharing with partners or friends. 'April', 24, commented she 
often smokes blunts with her boyfriend, sharing up to four a 
day. When she is not sharing with him, she prefers to use her 
personal vaporiser while at work, or, if by herself, smoke mari-
juana in a glass pipe. She reflected, 'blunts are kind of more 
social…I'd rather smoke blunts in a social setting rather than 
hitting a pipe and passing it…That's just how it's always been 
with me and my friends. If we're all together, a blunt will last 
longer and it's easier [to] just pass…you keep it continuously lit 
and continuously circling'. 
Participants also reported using cigarettes, particularly 
menthols, to extend the high from marijuana, or for mixing 
marijuana with comparatively inexpensive tobacco. As 'Andre' 
states: </p>

<p>I know a lot people who need cigarettes and weed…they smoke 
a blunt and then they're high…they say cigarettes keep their high 
going. They'll have like two cartons of cigarettes…weed is way 
more expensive…so they'll try to have plenty of cigarettes and 
just a little bit of weed…that's a cheaper way to keep a buzz 
going. I've even seen people with a little bit of weed…break 
down the cigarette, use all the tobacco. It will be more tobacco 
than weed, but they mix it all together… cigaweed. That's what 
they call it, cigaweed. [laughs]. </p>

<p>Electronic vaporisers for nicotine and marijuana </p>

<p>Adding complexity to this 'smoking' landscape, participants 
questioned whether or not electronic cigarettes should be con-
sidered tobacco products, and reflected on the use of electronic 
vaporisers for marijuana. 
'Victor', 24, used to smoke marijuana blunts using Dutch 
Masters cigar wraps when living in Florida. But since moving to 
Colorado, he has switched to vaporising concentrates, primarily 
cannabis wax in a portable vaporising pen. As he explains, he 
barely smokes 'real weed' anymore, because 'flower' does not 
get him high. He tries not to smoke much while at his job in 
construction, 'if anything I'll take a little hit (from a vape pen), 
just to line up the head, and just keep going'. 
Participants also reflected on using marijuana vaporisers in 
locations where marijuana use is illegal due to public consump-
tion laws. For example, 'Rashawn', 24, indicated that vaporisers 
can be used while driving. He explained, 'I do drive when I'm 
high…marijuana is not necessarily something that makes you </p>

<p>impaired'. When asked if he worried about the legality of 
driving under the influence, he explained, '…I try and be a little 
safe since I know what [the police are] looking for. I use a 
vaporizer if I'm driving because they're basically odorless…and 
it's a lot better than smoke because if they do smell marijuana 
in your car, I guess they're allowed to search it or check you for 
anything'. 
Another reason for using marijuana vaporisers was the ability 
to smoke while at work. 'April' commented, 'If I'm traveling 
and I don't really want to be smoking a bowl in the middle of 
wherever, then I like the marijuana version of [an e-cigarette]. If 
I'm at a job where I'm okay smoking, then on break I'll go out 
to the parking lot or whatever and maybe smoke a vaporizer'. 
The lack of potent smell was associated not only with evading 
public consumption laws but also with managing social stigma. 
'Danielle', 25, commented: </p>

<p>I guess it's more-especially the vape pens-more subtle… This 
one girl at school…she always gives me this death stare. It's like, 
'I can't believe you're smoking pot.' So yeah, I'm trying to vapor-
ize just for that. There's still a little bit of a stigma there. I mean, 
everyone [in Colorado] smokes…at the same time, I feel it's 
polite to keep it under wraps sometimes. </p>

<p>Participants commented that some personal vaporisers could 
be used for marijuana concentrates or for nicotine solutions. 
When asked to clarify whether she was referring to using a 
vaporiser for nicotine or marijuana, 'Angela', 18, commented 
'You can do both on the pen that I have…You can go up to the 
[marijuana] dispensary and get it filled up for 30 bucks. Or you 
can go to the gas station and get nicotine for 5 bucks'. 
Some participants reported that the legalised marijuana 
market has encouraged the proliferation of electronic devices 
and expanded interest in electronic vaporisers more broadly. 
'Molly', 25, commented, 'I think because marijuana has been so 
present in Colorado, all these different smoking devices are very 
common. You just see everyone walking around with electronic 
cigarettes or with vape pens…it's just the culture here'. 
Some exclusive nicotine users felt troubled by the inability to 
distinguish between vaporisers used for marijuana and nicotine. 
'Samuel', 21, commented, 'A lot of vape shops take a negative 
stance towards the electronic vaporization of marijuana because 
then people tend to associate you with [marijuana] no matter 
what. When you're walking down the street and you're vaping, a 
lot of people straight up just assume it's marijuana'. He contin-
ued, '…if I ever get pulled over while driving…the cop comes 
up, and he's, like, 'well, what's all this? Is this just an electronic 
cigarette or is there tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) in it?' Because 
there's no public knowledge of this; you wouldn't know unless 
you were vaping'. </p>

<p>Smoke is smoke? Young adults assess harm of secondhand 
tobacco and secondhand marijuana smoke </p>

<p>Participants consistently viewed secondhand tobacco smoke 
negatively, commenting that it 'smells bad' and is harmful for 
bystanders. Secondhand marijuana smoke, however, was identi-
fied as having a 'pleasant aroma' that quickly dissipated. 
Participants sometimes mentioned that there may be harmful 
effects of secondhand marijuana smoke ('smoke is smoke'), but 
marijuana smoke was generally considered less dangerous. 
Participants often differentiated between cigarettes and mari-
juana in maintaining smoke-free spaces. 'Scott', 26, remarked 
that marijuana and alcohol were similar in that 'you can't drink 
on the streets, you can't smoke on the streets. You have to go to 
a private place'. Yet, he noted, there are no public cannabis bars, </p>

<p>McDonald EA, et al. Tob Control 2016;25:i96-i102. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2016-053091 
i99 </p>

<p>Research paper </p>

<p>requiring young adults to create their own use rules in private 
(and sometimes public) spaces. Here, the distinction between 
cigarettes and cannabis comes into relief. As 'Scott' remarked: </p>

<p>As far as secondhand cigarette smoke goes, I'm glad that you 
can't smoke cigarettes in a bar because I personally don't like the 
smell. I think it leaves a really gross stench. And I don't let 
people smoke [cigarettes] in my apartment…[or] in my car…I'm 
not concerned about the health effects of secondhand smoke 
because it just never concerned me. But for me, it's just I don't 
like the smell. </p>

<p>When asked to compare the smell of cigarette smoke to can-
nabis smoke, 'Scott' explained: </p>

<p>I enjoy the smell of cannabis. And I think a lot of people [do]. 
Ever since I was younger, I love the smell of it. It was just intoxi-
cating. And the smell doesn't linger as much. </p>

<p>Smoke tobacco outside, smoke marijuana inside </p>

<p>While many young adults established household rules prohibit-
ing tobacco smoke indoors, they were far more lenient about 
indoor use of marijuana or e-cigarettes. 
'Danielle' maintained strict rules prohibiting the use of cigar-
ettes in her home, but had no such prohibitions against smoking 
marijuana. When asked if she lets friends smoke inside her 
home, she explained: </p>

<p>No, no, no. I mean, we smoke weed. Yeah, that's for sure. But 
not smoke tobacco. I don't see why not [smoke marijuana] unless 
the smell is too bad. We can open a window. But no cigarettes in 
the house for sure…cigarettes smell worse. They're no fun for 
secondhand smokers. It's worse for you as a secondhand smoker 
than it is as a first-hand smoker. </p>

<p>'Danielle' mentioned that while growing up in Southern 
California, she saw many educational antitobacco messages, 
which she described as 'these horror stories of how tobacco 
destroyed lives and families and stuff '. Most saliently, she 
recalled the story of a man whose smoking affected his kids and 
pets. As she remembered thinking, '"Not the dog!" So, I won't 
have [tobacco smoke] around my cats or dog. You're going to 
kill them. That's why I don't like that in the house'. When 
asked if secondhand marijuana smoke would affect her pets, she 
explained, 'Oh, I mean, it definitely affects them, but…it's not 
bad for them…there's marijuana in pet medicine…there's so 
many medicinal properties'. 
When asked about rules regarding smoking in his multiunit 
housing complex, 'Xavier', 24, mentioned that 'technically' he 
was in a non-smoking building. He explained that cigarette 
smoke negatively affects furniture and walls, and that tenants 
'technically would have to go outside'. When asked if these 
rules also applied to marijuana, he responded, 'I don't know. I 
think it might say cigarettes specifically. I know the picture [on 
the sign] is cigarettes. But, it could just say a general "no 
smoking," with a cigarette and the non-smoking [symbol]. I 
couldn't tell you. I just assumed it was cigarettes, I guess'. He 
continued, 'marijuana smoke disappears a lot quicker…just the 
smell and the aroma. I don't think it's as harmful. Not only to 
you, but to the surrounding area. That's just my personal 
opinion on marijuana smoke'. 
Another reason participants chose to smoke marijuana inside 
is that doing so had protected them from police surveillance 
during the years marijuana was illegal. 'Teresa', 21, explained 
that when she started smoking marijuana at the age of 13, her 
mother told her 'just smoke the weed in the house. Don't go </p>

<p>outside. Just go in the bathroom. Lock yourself in there. Don't 
let nobody see you. Don't do it out on the street'. 
Finally, some participants elected to smoke marijuana indoors 
because they did not have access to private, outdoor spaces 
(such as a backyard), or lived in multiunit housing where 
outdoor space was shared. When young adults did have access 
to private, outdoor spaces, they reported being more likely to 
smoke outside. 'Daniela' stated that, '[m]ost of my friends are 
not super-duper potheads. They don't want their house smelling 
like marijuana or anything like that, so they do go outside… 
they have a little patio-their backyard'. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The emerging issues uncovered in this qualitative study highlight 
the need to reconsider the traditional silo-based approach to 
tobacco control and marijuana research. It is particularly 
important to consider the triangulum of tobacco, marijuana and 
vaporisers, and we believe this is the first study to address this 
intersection in the context of legalised marijuana. 
We found widespread ambiguity about whether 'to smoke' 
referred to the use of tobacco or marijuana products. While not 
unique to Colorado, this linguistic equivalence between tobacco 
and marijuana use may signal increasing normalisation of mari-
juana. Researchers should be aware of this ambiguity in design-
ing precisely worded research instruments. Additionally, 
antitobacco messaging that focus on 'smoke' or 'smoker' iden-
tity may be diluted in this context, as combustible marijuana 
moves towards legality and widespread availability. 
Participants reported the use of tobacco products as part of 
the consumption of marijuana. This points to several key issues. 
Tobacco products are used as a delivery method for marijuana 
(eg, blunts) because of convenience and/or to facilitate sharing, 
even when tobacco products are not explicitly desired. 
Therefore, tobacco consumption may increase and become nor-
malised even in the absence of the desire to use tobacco. 
Second, as noted previously, 
20 21 participants reported using 
traditional tobacco cigarettes to extend the 'high' of marijuana 
consumption, particularly because of tobacco's comparatively 
lower cost. Third, participants did not uniformly agree whether 
the use of tobacco products for consuming marijuana 'counted' 
as using tobacco. This may lead to a significant under-reporting 
of current tobacco use. For example, the participant who 
reported using tobacco products 3 days of the last 30 on the 
questionnaire revealed during his interview that he used tobacco 
wrappers for marijuana 30 days out the past 30 (3-4 per day). It 
was not until specifically asked about his method of marijuana 
consumption that it became evident he was a daily tobacco user. 
Tobacco researchers should be aware that tobacco products used 
to consume marijuana may not be reported as tobacco use, and 
should specifically ask about the use of blunt wraps and cigaril-
los for marijuana consumption. While this issue has been raised 
before, 
14 with at least one nationally representative survey 
(National Survey on Drug Use and Health (NSDUH)) asking 
about cigarillos for marijuana consumption, 
22 it has not been 
widely adopted and will become increasingly critical as mari-
juana is more widely legalised. 
Participants reported the appeal of electronic vaporisers for 
nicotine and marijuana. Some participants used the same vapor-
iser for both products (switching cartridges between marijuana 
concentrates and nicotine solutions), while others reported 
owning devices for each. Although past studies showed that 
vaping was less common than smoking marijuana among a con-
venience sample of adults, 
16 given the rapid growth of the mari-
juana vaporiser industry 
23 24 and the growing popularity of </p>

<p> 
McDonald EA, et al. Tob Control 2016;25:i96-i102. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2016-053091 </p>

<p>Research paper </p>

<p>electronic vaporisers, especially in states with legalised medical 
marijuana, 
16 it is essential to study perceptions and practices 
related to electronic vaporisers for marijuana. 
Reduced odour was frequently mentioned in the appeal of 
marijuana vaporisers, cited as advantageous when consuming 
marijuana in public spaces (currently illegal under Colorado's 
public consumption laws). Those wishing to vaporise marijuana 
in public may benefit from the broader normalisation of nico-
tine vaporising (legal in many, though not all, outdoor, public 
spaces), as the similar appearance of the devices may make it dif-
ficult for the passers-by or law enforcement to identify which 
product is being consumed. This was experienced negatively by 
some participants who exclusively vaporise nicotine, as they felt 
falsely identified as marijuana users. 
Communities concerned about the use of marijuana in public 
spaces should consider including all vaporisers (for nicotine or 
marijuana) in smoke-free regulations to prevent this confusion. 
Additionally, there is a concern that growing popularity of 
vaping, for tobacco and marijuana, might renormalise 
smoking. </p>

<p>25   Participants clearly differentiated between secondhand 
tobacco and secondhand marijuana smoke. Many were quick to 
cite the dangers of tobacco, including secondhand smoke, and 
enforced rules determining where combustible tobacco could 
and could not be used in their own spaces. In contrast, mari-
juana smoke was largely regarded as benign, neutral or even 
pleasant. Few participants expressed concern about secondhand 
marijuana smoke, or limited where combustible marijuana could 
be used. This was, in part, due to the subjective experiences of 
marijuana smoke being much 'milder' than tobacco smoke, and 
dissipating more quickly. Participants also reported that aerosol 
produced by vaporisers ('vapour'), whether nicotine or mari-
juana, smelled less strongly than combustible smoke, and gener-
ally allowed its use indoors. 
This is in contrast to a study in Georgia that found 83% of 
surveyed college students adopted smoke-free policies for mari-
juana and 86% for tobacco in their homes. 
26 State policies 
around legal marijuana might affect young adults' personal 
smoke-free rules. Our participants reported that smoking com-
bustible marijuana indoors was often the only viable option 
available. Colorado law prohibits the use of marijuana in public 
places (including public outdoor spaces adjacent to homes). 
Since many of our participants lived in lower income, multiunit 
housing, they did not often have private outdoor spaces where 
they could legally smoke marijuana. Their choice, therefore, was 
either to break the law and smoke marijuana in an outdoor 
public space, or, following the law, smoke combustible mari-
juana in indoor, home spaces. Furthermore, 'no smoking' signs 
in housing units and other spaces were sometimes unclear, with 
young adults unsure whether prohibitions were limited to 
tobacco or included marijuana. 
Current research indicates that secondhand marijuana smoke 
contains many of the same chemicals as secondhand tobacco 
smoke and some in greater concentrations 
27 with recent studies 
demonstrating that secondhand marijuana smoke has negative 
cardiovascular effects similar to tobacco smoke. </p>

<p>28  29   Non-smokers exposed to secondhand marijuana smoke had 
detectable levels of THC and metabolites, with levels increasing 
when higher potency marijuana was used. 
30-33 Non-smokers 
exposed to cannabis smoke for 60 min in an unventilated room 
had detectable levels of THC in blood following the exposure, 
increased heart rate, mild to moderate self-reported sedative 
drug effects and performed worse on a cognitive test. 
34 As nor-
malisation of marijuana use continues, it is important to </p>

<p>monitor the effects of normalisation on tobacco use, perceptions 
and smoke-free spaces. Smoke-free policies should cover all pro-
ducts, including combustible marijuana and electronic vaporisers 
for tobacco and marijuana. Signs and information signalling 
smoke-free policies should be adapted to clearly include mari-
juana smoke where applicable. Information about harmful 
effects of secondhand tobacco smoke was found to be a deter-
rent to smoking initiation and a motivator for cessation for 
youth. 
35-37 Studies should explore messaging around the nega-
tive effects of secondhand marijuana smoke. 
As a qualitative study, our relatively small sample provides 
insight into how some young adults in Colorado integrate 
tobacco, marijuana and vaporiser use. While these experiences 
may not be representative, this work begins to shed light on 
how these products are used and made sense of alongside one 
another. Further in-depth qualitative work is needed to docu-
ment the complexities of perceptions of tobacco and mari-
juana in distinct legal contexts (including in other states and 
countries), and examine differences between perceptions of 
medical and retail marijuana in relationship to tobacco. More 
work is also needed to understand those who primarily vapor-
ise nicotine, those who vaporise marijuana and those who use 
both. 
The SCTC research initiative addresses high-priority gaps in 
tobacco control research through collaboration between aca-
demic researchers and local tobacco control agencies and com-
munity organisations. Legalisation of marijuana is one area that 
is highly salient for many state and community tobacco pro-
grammes because of its potential to affect use and perceptions 
of tobacco. Moreover, tobacco control experts within agencies 
are frequently tasked with recommending marijuana policies or 
educating citizens about rules of use and potential health 
effects. 
Tobacco, marijuana and vaporisers are most effectively 
studied together and future research should address perceptions 
of comparative harm of these products; social, political and 
health effects of their use; and adequate measurement of use 
patterns, especially when products are combined. Finally, 
tobacco programmes and policies should take into account 
emerging research on the complexities of this triangulum, par-
ticularly in the context of marijuana legalisation. </p>

<p>What this paper adds </p>

<p>▸ In collaboration with local health agencies, we conducted 
the first in-depth qualitative study exploring the triangulum 
of tobacco, marijuana and electronic vaporisers among 
young adults in Colorado, the first state with legal retail 
marijuana. 
▸ We found widespread ambiguity about whether 'to smoke' 
refers to the use of tobacco or marijuana products. Smoking 
marijuana blunts (the emptied shell of a tobacco cigarillo 
filled with marijuana) was common, but few interpreted this 
as tobacco use. Marijuana vaporisers were used to 
circumvent public consumption laws (such as when at work 
or while driving). Young adults considered secondhand 
tobacco smoke dangerous, but secondhand marijuana 
smoke was seen as benign and its use indoors was 
common. 
▸ Tobacco, marijuana and electronic vaporisers are frequently 
used together and should be studied together, rather than 
separately, in order to inform policy. </p>

<p>McDonald EA, et al. Tob Control 2016;25:i96-i102. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2016-053091 
i101 </p>

<p>Research paper </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors gratefully acknowledge the support of Tracey 
Richers Maruyama, Erica Berg, Ava Cannon and staff at Denver Public Health, 
Donna Viverette, Andrzej Stadnik and staff at Jefferson County Public Health. 
Additionally, the authors acknowledge the participants of this study as well as 
Rachel Barry and Dr Nicolas Sheon for help with data collection and analysis. </p>

<p>Contributors EAM, LP and PL designed the study and collected the data. EAM 
and LP conducted data analysis and wrote the initial draft. All authors contributed 
to the writing and revision and approved the final version of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding This work was supported by the National Cancer Institute of the National 
Institutes of Health (U01 CA154240 and K99CA187460). Additional funding was 
provided by the City University of New York (CUNY), John Jay College of Criminal 
Justice Funded Faculty Incentive Program. </p>

<p>Disclaimer The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not 
necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health or CUNY. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Committee on Human Research at the University of California, 
San Francisco. 
Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which 
permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, 
and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is 
properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p> 
McDonald EA, et al. Tob Control 2016;25:i96-i102. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2016-053091 </p>

<p>Research paper </p>

</text></tei>