<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5271394" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: The aim of this study was to assess the effectiveness of the Verion-LenSx guided 
arcuate incision technique to reduce refractive astigmatism in a pseudophakic population. 
Patients and methods: A prospective single-arm study was conducted in which one or both 
eyes of subjects required reduction of 1.0-2.0 D of refractive astigmatism after previous cataract 
surgery or refractive lens exchange. The surgeon used the refractive cylinder in the eye and the 
Woodcock astigmatism nomogram for preoperative planning, while the LenSx femtosecond 
laser with the Verion Image Guided System was used to create all arcuate incisions. The primary 
outcome measure was the uncorrected monocular distance visual acuity (UCVA). Secondary 
outcome measures included the change in corneal astigmatism, the change in refractive astigma-
tism, the best-corrected visual acuity and spectacle independence at distance from preoperative 
stage to 1 month and 2 months postoperatively. 
Results: Twenty-eight eyes of 18 subjects were treated. The best-corrected visual acuity at the 
2-month postoperative (PO) stage was not statistically significantly different from the preoperative 
visual acuity (0.02 logarithm of the minimum angle of resolution [logMAR] in both cases, P.0.05). 
Uncorrected visual acuity was statistically significantly better at the 2-month PO stage relative 
to the preoperative value (0.14 versus 0.34 logMAR, P,0.01). The mean change in refractive 
cylinder from the preoperative stage to the 2-month PO stage was 1.0 D. At the 2-month PO stage, 
two-thirds of the subjects (12/18) reported that they did not use glasses for distance vision and that 
their spectacle use for distance vision at 2 months was "lower" or "much lower" than the preopera-
tive stage; in 71% of eyes (20/28), the residual refractive cylinder was #0.50 D. Vector changes 
in keratometric astigmatism were weakly associated with changes in refractive cylinder. 
Conclusion: Arcuate incisions made with a femtosecond laser to treat moderate levels of 
residual refractive astigmatism after previous cataract surgery may reduce dependence on 
spectacles for distance vision. 
Significant corneal astigmatism at the time of cataract surgery is relatively common; 
in a large sample of older patients, corneal astigmatism was .1.0 D in one-third of 
all eyes. 
1 If postoperative (PO) refractive astigmatism is of approximately the same 
magnitude, uncorrected vision will be compromised. 
2,3 This can be problematic in 
patients who wish to reduce their dependence on spectacles, particularly for those 
implanted with multifocal lenses. 
4,5 Surgical options for reducing astigmatism after 
cataract extraction and lens implantation are limited to corneal refractive surgery 
(laser-assisted in situ keratomileusis, photorefractive keratectomy) or corneal relaxing 
incisions if an intraocular lens (IOL) exchange is not desired. </p>

<p>Correspondence: richard potvin 
Science in Vision, 6197 Dye road, 
akron, nY 14001, USa 
Tel +1 407 697 6008 
Fax +1 716 442 5110 
email rick@scienceinvision.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Ophthalmology 
23 January 2017 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>202 </p>

<p>Blehm and potvin </p>

<p>Corneal relaxing incisions are one of the most common 
methods of reducing low-to-moderate levels of astigmatism at 
the time of cataract surgery. Historically, these incisions were 
performed manually with a knife. Results have been mixed; 
in a large meta-analysis, the average residual astigmatism in 
225 eyes receiving relaxing incisions was as high as 1.32 D, and 
it was suggested that relaxing incisions may not significantly 
reduce spectacle dependence when compared to cases that do 
not receive astigmatism-correcting procedures. 
6 Two studies 
included in this meta-analysis show poor reduction of corneal 
astigmatism (mean change of only 0.18 D) 
7 and high spectacle 
dependence (45% in one study). 
8 The latter study reported that 
15% of eyes had uncorrected visual acuity worse than 20/40. 
The introduction of femtosecond laser-assisted cataract 
surgery has provided surgeons with the ability to make 
image-guided laser arcuate incisions to correct residual astig-
matism after cataract surgery. Studies show that compared to 
manual incisions, laser incisions likely allow for improved 
precision 
9 and may be less harmful to tissue, 
10 both of which 
may improve the predictability, safety and effectiveness of 
astigmatism correction. The mean difference between the 
intended and achieved laser incision sizes, documented to be 
within 0.1 mm, 
11 shows a precision that cannot be matched 
with manual techniques. Laser arcuate incisions have been 
demonstrated to significantly reduce corneal astigmatism. </p>

<p>12,13 </p>

<p>The incision may remain closed or may be opened if further 
astigmatism reduction is deemed necessary. 
12 Uncorrected 
visual acuity has been reported to improve from a mean 
uncorrected visual acuity of ∼20/63 preoperatively to ∼20/30 
at 5 months postoperatively. 
14 Laser arcuate incisions were 
demonstrated in one study to provide similar effectivity as 
toric lenses, 
14 in contrast to results with manual incisions, 
which have been consistently demonstrated to be less effec-
tive than toric IOLs. 
6 Femtosecond laser systems include 
image guidance, allowing for great precision with regard to 
the location, arc length and depth of the corneal incisions they 
make; this is a likely source of these improved outcomes. To 
further improve accuracy, separate imaging systems may be 
used to measure corneal astigmatism and allow for proper 
orientation of the eye in the upright position to incisions 
made by the laser in the supine position. 
As noted earlier, corneal arcuate incisions for the cor-
rection of astigmatism are generally performed at the time 
of cataract surgery. However, there is nothing to indicate 
that such incisions would be less effective at a later time. If 
created at the time of cataract surgery, incisions are gener-
ally based on anterior corneal astigmatism, which will not 
include the effects of surgical incisions, lens centration and </p>

<p>posterior corneal astigmatism. Correction of astigmatism 
after refractive stability has been achieved can be based 
on the patient's manifest refraction, which will inherently 
include the refractive effects of the factors cited earlier. As 
such, it is possible that corneal arcuate incisions performed 
after cataract surgery may actually provide better outcomes 
in the correction of astigmatism. 
The purpose of the current study was to assess the 
effectiveness of corneal arcuate incisions, planned using an 
image-guided system (Verion 
® Image Guided System; Alcon, 
Fort Worth, TX, USA) and created using a femtosecond laser 
system (LenSx </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>; Alcon), on patients who had previous cata-
ract surgery. The hypothesis was that the arcuate incisions 
would improve uncorrected distance visual acuity and reduce 
dependence on spectacles for distance vision. </p>

<p>Patients and methods </p>

<p>This was a prospective single-arm study of pseudophakic 
subjects $40 years of age presenting for astigmatism reduc-
tion in one or both eyes; target enrollment was 30 eyes, with 
one or both eyes of a subject eligible for enrollment. Sample 
size was based on reliably detecting a one-line change in 
uncorrected distance visual acuity, with a 30% correction 
factor to adjust for likely correlation between eyes in bilater-
ally enrolled subjects. Subjects must have been previously 
implanted with a monofocal IOL, have demonstrated PO 
refractive stability for at least 3 months, have good ocular 
health with no pathology that might compromise visual acuity 
(outside of residual refractive error) and have 1.0-2.0 D of 
refractive astigmatism with a spherical equivalent refraction 
between -0.50 D and +0.25 D. Exclusion criteria include 
irregular astigmatism and previous ocular surgery (besides 
cataract surgery). Institutional review board (IRB) approval 
for the study was requested and obtained (Salus IRB, Austin, 
TX, USA). The study was registered with clinicaltrials.gov 
(NCT02763124) and was conducted in compliance with the 
tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki and adhered to appli-
cable regulatory requirements. Written informed consent was 
obtained from all study subjects. 
The surgeon used the patient's refractive astigmatism data 
to plan the arcuate incisions. The December 2011 version of 
the Woodcock nomogram (Figure 1) was used to determine 
incision length and location. Incisions were created using the 
LenSx femtosecond laser system under a local anesthetic, 
aligning the incisions with the Verion Image Guided System 
(both Alcon). All eyes received paired incisions 180° apart on 
an 8 mm diameter circle using 90° side cuts to a depth of 90% 
of the cornea; pulse energy was 2 µJ with a spot separation of </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>203 </p>

<p>pseudophakic astigmatism reduction with laser-assisted arcuate incisions </p>

<p>3 µm. Immediately following the laser treatment, the arcuate 
incisions were opened at an operating microscope using the 
surgeon's standard technique. All study subjects were placed 
on an appropriate antibiotic and steroid drop four times a day 
(QID) for 1 week, followed by only the steroid drop on a 
tapered dose for the following 3 weeks. All adverse events/ 
serious adverse events (AEs/SAEs) were recorded at the 
operative visit and all PO visits. 
Subjects were examined at six visits: a preoperative visit, 
the surgical visit and follow-up visits at PO 1 day, 1 week, 
1 month and 2 months. Clinical evaluations included measure-
ment of visual acuity, manifest refraction, corneal astigmatism 
(with three different keratometers) and a standard slit lamp 
examination. All clinical evaluations were recorded at the 
preoperative visit and all PO visits, except for the 1-day and 
1-week visits, where only the uncorrected visual acuity was 
recorded. The three keratometers used were the IOLMaster 
500 (Carl Zeiss Meditec, Berlin, Germany), Verion (Alcon) 
and autokeratometry using a handheld autorefractor (model 
AR-20ST1; NIDEK Co Limited, Tokyo, Japan). Preopera-
tively and at the 1-month and 2-month PO visits, patients 
were asked about their spectacle use for distance vision; the 
questions and possible answers are shown in Figure 2. 
The primary outcome measure was the uncorrected mon-
ocular distance visual acuity (UCVA) of the eyes. Secondary 
outcome measures included changes in corneal astigmatism, 
refractive astigmatism, best-corrected visual acuity (BCVA) 
and spectacle independence at distance. All visual acuities 
were measured in Snellen notation and converted to the 
logarithm of the minimum angle of resolution (logMAR) 
for analysis. </p>

<p>The data were recorded and entered in an Excel spread-
sheet; this spreadsheet was imported into an MS Access 
database for data checking, collation and preliminary 
analysis (both Microsoft Corp, Redmond, WA, USA). Sta-
tistical analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Dell Statistica 
data analysis software system</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 13</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Dell, Inc, Round Rock, TX, USA</rs>). Statistical testing was performed using 
analysis of variance (ANOVA) on continuous variables and 
appropriate nonparametric tests on categorical data. Statis-
tical significance was set at P=0.05. Vector math was used 
where appropriate for astigmatism analysis. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Twenty-eight eyes of 18 subjects were treated. Demographic 
and preoperative data are shown in Table 1. There was a </p>

<p>Figure 1 Woodcock nomogram for arcuate incision planning. 
Notes: Only one arc should be used for 0.5 D astigmatism; other amounts use paired arcs. Center on visual axis; decentered arcs may overcorrect or cause irregular 
astigmatism; take caution when using nomogram in red zone; consider pairing lenSx with toric iOl using the Ora™ intraoperative aberrometer (alcon laboratories, inc., 
Fort Worth, TX, USa). if Ora is available, do not open arcs if astigmatism is not on expected axis, or if astigmatism measures ,1.0 D; open later in the office PRN. Mark 
cornea prior to lenSx application and compensate for cyclorotation. 
Abbreviations: iOl, intraocular lens; prn, as needed; D, diopters. </p>

<p>1. How often do you use corrective lenses (glasses) for distance 
vision? 
a. Not at all 
b. Some of the time 
c. Half of the time 
d. Most of the time 
e. All of the time 
2. How would you rate your need for corrective lenses for dis-
tance vision now, compared to before the procedure? 
a. Much lower 
b. Lower 
c. About the same 
d. Higher 
e. Much higher </p>

<p>Figure 2 Spectacle independence questionnaire. 
Notes: This questionnaire was completed by subjects preoperatively (Q1) and at 
1 month and 2 months postoperatively (Q1, Q2). </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>204 </p>

<p>Blehm and potvin </p>

<p>statistically significant difference in average keratometry 
by device (P=0.01), with the Verion device reading ∼0.25 D 
higher than the other two devices on average. There was no 
statistically significant difference in the magnitude of corneal 
astigmatism measured by the three devices (P=0.76). All pre-
operative corneal astigmatism measurements were ,2.4 D, 
with the exception of one anomalous autokeratometry reading 
of 6.5 D in one eye; the average measure for the other two 
devices in that eye was 2.2 D. 
Each patient was treated with a two-arc incision pattern 
of 8 mm diameter with 90% depth. Average arc subtense in 
degrees is shown in Table 1. All surgeries required between 
4 seconds and 8 seconds of laser time. There were no com-
plications at the time of surgery. 
Figure 3 shows the mean UCVA and BCVA over 
time. There was a statistically significant difference in 
BCVA over time (P=0.01), a result of a two-letter loss 
at 1 month. The BCVA at 2 months PO was not statisti-
cally significantly different than the preoperative value 
(Tukey's Honestly Significant Difference post hoc test; 
P.0.05). No eye had more than a two-letter loss of BCVA 
at 2 months. UCVA was statistically significantly better 
at both 1-month and 2-month PO stage relative to preop-
erative stage (P,0.01), with an average of two lines of 
improvement at 2 months. In 79% of eyes (22/28), UCVA 
increased by more than one line, while no eye lost UCVA 
at 2 months. 
The change in refraction is shown in Figure 4. There 
was no statistically significant difference in the spherical </p>

<p>equivalent refraction between the preoperative, 1-month and 
2-month visits (P=0.34). The manifest refractive cylinder was 
statistically significantly lower than the preoperative condi-
tion at both the 1-month and 2-month visits (P,0.01). The 
mean change in refractive cylinder from preoperative stage 
to the 2-month PO value was 1.0 D. In 71% of eyes (20/28), 
the residual refractive cylinder at 2 months was #0.50 D, 
while in 93% of eyes (26/28), it was #0.75 D. Only one 
eye (1.25 D) had a residual refractive cylinder .1.00 D at 
2 months; the preoperative refractive cylinder in that eye 
was 2.00 D. The magnitude of the mean refractive cylinder 
was 0.25 D lower at 2 months than at 1 month, which was 
statistically significant (P=0.02), but perhaps not clinically 
significant, given the challenges in test-retest reliability of 
refractions. In 79% of eyes (22/28), the refractive cylinder </p>

<p>Table 1 Subject preoperative demographics </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Mean 
SD 
Minimum 
Maximum </p>

<p>age, years 
68.8 
6.1 
59 
83 
Days after cataract 
surgery </p>

<p>1,044 
1,377 
1,01 
5,517 </p>

<p>Spherical equivalent 
refraction, D </p>

<p>-0.14 
0.26 
-0.50 
0.25 </p>

<p>refractive cylinder, D 
1.35 
0.30 
1.00 
2.00 
average K, D 
IOL Master 
44.27 
1.41 
41.62 
46.79 
Verion 
44.54 
1.54 
41.65 
47.42 
autoK 
44.29 
1.42 
41.31 
46.75 
Corneal 
astigmatism, D 
IOL Master 
1.42 
0.54 
0.35 
2.26 
Verion 
1.35 
0.57 
0.11 
2.25 
autoK 
1.46 
1.12 
0.25 
6.50 
arc subtense, degrees 
35.8 
6.1 
27.0 
47.0 </p>

<p>Note: Total number of subjects was 18 (12 females, 6 males), and total number of 
eyes was 28. 
Abbreviations: autoK, autokeratometry; iOl, intraocular lens; SD, standard deviation; 
K, keratometry; D, diopters. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Visual acuity over time. 
Note: Vertical bars denote 95% confidence intervals. 
Abbreviation: logMAR, logarithm of the minimum angle of resolution. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Spherical equivalent refraction and refractive cylinder over time. 
Note: Vertical bars denote 95% confidence intervals. 
Abbreviation: D, diopters. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>205 </p>

<p>pseudophakic astigmatism reduction with laser-assisted arcuate incisions </p>

<p>magnitude at 2 months was equal to or lower than the 
magnitude at 1 month, and in only one eye was it .0.50 D 
higher (0.75 D). 
Preoperatively, 72% of subjects (13/18) reported using 
their glasses for distance vision all of the time, while another 
17% (3/18) reported using them most of the time. At the 
2-month PO visit, two-thirds of the subjects (12/18) reported 
that they did not use glasses for distance vision. Only two 
subjects (11%) reported using their glasses for distance vision 
all of the time. Half of the subjects (9/18) reported that their 
spectacle use for distance vision at 2 months was "much 
lower" than their preoperative use, while two-thirds (12/18) 
reported it was "lower" or "much lower". Only one subject 
reported that spectacle use for distance vision at 2 months 
was "higher" than the preoperative use, but this result was 
ambiguous; the subject reported not using spectacles at all 
for distance vision at either the 1-month or 2-month visits, as 
well as reporting that use was "lower" than the preoperative 
use at the 1-month visit. 
The vector change in keratometry from the preoperative 
stage to the 2-month PO visit was calculated for each of the 
three measurement devices. There was no statistically sig-
nificant difference in the magnitude of the change in corneal 
astigmatism measured by device (P=0.95) or the orientation 
of the change (P=0.78). Given this result, it was sufficient 
to measure the refractive change relative to any one of the 
keratometric measures. The IOL Master keratometry was 
used for this purpose. 
To determine how the keratometry changes were related 
to the refractive changes, two vectors were calculated. 1) The 
vector representing the change in refractive cylinder from 
the preoperative to 2 months postoperatively. 2) The vector 
representing the change in IOL Master keratometry in the 
same time period. These vectors were divided into orthogo-
nal components, using double-angle vector math. The first 
component was along the steep refractive meridian which 
represents the intended effects of the corneal changes made 
using the arcuate incision. The second component was along 
the orthogonal meridian which represents the unintended 
effects of the corneal changes made using the arcuate inci-
sion -effectively an error. These data, and the percentage 
of the keratometry change relative to the refractive change 
in the meridian of the existing refractive cylinder, are shown 
in Table 2. Also shown is the refractive change relative to 
the steep refractive meridian. 
The mean percentage change in refraction relative to the 
change in keratometry was 100.8%, demonstrating how the 
arcuate corneal incision changed the refractive astigmatism </p>

<p>almost precisely as one would expect. This suggests that, in 
general, the keratometric change is predictive of the refrac-
tive change, so there was no apparent bias related to over-or 
undercorrection of corneal astigmatism versus refractive 
astigmatism. A single-sample t-test showed that the percentage 
change was not statistically significantly different from 100% 
(P=0.94). Using the same test, the orthogonal (error) term was 
not statistically significantly different from zero for either the 
change in refractive cylinder (P=0.28) or the change in ker-
atometric astigmatism (P=0.12). However, the change in the 
refractive astigmatism from the preoperative to the 2-month 
postop reading averaged 88%; this was statistically signifi-
cantly different from 100% (P=0.01). This indicates that the 
astigmatism was undercorrected by ∼10%, suggesting that the 
nomogram might benefit from a 10% increase in treatment. 
Figure 5 shows a plot of the magnitude of the vector 
change in IOL Master keratometric astigmatism, in terms of 
the orientation of the refractive change, versus the change in 
refractive cylinder at the same orientation, from the preop 
visit to the 2-month postop visit. As can be seen, the best fit 
is quite close to 1:1 (a slope of 0.95), but there is significant 
variability in the results between eyes. 
There was one non-SAE. One subject returned 4 days 
after surgery with a history of redness and pain. A course 
of fortified vancomycin and tobramycin every 2 hours was 
initiated; the patient was seen daily for two days and then 
referred to a corneal specialist for further evaluation and 
treatment. The patient was diagnosed with a corneal ulcer 
over one of the incisions. At the 2-month visit, all symptoms 
had resolved, with a small corneal scar remaining over one </p>

<p>Table 2 Vector analysis of refractive and keratometric changes </p>

<p>Properties 
Mean Minimum Maximum SD </p>

<p>Change in refractive cylinder, D 
Total 
1.21 
0.29 
2.00 
0.42 
along original refractive 
cylinder meridian </p>

<p>1.20 
0.28 
2.00 
0.42 </p>

<p>Orthogonal 
-0.04 -0.50 
0.26 
0.18 
Change in corneal (keratometric) astigmatism, D 
Total 
1.20 
0.13 
2.92 
0.74 
along original refractive 
cylinder meridian </p>

<p>1.16 
0.09 
2.92 
0.77 </p>

<p>Orthogonal 
-0.07 -0.55 
0.38 
0.22 
percentage of keratometric 
to refractive correction </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>100.8 5.0 
185.7 
51.6 </p>

<p>percentage of refractive 
correction to original 
refractive cylinder meridian </p>

<p>88.0 
28.0 
137.0 
23.8 </p>

<p>Note: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The percentage of keratometric to refractive correction = the change in 
corneal (keratometric) astigmatism along original refractive cylinder meridian/the 
change in refractive cylinder along original refractive cylinder meridian. 
Abbreviation: SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>206 </p>

<p>Blehm and potvin </p>

<p>incision. There was a one-letter loss of BCVA (20/20 or 0.0 
to 20/20-1 or 0.02), while uncorrected acuity improved by 
one line, from 20/40 (0.32) to 20/30 (0.22) at 2 months. The 
subject reported no need for spectacles for distance vision 
at 1 month and 2 months postoperatively. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The agreement between the three different keratometry mea-
surements seen here appears consistent with the literature; 
the small difference between the Verion and the IOLMaster 
noted here has been previously documented. 
15 Another study 
comparing Verion, IOLMaster and autokeratometry found 
more differences between all three measurement devices 
than noted in the current study, though this was primarily a 
function of the autokeratometer. 
16 Using the IOL Master or 
the Verion unit for measuring corneal astigmatism appears 
equally effective. 
The current study examined visual outcomes from laser 
arcuate incisions performed on patients who had previous 
cataract surgery. As the eyes were already pseudophakic, 
with stable refractions, the incisions were based on refractive 
cylinder rather than keratometric astigmatism. The primary 
outcome measure indicated that 80% of eyes gained a line 
or more of uncorrected visual acuity after the procedure, 
consistent with the observed reduction in refractive cylinder. 
UCVA improved on average by two lines at 2 months, which 
appears consistent with previous findings related to clinical 
outcomes with laser arcuate incisions. 
14 The mean UCVA 
of 0.14 logMAR at 2 months was similar to that observed in 
the same time period with toric IOLs. </p>

<p>8,17 </p>

<p>With 70% of eyes having #0.5 D of residual refrac-
tive cylinder after surgery, results appear as good as those 
reported in a meta-analysis of toric IOL outcomes, where a 
pooled average of 71% was calculated. 
18 However, the level </p>

<p>of astigmatism correction in the current study was more lim-
ited (1.0-2.0 D) than for some of the toric studies included 
in that meta-analysis. 
The mean change in both refractive and corneal astig-
matism reported in the current study was 1.2 D, somewhat 
higher than the results previously reported. 
13 This could 
be attributed to the fact that refractive cylinder rather than 
corneal astigmatism was used for incision planning. In addi-
tion, the mean change in refractive cylinder was equal to the 
mean corneal astigmatism change in this study. That is not 
usually the case when the incision planning is based only 
on reducing corneal astigmatism. 
19 Finally, the correlation 
coefficient in the current study (0.27) was higher than that 
observed in arcuate incision studies in the past (0.17 
12 and 
0.20 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>). Some of this difference may be due to the use of a 
laser-specific nomogram (the Woodcock nomogram), but 
it may also be due to the alignment of the corneal incision 
with the axis of the residual refractive cylinder in the current 
study. With regard to the nomogram used, results suggest that 
a slightly higher value be used to achieve a more "centered" 
distribution of results, as the mean refractive reduction in the 
current study was 88%. 
At the 2-month follow-up, two-thirds of subjects (12/18) 
reported being spectacle independent, with the same percent 
reporting a decrease in their use of corrective lenses. This 
appears consistent with the spectacle independence rates for 
distance vision with toric IOLs. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Figure 5 illustrates that while changes in mean refractive 
and keratometric cylinders are correlated, there is a fair bit of 
variability from eye to eye. Some of this variability is likely 
due to test-retest reliability in the measurement of corneal 
astigmatism and refractive cylinder. Some of this variability 
is also likely a function of changes in the posterior cornea, 
which may not be evident in the keratometry measures but 
which might affect the refraction. Posterior corneal astigma-
tism has been demonstrated to be a significant contributor 
to total corneal astigmatism. 
21 The effect of any incision is 
also dependent on patient-specific factors, particularly spe-
cific corneal properties that might affect wound healing. 
3 As 
such, while the nomogram was relatively good for balancing 
the mean correction, it would appear that some additional 
variables to help customize the nomogram to individual eyes 
would be helpful. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>There are limitations to the current study. The number 
of subjects was relatively low, sufficient to demonstrate a 
change in UCVA but insufficient to allow detailed post hoc 
analysis of the factors that might have influenced the effec-
tiveness of the incisions; as noted herein, such an analysis 
might lead to better "customization" of incisions. Another </p>

<p>Figure 5 Change in keratometric astigmatism relative to change in refractive 
cylinder from the preoperative visit to the 2-month postoperative visit. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/clinical-ophthalmology-journal </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology is an international, peer-reviewed journal 
covering all subspecialties within ophthalmology. Key topics include: 
Optometry; Visual science; Pharmacology and drug therapy in eye 
diseases; Basic Sciences; Primary and Secondary eye care; Patient 
Safety and Quality of Care Improvements. This journal is indexed on </p>

<p>PubMed Central and CAS, and is the official journal of The Society of 
Clinical Ophthalmology (SCO). The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>207 </p>

<p>pseudophakic astigmatism reduction with laser-assisted arcuate incisions </p>

<p>limitation was that at the time of study design, it was felt 
that the 1-month and 2-month follow-up times would be 
sufficient to demonstrate refractive stability. Results suggest 
that stability might still be an issue in some eyes. A larger 
study with longer follow-up (eg, 3 months and 6 months) 
would be helpful to address these limitations. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Laser arcuate incisions in patients who have had previous 
cataract surgery appear to be an effective means of reducing 
refractive astigmatism, improving uncorrected visual acuity 
and reducing dependence on spectacles for distance vision for 
a high percentage of patients. Basing the arcuate incisions on 
residual refractive cylinder rather than corneal astigmatism 
appears to have some benefit. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Sarah Makari, OD, of Science in Vision, assisted in the 
preparation of the manuscript. Dr Clayton Blehm received 
an investigator-initiated study grant from Alcon to conduct 
this research (IIT proposal number 17077577). He provided 
funding to Science in Vision (Dr Potvin) to assist with 
study management, data analysis and preparation of this 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>