<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5364865" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The retina of the human eye is extremely vulnerable 
to oxidative damage. Previous studies have demonstrated that 
oxidative stress is the predominant mechanism associated with 
the pathogenesis of age-related macular degeneration, diabetic 
retinopathy, glaucoma and retinitis pigmentosa. MTP-131, 
a novel mitochondria-targeted peptide, has been demon-
strated to specifically concentrate in the inner mitochondria 
membrane and to exhibit remarkable antioxidant effects both 
in vitro and in animal models. In the present study, the protec-
tive effect of MTP-131 was evaluated in response to hydrogen 
peroxide (H 2 O 2 )-induced oxidative damage in a retinal 
ganglion cell line, RGC-5. Cell viability was measured by 
lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) assay. Changes of mitochondrial 
membrane potential and generation of intracellular reactive 
oxygen species (ROS) were measured by flow cytometry and 
confocal microscopy, respectively. Annexin V-fluorescein 
isothiocyanate/propidium iodide staining was used for assess-
ment of apoptosis. Release of cytochrome c was analyzed by 
confocal microscopy. Pretreatment of cells with MTP-131 
inhibited H 2 O 2 -induced cytotoxicity and reduced LDH release 
in a dose-dependent manner, compared with cells treated with 
H 2 O 2 alone. Mitochondrial depolarization and ROS generation 
were also prevented by MTP-131 pretreatment. In addition, 
MTP-131 pretreatment inhibited cytochrome c release from 
mitochondria to cytoplasm, and significantly reduced apop-
tosis in RGC-5 cells, compared with cells treated with H 2 O 2 
alone. In conclusion, mitochondria-targeted peptide MTP-131 </p>

<p>exhibited a protective effect against oxidative stress-induced 
apoptosis in RGC-5 cells, which may provide a novel approach 
for the treatment of age-associated retinal diseases. </p>

<p>Previous studies have demonstrated the importance of mito-
chondria and oxidative stress in the development of neuronal 
diseases, such as Parkinson's disease (PD) and Alzheimer's 
disease (1,2). In human eyes, the retina is extremely vulnerable 
to oxidative damage. Oxidative stress has been demonstrated 
to be the predominant mechanism associated with the 
pathogenesis of age-related macular degeneration (AMD), 
diabetic retinopathy (DR), glaucoma and retinitis pigmentosa 
(RP) (3-6). Novel strategies targeting mitochondria and reac-
tive oxygen species (ROS) generation may provide promising 
prospects towards antioxidant therapy in these retinal diseases. 
A novel mitochondria-targeted peptide, MTP-131 (also 
known as SS-31 or Bendavia), originally designed by 
Hazel H. Szeto and Peter W. Schiller (7), is a water-soluble 
peptide with an alternating aromatic cationic motif 
(D-Arg-dimethylTyr-Lys-Phe-NH 2 ) and a 3+ net charge at 
physiological pH (8). The fraction of the peptide partitioned 
to mitochondria has been estimated to be 1,000 to 5,000-fold 
compared with the extra-mitochondrial concentration, and 
the peptide is predominately localized to the inner mito-
chondrial membrane (7). MTP-131 reduces ROS production 
in a dose-dependent manner and prevents oxidative damage 
in neuronal cell lines (9). In addition, treatment of mice with 
MTP-131 prevents loss of neurons and increases survival in 
PD and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis animal models (10). 
Since MTP-131 has a unique mitochondria-targeted 
delivery, and exhibits potent antioxidant and neuroprotective 
effect both in vitro and in vivo, the present study aimed to 
evaluate the protective effect of MTP-131 against hydrogen 
peroxide (H 2 O 2 )-induced oxidative damage in RGC-5 cells. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Reagents and chemicals. MTP-131 (D-Arg-(2'6'-dimethylTyr)-
Lys-Phe-NH 2 ) was kindly provided by Stealth BioTherapeutics, 
Inc. (Newton, MA, USA). Gibco Dulbecco's modified Eagle's 
medium (DMEM) and fetal bovine serum (FBS) were </p>

<p>Protective effect of mitochondria-targeted peptide MTP-131 
against oxidative stress-induced apoptosis in RGC-5 cells </p>

<p>MIN CHEN 
1 , BINGQIAN LIU 
2 , JIAN MA 
1 , JIAN GE 
2 and KAIJUN WANG </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 Eye Center, The 2nd Affiliated Hospital, Medical College of Zhejiang University, Zhejiang Provincial </p>

<p>Key Lab of Ophthalmology, Hangzhou, Zhejiang 310009; 
2 State Key Laboratory of Ophthalmology, </p>

<p>Zhongshan Ophthalmic Center, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong 510060, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received January 22, 2016; Accepted January 19, 2017 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/mmr.2017.6271 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Dr Kaijun Wang, Eye Center, The 2nd </p>

<p>Affiliated Hospital, Medical College of Zhejiang University, 
Zhejiang Provincial Key Lab of Ophthalmology, 88 Jiefang Road, 
Hangzhou, Zhejiang 310009, P.R. China 
E-mail: kaijwang@126.com </p>

<p>Dr Jian Ge, State Key Laboratory of Ophthalmology, Zhongshan 
Ophthalmic Center, Sun Yat-sen University, 54 South Xianlie Road, 
Guangzhou, Guangdong 510060, P.R. China 
E-mail: gejian@mail.sysu.edu.cn </p>

<p>Key words: retinal ganglion cell, mitochondria, oxidative stress, </p>

<p>apoptosis, eye, antioxidants </p>

<p>CHEN et al: ANTIOXIDANT EFFECT OF MITOCHONDRIAL TARGETED PEPTIDE MTP-131 IN RGC-5 CELLS </p>



<p>obtained from Thermo Fisher Scientific (Waltham, MA, 
USA). Lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) assay kit was obtained 
from Roche Diagnostics Gmbh (Mannheim, Germany). 
Tetramethylrhodamine methyl ester perchlorate (TMRM), 
2',7'-dichlorodihydrofluorescein diacetate (H 2 DCFDA) and 
MitoTracker Deep Red FM were obtained from Thermo Fisher 
Scientific, Inc. and prepared as 50 µM, 1 and 1 mM stock solu-
tions in dimethyl sulfoxide, respectively. Annexin V-fluorescein 
isothiocyanate (FITC)/propidium iodide (PI) apoptosis assay kit 
was from Multisciences Lianke Biotech Co., Ltd. (Hangzhou, 
China). Unless specified, all other reagents were obtained from 
Sigma-Aldrich; Merck KGaA (Darmstadt, Germany). </p>

<p>Cell culture. The RGC-5 cell line was kindly provided by Dr 
Zhiqun Tan (Department of Neurology, UC Irvine School 
of Medicine, Irvine, CA, USA). Undifferentiated RGC-5 
cells were used in the present study. Cells were cultured in 
DMEM containing 10% FBS, and 1% penicillin-streptomycin 
(100 U/ml penicillin and 100 µg/ml streptomycin) at 37˚C and 
5% CO 2 . Cells were passaged by trypsinization every 3 days. 
All cell culture dishes and plates were obtained from BD 
Biosciences (Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). </p>

<p>MTP-131 pretreatment and induction of oxidative stress. 
RGC-5 cells were seeded at a density of 1x10 
4 cells/well in 
6-well plates and incubated in 5% CO 2 at 37˚C for 24 h. Cells 
at approximately 70% confluence were pretreated with 0.01, 
0.1 or 1 µM MTP-131 in serum-free DMEM at 37˚C for 1 h 
and then rinsed twice with PBS. Then, RGC-5 cells were 
exposed to 500 µM H 2 O 2 in serum-free DMEM for 24 h to 
induce a sustained oxidative stress in vitro. Untreated cells and 
cells treated with H 2 O 2 alone were used as normal and H 2 O 2 
control, respectively. </p>

<p>Measurement of cell viability. Cell viability was assessed by 
LDH assay using the Cytotoxicity Detection kitPLUS (Roche 
Diagnostics Gmbh) according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions and as described previously (11). Briefly, RGC-5 cells 
were seeded in 96-well plates at a density of 5x10 
3 /well, and 
treated as described above. Culture supernatant (50 µl) from 
each well was transferred to a new 96-well plate and 100 µl 
reaction mixture solution was added to each well. Following 
incubation at room temperature in the dark for 30 min, 50 µl of 
stop solution was added to each well to terminate the reaction. 
Absorbance was measured using a microplate reader (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories, Inc., Hercules, CA, USA), at 490 nm test wave-
length and at 630 nm reference wavelength. Cell viability 
was estimated as follows: cytotoxicity (%) = (experimental 
value-low control) / (high control-low control) x100%. </p>

<p>Measurement of mitochondrial membrane potential changes 
(ΔΨm). TMRM, a cationic fluorescent probe which is taken 
up by mitochondria in a potential-dependent manner, was 
used to evaluate ΔΨm, as described previously (9). To quan-
tify ΔΨm by flow cytometry, RGC-5 cells (1x10 
4 cells/well 
in a 6-well plate) were pretreated with 0.01, 0.1 or 1 µM 
MTP-131 for 1 h and then incubated with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 
2 h. Cells were harvested and suspended in freshly prepared 
TMRM (200 nM) in phenol red and serum-free DMEM for 
30 min at 37˚C in the dark. All samples were rinsed twice </p>

<p>with PBS and analyzed immediately by flow cytometry using 
a FACSAria II (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA) 
and excitation/emission (ex/em) wavelengths 548/573 nm. A 
total of 1x10 
4 cells were routinely collected, and results were 
expressed in arbitrary units as the mean fluorescence intensity 
(MFI) from the average of at least three separate experiments. 
For confocal microscopy, RGC-5 cells were plated in Petri 
dishes. Following MTP-131 pretreatment and H 2 O 2 incuba-
tion, cells were rinsed twice and loaded with freshly prepared 
500 nM TMRM for 30 min at 37˚C in the dark. Following two 
rinses with PBS, cells were visualized by confocal microscopy 
using a LSM 510 microscope (Carl Zeiss AG, Oberkochen, 
Germany) and ex/m wavelengths 548/573 nm. </p>

<p>Measurement of intracellular ROS. Intracellular ROS in 
RGC-5 cells was measured with H 2 DCFDA, as described 
previously (12). This nonfluorescent probe accumulates within 
cells and transforms into 2',7'-dichlorodihydrofluorescein 
(H 2 DCF) by deacetylation, which then reacts with ROS to 
form the fluorescent dichlorofluorescein (DCF). To quantify 
ROS by flow cytometry, RGC-5 cells (1x10 
4 cells/well in a 
6-well plate) were pretreated with 0.01, 0.1 or 1 µM MTP-131 
for 1 h and then incubated with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h. Cells 
were harvested and suspended in freshly prepared H 2 DCFDA 
(5 µM) in phenol red and serum-free DMEM for 30 min at 
37˚C in the dark. All samples were rinsed twice with PBS and 
analyzed immediately by flow cytometry (ex/em: 488/530 nm). 
Ten thousand cells were routinely collected, and results were 
expressed as the MFI in arbitrary units from the average of at 
least three separate experiments. 
For visualization by confocal microscopy, cells were 
plated in Petri dishes. Following pretreatment with MTP-131 
and incubation with H 2 O 2 , 5 µM freshly prepared H 2 DCFDA 
was added into cells and incubated at 37˚C for 30 min in the 
dark. Following two rinses with PBS, cells were immediately 
imaged by confocal microscopy (ex/em: 495/525 nm). </p>

<p>Measurement of apoptosis. Apoptosis was measured using 
an Annexin V-FITC/PI apoptosis assay kit, according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, cells were pretreated with 
0.01, 0.1 or 1 µM MTP-131 for 1 h and then incubated with 
500 µM H 2 O 2 for 4, 8, 12 and 24 h. To quantify apoptosis by 
flow cytometry, cells were collected by trypsinization and 
centrifugation (100 x g for 5 min, at room temperature) at the 
appropriate time point. Following two rinses with PBS, cells 
were resuspended in 500 µl loading buffer and incubated 
with 5 µl Annexin V and 10 µl PI at room temperature for 
5 min in the dark. Flow cytometry analysis was immediately 
performed (ex/em: 488/530 nm), using a FITC signal detector 
(FL1 channel) and PI emission signal detector (FL2 channel) 
to analyze Annexin V-FITC binding and PI staining, respec-
tively. A total of 1x10 
4 cells were collected and divided into 
four groups: viable cells (Annexin V 
-/PI </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>, Q3), early apoptotic 
cells (Annexin V 
+ /PI 
-, Q4), late apoptotic cells (Annexin 
V 
+ /PI </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, Q2) or dead cells (Annexin V 
-/PI </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, Q1). The apoptotic 
rate was calculated as the sum of the percentages of early 
apoptotic cells (Q4) and late apoptotic cells (Q2). </p>

<p>Measurement of cytochrome c release. The release of cyto-
chrome c from mitochondria to the cytoplasm was measured </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 15: 2179-2185, 2017 </p>



<p>by confocal microscopy as previously described (13). Briefly, 
cells were seeded onto Fisherbrand cover glass (Thermo Fisher 
Scientific, Inc.) at a density of 2,000 cells/chamber. Following 
pretreatment with 1 µM MTP-131 for 1 h, cells were incubated 
in the presence or absence of 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 6 h at 37˚C in 
5% CO 2 . Freshly prepared MitoTracker (500 nm) was added to 
the cells and incubated for 30 min, just before the end of the 
6 h incubation period. Cells were rinsed twice with PBS and 
fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 15 min, followed by 5 min 
permeabilization with methanol on ice. Following blocking with 
5% bovine serum albumin (BSA, Jackson ImmunoResearch 
Europe Ltd. Suffolk, UK) for 30 min, cells were incubated 
with mouse monoclonal anti-cytochrome c antibody (sc-4280; 
1:100, diluted with 1% BSA; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., 
Dallas, TX, USA) at 4˚C overnight. Following three rinses 
with PBS, cells were incubated with DyLight 488-conjugated 
goat anti-mouse immunoglobulin G antibody (85-11-4011-85; 
1:500, diluted with 1% BSA; Multisciences Lianke Biotech 
Co., Ltd.) for 30 min at 37˚C in the dark. Finally, cells were 
stained with Hoechst 33342 (1:1,000, Thermo Fisher Scientific, 
Inc.) for 5 min, washed and mounted with anti-fade fluorescence 
mounting medium (Applygen Technologies, Inc., Beijing, China). 
Images were visualized by confocal microscopy. Translocation 
of cytochrome c from mitochondria to cytoplasm was analyzed 
by overlapping staining of cytochrome c and MitoTracker. In 
each group, six slides were selected and five fields of view from 
each were assessed. </p>

<p>Analysis of cell morphology. RGC-5 cells were seeded at 
a density of 1x10 
4 cells/well on a 6-well plate. Following 
pretreatment with 1 µM MTP-131 for 1 h and subsequent treat-
ment with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h, micrographs of all cultures 
were captured using a Zeiss LSM 510 Cell Observer system 
(Carl Zeiss, AG) to examine changes in cell morphology. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. All assays were performed in at least three 
independent experiments and data are presented as the mean + 
standard error of the mean. Statistical analysis was performed 
by one-way analysis of variance and Newman-Keuls multiple 
comparison test, using <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software Inc.</rs>., La Jolla, CA, USA). P&lt;0.05 was 
considered to indicate a statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>MTP-131 treatment reduces H 2 O 2 -induced LDH release in 
RGC-5 cells. LDH assay was performed to assess cell viability 
in RGC-5 cells following H 2 O 2 -induced sustained oxidative 
stress. Incubation with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h resulted in 
loss of cell viability compared with untreated cells, and the 
percentage of LDH release was 28.62±2.94% relative to the 
untreated cells (Fig. 1). Pretreatment with 1, 0.1 and 0.01 µM 
MTP-131 reduced LDH release in a dose-dependent manner 
compared to cells treated with H 2 O 2 alone, with LDH release 
measured at 6.05±0.44, 13.08±0.53 and 22.39±1.73% relative 
to the untreated cells, respectively (P&lt;0.01, P&lt;0.01 and P&lt;0.05, 
respectively, compared with H 2 O 2 alone; Fig. 1). </p>

<p>MTP-131 treatment prevents H 2 O 2 -induced mitochondrial 
depolarization. RGC-5 cells were pretreated with 1 µM </p>

<p>MTP-131 for 1 h, and then incubated with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 2 h. 
TMRM, a lipophilic cation which accumulates in mitochondria 
in a manner dependent on the membrane potential, was used 
to demonstrate ΔΨm in RGC-5 cells. As expected, untreated 
RGC-5 cells with healthy mitochondrial membrane potential 
exhibited high fluorescence intensity for TMRM (Fig. 2A, left 
panel), while incubation with 500 µM H 2 O 2 alone for 2 h led to 
mitochondrial depolarization, resulting in loss of the TMRM 
dye from the mitochondria and a decrease in fluorescence 
intensity (Fig. 2A, middle panel). Pretreatment of the cells 
with 1 µM MTP-131 for 1 h, however, inhibited H 2 O 2 -induced 
mitochondria depolarization, as evidenced by the higher 
fluorescence intensity of TMRM in the MTP-131-treated cells 
(Fig. 2A, right panel) compared with the cells treated with 
H 2 O 2 alone. Flow cytometry analysis confirmed that pretreat-
ment with MTP-131 significantly prevented H 2 O 2 -induced 
mitochondria depolarization in a dose-dependent manner, 
compared with cells treated with H 2 O 2 alone (Fig. 2B and C). </p>

<p>MTP-131 treatment inhibits H 2 O 2 -induced intracellular ROS 
production. RGC-5 cells were pretreated with 1 µM MTP-131 
for 1 h, then incubated with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h. Cells were 
then loaded with H 2 DCFDA for 30 min and DCF fluorescence 
was measured by flow cytometry and confocal microscopy. As 
demonstrated in Fig. 3A, incubation with H 2 O 2 increased ROS 
production, as evidenced by the elevated DCF fluorescence 
intensity in the H 2 O 2 -treated cells (middle panel) compared with 
the untreated cells (left panel). Pretreatment with MTP-131, 
however, inhibited H 2 O 2 -induced ROS production, as evidenced 
by the lower DCF fluorescence intensity in MTP-131-treated 
cells (right panel; Fig. 3A) compared with the H 2 O 2 -treated 
cells (middle panel; Fig. 3A). Flow cytometry analysis further 
confirmed that pretreatment with MTP-131 reduced ROS gener-
ation in RGC-5 cells in a dose-dependent manner compared 
with cells treated with H 2 O 2 alone (Fig. 3B and C). </p>

<p>MTP-131 treatment protects against H 2 O 2 -induced apoptosis. 
Apoptosis was measured by Annexin V-FITC/PI staining and </p>

<p>Figure 1. MTP-131 treatment reduces H 2 O 2 -induced LDH release in RGC-5 
cells. RGC-5 cells were pretreated with 1, 0.1 or 0.01 µM MTP-131 for 1 h, 
then incubated with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h. RGC-5 cells treated with H 2 O 2 
alone were used as the control. Viability was calculated as the LDH release % 
increase over untreated RGC-5 cells. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05, </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 and </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001, with 
comparisons indicated by lines. MTP, mitochondria-targeted peptide; LDH, 
lactate dehydrogenase; H 2 O 2 , hydrogen peroxide. </p>

<p>CHEN et al: ANTIOXIDANT EFFECT OF MITOCHONDRIAL TARGETED PEPTIDE MTP-131 IN RGC-5 CELLS </p>



<p>flow cytometry analysis. RGC-5 cells were pretreated with 
MTP-131 for 1 h and then incubated with 500 µM H 2 O 2 
for 4, 8, 12 and 24 h. Following incubation with H 2 O 2 , the 
survival rate of RGC-5 cells decreased in a time-dependent 
manner compared with untreated cells (Fig. 4 and Table I). 
Pretreatment with 1 and 0.1 µM MTP-131 inhibited 
H 2 O 2 -induced apoptosis at 4, 8, 12 and 24 h compared with 
cells treated with H 2 O 2 alone at the same time points (P&lt;0.001 
compared with H 2 O 2 alone; Fig. 4 and Table I). Pretreatment 
with 0.01 µM MTP-131 also alleviated apoptosis at 4 and 8 h 
following H 2 O 2 incubation, but no effect was observed at 12 
and 24 h compared with cells treated with H 2 O 2 alone (Fig. 4 
and Table I). </p>

<p>MTP-131 treatment inhibits H 2 O 2 -induced release of cyto-
chrome c from mitochondria to cytoplasm. The release of 
cytochrome c from mitochondria into the cytoplasm was 
examined by confocal microscopy. As demonstrated in 
Fig. 5, no release of cytochrome c (green fluorescence signal) 
from mitochondria (red fluorescence signal) was evident in 
untreated RGC-5 control cells (upper panels). Incubation 
with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 6 h, however, resulted in enhanced 
cytochrome c staining in the cytoplasm of RGC-5 cells 
(middle panels) compared with the untreated RGC-5 cells 
(Fig. 5), indicating that H 2 O 2 induced the release of cyto-
chrome c from mitochondria to cytoplasm. Pretreatment with 
1 µM MTP-131 for 1 h inhibited the H 2 O 2 -induced release of 
cytochrome c, as evidenced by the decreased cytochrome c 
(green) fluorescent staining in MTP-131-treated cells (lower 
panels) compared with cells treated with H 2 O 2 alone (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>MTP-131 treatment alleviates H 2 O 2 -induced morphological 
changes in RGC-5 cells. Morphological changes in RGC-5 
cells were analyzed by phase contrast microscopy. As demon-
strated in Fig. 6, normal untreated RGC-5 cells exhibit a 
neuron-like appearance, with thin axons extending from the 
cell bodies (left panel). However, following incubation with 
500 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h, most cells exhibited a degenerative 
appearance, evidenced by the presence of vacuolar cell bodies 
and shrinkage of the axons (middle panel, Fig. 6) compared 
with the untreated cells. Pretreatment with 1 µM MTP-131 
prevented the H 2 O 2 -induced morphological changes, with 
MTP-131-treated cells maintaining a relatively healthy appear-
ance, with flat cell bodies and regular axon extensions (right 
panel, Fig. 6). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, the antioxidant effect of MTP-131 against 
H 2 O 2 -induced sustained oxidative stress was examined in 
undifferentiated RGC-5 cells. The present findings demon-
strated that MTP-131 treatment prevented mitochondrial 
depolarization, decreased intracellular ROS production, and 
inhibited apoptosis induced by sustained oxidative stress in 
RGC-5 cells. 
H 2 O 2 is widely used to induce oxidative stress in 
experimental studies, leading to an increase in intracellular 
accumulation of ROS and RGC apoptosis (14-16). In the 
present study, H 2 O 2 (500 µM for 24 h) was used to induce 
a sustained oxidative stress, and was demonstrated to cause 
significant cell damage in RGC-5 cells, which is consistent </p>

<p>Table I. Summary of flow cytometry data measuring apoptosis. </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 (500 µM)+MTP-131 (µM) 
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Time point 
Quadrant 
RGC-5 
H 2 O 2 (500 µM) 
1 
0.1 
0.01 </p>

<p>4 h 
Q3 
94.50±0.10 
81.27±0.50 
93.27±0.59 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>94.33±0.45 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>92.40±0.09 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Q4 
0.90±0.06 
13.77±0.38 
0.83±0.03 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.93±0.06 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.77±0.09 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Q2 
3.93±0.30 
4.80±0.15 
4.56±0.50 
4.20±0.42 
5.07±0.13 
Q2+Q4 
4.83±0.24 
18.57±0.45 
5.40±0.47 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>5.13±0.48 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>5.83±0.22 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>8 h 
Q3 
93.80±0.74 
81.30±1.01 
95.07±0.58 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>90.93±1.17 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>91.37±0.75 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Q4 
0.53±0.03 
15.40±0.90 
0.57±0.09 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.67±0.12 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.47±0.09 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Q2 
4.60±0.70 
3.20±0.40 
3.93±0.57 
7.70±0.85 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>7.47±0.92 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Q2+Q4 
5.13±0.73 
18.60±1.01 
4.50±0.57 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>8.37±0.93 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>7.93±0.96 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>12 h 
Q3 
91.40±0.30 
75.20±1.99 
93.00±0.31 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>93.00±1.11 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>75.70±0.55 
Q4 
0.53±0.17 
17.03±0.22 
0.63±0.07 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.53±0.07 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>17.63±1.17 
Q2 
5.67±0.52 
7.67±1.88 
5.10±0.25 
5.50±0.92 
6.57±1.45 
Q2+Q4 
6.20±0.68 
24.70±1.99 
5.73±0.28 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.03±0.98 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>24.20±0.60 
24 h 
Q3 
93.30±1.20 
58.97±0.56 
93.77±0.46 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>91.87±0.96 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>60.10±3.38 
Q4 
0.90±0.02 
34.10±2.96 
1.20±0.17 
1.37±0.17 
34.73±2.19 
Q2 
4.87±1.11 
6.93±2.85 
4.43±0.52 
6.27±0.95 
5.13±1.53 
Q2+Q4 
5.76±1.23 
41.03±0.56 
5.63±0.54 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>7.63±0.90 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>39.87±3.38 </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean % of total cells ± standard error of mean. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 and 
b P&lt;0.01 compared with RGC-5 cells treated with H 2 O 2 
alone (by one-way analysis of variance). H 2 O 2 , hydrogen peroxide; MTP, mitochondria-targeted peptide; Q3, viable cells; Q4, early apoptotic 
cells; Q2, late apoptotic cells. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 15: 2179-2185, 2017 </p>



<p>Figure 2. MTP-131 treatment prevents H 2 O 2 -induced mitochondrial depolarization. RGC-5 cells were pretreated with MTP-131 for 1 h, then incubated with 
500 µM H 2 O 2 for 2 h. Cells were then loaded with TMRM and measured by confocal microscopy and flow cytometry. Untreated RGC-5 cells and cells 
treated with H 2 O 2 alone were used as controls. (A) Representative images from confocal microscopic analysis of (left panels) untreated RGC-5 cells, (middle 
panels) cells treated with H 2 O 2 alone and (right panels) cells treated with 1 µM MTP-131 and H 2 O 2 . Upper images: Original magnification, x400. Lower 
images are enlargements of segments of the upper images denoted by the white boxes. (B) Quantification of ΔΨm (% relative to the untreated RGC-5 cells) as 
measured by flow cytometry. Data represent mean values from three independent experiments. </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 vs. H 2 O 2 alone control. (C) Overlay of representative 
one-dimensional histograms from one flow cytometry experiment. MTP, mitochondria-targeted peptide; H 2 O 2, hydrogen peroxide; TMRM, tetramethylrhoda-
mine methyl ester perchlorate; ΔΨm, mitochondrial membrane potential change. </p>

<p>Figure 3. MTP-131 treatment inhibits H 2 O 2 -induced intracellular ROS production. RGC-5 cells were pretreated with MTP-131 for 1 h, and then incubated with 
500 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h. Cells were loaded with H 2 DCFDA and DCF fluorescence was measured by confocal microscopy and flow cytometry. Untreated RGC-5 
cells and cells treated with H 2 O 2 alone were used as controls. (A) Confocal microscopic analysis of (left panel) untreated RGC-5 cells, (middle panel) cells 
treated with H 2 O 2 alone and (right panels) cells treated with 1 µM MTP-131 and H 2 O 2 . Original magnification, x400. (B) Quantification of ROS (%) relative 
to the untreated RGC-5 cell control. MTP-131 pretreatment dose-dependently reduced H 2 O 2 -induced intracellular ROS production. </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 vs. H 2 O 2 alone 
control. (C) Overlay of representative one-dimensional histograms from one flow cytometry. MTP, mitochondria-targeted peptide; H 2 O 2 , hydrogen peroxide; 
ROS, reactive oxygen species; H 2 DCFDA, 2',7'-dichlorodihydrofluorescein diacetate; DCF, dichlorofluorescein. </p>

<p>CHEN et al: ANTIOXIDANT EFFECT OF MITOCHONDRIAL TARGETED PEPTIDE MTP-131 IN RGC-5 CELLS </p>



<p>with previous studies (14). MTP-131 pretreatment protected 
RGC-5 cells from mitochondrial membrane depolarization, 
reduced ROS production and inhibited cytochrome c release 
from mitochondria to cytoplasm. These effects were demon-
strated to alleviate apoptosis in RGC-5 cells, thus suggesting 
that MTP-131 exhibited a potential protective effect against 
oxidative stress in RGC-5 cells through direct inhibition of 
mitochondria-mediated pathways. 
RGC-5 cells have been widely used in in vitro experi-
mental studies (17-19). However, the validity of this cell line 
is now questioned. It has been demonstrated that the RGC-5 
cell line is of mouse origin, not rat as it was first described, 
and that it express photoreceptor markers instead of retinal 
ganglion markers (20,21). However, RGC-5 cells still have 
several properties in common with retinal progenitor cells and 
is therefore appropriate for neuronal cell studies (20). A series 
of retinal disorders have been related to oxidative damage, 
such as AMD, DR and RP (3,4,6). The retina is constantly 
exposed to visible light, which makes it extremely vulnerable 
to oxidative damage, due to its great energy demands and high 
oxygen consumption (5). A previous study have demonstrated 
that oxidative stress is extremely important in the retinal 
pigment epithelium (RPE) cells. ROS induces mitochondrial 
dysfunction in RPE, leading to RPE cell apoptosis and death 
of photoreceptor cells (22). 
Compared with traditional antioxidants, MTP-131 repre-
sents the only known class of cell-permeable compounds 
that specifically concentrates in the inner mitochondrial 
membrane (7). With a 3+ net charge, MTP-131 selectively 
binds to cardiolipin and modulates its interaction with cyto-
chrome c. By inhibiting the cytochrome c/cardiolipin complex 
peroxidase activity, MTP-131 optimizes mitochondrial elec-
tron transport and ATP synthesis (23,24). Numerous in vitro 
and animal studies have demonstrated the remarkable efficacy 
of MTP-131 in age-associated diseases. For example, daily 
treatment with MTP-131 reverses mitochondrial dysfunction 
and inhibits neuronal apoptosis and inflammation in mice with 
sepsis-associated encephalopathy (25). In addition, MTP-131 
exhibits protective effects against cardiac ischemia-reperfu-
sion injury (26). The effectiveness of cardiolipin combined </p>

<p>with MTP-131 is currently being evaluated in a multinational 
clinical trial for reperfusion injury in patients with acute </p>

<p>Figure 6. MTP-131 treatment alleviates H 2 O 2 -induced morphological changes 
in RGC-5 cells. RGC-5 cells were pretreated with 1 µM MTP-131 for 1 h and 
then incubated with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h. Untreated RGC-5 cells and cells 
treated with H 2 O 2 alone were used as controls. Representative images are 
depicted here from phase contrast light microscopy analysis (original magni-
fication, x20). H 2 O 2, hydrogen peroxide; MTP, mitochondria-targeted peptide. </p>

<p>Figure 4. MTP-131 treatment reduces H 2 O 2 -induced apoptosis in RGC-5 cells. RGC-5 cells were pretreated with 1, 0.1 and 0.01 µM MTP-131 for 1 h, and then 
incubated with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 4, 8, 12 and 24 h. Apoptosis was evaluated by flow cytometry analysis at the indicated time points. Untreated RGC-5 cells and 
cells treated with H 2 O 2 alone were used as controls. Data are presented as mean % of total cells from three independent experiments. A detailed description of 
all data resulted from the apoptosis experiments is listed in Table I. H 2 O 2 , hydrogen peroxide; MTP, mitochondria-targeted peptide. </p>

<p>Figure 5. MTP-131 treatment inhibits H 2 O 2 -induced cytochrome c release 
from mitochondria to cytoplasm. RGC-5 cells were pretreated with 1 µM 
MTP-131 for 1 h, and then incubated with 500 µM H 2 O 2 for 6 h. MitoTracker 
(red) was used to label mitochondria, Hoechst 33342 was used to label nuclei 
(blue) and immunostaining with a specific antibody was used to detect cyto-
chrome c (green). Representative images from confocal microscopic analysis 
are depicted here for untreated RGC-5 cells (upper panels), cells treated with 
H 2 O 2 alone (middle panels) and cells pretreated with MTP-131 (lower panels). 
H 2 O 2 , hydrogen peroxide; MTP, mitochondria-targeted peptide. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 15: 2179-2185, 2017 </p>



<p>coronary events (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT01572909), 
and a Phase 2 trial is underway assessing the effectiveness of 
MTP-131 on improving renal function following angioplasty 
for severe renal artery stenosis (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: 
NCT01755858) (27). Since MTP-131 has a unique mitochon-
dria-targeted delivery, and exhibits potent antioxidant and 
neuroprotective effects both in vitro and in vivo, the present 
study aimed to evaluate the protective effect of MTP-131 
against H 2 O 2 -induced oxidative damage in RGC-5 cells. 
The present findings demonstrated that MTP-131 inhibited 
H 2 O 2 -induced mitochondria depolarization, reduced intracel-
lular ROS and prevented apoptosis in RGC-5 cells. 
In conclusion, this novel class of targeted peptide 
therapeutics, including MTP-131, has the potential to restore 
mitochondrial bioenergetics. Further studies using animal 
models will be needed in order to fully explore this novel 
antioxidant approach for the treatment of age-related retinal 
diseases. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Stealth Peptides International 
Inc. for providing us with MTP-131 and a research grant. The 
present study was supported by the Zhejiang Provincial Natural 
Science Foundation of China (grant nos. LQ15H120001 and 
LY12H12008) and the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China (grant no. 81372930). </p>



</text></tei>