<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5295802" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Context: The biology of fatigue and depression in cancer patients is poorly understood. 
Hypotheses regarding cytokines and growth factors related to sickness behavior and disruption 
of circadian signaling have been proposed. 
Objectives: We prospectively examined proinflammatory cytokines (e.g., sickness behavior 
model) and epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) ligands (e.g., circadian disruption model) 
in the serum of cancer patients enrolled in a clinical trial testing levocarnitine for fatigue. 
Methods: Serum samples were collected at baseline and week 4. Cytokine/growth factor 
analyses were performed with a Luminex analyzer. The Brief Fatigue Index and the Center for 
Epidemiologic Studies Depression Index were used to measure fatigue and depression severity. 
The association between cytokine and symptoms was examined using logistic models. 
Results: Among 101 analyzable patients, all ten cytokines/growth factors examined were highly 
elevated at baseline and all significantly decreased at week 4 (p&lt;0.001) regardless of treatment 
intervention. At baseline, the odds of severe fatigue significantly increased for patients with 
higher level of interleukin-1 receptor antagonist (IL-1Ra), whereas patients with higher levels 
of IL-1Ra, tumor necrosis factor-α, interleukin (IL)-6, IL-8, interferon-γ, transforming growth 
factor α, and vascular endothelial growth factor had higher odds of severe depression. At week 
4, fatigue (p=0.023) and depression (p=0.007) responders had less decrease in IL-1 level than 
the corresponding non-responders. 
Conclusion: In this correlative analysis of a fatigue clinical trial, levels of fatigue were signifi-
cantly associated with levels of IL-1 and IL-1Ra. Circadian-signaling pathways related to EGFR 
signaling were correlated with depression as were other cytokines. A major placebo effect was 
associated with a global decrease in cytokine and growth factors. These data provide further basis 
for testing hypotheses regarding the mechanisms of fatigue and depression in cancer patients. 
Fatigue is the most commonly reported symptom in cancer patients. Clinical factors 
that may impact the development of fatigue, such as disease progression, depression, 
poor nutritional status, and treatment, are often considered. The underlying molecular </p>

<p>Correspondence: Tyvin Rich 
Hampton University Proton Therapy 
Institute, 40 Enterprise Parkway, 
Hampton, VA 23666, USA 
Tel +1 757 251 6819 
Email Tar4d@virginia.edu </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Cancer Management and Research 
31 January 2017 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Cancer Management and Research 2017:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Rich et al </p>

<p>mechanism of fatigue, however, is still poorly understood. 
Biological factors that have been examined in recent years 
include cytokine dysregulation, hypothalamic-pituitary-
adrenal axis dysfunction, 5 hydroxy tryptophan neurotrans-
mitter dysregulation, circadian rhythm disruption, alterations 
of muscle metabolism, vagal afferent activation, and genomic 
factors. 
1 Two "cytokine" hypotheses regarding the production 
of fatigue and related symptoms in cancer patients are the 
focus in this report. 
The first is based on the "sickness behavior model" </p>

<p>2   that is thought to be related mechanistically to elevation 
of serum and brain levels of proinflammatory cytokines of 
the interleukin (IL) family (e.g., IL-1, IL-1Ra, and IL-6). </p>

<p>3-9   Activation of this cytokine signaling in the peripheral and 
central nervous system by cancer or cancer treatment has 
been shown to lead to malaise, poor appetite, and social 
withdrawal, which are believed to underlie fatigue, cognitive 
disturbances, and depression. 
10,11 The second hypothesis is 
that symptoms could be due to the inhibition of circadian-
signaling pathways. This hypothesis is based on extensive 
laboratory data 
12 showing inhibition of downstream hypotha-
lamic signaling from the master clock in the suprachiasmic 
nucleus and corroborated by clinical observations. 
13 The 
inhibition of these hypothalamic signaling pathways can pro-
duce fatigue, suppress feeding activity, and cause malaise. 
Elevation of circulating levels of ligands of the epidermal 
growth factor receptor (EGFR), such as epidermal growth 
factor (EGF), transforming growth factor α (TGF-α), and 
neuregulin, 
14,15 can act to inhibit neural signaling that drives 
normal behaviors, in laboratory studies. 
The patients reported here were enrolled on a treatment 
intervention study conducted by The Eastern Cooperative 
Oncology Group (ECOG) E4Z02: a phase III, randomized, 
double-blinded, placebo-controlled study to determine the 
effectiveness of levocarnitine supplementation in the man-
agement of moderate-to-severe fatigue in cancer patients. 
The mechanism for this intervention and the preliminary 
laboratory and clinical data supporting this have been 
described previously. 
16 The final analysis of the primary 
endpoint showed no significant difference in fatigue 
between levocarnitine and placebo treatments. 
16 Shortly 
after the E4Z02 study opened, this correlative laboratory 
study of ten serum cytokines was initiated based on the 
hypotheses mentioned above. The specific objectives of 
the correlative study are: 1) to measure serum levels of 
proinflammatory cytokines and growth factors (hereafter 
referred to as cytokines), and 2) to correlate cytokines with 
fatigue and depression. </p>

<p>Patients and methods 
Patients and treatment </p>

<p>A subset of the E4Z02 patients was included in the current 
report (Figure 1). All patients were enrolled to E4Z02 through 
ECOG-affiliated institutions and were recruited when they 
checked in for their clinical appointment. Eligible patients 
were required to have a confirmed invasive malignant disorder 
(at any stage of any site and at any point in their cancer treat-
ment) and have moderate-to-severe fatigue (defined as a score 
of ≥2 on a Likert-type 0-4 rating scale from the Functional 
Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy (FACIT-F; http://www. 
facit.org/) question: "I feel fatigued") recorded as an outpa-
tient within 4 weeks prior to registration. More details about 
patient eligibility criteria could be found in Cruciani et al. 
17 The 
protocol was approved by the Eastern Cooperative Oncology 
Group (ECOG) national review board at each participating 
institution. After providing written informed consent, patients 
were randomized in a 1:1 ratio to receive 2000 mg/day (two 
1000 mg doses) of either levocarnitine or placebo (both in 
liquid form) for 4 weeks. For weeks 5-8 (extension phase), all 
patients received 2000 mg/day of open-label levocarnitine. </p>

<p>16   Assessment of symptoms </p>

<p>All symptom assessments were completed at baseline (prior 
to the initiation of levocarnitine or placebo) and week 4 
(after starting protocol therapy). Severity of fatigue was 
assessed using the Brief Fatigue Inventory (BFI). 
17 The 
total fatigue score (range: 0-10) was the average score for 
all nine items in BFI, with a higher score indicating worse 
fatigue. Severe fatigue, however, is defined as scores ≥7 for 
the "worst" fatigue level during past 24 hours item due to "its 
conceptual simplicity and close relation to function interfer-
ence". 
17 Severity of depression was assessed with Center 
for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D). </p>

<p>18,19   The total depression score (range: 0-60) was the sum of the 
scores for all 20 items, with a higher score indicating worse 
depression. A total score of ≥16 was considered a potentially 
significant level of depression, 
18,19 which was called severe 
depression in the study. 
Compared with baseline, a ≥50% improvement at 4 weeks 
of the BFI and CES-D total scores was considered a symptom 
response in the present analysis. 
20 As a sensitivity analysis, 
symptom response was also defined as ≥4-point decrease for 
BFI total score and ≥10-point decline for CES-D total score 
at week 4 assessment. In the sensitivity analysis, symptom 
response was only examined in patients with baseline score 
of no less than the above-specified cutoff points. The above </p>

<p>Cancer Management and Research 2017:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Association of cytokines with fatigue and depression </p>

<p>cutoff points were chosen because we believed those levels of 
improvement in fatigue and depression could be considered 
clinically meaningful. </p>

<p>Serum collection and cytokine ELISA 
analysis </p>

<p>After activation of the amendment incorporating this cyto-
kine correlative study into E4Z02 trial, serum samples were 
collected from consenting patients at baseline (prior to the 
initiation of protocol therapy) and week 4 (prior to first treat-
ment of the extension phase). The baseline blood draw was 
done between 6 and 10 am (8 am optimal) before receiving 
cancer therapy if applicable. The week 4 blood draw was 
collected at the same time of day as the baseline blood. After 
the blood was drawn, the blood was centrifuged at ~3,500× 
g at 4°C for 10 minutes to separate the serum. The serum 
was then drawn into a sterile syringe (or a transfer pipette) 
and then evenly dispensed (aliquot) into labeled cryotubes 
in 2-mL aliquots. The vials were capped securely and the 
serum was frozen at −70°C or colder at the local institutions 
and shipped to the central ECOG Pathology Coordinating </p>

<p>Office repository after collection of both baseline and week 
4 evaluation samples. 
After all the samples were collated upon completion of 
the clinical study, the ECOG Pathology Coordinating Office 
shipped these samples to investigators at the University of 
Virginia, where all cytokine analyses were conducted. The 
ten cytokines assayed were IL-1, IL-1β, IL-6, IL-8, IL-1Ra, 
interferon-γ (IFN-γ), tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), EGF, 
TGF-α, and vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF). 
Cytokines IL-1β, IL-6, and TNF-α were tested via the 
ELISA kits from DRG International, Inc (Springfield, NJ, 
USA). TGF-α and EGF were tested using ELISA kit QIA61 
from Oncogene Research Products (Cambridge, MA, USA), 
and VEGF was tested using ELISA kit DVE00 from R&amp;D 
Diagnostics (Minneapolis, MN, USA). 
The cytokine analysis was performed with a Luminex 
analyzer on first thawed samples using up to 500 µL for 
duplicate assays. Detection was achieved through a bead-
based antibody-antigen sandwich method. Briefly, samples 
were incubated with color-coded beads that were precoated 
with analyte-specific capture antibodies for the molecule of </p>

<p>Stratify </p>

<p>• Gender (male, female) 
• Performance status (0,1) 
• Chemotherapy (yes, no) </p>

<p>Levocarnitine (n=189) </p>

<p>• Before cytokine study activation (n=99) 
• Consented to cytokine study (n=90) </p>

<p>Placebo (n=187) </p>

<p>• Before cytokine study activation (n=105) 
• Consented to cytokine study (n=82) </p>

<p>Serum sample at baseline/week 4 (n=47) </p>

<p>Randomization </p>

<p>Serum sample at baseline/week 4 (n=54) </p>

<p>Total enrollment for E4Z02 (N=376) </p>

<p>• Before cytokine correlative study activation (N=204) 
• After cytokine correlative study activation and consented to cytokine study (N=172) </p>

<p>No blood draw, sample misplaced, 
sample damaged, sample not 
processed properly or lost (n=43) </p>

<p>No blood draw, sample misplaced, 
sample damaged, sample not 
processed properly or lost (n=28) </p>

<p>Figure 1 CONSORT diagram. </p>

<p>Cancer Management and Research 2017:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Rich et al </p>

<p>interest. Expression levels were determined following incuba-
tion with a biotinylated detection antibody and streptavidin-
conjugated phycoerythrin (PE). Using a Luminex 
® analyzer, 
independent lasers determined the color of each bead and the 
magnitude of the PE-derived signal, which was directly pro-
portional to the levels of bound analyte. Samples were given 
a missing value for cytokines if the levels of cytokines were 
below the detection level of the kits. Samples with missing 
values for cytokine levels were excluded from correspond-
ing analysis. Hence, the sample size might vary for different 
cytokines. The average of the duplicates was used for each 
cytokine in all analyses. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The target accrual for the correlative serum study was 
160 patients to give an 80% power to detect a 0.5 standard 
deviation (SD) difference in mean serum levels of any of 
the cytokines between patients with severe and non-severe 
symptoms, using Wilcoxon rank sum test with a 0.05 two-
sided type I error. Wilcoxon signed-rank test and rank sum 
test were used to examine the difference between groups for 
continuous variables. Fisher's exact test was used to test the 
association between categorical/binary variables. Multivari-
able linear and logistic models and generalized estimating 
equation (GEE) models were used for regression analysis. 
No adjustment was made for multiple comparisons in this 
exploratory analysis. All p values were two-sided and a p 
value of 0.05 was considered statistically significant. <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">11.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp</rs>., College Station, TX, USA) was used for 
all analyses. </p>

<p>Results 
Patient characteristics </p>

<p>A total of 376 patients were enrolled to E4Z02 between 
November 2005 and January 2007, and 172 of them were 
enrolled after the activation of the correlative study in Sep-
tember 2006. Serum samples were available for 101 patients 
at baseline and 4 weeks after initiation of protocol therapy; 
47 on levocarnitine, and 54 on placebo. Figure 1 displays 
the study CONSORT diagram. No significant difference in 
baseline patient characteristics was found except for dis-
proportionately lower overall metastatic disease rate among 
the 101 patients compared with the remaining 275 patients 
without cytokine assessment (data not shown). The baseline 
symptom levels were similar as well (Figure 2A, C). Of the 
101 patients with cytokine data, the patient characteristics 
were well balanced between the levocarnitine and placebo 
arms except for a lower proportion of males in the levocar-</p>

<p>nitine arm (Table 1). Hence, we analyzed the data regarding 
the symptoms correlated with cytokines on the collapsed 
population of 101 patients. </p>

<p>Fatigue and depression at baseline and 
week 4 assessments </p>

<p>Table 2 shows a significant decrease in fatigue and depres-
sion levels between baseline and week 4. Of the 101 patients, 
64.4% had severe fatigue at baseline and 54.0% reported 
severe fatigue at 4-week assessment. The mean percent 
change of BFI total score was −17.4%, and 16.2% (n=16) 
of patients had a ≥50% improvement in BFI total scores 
(fatigue responders). For depression, 44.6% and 36.0% of 
patients reported severe depression at baseline and week-4 
assessments, respectively. The mean percent change of the 
CES-D total scores was −5.4%, and 24.2% (n=24) of patients 
had a ≥50% improvement in CES-D total scores (i.e., they 
were depression responders). As illustrated in Figure 2B, D, 
symptoms improved significantly for all patients independent 
of treatment arm. </p>

<p>Cytokines at baseline and week 4 
assessments </p>

<p>The mean serum levels for all cytokines are displayed in 
Table 2. All cytokines were elevated at baseline compared 
with the normal levels from the literature. Multivariable 
linear regression analyses show that patients with current 
radiotherapy had a higher level of IL-1β (p=0.002), IFN-γ 
(p=0.026), and TGF-α (p=0.03) at baseline, after adjusting 
for other covariates. Patients with metastatic disease had a 
higher level of TNF-α (p=0.047) and IL-8 (p=0.044). Male 
patients had a higher level of IL-1β (p=0.028) and IL-1Ra 
(p=0.023; data not shown). Overall, the mean serum levels 
significantly decreased between baseline and week 4 for all 
cytokines (p&lt;0.001 for all cytokines, Table 2). The GEE 
analyses showed that the most significant cytokine decreases 
over time were on the placebo arm and in patients currently 
receiving irradiation (data not shown). </p>

<p>Association between cytokines and 
symptoms at baseline </p>

<p>There was no statistically significant difference in cytokine 
levels between symptom groups (severe vs. non-severe 
fatigue and severe vs. non-severe depression) at baseline 
based on the Wilcoxon rank sum test (p&gt;0.05 for all cyto-
kines, data not shown). However, patients with higher levels 
of IFN-γ (odds ratio [OR]=1.45, p=0.013), IL-1Ra (OR=1.62, </p>

<p>Cancer Management and Research 2017:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Association of cytokines with fatigue and depression </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Mean BFI scores </p>

<p>No cytokine data (N=275) 
Included in cytokine study (N=101) 
lb/ub </p>

<p>Baseline 
Week 4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Mean BFI scores 
Carnitine (C) 
Placebo (P) 
lb/ub </p>

<p>Baseline 
Week 4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Mean CES-D scores 
No cytokine data (N=275) 
Included in cytokine study (N=101) 
lb/ub </p>

<p>Baseline 
Week 4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Mean CES-D scores 
Carnitine (C) 
Placebo (P) 
lb/ub </p>

<p>Baseline 
Week 4 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>Figure 2 Mean fatigue and depression levels at baseline and week 4. 
Notes: (A) Mean BFI scores for patients included in or excluded from the cytokine study. (B) Mean BFI scores by treatment arm in patients included in the cytokine study. 
(C) Mean CES-D scores for patients included in or excluded from the cytokine study. (D) Mean CES-D scores by treatment arm in patients included in the cytokine study. 
lb, Lower bound of 95% confidence interval; ub, upper bound of 95% confidence interval. 
Abbreviations: BFI, Brief Fatigue Inventory; CES-D, Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale. </p>

<p>p=0.022), IL-6 (OR=1.45, p=0.015), IL-8 (OR=1.85, 
p=0.003), TNF-α (OR=1.79, p=0.004), TGF-α (OR=1.57, 
p=0.019), and VEGF (OR=1.75, p=0.027) had statistically 
significantly higher odds of having severe depression at 
baseline, after adjusting for available confounding variables 
in the multivariable logistic models (Table 3). Patients with 
a higher level of IL-1Ra also had increased odds of having 
severe fatigue at baseline (OR=1.57, p=0.033; Table 3). </p>

<p>Association between cytokine change and 
symptom response </p>

<p>Table 4 displays the association between cytokine change 
and symptom response. Between the week 4 and base-
line assessments, both fatigue (p=0.023) and depression 
(p=0.007) responders had significantly less decrease in IL-1 
level compared with the corresponding non-responders. 
Furthermore, depression responders had significantly less 
decrease in IFN-γ (p=0.005) and VEGF (p=0.045) levels as 
well. When symptom response was evaluated by absolute 
score change, IL-1 was still significantly associated with </p>

<p>symptom response for both fatigue and depression, and 
IFN-γ and VEGF were no longer statistically significant for 
depression (data not shown). </p>

<p>Sensitivity analysis for association 
between cytokines and symptoms </p>

<p>A sensitivity analysis was conducted where the lowest detec-
tion level was imputed for samples with levels of cytokines 
below that. The results about association between cytokines 
and symptoms were similar in the subjects where samples 
were given missing values in the same situation (data not 
shown). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This prospective study of a heterogeneous group of patients 
with invasive malignancy and moderate-to-severe fatigue 
shows that all cytokines are elevated at baseline compared 
with the normal levels reported in other studies. 
21,22 The very 
high levels found here may be related to factors known to 
elevate cytokine levels like stress, chronic illness, irradiation, </p>

<p>Cancer Management and Research 2017:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Rich et al </p>

<p>Table 1 Patient demographics and disease characteristics at baseline </p>

<p>Variable 
Total (n=101) 
Cartinine (n=47) 
Placebo (n=54) </p>

<p>n 
Percent 
n 
Percent 
n 
Percent </p>

<p>Age, years </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>-
65 (39-84) 
-
64 (42-83) 
-
67 (39-84) 
Male sex 
45 
44.6 
16 
34.0 
29 
53.7 
Race 
White 
98 
99.0 
46 
100.0 
52 
98.1 
Black 
1 
1.0 
0 
0 
1 
1.9 
Unknown 
2 
-
1 
-
1 
-
Ethnicity 
Non-Hispanic or Latino 
81 
98.8 
37 
100.0 
44 
97.8 
Hispanic or Latino 
1 
1.2 
0 
0 
1 
2.2 
Unknown 
19 
-
10 
-
9 
-
ECOG performance status 
0 
32 
31.7 
16 
34.0 
16 
29.6 
1 
57 
56.4 
27 
57.5 
30 
55.6 
2 
12 
11.9 
4 
8.5 
8 
14.8 
Years since initial diagnosis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>89 
0.8 (0.09-20.3) 
41 
0.7 (0.09-15.0) 
48 
0.8 (0.1-20.3) 
Metastatic disease 
48 
47.5 
25 
53.2 
23 
42.6 
Current cancer treatment 
No current cancer therapy 
18 
17.8 
4 
8.5 
11 
20.4 
Current radiotherapy only 
8 
7.9 
3 
6.4 
6 
11.1 
Current chemo only 
64 
63.4 
36 
76.6 
30 
55.6 
Both chemo and radiotherapy 
11 
10.9 
4 
8.5 
7 
13.0 
Taking other medication at baseline 
Psychostimulants 
5 
5.0 
2 
4.3 
3 
5.6 
Analgesics 
39 
39.0 
19 
40.4 
20 
37.0 
Antidepressants 
33 
32.7 
14 
29.8 
19 
35.2 
Site of disease 
Bone 
2 
2.4 
0 
0 
2 
3.7 
Breast 
26 
29.6 
16 
34.0 
10 
18.5 
Effusion/ascites 
3 
3.5 
1 
2.1 
2 
3.7 
Gastrointestinal 
17 
19.8 
7 
14.9 
10 
18.5 
Genitourinary 
12 
13.8 
5 
10.6 
7 
13.0 
Head and neck 
3 
3.5 
3 
6.4 
2 
3.7 
Liver 
18 
20.9 
1 
2.1 
2 
3.7 
Lung 
11 
12.6 
7 
14.9 
11 
20.4 
Nodes 
22 
25.6 
3 
6.4 
8 
14.8 
Other 
2 
2.4 
8 
17.0 
14 
25.9 
Hemoglobin, g/dL (mean, SD) 
12.4 
1.5 
12.2 
1.4 
12.5 
1.5 
Hematocrit, % (mean, SD) 
36.8 
4.2 
36.3 
4.0 
37.3 
4.4 
Iron, µg/dL (mean, SD) 
80.7 
47.8 
71.6 
44.3 
88.9 
49.9 
Thyroid-stimulating hormone, µU/mL (mean, SD) 
2.2 
1.9 
1.9 
1.3 
2.4 
2.3 </p>

<p>Note: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Data presented as median (range). 
Abbreviations: ECOG, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group, SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>and infection. Certain patient demographic and disease 
characteristics were found to be associated with higher levels 
of cytokines in our study, such as metastatic disease, current 
radiotherapy, and male sex. Performance status per se is not 
associated with cytokine levels in our study. 
Consistent with our study hypothesis, higher levels of 
cytokines appear to be associated with a greater symptom 
burden (Table 3). At the baseline assessment, a multivariable 
analysis shows that a high level of IL-1Ra is associated with 
severe fatigue. This observation is consistent with a study 
of fatigued breast cancer and prostate cancer survivors. 
23 A </p>

<p>meta-analysis of over 1000 cancer patients also found that 
the circulating levels of IL-1Ra and IL-6 are associated with 
fatigue. 
24 In our multivariable analysis for depression, seven 
(IL-1Ra, TNF-α, IL-6, IL-8, IFN-γ, TGF-α, and VEGF) of 
the ten cytokines are significantly associated with severe 
depression. This observation about IL-6 is consistent with 
previous studies. </p>

<p>6,25   Cancer-related fatigue is extensively studied because 
it is prevalent and associated with significant morbidity, 
functional impairment, and loss of quality of life. 
26 Several 
studies have been conducted to examine whether targeted </p>

<p>Cancer Management and Research 2017:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Association of cytokines with fatigue and depression </p>

<p>Table 2 Symptoms and cytokine levels at baseline and 4-week assessments </p>

<p>Symptoms (range) Baseline 
Week 4 
Change (baseline to week 4) </p>

<p>N 
Mean (SD) 
Median N 
Mean (SD) 
Median N 
Mean 
change </p>

<p>Median 
change </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean percent 
change </p>

<p>Fatigue (0-10) 
101 7.1 (2.2) 
8 
100 6.1 (2.6) 
7 
100 −1.0 
−1 
−17.4 
Depression (0-60) 
101 16.0 (9.3) 
15 
100 13.1 (8.5) 
12 
100 −3.1 
−2 
−5.4 </p>

<p>Cytokine (pg/mL) 
N 
Mean (SD) 
Median N 
Mean (SD) 
Median N 
Mean 
change </p>

<p>Median 
change </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>No. of patients 
with decrease in 
cytokine 
c (%) </p>

<p>EGF 
92 
522.0 (559.1) 
273.6 
97 
157.6 (163.7) 
95.6 
90 
−364.5 
−117.1 
75.6 </p>

<p>IFN-γ 
92 
239.4 (424.5) 
68.6 
98 
69.3 (117.6) 
14.2 
90 
−156.6 
−6.0 
72.2 
IL-1 
72 
883.4 (1429.2) 
294.1 
70 
549.3 (1511.4) 
80.4 
63 
−258.0 
−161.9 
87.3 </p>

<p>IL-1β 
77 
37.9 (82.6) 
7.5 
75 
26.3 (9.9) 
4.0 
64 
−13.4 
−3.3 
71.9 
IL-1Ra 
73 
947.3 (2865.6) 
205.2 
63 
701.6 (2892.8) 
72.0 
57 
−297.4 
−45.0 
36.6 
IL-6 
93 
406.1 (668.9) 
85.4 
97 
123.9 (224.3) 
24.6 
89 
−243.1 
−25.5 
77.5 
IL-8 
96 
253.0 (295.4) 
97.8 
100 58.3 (80.4) 
30.6 
95 
−194.1 
−37.3 
75.8 </p>

<p>TGF-α 
92 
160.1 (271.6) 
33.2 
100 44.7 (130.2) 
9.9 
92 
−112.1 
−10.0 
75.0 </p>

<p>TNF-α 
94 
105.4 (185.2) 
15.6 
100 25.0 (72.4) 
6.6 
93 
−87.0 
−3.6 
71.0 
VEGF 
95 
1778.4 (1755.0) 1319.6 
94 
1037.5 (1873.20) 579.0 
92 
−690.1 
−153.3 
70.6 </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Both fatigue and depression severity declined significantly at week 4, p&lt;0.01 using Wilcoxon signed-rank test. 
b All cytokines had statistically significant decrease 
from baseline to week 4, p&lt;0.01 using Wilcoxon signed-rank test. 
c Number of patients with decrease in cytokine was defined as 100×(number of patients with any amount of 
decrease in levels of cytokine divided by all patients with cytokine data at both visits). The percentage was lowest for IL-1Ra (p&lt;0.001 comparing IL-1Ra with other cytokines 
using Fisher's exact test). 
Abbreviations: EGF, epidermal growth factor; IFN-γ, interferon-γ; IL, interleukin; SD, standard deviation; TGF-α, transforming growth factor-α; TNF-α, tumor necrosis 
factor-α; VEGF, vascular endothelial growth factor. </p>

<p>Table 3 Multivariable logistic regression analysis for association between cytokine and symptoms at baseline </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Cytokine (natural 
logarithm transformed) 
as independent variable </p>

<p>No. of 
patients </p>

<p>Dependent variable = severe 
depression </p>

<p>Dependent variable = severe fatigue </p>

<p>Adjusted OR (95% CI) 
p-Value 
Adjusted OR (95% CI) 
p-Value </p>

<p>EGF 
79 
1.57 (0.93, 2.65) 
0.09 
1.17 (0.73, 1.85) 
0.51 
IFN-γ 
80 
1.45 (1.08, 1.94) 
0.013 
1.16 (0.90, 1.48) 
0.25 
IL-1 
63 
0.98 (0.60, 1.60) 
0.93 
0.71 (0.43, 1.17) 
0.18 
IL-1β 
68 
1.35 (0.92, 1.99) 
0.13 
0.88 (0.63, 1.24) 
0.47 
IL-1Ra 
63 
1.62 (1.07, 2.45) 
0.022 
1.57 (1.04, 2.36) 
0.033 
IL-6 
80 
1.45 (1.07, 1.96) 
0.015 
1.02 (0.79, 1.32) 
0.87 
IL-8 
83 
1.85 (1.23, 2.79) 
0.003 
0.98 (0.72, 1.32) 
0.88 
TGF-α 
79 
1.57 (1.08, 2.28) 
0.019 
1.09 (0.80, 1.50) 
0.58 </p>

<p>TNF-α 
81 
1.79 (1.21, 2.66) 
0.004 
1.02 (0.75, 1.40) 
0.90 
VEGF 
82 
1.75 (1.07, 2.86) 
0.027 
1.20 (0.79, 1.82) 
0.39 </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>A multivariable logistic regression model was fit for each symptom to estimate the adjusted OR for each cytokine. In these models, the same set of adjusting 
covariates was included for all cytokines. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; EGF, epidermal growth factor; IFN-γ, interferon-γ; IL, interleukin; OR, odds ratio; TGF-α, transforming growth factor-α; TNF-α, 
tumor necrosis factor-α; VEGF, vascular endothelial growth factor. </p>

<p>interventions based on molecular mechanisms could help 
alleviate fatigue. For example, a study of the prospective use 
of dexamethasone for fatigue in advanced cancer patients 
showed modest benefit at 2 weeks. 
27 Another recent trial using 
the anti-IL-6 antibody ALD 518 has shown some promising 
results and indicates that the IL-6 pathway disruption may be 
a promising avenue to pursue. 
28 The multidimensional causes 
of cancer fatigue production, in particular, the possible rela-
tionship with disruption of the biologic timing mechanism by </p>

<p>ligands of the EGFR family, is another potential therapeutic 
intervention. Supporting this notion are the results with the 
tyrosine kinase inhibitor, gefitinib, that showed early reversal 
of multiple symptoms that are hard to explain solely on the 
basis of tumor response. 
29 Furthermore, in a small pilot trial, 
we found that the use of the tyrosine kinase inhibitor did 
reverse objective measurements of the circadian system with 
normalization of wrist actigraphy measurements, indicating 
fatigue in a cohort of patients with metastatic non-small cell </p>

<p>Cancer Management and Research 2017:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Rich et al </p>

<p>Table 4 Association between percent change (%) of cytokine and symptom response </p>

<p>Cytokine 
Non-response 
Response 
p-Value 
(Wilcoxon rank 
sum) </p>

<p>N 
Median of % 
change </p>

<p>Mean of 
% change </p>

<p>N 
Median of % 
change </p>

<p>Mean of % 
change </p>

<p>Fatigue 
EGF 
73 
−59.2 
−26.7 
15 
−70.4 
−43.0 
0.85 </p>

<p>IFN-γ 
75 
−48.6 
−9.5 
13 
−40.0 
18.5 
0.39 
IL-1 
54 
−72.3 
−28.1 
8 
−9.8 
91.9 
0.023 </p>

<p>IL-1β 
53 
−54.8 
180.1 
11 
−29.3 
34.5 
0.64 
IL-1Ra 
44 
−43.7 
67.0 
12 
−35.0 
79.0 
0.68 
IL-6 
73 
−53.0 
−14.7 
14 
−67.2 
9.7 
0.54 
IL-8 
79 
−53.5 
36.1 
14 
−47.3 
5.4 
0.53 </p>

<p>TGF-α 
75 
−60.2 
−28.4 
15 
−60.5 
−20.2 
0.97 </p>

<p>TNF-α 
77 
−44.8 
−10.6 
14 
−29.4 
−23.3 
0.82 
VEGF 
75 
−30.7 
−0.2 
15 
−16.3 
−20.0 
0.68 
Depression 
EGF 
68 
−61.8 
−27.2 
20 
−58.1 
−41.0 
0.75 </p>

<p>IFN-γ 
70 
−59.4 
−24.1 
18 
22.9 
66.7 
0.005 
IL-1 
47 
−74.7 
−13.6 
15 
−17.9 
−10.7 
0.007 </p>

<p>IL-1β 
44 
−69.2 
212.5 
19 
−27.0 
28.8 
0.08 
IL-1Ra 
38 
−44.9 
68.4 
17 
−21.1 
76.0 
0.56 
IL-6 
65 
−59.1 
−14.9 
22 
−55.9 
−2.0 
0.67 
IL-8 
71 
−59.6 
40.4 
22 
−39.8 
0.2 
0.38 </p>

<p>TGF-α 
69 
−60.2 
−26.0 
21 
−62.3 
−34.5 
0.94 </p>

<p>TNF-α 
69 
−45.7 
−18.4 
22 
−35.2 
4.0 
0.55 
VEGF 
69 
−38.3 
−8.2 
21 
1.1 
9.5 
0.045 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: EGF, epidermal growth factor; IFN-γ, interferon-γ; IL, interleukin; TGF-α, transforming growth factor-α; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; VEGF, vascular 
endothelial growth factor. </p>

<p>lung cancer. 
30 Future studies with anti-EGFR agents should 
explore the potential for improvement of symptoms as well 
as antitumor activity in the quest for better understanding of 
the interventional potential of this class of agents. 
In the parent E4Z02 trial 
16 and in our correlative cytokine 
study reported here, and in a separately published random-
ized fatigue intervention trial, 
31 improvement in symptoms 
occurred independent of the therapeutic intervention and rep-
resents a placebo effect. We show here that fatigue improve-
ment is associated with a decline of the IL-1/IL-1Ra pathway 
in this population that experience the placebo effect (Table 2), 
thus contributing to the understanding of fatigue within the 
emerging knowledge of the importance of neural-chemical 
pathways in producing placebo effects per se. 
32 Although the 
precise neurochemical mechanism is unknown, the observed 
placebo effects can be important confounding factors in 
clinical symptom research. One approach to account for this 
would be to assess patient's expectations, a dimension that 
has been shown to influence treatment intervention in stud-
ies concerning pain and inflammation. 
33 Another way could 
examine the actual language used by health workers (e.g., 
certified research assistants and doctors) enrolling patients 
onto clinical trials that could provide an elevated sense of </p>

<p>anticipation that has been shown to influence outcomes 
positively or negatively (placebo or nocebo, respectively). </p>

<p>32   There are some important limitations for this correlative 
study. First, only one follow-up was made, at week 4. Multiple 
evaluations of the cytokine levels at specific times as well 
as follow-up extended beyond 1 month might be important, 
given the known circadian variation in these cytokine levels 
as well as changing trajectory of fatigue over time. Second, 
various additional variables were not collected (e.g., duration 
of fatigue before study entry, body mass index, menopausal 
status of female subjects, sleep problems, concomitant use of 
sleep aid, nutrition and oxygen status, the type and the tim-
ing of chemotherapeutic agents used, hormone therapy, and 
immunotherapy). Some of these additional variables might 
mediate the association between cytokines and fatigue. Third, 
some details about the blood draw (e.g., whether it is collected 
before taking the study drug intervention) are not explicitly 
specified in the protocol, which might have an impact on the 
study results. Fourth, we did not adjust these exploratory 
analyses for multiple comparisons. Finally, the analyses are 
underpowered due to the small sample size. Overall, these 
correlative study data should be considered as exploratory 
and hypothesis generating. </p>

<p>Cancer Management and Research 2017:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Association of cytokines with fatigue and depression </p>

<p>In summary, this correlative study of a placebo-controlled 
trial involving a drug intervention to treat fatigue indicates 
that there are elevations in proinflammatory cytokines 
(IL-1 and IL-1Ra) and ligands of the EGFR family that are 
correlated with fatigue and depression in cancer patients. 
Correlative studies are an important component of placebo-
controlled symptom interventions, providing biological 
insights and leads that enhance the value proposition of 
this research even when the investigational treatments lack 
efficacy. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors wish to acknowledge the work of Dr. Mehmet 
Koc and the laboratory facilities of Dr. Jeffery Lisiak at the 
University of Virginia for the cytokine assays. 
This study was conducted by the Eastern Cooperative 
Oncology Group and supported in part by Public Health 
Service Grants CA23318, CA66636, CA21115, CA49957, 
CA39229, and CA104362 from the National Cancer Institute, 
National Institutes of Health, and the Department of Health 
and Human Services. Its contents are solely the responsibility 
of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official 
views of the National Cancer Institute. 
These data were previously presented at the Annual Meet-
ing of the American Society of Clinical Oncology in 2011. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Cancer Management and Research 2017:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Cancer Management and Research </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: https://www.dovepress.com/cancer-management-and-research-journal </p>

<p>Cancer Management and Research is an international, peer-reviewed 
open access journal focusing on cancer research and the optimal use of 
preventative and integrated treatment interventions to achieve improved 
outcomes, enhanced survival and quality of life for the cancer patient. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes </p>

<p>a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>10 </p>



</text></tei>