<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5210339" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background--Although several risk factors for acute kidney injury (AKI) have been identified, early detection of AKI in acute 
decompensated heart failure patients remains a challenge. The aim of this study was to develop and validate a risk score for early 
prediction of AKI in acute decompensated heart failure patients. </p>

<p>Methods and Results--A total of 676 consecutive acute decompensated heart failure participants were prospectively enrolled 
from 6 regional central hospitals. Data from 507 participants were analyzed. Participants from 4 of the 6 hospitals (n=321) were 
used to develop a risk score and conduct internal validation. External validation of the developed risk score was conducted in 
participants from the other 2 hospitals (n=186). Sequential logistic regression was used to develop and validate the risk score. The 
c statistic and calibration plot were used to assess the discrimination and calibration of the proposed risk score. The overall 
occurrence of AKI was 33.1% (168/507). The risk score, ranging from 0 to 55, demonstrated good discriminative power with an 
optimism-corrected c statistic of 0.859. Similar results were obtained from external validation with c statistic of 0.847 (95% CI 
0.819-0.927). The risk score had good calibration with no apparent over-or under-prediction observed from calibration plots. </p>

<p>Conclusions--The novel risk score is a simple and accurate tool that can help clinicians assess the risk of AKI in acute 
decompensated heart failure patients, which in turn helps them plan and initiate the most appropriate disease management for 
patients in time. ( J Am Heart Assoc. 2016;5:e004035 ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>renal dysfunction, these studies have yielded varied perfor-
mance. This suggests that a single biomarker (or single type 
of biomarkers) is not sufficient for the evaluation of clinical 
settings such as CRS. 
15,17 Therefore, reformulating the </p>

<p>predictive approach of AKI, ie, a multimarker approach, is 
more likely to be of greater use. 
23 The major purpose of our </p>

<p>study is to incorporate both clinical risk factors and the novel 
kidney injury biomarkers for such prediction that we can 
predict CRS early and improve the risk reclassification in this 
disorder. Precisely, we will develop and validate a risk score 
that can identify patients with either a very high or a very low 
probability of developing AKI using only baseline character-
istics and effective urine biomarkers before a detectable 
change in serum creatinine in ADHF patients. </p>

<p>The primary outcome was the development of AKI. It was 
defined as an increase in serum creatinine by 26.5 lmol/L 
(0.3 mg/dL) within 48 hours of admission, or a 50% 
increase in serum creatinine from preadmission level (mean 
of at least 3 measurements over a 6-month period before 
admission) within 7 days of admission according to the </p>

<p>KDIGO Clinical Practice Guidelines for Acute Kidney Injury. </p>

<p>26   We did not use urine output criteria (ie, &lt;0.5 mL/kg per 
hour for &gt;6 hours) for AKI diagnosis because of lack of 
practicality in measurement when an indwelling urinary 
catheter was not present. </p>

<p>Sample Size and Missing Data </p>

<p>Sample size determination for observational study is difficult, 
especially in multiple regression model settings. We had used 
the rule of thumb recommended by Peduzzi et al 
27 and Harrell </p>

<p>et al, 
28 namely, events per variable (EPV) being 10 or greater </p>

<p>under this circumstance. We considered about 5 to 8 
significant clinical factors and 2 to 3 biomarkers in developing 
a model. This would have required us to recruit a minimum of 
110 (11910) participants who had events to predict the 
development of AKI. 
There were 2 cases with incomplete measurements. We 
performed simple imputation for these 2 cases. One case with 
missing serum albumin was imputed by mean, and the other 
with missing N-terminal pro-B-type natriuretic peptide (NT-
proBNP) by median because of skewness. All analyses were 
performed based on imputed complete cases. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>We took 2 steps to develop the risk model based on the 
development cohort. The first step was to select meaningful 
clinical risk factors (nonurine markers) by logistic regression 
with backward elimination. Clinical candidate predictors 
significant at P&lt;0.1 in univariate logistic regression models 
were considered for backward elimination. In this step, a 
clinical model with clinical factors was developed. Then, urine 
biomarkers (urine albumin-to-creatinine ratio [UACR], urinary 
NGAL [uNGAL], and uAGT) were evaluated sequentially based 
on this clinical model. Category-free (continuous) net reclas-
sification index (NRI), integrated discrimination improvement 
(IDI), 
29 and added value of c statistics were used to quantify </p>

<p>the additional contribution of these urine biomarkers to risk 
reclassification. 
To develop the risk score, the scoring method similar to 
that of Sullivan et al, 
30 was employed based on the developed </p>

<p>risk model. The predictive accuracy of the risk score was 
assessed by both discrimination measured by c statistic 
31 and </p>

<p>calibration evaluated by Hosmer-Lemeshow chi-squared 
statistic 
32 and calibration plot, a plot of observed proportions </p>

<p>versus predicted probabilities. Bootstrapping technique was 
used to adjust for overfitting and overoptimistic model 
performance. An optimism-corrected c statistic using 1000 
bootstrap samples created with replacement was reported. 
Furthermore, external validation of the risk score was 
conducted to assess the stability of the model. </p>



<p>Risk Prediction for AKI in ADHF Patients 
Zhou et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Predefined interactions (sex9preexisting chronic kidney 
disease [pre-CKD], pre-CKD9uNGAL, and pre-CKD9uAGT) 
between predictors and potential nonlinear association of 
included biomarkers were also examined at the 5% signifi-
cance level. Sensitivity analysis was conducted to assess the 
influence of the 2 incomplete measures by leaving the 
corresponding 2 cases out. All analyses were done with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc</rs>, Cary, NC, version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">9.4</rs>). A 2-sided P&lt;0.05 
was considered statistically significant. 
The reporting of the present study closely follows the 
Transparent Reporting of a multivariable prediction model for 
Individual Prognosis Or Diagnosis (TRIPOD) statement. </p>

<p>33   Additional study methods are described in Data S1. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The flow of participants is presented as Figure S1. Among the 
507 participants, 168 (33.1%) developed AKI during the first 
7 days of hospitalization, of whom 108 (64.3%) developed AKI 
during the first 48 hours of hospitalization. A total of 113 
(35.2%) participants developed AKI during hospitalization in 
the development cohort, and 55 (29.6%) in the validation 
cohort. Sixty-one (12.0%) patients died during hospitalization. 
Overall, the mean age of the participants was 65.2 years, and 
63.1% were male. For the clinical conditions, participants with 
hypertension, diabetes mellitus and pre-CKD accounted for 
49.9%, 25.4%, and 26.2%, respectively. Table 1 shows the 
characteristics of eligible participants for both the develop-
ment and validation cohort recorded on admission. The 
baseline characteristics of the validation cohort were gener-
ally similar to those of the development cohort, although the 
validation cohort was drawn from an independent group of 
participants. Two cases with incomplete measurements were 
imputed as described in the Sample Size and Missing Data 
section. Baseline characteristics outlining those who devel-
oped versus those who did not develop AKI were presented in 
Table S1. </p>

<p>Risk Score Development </p>

<p>The clinical model, including age, sex, pre-CKD, serum 
albumin (ALB), and NT-proBNP (Table 2), had a c statistic of 
0.767 (95% CI 0.714-0.820). The first urine biomarker added 
to the clinical model was uAGT, with a category-free NRI of 
0.809 (P&lt;0.001) and an IDI of 0.169 (P&lt;0.001). The second 
urine biomarker added to the clinical model with uAGT was 
uNGAL, with a category-free NRI of 0.293 (P=0.012) and an 
IDI of 0.023 (P=0.011). However, UACR did not improve 
model prediction significantly, nor did it make an additional 
contribution to risk reclassification (Table S2). Thus, the risk 
model was obtained by adding uAGT and uNGAL rather than </p>

<p>UACR to the clinical model. Neither nonlinearity nor interac-
tions were found significant. The risk model has excellent 
discriminative power with a c statistic of 0.874 (95% CI 0.835-
0.913), significantly larger than that of the clinical model 
(DeLong test, P&lt;0.001). 
Scores based on the risk model for all predictors are 
presented in Table 3. The estimated predicted probability of 
developing AKI during the first 7 days after admission for an 
individual ADHF patient according to the proposed risk score 
is expressed as </p>

<p>p(AKI) ¼ 
1 
1 þ e ÀðÀ4:027þ0:115ÃtotalriskscoreÞ </p>

<p>where À4.027 and 0.115 are the intercept and slope 
coefficients of the regression, respectively. The total risk 
score ranges from a minimum value of 0 (lowest risk) to a 
maximum value of 55 (highest risk), with corresponding 
estimated predicted probabilities of developing AKI ranging 
from 1.8% to 90.9% (Table S3). The optimism-corrected c 
statistic of the risk score in the development cohort, by the 
bootstrapping technique, was 0.859. 
To illustrate the application of the risk score, consider a 
60-year-old woman with ADHF, preexisting CKD, ALB of 40 g/ 
L, NT-proBNP of 3200 pg/mL, uNGAL of 65 lg/g Cr, and 
uAGT of 35 lg/g Cr. The total risk score she gets is 
0+2+9+0+0+6+13=30 from Table 3, and the estimated 
predicted probability that she will develop AKI is 36.0% 
according to Table S3. An easy-to-use online tool (http:// 
www.echobelt.org/risk/) as well as an Excel tool was 
developed whereby an individual's underlying risk of AKI can 
be estimated by entering the individual's own characteristics. </p>

<p>Validation of Risk Score </p>

<p>In an independent validation cohort, the c statistics of the 
developed risk score was 0.847 (95% CI 0.795-0.910). The 
receiver operating characteristics curves (ROCs) of the clinical 
model, the risk model, the risk score, and models with only 
uNGAL or uAGT are shown in Figure 1. The calibration plots 
for both cohorts show the close agreement between predicted 
and observed risk of AKI, with no apparent over-or under-
prediction (Figure 2). AKI rates from both development and 
validation cohorts are also concordant with each other. </p>

<p>Clinical Implications of the Risk Score </p>

<p>We divided the risk scores into 4 groups, that is, low risk (0-24 
points), moderate risk (25-34 points), high risk (35-44 points), 
and very high risk (45-55 points) (Figure 3), according to the 
quartiles of estimated risk, to enhance the clinical utility of the 
risk score. In the development and validation cohorts AKI was </p>

<p>Demographics </p>

<p>Mean (SD) age, y 
64.9 (15.5) 
65.7 (14.0) 
65.2 (15.0) </p>

<p>Male 
216 (67.3) 
104 (55.9) 
320 (63.1) </p>

<p>Preexisting clinical conditions </p>

<p>Hypertension 
169 (52.6) 
84 (45.2) 
253 (49.9) </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus 
86 (26.8) 
43 (23.1) 
129 (25.4) </p>

<p>Pre-CKD* 
90 (28.0) 
43 (23.1) 
133 (26.2) </p>

<p>Prior hospitalization for HF 
165 (51.4) 
96 (51.6) 
261 (51.5) </p>

<p>Primary causes of heart failure </p>

<p>Ischemic heart disease 
165 (51.4) 
106 (57.0) 
271 (53.5) </p>

<p>Hypertension 
44 (13.7) 
21 (11.3) 
65 (12.8) </p>

<p>Rheumatic heart disease 
46 (14.3) 
24 (12.9) 
70 (13.8) </p>

<p>Cardiomyopathy 
42 (13.1) 
20 (10.8) 
62 (12.2) </p>

<p>Other 
24 (7.5) 
15 (8.1) 
39 (7.7) </p>

<p>Characteristics on admission </p>

<p>LVEF &lt;45% 
155 (48.3) 
79 (42.5) 
234 (46.2) </p>

<p>NYHA, class IV 
151 (47.0) 
92 (49.5) 
243 (47.9) </p>

<p>Median (IQR) NT-proBNP, pg/mL 
5500 (2292-9000) 
4235 (2271-8540) 
5099 (2284-9000) </p>

<p>Mean (SD) SBP, mm Hg 
125.2 (24.1) 
130.6 (24.4) 
127.2 (24.3) </p>

<p>Mean (SD) DBP, mm Hg 
73.7 (14.7) 
78.1 (16.7) 
75.3 (15.6) </p>

<p>Mean (SD) serum creatinine, lmol/L 
Prognosis </p>

<p>AKI, n (%) 
113 (35.2) 
55 (29.6) 
168 (33.1) </p>

<p>Values are numbers (percentages) unless stated otherwise. AKI indicates acute kidney injury; pre-CKD, preexisting chronic kidney disease; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; HF, heart failure; 
IQR, interquartile range; LVEF, left ventricular ejection fraction; NYHA, New York Heart Association; SBP, systolic blood pressure; UACR, urine albumin-to-creatinine ratio; uAGT, urinary 
angiotensionogen; uNGAL, urinary neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalin. 
*Defined as preadmission eGFR &lt;60 mL/min per 1.73 m 
2 . Preadmission eGFR is the mean of at least 3 measurements over a 6-month period before admission. </p>



<p>Risk Prediction for AKI in ADHF Patients 
Zhou et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>present in, respectively, 9.3% and 9.5% participants of the 
low-risk group, 31.1% and 40.0% of the moderate-risk group, 
63.9% and 66.7% of the high-risk group, and 83.7% and 78.6% 
of the very high-risk group. As Figure 3 shows, the risk of 
developing AKI is highly and positively associated with the risk 
scores (Pearson contingency coefficient=0.517, P for trend 
&lt;0.001). We also performed subgroup analysis according to 
LVEF. The c statistics of the risk score for participants with 
LVEF &lt;45% and ≥45% are 0.849 (95% CI 0.786-0.912) and 
0.870 (95% CI 0.811-0.928), respectively. The discrimination 
power of 2 subgroups was similar, suggesting that the risk 
score was applicable for both subgroups of participants. 
The generated risk score was also correlated with the 
presence and stage of AKI. The score was significantly higher 
in those patients who developed AKI than those who did not. 
Higher risk score was observed in patients with higher stage 
of AKI (Spearman rank correlation coefficient, r=0.59, 
P&lt;0.001, Figure S2). In addition, the discriminatory ability of 
the score for predicting death was also good, with a c statistic 
of 0.815 (95% CI 0.762-0.867) (Figure S3). </p>

<p>Furthermore, we also developed a clinical score based on 
the clinical model with prognostic factors presented in 
Table 2. The clinical score had an acceptable c statistic of 
0.729 (95% CI 0.672-0.786). Validation of the clinical score 
was performed on the development data set with bootstrap 
internal validation and the validation data set as external 
validation, with c statistic of 0.730 (95% CI 0.673-0.786) and 
0.742 (95% CI 0.666-0.818), respectively. Risk score for each 
variable is given in Table S4. The ROCs and calibration plots, 
as well as risk categories, are presented in Figures S4 through 
S6. </p>

<p>Sensitivity Analysis </p>

<p>First, to assess the influence of the 2 incomplete measures, 
we derived a risk model on a complete data set by leaving the 
corresponding 2 cases out. The discrimination power (c 
statistic 0.873, 95% CI 0.834-0.912) was almost the same as 
that from imputed complete cases. Further, applying the risk 
score to all participants yielded a c statistic of 0.855 (95% CI </p>

<p>Table 2. Univariate and Multivariate Logistic Regression Analysis of Candidate Risk Factors for AKI (Development Cohort, n=321) </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Univariate Analysis 
Clinical Model 
Risk Model* </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
P Value 
OR (95% CI) 
P Value 
Coefficient 
OR (95% CI) 
P Value </p>

<p>Age 
1.03 (1.02-1.05) 
&lt;0.001 
1.03 (1.01-1.05) 
0.002 
0.0141 
1.01 (0.99-1.04) 
0.22 </p>

<p>Serum albumin 
0.92 (0.88-0.96) 
0.001 
0.94 (0.90-0.98) 
0.007 
À0.0117 
0.99 (0.93-1.05) 
0.69 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin 
0.99 (0.98-0.99) 
0.003 </p>

<p>Use ACEI/ARB preadmission 
1.16 (0.71-1.91) 
0.55 </p>

<p>Use diuretic preadmission 
1.22 (0.75-1.99) 
0.42 </p>

<p>ln-UACR </p>

<p> † </p>



<p>Risk Prediction for AKI in ADHF Patients 
Zhou et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>0.820-0.890), which was similar to that from the development 
cohort, suggesting high stability of the risk score. We also 
conducted sensitivity analysis to assess the single biomarker 
discriminative power by adding a single biomarker to the 
clinical model. The results are presented in Table S5. Briefly, 
the final risk model had the lowest AIC and highest c statistic 
in the development data set. Furthermore, because of the 
correlation between pre-CKD and eGFR, eGFR was not 
selected during the backward selection. Thus, we kept the 
final risk model with pre-CKD. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Main Finding </p>

<p>We have developed and validated a clinical scoring system to 
identify patients at a very high as well as a very low risk of </p>

<p>Table 3. Risk Score for Single Risk Factors Associated With 
Developing AKI in ADHF Patients (Development Cohort)* </p>

<p>Risk Factor 
Score 
c-Statistic for Single Variable </p>

<p>Age, y 
0.638 (0.574-0.701) </p>

<p>≤55 
0 </p>

<p>56 to 65 
2 </p>

<p>66 to 75 
3 </p>

<p>76 and older 
5 </p>

<p>Sex 
0.514 (0.460-0.568) </p>

<p>Male 
1 </p>

<p>Female 
0 </p>

<p>Pre-CKD 
0.680 (0.627-0.732) </p>

<p>Yes 
9 </p>

<p>No 
0 </p>

<p>Serum albumin, mmol/L 
0.640 (0.576-0.704) </p>

<p>≤35 
1 </p>

<p>&gt;35 
0 </p>

<p>NT-proBNP, pg/mL </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.635 (0.572-0.698) </p>

<p>&lt;5578 
0 </p>

<p>≥5578 
5 </p>

<p>uNGAL, lg/g Cr </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.762 (0.707-0.816) </p>

<p>&lt;25 
0 </p>

<p>25 to 49.99 
5 </p>

<p>50 to 99.99 
6 </p>

<p>≥100 
11 </p>

<p>uAGT, lg/g Cr </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.814 (0.767-0.861) </p>

<p>&lt;25 
0 </p>

<p>25 to 49.99 
13 </p>

<p>50 to 99.99 
16 </p>

<p>≥100 
23 </p>

<p>ADHF indicates acute decompensated heart failure; AKI, acute kidney injury; Pre-CKD, 
preexisting chronic kidney disease; UACR, urine albumin-to-creatinine ratio; uAGT, 
urinary angiotensionogen; uNGAL, urinary neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalin. 
*The highest observed total risk score of 55 coincides with the highest theoretical risk 
score. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Categories and scores of those variables are present according to their untransformed 
value for clinical use. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Receiver operator characteristic curves showing area </p>

<p>under the curve for AKI in ADHF patients. Receiver operator 
characteristic curves showing area under the curve for clinical 
model alone, 0.765; uNGAL, 0.762; uAGT, 0.814; risk model, 
0.874; risk score in development cohort, 0.859; risk score in 
validation cohort, 0.847. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Calibration plot of observed vs predicted fracture risk </p>

<p>for developing AKI during the first 7 days of hospitalization. 
Hosmer-Lemeshow chi-squared statistic is shown for the risk 
score in both development and validation cohorts. The points and 
circles indicate the observed frequencies by decile of predicted 
probability. </p>



<p>Risk Prediction for AKI in ADHF Patients 
Zhou et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>developing AKI before a detectable change in serum crea-
tinine in ADHF patients. The risk score was derived from a risk 
model including 5 clinical factors and 2 urine biomarkers. The 
clinical risk factors in the model were similar to those in 
previous reports. 
34,35 Two selected biomarkers, uAGT and </p>

<p>uNGAL, were highly predictive. The proposed risk score shows 
high discriminant power (optimism-corrected c statistic of 
0.859) and is strongly supported by external validation (c 
statistics of 0.847). To our knowledge, this is the first clinical 
scoring system derived and validated for early prediction of 
AKI in ADHF patients incorporating clinical risk factors and 
novel kidney injury biomarkers. </p>

<p>Need for Early Predicting AKI in ADHF </p>

<p>Coexistence of ADHF and AKI, namely acute CRS, is a 
serious clinical condition associated with significantly 
increased morbidity and mortality in patients with heart 
failure. 
10,36 A major barrier to improving clinical outcomes in </p>

<p>ADHF patients is the lack of ability to identify patients at 
high-risk of CRS early enough to initiate interventions. 
37 The </p>

<p>clinical benefits of an early diagnosis of AKI have not been 
fully realized due to the restriction of using serum creatinine 
for diagnosis. This restriction often leads to diagnostic 
delays and potential misclassification of actual injury status 
and provides little information regarding underlying cause. 
Actually, all successful therapeutic approaches in animal 
models used in patients have yielded disappointing results. </p>

<p>38   Major reasons are the scarcity of early biomarkers for AKI 
and consequent unacceptable delay in initiating treatment 
regimens. </p>

<p>15   AKI is a major contributor to poor patient outcomes. The 
International Society of Nephrology (ISN)'s 0by25 (zero 
preventable deaths by 2025) initiative aims to eliminate 
preventable deaths from AKI by 2025 by calling for global 
strategies that permit timely diagnosis and treatment of 
potentially reversible AKI. 
39 As Mehta et al addressed in the </p>

<p>Future Perspective Section, "the effect of AKI on morbidity 
and mortality will be shaped by advances in methods to 
detect AKI earlier in the disease course." 
39 Because early </p>

<p>detection of AKI is helpful in identifying early kidney injury and 
preventing the progression of the kidney damage, our work 
may provide the first step forward to avoid harm to the kidney 
and devise early preventive strategies in CRS. </p>

<p>Clinical and Policy Implications </p>

<p>The present study derived and validated a potential clinical 
prediction tool rather than a decision rule. It is to aid the 
attending physician who will make the clinical decision. The 
factors incorporated in the proposed risk score are readily 
available data recorded on admission or from routine medical 
examination. Both uAGT and uNGAL are accepted and utilized 
biomarkers of kidney injury. To date, clinical studies that use 
the biomarkers to predict acute CRS yield only modest 
performance in general. 
40,41 Individual prediction of AKI </p>

<p>remains a challenge in the setting of ADHF. Therefore, 
stratification of risk level according to the score incorporating 
both clinical factors and biomarkers is clinically relevant, 
particularly in critically ill patients with multiorgan dysfunc-
tions. </p>

<p>Comparison With NGAL and Other Risk Score </p>

<p>NGAL is a novel biomarker widely utilized to identify AKI 
patients and detect patients with likely subclinical AKI who 
have an increased risk of adverse outcomes. 
42 A systematic </p>

<p>review and meta-analysis 
43 demonstrated that the overall c </p>

<p>statistic of NGAL to predict AKI is 0.815. This meta-analysis 
synthesized data from different settings and varied study 
populations, such as contrast-induced nephropathy, cardiac 
surgery-associated acute kidney injury. The c statistics of 
NGAL reported from individual study were less than 0.74, 
except for 1 study with the c statistic of 0.93, 
13 the study </p>

<p>population of which was a subgroup of children with an 
extremely high cutoff point (170 ng/L) and relative small 
sample size of 119. In contrast, our study has included 507 
ADHF adult patients, and the c statistic of NGAL alone as a 
predictor is only 0.761, much less than that of our risk model 
(c statistic of 0.874) and risk score (c statistic of 0.859). 
Thakar et al 
44 reported a risk score using clinical param-</p>

<p>eters from patients receiving open-heart surgery and yielded 
an excellent c statistic of 0.81 (95% CI 0.78-0.83). Our score </p>

<p>Figure 3. Risk levels according to the risk score in development </p>

<p>and validation cohorts. Risks were categorized into low risk (0-24 
points), moderate risk (25-34 points), high risk (35-44 points), and 
very high risk (45-55 points). Higher points means higher risk of 
developing AKI in patients with ADHF; P for trend &lt;0.001. </p>



<p>Risk Prediction for AKI in ADHF Patients 
Zhou et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>was developed in a cohort of ADHF patients whose clinical 
characteristics and risk exposure were different from those of 
the patients with heart surgery. The c statistic of the proposed 
score for predicting acute CRS reached 0.859, demonstrating 
excellent performance of our risk score in ADHF patients. 
Sensitivity analysis showed that the 2 incomplete mea-
sures had little influence on the risk model. Furthermore, we 
have kept age, sex, NT-proBNP, and serum albumin in the final 
risk model, although they were not statistically significant. 
Age and sex were given factors for controlling potential 
patients' heterogeneity. NT-proBNP and serum albumin were 
also found significantly associated with the development of 
AKI in univariate analysis and by other researchers. 
45,46 We </p>

<p>also developed a clinical score that reached acceptable 
performance. Clinicians could choose the one that fits their 
clinical practice best. </p>

<p>Strengths and Limitations of This Study </p>

<p>Our study has several strengths. First, our risk score was 
derived for early detection of patients at high risk of 
developing AKI incorporating, for the first time, both baseline 
characteristics and novel biomarkers recorded on the first day 
of admission before a clinically significant change in serum 
creatinine. Second, the risk score possesses high discrimina-
tive power as well as high stability and reproducibility, as 
shown by concordance between internal and external valida-
tion. Third, to develop a prediction tool for early detection of 
patients who would develop AKI during hospitalization, 
researchers should exclude those who already have AKI on 
admission. In our study we excluded those having AKI on 
admission based on preadmission measurements of serum 
creatinine, but we did not use this information in developing 
the risk score; thus, the use of the developed predicting tool is 
not limited by the need for preadmission serum creatinine. 
Last, our article closely follows the TRIPOD statement. 
The study also has limitations. First, AKI diagnosed by an 
increase in serum creatinine may introduce the dilemma of 
using a surrogate outcome to assess the performance of 
novel models. 
47 Evidence of AKI on renal biopsy would be the </p>

<p>gold standard but was not feasible in our large cohort. As is 
the case in most AKI studies, we did not use urine output 
criteria (ie, &lt;0.5 mL/kg per hour for &gt;6 hours) for AKI 
diagnosis because urine output as the diagnostic criterion for 
AKI has been questioned recently for its limited sensitivity 
when diuretics are administered, reduced specificity in the 
presence of dehydration, and lack of practicality when an 
indwelling urinary catheter is not present (as in our setting). </p>

<p>15   Second, our findings remain to be confirmed by other 
independent studies. The question of whether the model 
predicts AKI in the special setting of ADHF versus AKI from 
other causes remains to be addressed. Third, although the </p>

<p>study participants were recruited from 6 hospitals located in 5 
cities in China, generalizability of the risk score to other 
populations still needs to be validated. In addition, the 
bootstrap procedure to estimate the overoptimism was 
conducted based on the developed risk score, which did not 
include the model selection step. The estimate of the 
overoptimism could be substantially biased under this 
circumstance. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>We developed and validated a novel risk score by incorporat-
ing both major clinical risk factors and effective urine 
biomarkers to predict AKI in ADHF patients early. Individual 
risk prediction, as well as risk stratification based on the risk 
score, may assist clinicians to assess the risk of AKI in ADHF 
patients, which, in turn, would help them to plan and initiate 
the most appropriate disease management for patients in 
time. </p>

<p>The authors have followed the STROBE checklist in collecting and 
reporting their data and the TRIPOD checklist in reporting the 
prediction model. Elements of the checklist are incorporated into the 
manuscript. Further details of any particular checklist item are 
available on request from the corresponding authors. </p>

<p>Sources of Funding </p>

<p>This study was supported by the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (no. 81273191/81673270) granted to 
Prof Chen and the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China (no. 81430016) to Dr Hou. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>None. </p>





<p>Risk Prediction for AKI in ADHF Patients 
Zhou et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>



<p>46. Pfister R, M€ uller Ehmsen J, Hagemeister J, Hellmich M, Erdmann E, Schneider 
CA. NT-pro-BNP predicts worsening renal function in patients with chronic 
systolic heart failure. Intern Med J. 2011;41:467-472. </p>

<p>47. McIlroy DR, Wagener G, Lee HT. Neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalin and 
acute kidney injury after cardiac surgery: the effect of baseline renal function 
on diagnostic performance. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2010;5:211-219. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004035 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Risk Prediction for AKI in ADHF Patients 
Zhou et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>



<p>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL </p>



<p>Data S1. </p>

<p>Supplemental Methods </p>

<p>Study Design. The study is a prospective, multi-center, observational study. All patients </p>

<p>provided informed written consent for the procedure(s) and the study was approved by the </p>

<p>Institutional Review Board. </p>

<p>Study Population. A total of 676 consecutive participants, aged 18-80 years old, were </p>

<p>prospectively enrolled between September 2011 and August 2014 from six regional central </p>

<p>hospitals located in five cities in China. Among the participants, 169 were excluded </p>

<p>according to exclusion criteria (Figure 1), and the remaining 507 participants formed our </p>

<p>study population. </p>

<p>The inclusion criteria were patients with ADHF 1) who were admitted to the six </p>

<p>participating hospitals, and 2) who had at least three measurements of serum creatinine over a </p>

<p>six-month period before admission. Exclusion criteria were 1) exposing to nephrotoxins, such </p>

<p>as contrast media, aminoglycoside antibiotics, vancomycin, and/or non-steroidal </p>

<p>anti-inflammatory drugs except aspirin, within 4 weeks before admission or during hospital </p>

<p>stay, 2) pre-existing advanced chronic kidney disease (CKD) (chronic dialysis or </p>

<p>pre-admission estimated glomerular filtration rate [Egfr] &lt;30 ml/min/1•73m 
2 ), 3) urinary </p>

<p>tract infection or obstruction, cancer, a concurrent diagnosis of an acute coronary syndrome, </p>

<p>cardiogenic shock or need for inotropes, 4) heart failure following cardiac surgery, and 5) </p>

<p>having AKI on admission (i.e., those with a 50% increase in serum creatinine from </p>

<p>preadmission level on the day of hospitalization). </p>

<p>Laboratory measurements </p>

<p>Urine and blood samples were measured in a central laboratory with standard protocol. A </p>

<p>sandwich ELISA kit (Immuno-Biologic Laboratories Co. Ltd, Japan) was used for </p>



<p>quantifying AGT in urine, and further confirmed by western blot analyses. uNGAL was </p>

<p>measured with an ELISA kit (Antibody Shop, Denmark). Urine albumin to creatinine ratio </p>

<p>(UACR) was measured using an automatic analyzer (Siemens BNPro Spec, Germany). All </p>

<p>urine biomarkers were normalized based on the level of urinary creatinine. Estimated </p>

<p>glomerular filtration rate (GRF) was determined by Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology </p>

<p>Collaboration (CKD-EPI) equation (1). </p>

<p>Candidate predictors </p>

<p>Candidate predictors included clinical variables such as sex, age (years), hypertension, </p>

<p>diabetes mellitus, pre-existing CKD indicated from medical records, or reported by patients, </p>

<p>or diagnosed by doctor, prior hospitalization for heart failure, left ventricular ejection </p>

<p>fraction, severity of breathlessness by the New York Heart Association (NYHA) </p>

<p>classification, NT-proBNP (pg/ml), systolic and diastolic blood pressure (mmHg), serum </p>

<p>albumin (g/L), serum creatinine (μmol/L), hemoglobin (g/L), use of renin-angiotensin system </p>

<p>blockersand/or diuretic, and urine biomarkers such as urine albumin to creatinine ratio </p>

<p>(UACR, mg/g Cr), uNGAL (μg/g Cr) and uAGT (μg/g Cr). All these variables were assessed </p>

<p>and recorded on admission. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>We took two steps to develop a risk model based on the development cohort. The first was </p>

<p>to select meaningful clinical risk factors (non-urine markers) by logistic regression with </p>

<p>backward elimination. Clinical candidate predictors significant at P&lt;0.1 in univariate logistic </p>

<p>regression models were considered for backward elimination. In this step, a clinical model </p>

<p>with clinical factors was developed. Then, urine biomarkers (UACR, uNGAL and uAGT) </p>

<p>were evaluated sequentially based on this clinical model. The likelihood ratio χ 
2 test (2) was </p>

<p>used to evaluate the significance of the added urine biomarkers, and net-reclassification index </p>



<p>(NRI) and integrated discrimination improvement (IDI) (3) were used to quantify the </p>

<p>additional contribution of these urine biomarkers to risk reclassification. </p>

<p>To develop the risk score, the scoring method similar to Sullivan et al's (4) was employed </p>

<p>based on the developed risk model. Continuous variables were divided into categories in </p>

<p>terms of clinical significance except for NT-proBNP, for which the cut-off of 5578 pg/ml was </p>

<p>chosen to yield good sensitivity and specificity. Mid-point value was defined as the reference </p>

<p>value of each category. For the first and last categories of each variable, we used the 1 
st and </p>

<p>the 99 
th percentiles to minimize the influence of extreme values. For each risk factor, the </p>

<p>lowest risk category was chosen as the base category, and the distance of other categories </p>

<p>from the base category was calculated as the difference of reference values between </p>

<p>corresponding categories and base category multiplied by the regression coefficient of </p>

<p>corresponding variable in the generated risk model. One point of the risk score system was </p>

<p>defined as a constant of 0.141 which means the increase of risk associated with a 10-year </p>

<p>increase in age, that is 0.0141×10. The score of each base category was set at 0, and that of </p>

<p>other categories were computed by dividing corresponding distance from the base category </p>

<p>by the constant of 0.141 and then rounded to the nearest integer. The total risk score for an </p>

<p>individual patient is obtained by summing up the score of each predictive variable. </p>

<p>The predictive accuracy of the risk model and the risk score model was assessed by both </p>

<p>discrimination measured by C-statistic (5) and calibration evaluated by Hosmer-Lemeshow </p>

<p>χ² statistic (6) and calibration plot, a plot of observed proportions versus predicted </p>

<p>probabilities. Bootstrapping technique (7) was used to adjust for over-fitting and </p>

<p>over-optimistic model performance. </p>

<p>The natural logarithmic transformation of NT-proBNP and all urine biomarkers was </p>

<p>made because of their extreme positive skewness. Generalized additive model (GAM) (8)   was used to explore the potential nonlinear relationship between those continuous variables </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>and the outcome. The clinical meaningful interactions between predictors were also </p>

<p>examined. Continuous variables were expressed as mean (SD) or median (1 
st Quarter-3 </p>

<p>rd </p>

<p>Quarter). Categorical variables were expressed as percentages. Sensitivity analysis was </p>

<p>conducted to assess the influence of the two incomplete measures by leaving the </p>

<p>corresponding two cases out. Further, we also applied the risk score to the whole </p>

<p>participants as sensitivity analysis. All analyses were done with SAS (SAS Institute Inc., </p>

<p>Cary, NC, version 9.4). A two-sided P&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>



<p>Table S1: Baseline characteristics outlining those who developed versus not developed AKI. </p>

<p>Values are numbers (percentages) unless stated otherwise. </p>

<p>Non-AKI 
(n=339) </p>

<p>AKI 
(n=168) </p>

<p>P 
value 
Demographics 
mean (SD) age (years) 
63.0(15.3) 
69.6(13.1) 
&lt;.001 
Sex, Male 
211(62.2) 
109(64.9) 
0.562 
Pre-existing clinical conditions 
Hypertension 
146(43.1) 
107(63.7) 
&lt;.001 
Diabetes 
68(20.1) 
61(36.3) 
&lt;.001 
Pre-CKD 
55(16.2) 
78(46.4) 
&lt;.001 
Prior hospitalization for HF 
170(50.1) 
91(54.2) 
0.394 
Primary causes of heart failure 
Ischemic heart disease 
178(52.5) 
93(55.4) 
0.545 
Hypertension 
43(12.7) 
22(13.1) 
0.896 
Rheumatic heart disease 
47(13.9) 
23(13.7) 
0.957 
Cardiomyopathy 
48(14.2) 
14(8.3) 
0.059 
Other 
23(6.8) 
16(9.5) 
0.276 
Characteristics on admission 
LVEF&lt;45% 
153(45.1) 
81(48.2) 
0.512 
NYHA, class IV 
144(42.5) 
99(58.9) 
&lt;.001 
Median (IQR) NT-proBNP (pg/ml) 
4181.0(1942.0-8463.0) 7088.5(3699.3-9000.0) &lt;.001 
Mean (SD) SBP (mmHg) 
126.2(24.0) 
129.3(24.8) 
0.173 
Mean (SD) DBP (mmHg) 
75.6(16.1) 
74.8(14.4) 
0.591 
Mean (SD) Serum creatinine (μmol/L) 
98.5(40.0) 
128.8(59.1) 
&lt;.001 
Mean (SD) Serum albumin (g/L) 
34.8(5.8) 
30.8(5.9) 
&lt;.001 
Mean (SD) Hemoglobin (g/L) 
128.1(23.1) 
115.8(26.3) 
&lt;.001 
Treatment before Admission 
Use ACEI/ARB pre-admission 
90(26.5) 
54(32.1) 
0.189 
Mean (SD) Drug index of ACEI/ARBc 
4.3(1.1) 
4.1(1.2) 
0.283 
Use spironolactone 
103(30.4) 
60(35.7) 
0.226 
Mean (SD) Drug index of spironolactonec 
1.1(0.3) 
1.1(0.3) 
0.314 
Mean (SD) Drug score of RAAS blockerc 
5.4(1.1) 
5.2(1.4) 
0.476 
Use diuretic pre-admission 
117(34.5) 
66(39.3) 
0.292 
Use of high-dose diuretic 
5(1.5) 
5(3.0) 
0.253 
Biomarker measurement 
Median (IQR) UACR (mg/g Cr) 
51.2(16.2-182.4) 
180.4(63.7-491.5) 
0.012 
Median (IQR) uNGAL (μg/g Cr) 
29.7(14.9-78.3) 
114.2(39.1-417.2) 
&lt;.001 </p>







<p>Table S2. C-statistic, NRI and IDI for different models </p>

<p>Models 
VS 
LR χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P 
C-statistic(95%CI) 
NRI 
IDI </p>

<p>Clinical model (M1)* 
0.767(0.714-0.820) </p>

<p>M1 + uAGT (M2) 
M1 
64.923 &lt;0.001 0.861(0.820-0.925) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>0.809 
(p&lt;0.001) </p>

<p>0.169 
(p&lt;0.001) </p>

<p>M1 +uAGT+ uNGAL (M3) M2 
8.737 
&lt;0.013 0.874(0.835-0.913) #&amp; 0.293 
(p=0.012) </p>

<p>0.023 
(p=0.011) 
M1 +uAGT+ 
uNGAL+UACR (M4) 
M3 
1.582 
0.208 
0.875(0.836-0.914) 
0.105 
(p=0.369) </p>

<p>0.004 
(p=0.214) </p>

<p>* Clinical model included age, sex, pre-existing CKD, ALB and NT-proBNP. </p>

<p># VS M1, DeLong's test, P &lt; 0.001 
# VS M2, DeLong's test, P = 0.035 </p>



<p>Table S3. Predicted risk of AKI in patients with ADHF based on the risk score model. 
Total risk 
score </p>

<p>Predicted 
risk (%) </p>

<p>Total risk 
score </p>

<p>Predicted 
risk (%) </p>

<p>Total risk 
score </p>

<p>Predicted 
risk (%) 
0 
1.8 
19 
13.7 
38 
58.5 
1 
2.0 
20 
15.1 
39 
61.3 
2 
2.2 
21 
16.6 
40 
63.9 
3 
2.5 
22 
18.3 
41 
66.6 
4 
2.7 
23 
20.1 
42 
69.1 
5 
3.1 
24 
22.0 
43 
71.5 
6 
3.4 
25 
24.0 
44 
73.7 
7 
3.8 
26 
26.2 
45 
75.9 
8 
4.3 
27 
28.5 
46 
78.0 
9 
4.8 
28 
30.9 
47 
79.9 
10 
5.3 
29 
33.4 
48 
81.7 
11 
5.9 
30 
36.0 
49 
83.3 
12 
6.6 
31 
38.7 
50 
84.9 
13 
7.4 
32 
41.4 
51 
86.3 
14 
8.2 
33 
44.2 
52 
87.6 
15 
9.1 
34 
47.1 
53 
88.8 
16 
10.1 
35 
50.0 
54 
89.9 
17 
11.2 
36 
52.8 
55 
90.9 
18 
12.4 
37 
55.7 </p>



<p>Table S4. Risk score for single risk factors associated with developing AKI for clinical </p>

<p>score model in ADHF patients. </p>

<p>Risk Factor 
Score 
C-statistic for single 
variable 
Age (year) 
0.638 (0.574-0.701) 
≤55 
0 
56-65 
2 
66-75 
3 
76 and older 
5 
Sex 
0.514 (0.460-0.568) 
Male 
1 
Female 
0 
Pre-CKD 
0.680 (0.627-0.732) 
Yes 
5 
No 
0 
Serum albumin (mmol/L) 
0.640 (0.576-0.704) 
≤35 
4 
&gt;35 
0 
NT-proBNP (pg/ml)  † 
0.635 (0.572-0.698) 
＜5578 
0 
≥5578 
3 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Table S5. Sensitivity analysis of model performance of models with different included variables. 
Included variables 
Development dataset 
Validation dataset </p>

<p>C-statistic 
-2 Log L 
AIC 
C-statistic </p>

<p>Age / Sex / pre-CKD / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin 
345.736 
357.736 
0.767 
0.807 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / pre-CKD / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uNGAL 
314.196 
328.196 
0.819 
0.823 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / pre-CKD / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uAGT 
280.813 
294.813 
0.861 
0.888 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / pre-CKD / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uNGAL / ln-uAGT 
272.076 
288.076 
0.874 
0.890 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / eGFR / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin 
355.295 
367.295 
0.751 
0.825 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / eGFR / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uNGAL 
320.421 
334.421 
0.812 
0.841 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / eGFR / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uAGT 
288.065 
302.065 
0.854 
0.898 </p>

<p>Age / Sex / eGFR / ln-NT-proBNP / Serum albumin / ln-uNGAL / ln-uAGT 
277.847 
293.847 
0.867 
0.903 </p>



<p>Figure S1. Flow of enrollment of the study participants. </p>



<p>Figure S2. Boxplot showing the risk score across different AKI stage of the patients. 
Significant difference in average risk score of different AKI stage was found, with 
higher risk score in patients with higher stage of AKI (P value by one-way ANOVA 
analysis, &lt;0.001). </p>



<p>Figure S3. Receiver Operator Characteristic Curves showing the discriminatory 
power of the risk score for predicting death during hospitalization. </p>



<p>Figure S4. Receiver Operator Characteristic Curves showing Area Under the Curve 
of clinical model and clinical score for AKI in ADHF patients. </p>



<p>Figure S5. Calibration plot as well as the Hosmer-Lemeshow χ² statistic for the risk 
score in both development and validation cohorts. The points and circles indicate the 
observed frequencies by decile of predicted probability. </p>



<p>Figure S6. Risk levels according to the risk score in development and validation 
cohorts. Risks were categorized into low-risk (0-4 points), moderate-risk (5-9 points), 
high-risk (10-14 points), very high-risk (15-18 points). Higher points means higher 
risk of developing AKI in patients with ADHF, P for trend&lt;0.001. </p>

<p>Supplemental risk calculator AKI risk calculator. </p>





</text></tei>