<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5226643" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Establishing the age of the Moon is critical to understanding solar system evolution and the formation of rocky 
planets, including Earth. However, despite its importance, the age of the Moon has never been accurately 
determined. We present uranium-lead dating of Apollo 14 zircon fragments that yield highly precise, concordant 
ages, demonstrating that they are robust against postcrystallization isotopic disturbances. Hafnium isotopic analyses 
of the same fragments show extremely low initial 176 Hf/ 177 Hf ratios corrected for cosmic ray exposure that are near 
the solar system initial value. Our data indicate differentiation of the lunar crust by 4.51 billion years, indicating 
the formation of the Moon within the first ~60 million years after the birth of the solar system. </p>

<p>The surface of the Moon provides the most accessible record of plan-
etary formation processes and the early evolution of our solar system. 
Geochemical analyses of Apollo samples and lunar meteorites have 
contributed to the present paradigm of lunar formation through a giant 
impact (GI) on/with the proto-Earth (1, 2), followed by rapid accretion 
of the orbiting debris and nearly complete melting of the proto-Moon. 
Chemical differentiation and crystallization of this hypothesized global 
lunar magma ocean (LMO) produced dense mafic cumulates that sank 
to the base of the LMO and a buoyant plagioclase-rich crust that formed 
the lunar highlands (3). Although there is consensus for this general 
model of lunar formation and early evolution, the timing of the GI 
and subsequent events remains controversial, with some planetary 
scientists favoring the formation within ~100 million years (My) after 
the formation of the solar system [4.45 billion years ago (Ga) to 4.47 Ga] 
(4-6) and others arguing for a relatively late GI (4.35 Ga to 4.42 Ga), 
approximately 150 My to 200 My after the beginning of the solar system 
(7-10). The "young" ages for lunar formation are difficult to reconcile 
with the zircon records from the Hadean era of Earth's history (11) and 
from the Moon (12), which show ages as old as 4.38 Ga and 4.4 Ga, 
respectively. In addition, the vast majority of dynamical models are 
inconsistent with Moon-forming impact occurring 100 My after the 
birth of the solar system (13, 14). Therefore, knowledge of the age of 
the Moon is important not only for developing a detailed understanding 
of LMO duration and crystallization processes (15) but also for con-
straining competing models of solar system evolution during the later 
stages of planetary accretion. 
Attempts to determine an age for the formation of the Moon can 
be divided into two main approaches: dating the GI event through its 
possible collateral effects on other solar system bodies or dating 
products of the solidification of the LMO itself. Various recent pro-
posals to constrain the timing of events in relation to the GI include 
modeling of the addition of highly siderophile elements to Earth during 
the last stages of accretion (6), the timing of loss of volatile Pb relative 
to refractory U in the bulk silicate Earth following the GI (7), and dating 
of the thermal effects possibly due to the impact of numerous kilometer-
sized, high-velocity fragments of GI ejecta on main-belt asteroids, as 
monitored by Pb loss in meteoritic apatite grains (4) or by 40 Ar/ 39 Ar age </p>

<p>spectra (5). An insurmountable problem with these indirect approaches 
is that there is no way to ascertain that the measured effects (for exam-
ple, Pb isotope compositions or 40 Ar/ 39 Ar ages) are associated with the 
GI event. A more direct constraint on the age of the Moon can be 
obtained by dating the chemical differentiation events accompanying 
the crystallization of the LMO. This approach has been used in deriving 
Pb isotope model ages for the source regions of lunar basalts (10) and 
measuring Sm-Nd and Rb-Sr isochron ages of individual lunar rocks 
(7, 8). However, Pb model ages are uncertain because of poorly con-
strained U/Pb fractionation (high m) on the Moon (10, 16). Similarly, 
isochron ages can only date the LMO solidification if all the minerals 
crystallized synchronously and have subsequently remained undisturbed, 
a remote possibility for whole-rock data, given that the analyzed Apollo 
lunar rocks are impact-induced breccias. 
To avoid these difficulties, we use combined U-Pb and Lu-Hf isotope 
systematics in individual zircons crystallized from the LMO to construct 
a two-stage model age for the globally synchronous primary differenti-
ation of the Moon. This has the advantage of defining the age of the 
Moon without complications of lunar accretion following the GI. The 
investigated zircon fragments are ancient, robust against later isotopic 
disturbance (for example, impacts and brecciation), and amenable to 
high-precision absolute chronology. Hafnium isotopic analysis of the 
same volumes of zircon dated by high-precision U-Pb geochronology 
document exceedingly little ingrowth of radiogenic 176 Hf due to the de-
cay of 176 Lu in the magma from which the zircons were formed. A model 
differentiation age can be derived, with the assumption that initial Lu/Hf 
and Hf isotopic compositions in the source are known. Traditionally, a 
uniform chondritic composition [chondritic uniform reservoir (CHUR)] 
of refractory trace elements has been assumed for the Earth-Moon sys-
tem, but this was called into question by the finding of 142 Nd discrepan-
cies between Earth and chondrites (17), suggesting that Earth (and, by 
extension, the Moon) might have formed with a nonchondritic Sm-Nd. 
However, Burkhardt et al. (18) showed that this anomaly is actually the 
result of a small nucleosynthetic effect in Nd isotopic composition, which 
removes the only evidence for the Earth-Moon system deviating signif-
icantly from chondritic abundances of refractory trace elements. In ad-
dition, any nucleosynthetic effects (for example, in Hf isotopes) are 
thought to be small enough that they could not significantly affect 
Lu/Hf model ages (19). Finally, lunar zircons are thought to form in 
the KREEP (potassium, rare-Earth elements, and phosophorus enriched 
reservoir) reservoir, which formed only at the end of LMO crystalliza-
tion (20). Therefore, coupled U-Pb and Hf isotopic data on lunar zircons 
can be used to determine the age of bulk solidification of the Moon. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Earth, Planetary, and Space Sciences, University of California, Los Angeles, 
Los Angeles, CA 90095, USA. 2 Department of the Geophysical Sciences, The University of 
Chicago, Chicago, IL 60637, USA. 3 Department of Geosciences, Princeton University, 
Princeton, NJ 08544, USA. 4 Berkeley Geochronology Center, Berkeley, CA 94709, USA. 
*Corresponding author. Email: mbarboni@epss.ucla.edu </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Barboni et al. Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602365 
11 January 2017 
1 of 8 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>For this study, we selected the remaining fragments from eight Apollo 
14 zircon grains that had been previously analyzed by Taylor et al. (20). 
The zircons were separated from saw cuttings of polymict breccias 
14304 and 14321 as well as from 14163, a soil sample collected from 
the upper few centimeters of the lunar regolith (see the Supplementary 
Materials for further sample descriptions). The Taylor et al. study (20) 
reported U-Pb crystallization ages obtained by secondary ion mass 
spectrometry (SIMS) followed by laser ablation multiple collector in-
ductively coupled plasma MS (LA-MC-ICPMS) to determine Hf iso-
topic compositions and 176 Lu-176 Hf systematics. It suggested an early 
formation of the Moon (before 4.5 Gy, within the first 68 My of the solar 
system); however, the uncertainties were permissive of an LMO crystal-
lization age up to ~120 My after solar system origin (13). Hafnium iso-
tope data obtained from soil sample 14163 were not included in the 
published study because shifts in the nonradiogenic isotope ratios 
suggested problems likely attributable to cosmic ray exposure effects 
on the lunar surface, as the soil sample was known to comprise a 
complex mixture of materials, with some having very long exposure 
ages that range over 2 Gy (21, 22). In contrast, measured exposure ages 
for the zircons obtained from breccia samples 14304 and 14321 are rel-
atively short (&lt;30 My; Supplementary Materials). Two recent studies 
(23, 24) have quantified the effects of neutron capture on the Hf isotope 
ratios, demonstrating that initial 176 Hf/ 177 Hf ratios can shift by several 
e 176 Hf(t) units for samples with significant exposure to cosmic radia-
tion [note that e unit = 176 Hf/ 177 Hf deviation from chondritic com-
position (CHUR) in parts of 10 4 for a given, identical time (t)]. An 
additional potential issue with the previous lunar zircon data is that 
the precision of the SIMS U-Pb ages was insufficient to assess concor-
dance and thus rule out the possibility of ancient Pb loss that could bias 
crystallization ages to younger values. Also, SIMS U-Pb ages were 
determined at the very surface of the zircon (~1-mm-deep, 40-mm-
diameter pit), whereas LA-MC-ICPMS used a ~200 times larger analyt-</p>

<p>ical volume, therefore leaving open the possibility of inaccuracies in 
calculating e 176 Hf(t) by not measuring Lu-Hf and U-Pb isotopes in 
the same volume of zircon (25). Finally, the initial value and the evolu-
tionary trajectory of 176 Hf/ 177 Hf of the solar system (CHUR) has been 
recently revised by direct measurement of zircon grains from the eucrite 
Agoult (26) that crystallized within the first ~12 My of the solar system. 
This work has significantly improved the precision and accuracy with 
which CHUR is known and therefore allows the determination of Lu/Hf 
model ages with high confidence. 
We used isotope dilution thermal ionization mass spectrometry 
(ID-TIMS) on chemically abraded zircons to obtain U-Pb dates 
(table S1A). Crystallization ages for our analyzed zircons extend over 
365 My, from 4335 Ma to 3969 Ma, similar to the range of ages previ-
ously reported for Apollo 14 zircons by SIMS (20, 27). However, the 
improved precision on 206 Pb/ 238 U and 207 Pb/ 235 U dates afforded by 
ID-TIMS and the ability to remove zircon domains affected by Pb loss 
(by two leaching steps of 6 hours each at 185°C; see the Supplementary 
Materials) permit the use of only demonstrably closed-system zircon 
domains for our Hf model ages (Fig. 1). This approach is validated in 
that the first leaching steps yielded discordant U-Pb dates (table S1B), 
whereas most of the second leachates and residues are within ±0.5% of 
concordia (table S1A). One of the zircon residues (14163 z86) that dis-
played a small degree (2.5%) of Pb loss has a 207 Pb-206 Pb date that is 
within 13 My of its concordant second leachate, supporting the veracity 
of the residue age. Two other analyses that fall slightly off the concordia 
curve but are still used for Hf model ages are the youngest in the pop-
ulation (14304 z20; discordant by 1.2%) and a second leachate of 
14304 z52 (0.81% discordant). From these data, we conclude that the 
Apollo 14 zircons chosen for Hf analysis and presented in Fig. 1 and 
table S1A have not experienced significant amounts of Pb loss and that 
the 207 Pb/ 206 Pb ages accurately reflect the timing of zircon crystallization. 
We measured Hf isotopes by solution MC-ICPMS in the same 
volume of zircon as that used for the TIMS U-Pb dating by analyzing </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.7 
50 
45 
65 
60 
55 
70 
75 </p>

<p>206 </p>

<p>Pb/ 238 </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>207 Pb/ 235 U </p>

<p>4300 </p>

<p>4200 </p>

<p>3900 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>4100 </p>

<p>4400 </p>

<p>14163 z59 </p>

<p>14163 z59 L2 </p>

<p>14163 z86 </p>

<p>14163 z86 L2 </p>

<p>14163 z23 </p>

<p>14163 z52 </p>

<p>14163 z52 L2 
14304 z20 </p>

<p>14304 z1 </p>

<p>14304 z2 </p>

<p>14321 z17 </p>

<p>All errors are 2σ </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Concordia diagram of the Apollo 14 zircons used to determine Hf model ages. U-Pb ID-TIMS analyses of zircon leachate (empty ellipses) and analyses of the 
remaining zircon residues after step leaching (filled ellipses). Ellipses are color-coded for samples. </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Barboni et al. Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602365 </p>

<p>
the wash retrieved from the U-Pb chemistry (see the Supplementary 
Materials for analytical details). This approach allows us to unambigu-
ously link Hf isotope compositions to the U-Pb ages (28). The Lu/Hf 
of each zircon was measured by ICPMS on an aliquot of the same 
solution to correct for in situ radiogenic growth of 176 Hf since zircon 
crystallization. The effects of possible neutron capture on the Apollo 
14 zircon Hf isotopic ratios were assessed by examining the deviation 
of their 178 Hf/ 177 Hf ratios from normal (terrestrial and chondritic) 
values (24, 29). Most of our zircons [as well as the zircons analyzed by 
Taylor et al. (20)] have been affected to some degree by cosmic ray 
exposure with offsets up to 2.14 e 178 Hf from the terrestrial value (Fig. 2). 
We corrected for these effects using the data and procedure of Sprung et al. 
(23), resulting in shifts between 0 and 5.6 in e 176 Hf(t) (Supplementary </p>

<p>Materials). The corrected initial e 176 Hf(t) values, shown as a function of 
crystallization age in Fig. 3, are the lowest measured in lunar materials, 
with the least radiogenic samples in the Apollo 14 population having 
initial 176 Hf/ 177 Hf ratios within 1 to 2 e units (0.01 to 0.02%) of the solar 
system initial value (Supplementary Materials) (16). These data indicate 
the formation of the zircons in a highly enriched magma, termed urK-
REEP (30), which agrees with the previous conclusions of Taylor et al. 
(20). However, the precision of the data presented here and the correc-
tions for cosmic ray exposure (23) that permit accurate determination 
of initial e 176 Hf(t) values on individual zircons with concordant U/Pb 
ages place tight constraints on the timing of Lu/Hf fractionation during 
LMO crystallization. 
A model age for the separation of the LMO from the CHUR primor-
dial reservoir is determined by calculating when the LMO zircons and 
the primordial Earth-Moon reservoir had the same 176 Hf/ 177 Hf ratio, 
which requires an estimate of the 176 Lu/ 177 Hf of the magma from which 
the zircon crystallized (Supplementary Materials). We chose to calculate 
the model ages using 176 Lu/ 177 Hf source = 0, which corresponds to the 
maximum elemental fractionation possible for the reservoir that the 
zircons crystallized from. Although this represents extreme Lu/Hf 
fractionation, it is reasonably consistent with expectations for fractional 
crystallization of an LMO and production of zircon in the last residual 
melt (urKREEP). A <rs type="software">pMELTS</rs> simulation (31) with the <rs type="software">alphaMELTS</rs> 
interface (32) of 176 Lu/ 177 Hf during KREEP crystallization shows that 
it quickly evolves to &lt;0.01 at less than 50% melt remaining (Supplemen-
tary Materials). Any choice of a higher Lu/Hf ratio for the source neces-
sarily yields older model separation ages; our results therefore provide 
minimum ages for differentiation of the LMO from CHUR and a 
minimum age for the formation of the Moon. Our model age results 
are presented in Fig. 4, together with those from Taylor et al. (20) 
corrected for neutron capture effects. Because some of the Apollo 
14 zircons with initial e 176 Hf(t) values closer to chondritic could be 
derived from KREEP-rich magmas that had undergone partial as-
similation of crustal rocks, we take the oldest model ages as the 
minimum age for LMO solidification. To determine this minimum 
age, we averaged the four oldest zircon Lu/Hf model ages, resulting in 
4.51 ± 0.01 Gy (1s). </p>

<p>-0.5 
0.0 
0.5 
1.0 
1.5 
2.0 
2.5 </p>

<p>Taylor et al. (20) 
Apollo samples (this study) 
Terrestrial standards (this study) </p>

<p>ε 178 Hf </p>

<p>All errors are 1σ </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Magnitude of the neutron capture effect on Apollo zircons as shown 
by the shift in 178 Hf/ 177 Hf. The shift is expressed as a deviation in e 178 Hfs from the 
terrestrial value (56). Samples with a large offset in e 178 Hf all come from soil 14163 
that experienced longer cosmic ray exposure on the near surface of the Moon. </p>

<p>3.8 
3.9 
4.0 
4.1 
4.2 
4.3 
4.4 
4.5 
4.6 </p>

<p>-12 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>-8 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>This study 
Taylor et al. (20 ) 
Taylor et al. (20 ), NC-corrected 
CHUR </p>

<p>ε 176 </p>

<p>Hf </p>

<p>CHUR </p>

<p>Zircon crystallization age (Ga) </p>

<p>L u / H </p>

<p>f = </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>All errors are 1σ </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Plot of e 176 Hf CHUR versus 207 Pb/ 206 Pb zircon age (Gy). e 176 Hf CHUR is evaluated by the difference between initial e 176 Hf(t) and the Hf isotopic composition of 
CHUR at time t (26). Taylor et al. (20) reported the data before and after neutron capture (NC) correction. </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Barboni et al. Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602365 </p>

<p>
DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our model age is ~120 My to 150 My older than estimates based on 
Sm-Nd and Pb-Pb isochrons measured on ferroan anorthosites that are 
thought to represent early floatation cumulates of LMO crystallization 
(8) and dating of Mg suite lunar crustal rocks (9). We reiterate that our 
model age for differentiation of the LMO is actually a minimum 
estimate for the age of the Moon because we took the lowest possible 
value for Lu/Hf in the source reservoir (Lu/Hf source = 0). Furthermore, 
previous uncertainties regarding the chondritic nature of the Moon and 
the evolution of Hf isotopes in chondrites (CHUR) have recently been 
addressed (26). Therefore, the zircon Hf model ages are accurately re-
lated to an absolute time scale. Our data unambiguously show that the 
Moon was differentiated and mostly solidified by 4.51 Gy, so the young 
ages obtained on lunar highland samples cannot be directly dating the 
age of the Moon. If these Sm-Nd ages are not compromised by later 
disturbances, including brecciation and shocks, they may reflect the 
time of slow cooling through the low closure temperature of the Sm-
Nd system (33). However, if these limitations do not apply and the 
Moon cooled quickly, then a reexamination of the origin of ferroan 
anorthosites in the context of the LMO hypothesis is required, as 
suggested by Borg et al. (8). Our results are consistent with con-
straints given by the short-lived 182 Hf-182 W system that indicate that 
the formation of the Moon must have occurred later than ~50 My 
after the beginning of the solar system (34). Because the Hf isotopic 
composition of the lunar zircons requires solidification of the LMO by 
~4.51 Gy, we conclude that the GI and formation of the Earth-Moon 
system must have occurred within the first ~60 My of the formation of 
the solar system, with an uncertainty on the order of 10 My (1s). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Sample description 
We analyzed the fragments of eight zircons that were previously 
separated at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) from 
Apollo 14 samples by Taylor et al. (20). Four zircons were derived from 
14163, a soil sample representing the upper few centimeters of the lunar 
regolith. Cosmic ray exposure ages reported for 14163 soil particles (22) </p>

<p>and partnered sample 14161 (21) ranged from 100 My to 2.5 Gy, indic-
ative of a complex mixture of materials that have been cycled through 
the regolith, perhaps repeatedly, over a long period. Analyses of zircons 
from this sample were not included in the published study of Taylor et al. 
(20) because it was recognized that the long exposure age may have 
compromised Hf isotopic compositions through neutron capture re-
actions and, at the time, there was no method available to quantitatively 
correct for these effects. In the intervening time, Sprung et al. (23, 24) 
determined neutron capture effects on Hf isotope ratios so that we can 
now use correlated isotope ratios to accurately correct measured 176 Hf/ </p>

<p>177 </p>

<p>Hf in each zircon (see the "Lu-Hf parameters and model age calcu-
lation" section). Three zircons analyzed here and reported by Taylor et al. 
(20) were found among saw cuttings from the interior of rock 14304, 
a ~2.5-kg polymict breccia that was almost completely buried in the 
regolith at the time of collection. No cosmic ray exposure ages have been 
determined on 14304; however, exposure ages were measured on 14305, 
a nearby, similarly sized rock. The exposure ages for 14305 range from 
11 My (by the 129 Xe method) (35) to 28 My (by the 81 Kr method) (36). 
The final zircon reported here was obtained from saw cuttings of 14321, 
a complex polymict breccia that, at 9 kg, was the largest rock returned by 
Apollo 14 (37). The sample was partially buried in the ejecta blanket of 
Cone Crater, a relatively young [26 My (38)] crater that excavated 
material from the Fra Mauro formation that is thought to sample material 
from the Imbrium impact basin. Cosmic ray exposure ages of 14321 aver-
aged 24 My, consistent with the age of the Cone Crater. SIMS U/Pb 
ages previously obtained from zircons from 14321 range from 4.01 Gy 
to 4.33 Gy (39, 40). </p>

<p>U-Pb geochronology 
Individual zircon fragments were removed from epoxy mounts and 
thermally annealed by transferring the fragments into quartz crucibles 
and heated to 900°C for 48 hours. The fragments were then rinsed with 
acetone in 3-ml Savillex PFA (fluoropolymer) beakers, fluxed in 6 M 
HCl for 1 hour at 100°C, and rinsed again using MQ H 2 O. The zircon 
fragments were then loaded into 200-ml Savillex microcapsules with 
100 ml of 29 M HF + 15 ml of 3 M HNO 3 for the first step of chemical 
abrasion (41) in high-pressure Parr bombs for 6 hours at 185°C. </p>

<p>This study (residues) </p>

<p>Taylor et al. (20), NC-corrected </p>

<p>Hf model age (Ga) </p>

<p>Zircon crystallization age (Ga) </p>

<p>Upper limit from 
182 Hf-182 W = 4.52 Ga (34) </p>

<p>3.975 
4.125 
4.275 
4.050 
4.200 
4.350 </p>

<p>This study 
(4.51 ± 0.01 Ga) </p>

<p>Indirect ages (4-7 ) </p>

<p>Direct ages (8-10) </p>

<p>This study (2nd leachates) </p>

<p>All errors are 1σ </p>

<p>4.2 </p>

<p>4.3 </p>

<p>4.4 </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>4.6 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Hf model age (Gy) calculated for a Lu/Hf source = 0 as a function of 207 Pb/ 206 Pb zircon crystallization age (Gy). Ranges of previously proposed ages for the 
Moon's formation are also shown. </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Barboni et al. Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602365 </p>

<p>
Grains were rinsed 10 times after the first-step leaching with 6 M HCl, 
MQ H 2 O, and 29 M HF before being leached again with 100 ml of 29 M 
HF + 15 ml of 3 M HNO 3 for a second 6-hour step of chemical abrasion 
at 185°C. The same rinsing procedure done for the first-step leaching 
was also applied after the second-step leaching. Both leachates from 
the first and second steps (subsequently referred to as L1 and L2) 
were saved (21). L1 samples were spiked with the EARTHTIME </p>

<p>205 </p>

<p>Pb-233 U-235 U tracer (42, 43), and zircon fragment residues and L2 
samples were spiked with the EARTHTIME 202 Pb-205 Pb-233 U-235 U 
tracer (42, 43). The remaining zircon fragments (subsequently referred 
to as "residues") were then dissolved to completion in 100 ml of 29 M 
HF + 15 ml of 3 N HNO 3 in Parr bombs for 48 hours at 210°C. Leachates 
L1 and L2 were individually dried down and converted to chlorides by 
overnight redissolution using 100 ml of 6 N HCl in Parr bombs at 185°C. 
All samples (L1, L2, and residues) were subsequently dried down and 
brought up in 50 ml of 3 M HCl. The U-Pb and trace element aliquots 
(including Lu-Hf) were separated by anion exchange column chroma-
tography using a modified single 50-ml column and AG 1-X8 resin [200-
to 400-mesh chloride from Eichrom (44)]. The trace element aliquot 
(including Hafnium) was saved for multi-and single-collector ICPMS 
analysis. The U-Pb aliquots were collected in single beakers, dried down 
with a drop of 0.02 M H 3 PO 4 , and analyzed on a single outgassed zone-
refined Re filament in a Si gel emitter (45). 
Isotopic measurements were performed on an Isotopx Phoenix62 
TIMS at Princeton University. Pb was measured in dynamic mode 
on an axial ion-counting Daly photomultiplier. Dead time for the Daly 
was determined to be 40.5 ns during the period of analysis by repeated 
measurements of the NBS-981 and NBS-982 standard at up to 2.5 million 
counts per second. A correction for mass-dependent Pb fractionation 
was applied as follows. For analyses performed using the EARTHTIME </p>

<p>202 </p>

<p>Pb-205 Pb-233 U-235 U "double-Pb" tracer (L2 and residues), a cycle-by-
cycle fractionation correction was calculated from the deviation of 
measured 202 Pb/ 205 Pb from the known tracer 202 Pb/ 205 Pb [0.99924 ± 
0.00027 (1s)]. For analyses performed using the EARTHTIME 205 Pb-</p>

<p>233 </p>

<p>U-235 U "single-Pb" tracer (L1), a Pb fractionation of 0.16 ± 0.02% per 
atomic mass unit (1s) was used, as determined by repeat measurement 
of NBS-981 and NBS-982 and verified by those spiked with the double-
Pb tracer. Baseline measurements were made at each half-mass, and the 
average intensity bounding each measured peak was subtracted. Isobar-
ic interferences of BaPO 4 and Tl on sample Pb isotopes were monitored 
and corrected for by measuring masses 203 and 201. No corrections 
were applied for the L1 leachates analyzed with the EARTHTIME </p>

<p>205 </p>

<p>Pb-233 U-235 U, with the decay of mass 203 over the duration used 
as an indicator of declining isobaric interferences under all Pb masses. 
Corrections were applied to analyses using the EARTHTIME 202 Pb-</p>

<p>205 </p>

<p>Pb-233 U-235 U in the data reduction software <rs type="software">Tripoli</rs> (46), using ver-
sion 1 isotopic composition models for both species (www.earth-time. 
org). Data culling was done in this same program using the decreasing 
203/205 and the increasing 206/204 ratios over the course of an analysis. 
Depending on the sample intensities, U was measured in either static 
mode on Faraday cups on 10 12 -ohm resistors or dynamic mode on the 
Daly photomultiplier (dead time determined at 32.75 ns by repeated 
measurements of CRM U500). Uranium species were measured as 
UO 2 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, 233 UO 2 , and 235 UO 2 and were corrected for an oxygen isotopic 
composition of 0.002055 [see discussion by McLean et al. (43)]. Because </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>O/ 16 O typically grows at the beginning of an analysis before stabiliz-
ing, early blocks of data were deleted. Baselines for static analyses were 
measured at ±0.5 mass units for 30 s every 30 ratios. Correction for mass 
fractionation of U was done using the EARTHTIME 205 Pb-233 U-235 U </p>

<p>and EARTHTIME 202 Pb-205 Pb-233 U-235 U tracer solutions, assuming a 
sample 238 U/ 235 U ratio of 137.818 ± 0.021 (47). Variable 238 U/ 235 U was 
measured on Earth and meteorites, and changing the sample 238 U/ 235 U 
within those ranges can change the 207 Pb/ 206 Pb ages by several million 
years. However, this is not a significant source of uncertainty in the Hf 
model ages and therefore do not affect our age-of-moon analysis. We 
also note that uranium blanks could have a significant effect on the con-
cordance of very low U grains. However, a sensitivity test performed by 
varying the U blanks from 0.009 to 0.09 pg shows that the U blank 
composition is not important for the concordant and radiogenic grains 
that are included in the age-of-moon analysis (table S1A). 
All data reduction, error propagation, and U-Pb data plotting were 
done using the <rs type="software">U-Pb_Redux</rs> software package (48). All reported uncer-
tainties were 2s and included only internal sources of uncertainty 
(counting statistics, uncertainties in correcting for mass discrimination, 
and the uncertainty in common Pb composition). Forty procedural 
blanks spiked with the same tracers and run within a period of 3 years 
(21 of which in the course of this study) showed an amount of common 
Pb (Pbc = 0.2 to 13.9 pg; average, 3.6 pg) that agreed well with that found 
in zircon analyses; therefore, all common Pb was assumed to be derived 
from procedural blanks. The composition of the 40 spiked blanks is as 
follows: 206 Pb/ 204 Pb = 18.44 ± 0.18, 207 Pb/ 204 Pb = 15.53 ± 0.18, and </p>

<p>208 </p>

<p>Pb/ 204 Pb = 37.38 ± 0.53 (2s SD); these uncertainties were propagated 
into each U-Pb analysis. Data are presented in table S1 (A and B). U-Pb 
results show that L1 and some of L2 analyses had low radiogenic-to-
common Pb ratios and were discordant (table S1B), whereas most of the 
residues and L2 have high radiogenic-to-common Pb ratios and are 
concordant (table S1A). This illustrates that the chemical abrasion tech-
nique efficiently removed portion of grains that were affected by Pb loss. 
Hf measurements were performed only on the most concordant grains (ta-
bles S1A and S3), which are plotted on Fig. 1 in a traditional concordia plot. </p>

<p>Hf isotope analytical procedure 
Hf isotopic compositions were determined for the eight zircon residues 
and three of the L2 (14163_z86_L2, 14163_z59_L2, and 14163_z52_L2) 
aliquots that were separated during the TIMS U-Pb chemistry procedure 
(showing concordance or near concordance; see above and Fig. 1). 
Analyses were made by solution of MC-ICPMS on the ThermoFinnigan 
Neptune at UCLA using a Cetac "Aridus II" desolvating nebulizer. 
Analyses were done without matrix purification following the analytical 
protocol of D'Abzac et al. (49). Analytical parameters were summarized 
in table S2, and data were presented in table S3 (A and B). Ions were 
collected from masses 171, 173, 174, 175, 176, 177, 178, 179, and 181 
simultaneously in nine Faraday cups (10 11 -ohm resistors) to perform 
peak stripping of the interfering masses ( 176 Yb + and 176 Lu + with </p>

<p>176 </p>

<p>Hf + ). Blanks were measured before every lunar zircon analysis after 
washing the line for 6 min and were subtracted from the sample counts. 
The amount of 176 Yb + subtracted from the total signal at mass 176 was 
calculated cycle by cycle from the 171 Yb + intensity corrected for mass 
fractionation and assuming a normal 176 Yb/ 171 Yb ratio [0.901821 
(50)]. Similarly, the amount of 176 Lu + to be stripped was calculated 
from the measured 175 Lu + , normalized to 176 Lu/ 175 Lu [0.026549 (50)]. 
Instrumental mass bias correction for Yb and Hf (b Yb and b Hf ) was 
internally calculated cycle by cycle from the measured 173 Yb/ 171 Yb and </p>

<p>179 </p>

<p>Hf/ 177 Hf ratios using the exponential fractionation law. b Lu was 
determined by multiple analyses of the NIST 3130a Lu standard so-
lution, which we doped with Zr to match our solutions; variations in b Lu 
accounted for changes of &lt;0.1 e in 176 Hf/ 177 Hf and were therefore neg-
ligible. Data are presented in table S3A. </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Barboni et al. Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602365 </p>

<p>
To test the accuracy of the peak stripping procedure, we performed 
multiple analyses of three dissolved natural zircon standards [AS3, 
91500, and Mudtank (51)], four dissolved synthetic zircons variably 
doped with REE [MUNZirc 0, 1, 3, and 4 (52)], and the SPEX-1 Hf 
solution from CertiPrep. These samples covered a large range in Lu/ 
Hf and Yb/Hf (0 to 0.098 and 0 to 0.645, respectively), up to values 
matching the ratios of the lunar zircons. Five standards were run at the 
start of each analysis session, several more were interspersed between 
lunar zircon measurements, and five were again measured at the end 
of the session. Standard analyses are presented in table S3B. Our 
measured mean value of 176 Hf/ 177 Hf for all the standards was offset 
by an average of −0.54 ± 0.18 e from the published values. Because 
this offset was constant for all the standard zircons, we corrected all 
measured 176 Hf/ 177 Hf for this factor after peak stripping. That there 
was no remaining systematic error due to the peak stripping can be 
seen in fig. S1, which shows that all standard zircons plot within the 
error of their respective 176 Hf/ 177 Hf values (expected values from liter-
ature) even with the magnitude of the 176 Yb + interference varying by 
four orders of magnitude. Because our standards encompassed the 
full range of Yb/Hf concentrations seen in the Apollo 14 zircons, we 
were confident of the accuracy of the 176 Hf/ 177 Hf determinations within 
the stated precision. The reproducibility of ~0.2 e measured for the 
standards was propagated in our uncertainties on the Apollo samples 
(see section below). Additional tests were performed to check for errors 
arising from low-intensity signals by diluting concentrations of standards 
to match the lowest intensities we observed in the lunar samples (see 
table S3B). No systematic effects were found outside of quoted uncertain-
ties. We finally note that D'Abzac et al. (49) reported significant impact 
of Yb oxides on the peak-stripped 176 Hf/ 177 Hf ratios due to the changing 
mass fractionation exponent, b Yb . We did not observe such effects in 
our analytical session and believed that this difference is attributable 
to the different behavior of the cones (53), as D'Abzac et al. (49) used 
the "jet" skimmer cone, whereas we used the "x" cones. </p>

<p>Model age calculation 
Lu-Hf parameters and model age calculation. 
We used the Lu-Hf parameters for CHUR, as recently determined by 
Iizuka et al. (26), with a best solar system initial value of 176 Hf/ 177 Hf = 
0.279781 ± 0.000018, and took the decay constant for 176 Lu determined 
by Scherer et al. (29) (l 176Lu = 1.867 × 10 −11 year −1 ). Each zircon was 
corrected for the ingrowth of 176 Hf over the age of the zircon due to the 
small amount of 176 Lu incorporated in the zircon by using the zircon U-Pb 
age determined by TIMS and the measured zircon Lu/Hf. The Lu/Hf ratios 
were determined for every zircon and leachate by analyses of the remain-
ing solution after Hf isotope measurements. These analyses were con-
ducted at Princeton University on a ThermoFinnigan Element 2 
ICPMS and with a 2% standard reproducibility (six analyses of MUNZirc 
3 standard solution), which was propagated into the overall uncertainties 
(see section below). Individual model ages for each zircon can be 
calculated by passing a line through the measured data point using 
a slope based on an estimated 176 Lu /177 Hf of the source and finding 
the intersection with the chondritic evolution line (CHUR). As stated in 
the text, we chose to calculate the model ages using 176 Lu/ 177 Hf source = 0 
to model the most extreme fractionation possible for the reservoir and 
get the absolute minimum ages for its closure (diagram of 176 Hf/ 177 Hf 
versus age showing the two-step model age calculation presented in 
fig. S2). Taking the higher Lu/Hf ratios yields older model ages (fig. S3). 
We present the minimum age for the Moon as permitted by the Lu/Hf 
system. One zircon residue (14163 z86) yields an e 176 Hf(t) that is </p>

<p>apparently lower than the solar system initial (Figs. 3 and 4), but note 
that its great uncertainty, due to the small size of the grain, overlaps 
allowed solar system values. This zircon was not included in the average 
model age of 4.51 Gy. Data are presented in table S3A. 
pMELTS modeling. 
It has been suggested that the Apollo zircons crystallized from KREEP. 
We performed <rs type="software">pMELTS</rs> simulations (31) using the <rs type="software">alphaMELTS</rs> 
interface (32) to model the crystallization of KREEP and the evolution 
of the Lu/Hf ratio to the last residual melt present in the KREEP reser-
voir. We assumed closed system crystallization under isobaric condition 
(5 kbar was chosen for our runs), regulated by the QFM-5 (iron-wustite) 
and QFM-4 oxygen fugacity buffer. We used a starting liquid equivalent 
to the KREEP whole-rock composition reported by Warren (54) and 
the KREEP Lu and Hf abundances reported by Neal and Kramer 
(55). We used the modal phases predicted by <rs type="software">pMELTS</rs> together with 
partition coefficients from the earthref.org database to model the evo-
lution of 176 Lu/ 177 Hf with decreasing melt content and observed that 
this ratio quickly becomes &lt;0.01 below 50% melt and &lt;0.001 in the last 
fraction melt (fig. S4), suggesting that the Moon can have a low 176 Lu/ </p>

<p>177 </p>

<p>Hf source reservoir. 
Effect of neutron capture on the Hf isotopic ratios. 
Neutron capture can shift initial 176 Hf/ 177 Hf ratios by several e units, 
depending on exposure conditions (duration and energy). The most sig-
nificant reactions affecting the Hf isotope ratios are 177 Hf(n,g) 178 Hf and </p>

<p>178 </p>

<p>Hf(n,g) 179 Hf (23, 24). The problem that neutron capture creates for 
e 176 Hf determination is primarily in the mass bias correction because 
neutron capture can produce an elevated 179 Hf/ 177 Hf (23). We mea-
sured 178 Hf/ 177 Hf in the Apollo zircons and observed offsets up to 
2.14 e from the terrestrial value (56). We corrected for these effects using 
the data and procedure of Sprung et al. (23), and this correction resulted 
in shifts between 0 and 5.6 e 176 Hf(t) on the Apollo 14 zircons. We 
fitted the shift in e 176 Hf(t) of the lunar basalt data reported by Sprung 
et al. (23) versus the offset in e 178 Hf with a linear regression and applied 
it to our zircon data. 
Error propagation. 
Each analysis was reduced on a cycle-by-cycle basis for instrumental 
effects (that is, mass fractionation and peak stripping) through boot-
strapping (57). That is to say, we used the following procedure for each 
sample: (i) We resampled the 80 cycles with replacement (duplicates 
are allowed); (ii) We corrected each cycle for interfering masses and 
mass fractionation; (iii) We averaged the final isotope ratios; (iv) We 
repeated steps (i) to (iii) 10,000 times and saved the average of this 
grand data set and its SD. Once each analysis was corrected for 
instrumental/analytical effects, we corrected each sample for neutron 
exposure, 176 Hf ingrowth, and the −0.47 e 176 Hf offset from our standard 
analyses. Each uncertainty (including uncertainties on neutron capture, 
Lu/Hf measurements, and standard analyses) was incorporated using 
bootstrap resampling; that is, we randomly sampled a measured value 
for each sample as well as that for any correction and repeated the pro-
cedure 10,000 times to calculate the final uncertainty. Our approach is anal-
ogous to using a Monte Carlo procedure to propagate the uncertainties. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS </p>

<p>Supplementary material for this article is available at http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/ 
content/full/3/1/e1602365/DC1 
fig. S1. 176 Hf/ 177 Hf ratios normalized to the expected (present-day) value for standard zircons 
versus the magnitude of the peak stripping due to interfering Yb, measured as 173 Yb + / 177 Hf + . 
fig. S2. Initial 176 Hf/ 177 Hf of Apollo 14 zircons versus absolute time (My) and time after the start 
of the solar system [calcium-and aluminum-rich inclusions (CAIs)] in millions of years. </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Barboni et al. Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602365 </p>

<p>
fig. S3. Hf model age variations depending on the 176 Lu/ 177 Hf ratios for the source. 
fig. S4. KREEP 176 Lu/ 177 Hf evolutions through decreasing melt percent, as given by pMELTS 
simulations. 
table S1A. U-Pb isotopic data (zircons also measured for Hf isotope composition and used for 
the determination of the age of the Moon). 
table S1B. U-Pb isotopic data (zircons not measured for Hf isotope composition). 
table S2. Tuning parameters of the coupled Cetac "Aridus II" and ThermoFinnigan Neptune 
MC-ICPMS. 
table S3A. Hf isotopic data and model age calculations for lunar zircons. 
table S3B. Summary of Hf isotopes measured on terrestrial standards. 
References (58, 59) </p>



<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Barboni et al. Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602365 </p>



<p>
S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Barboni et al. Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602365 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>