<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5300861" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p> 
www.rde.ac </p>

<p>Risk difference, risk ratio, and odds ratio as measures of effects in cohort design </p>

<p>A cohort study design pursues the effect of exposure such as treatment, prospectively. In the cohort study, we extract an 
adequate size of a random sample from the target population, then randomly assign the subjects into either the expose 
group or unexposed group. The effect of exposure is observed as the changes in outcome of interest over time. Risk is easily 
calculated as the number of persons having the disease in exposed and unexposed groups divided by the number of all the 
persons in both groups. In the cohort study, we have a clear denominator: the number of persons assigned in the groups. 
RD and RR are frequently used to assess the association between the exposed and control groups. RD, which is also known 
as AR or excessive risk, represents the amount of risk, which decreased or increased when the exposure exists compared to 
that when the exposure is absent. A positive RD value means increased risk and a negative one means decreased risk by the 
exposure. RR is calculated as the risk of an exposed group divided by the risk of an unexposed group. A RR value of 1 means 
no difference in risk between groups, and larger or smaller values mean increased or decreased risk in an exposed group 
compared to the risk in an unexposed group, which can be interpreted that the occurrence of disease is more or less likely 
in the exposed group, respectively. 
In addition, we can also use OR for the same purpose in cohort studies. OR is the ratio of odds of disease in an exposed 
group and an unexposed group. The interpretation OR is not as intuitive as RR. An OR value of 1 means no difference in 
odds between groups, and larger value than 1 means increased odds in exposed group, interpreted as a positive association 
between having disease and having exposure. Contrarily an OR value of smaller than 1 means decreased odds in exposed 
group which is interpreted as the association between having disease and not having exposure. Though the interpretation 
of OR is similar to that of RR, they have similar values only when risks of both groups are very low, e.g., p &lt; 0.1. Otherwise, 
they show different values. As seen in Table 2, the values of RR and OR are approximately the same only when risk of both 
groups are very low (p &lt; 0.1, Examples 1 -5 in Table 2). However, when risks of either one or both groups are not very low 
(p &gt; 0.1), there are considerable discrepancy between RR and OR values (Examples 6 -14, Table 2). A general rule is that a 
value of OR is always reflecting larger effect size or stronger association, by showing smaller OR values than corresponding 
RR values when RR &lt; 1 and larger OR values when RR &gt; 1. In Table 2, we can confirm that all the cases with RR larger than 
1 had much larger OR values (Examples 6 -8 and 10 -14), and a case with RR smaller than 1 had a smaller OR value than 
the corresponding RR value (Example 9). Therefore, incorrect interpretation of OR value as RR will lead to an overstatement 
of the effect by either erroneously increasing or decreasing the true risks. Figure 1 depicts that the differences between OR 
and RR values get larger as the levels of baseline risk in the control group (I 0 ) increase. 
1 Especially when baseline risk is as 
large as 0.5, the maximum RR value is confined to 2, while OR value approaches infinity. </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of risk difference, risk ratio, and odds ratio based on risks (p) and odds of two competitive groups (assume 
n = 1,000 per group) </p>

<p>No. of event 
Risk (p) 
Odds 
Risk 
difference </p>

<p>Risk 
ratio </p>

<p>Odds 
ratio </p>

<p>Example 
Control 
Tx. 
Control (1) Tx. (2) Control (3) Tx. (4) 
(2) -(1) (2) / (1) (4) / (3) </p>

<p>1 
1 
2 
0.001 
0.002 
0.001 
0.002 
0.001 
2.000 
2.000 
2 
5 
10 
0.005 
0.010 
0.005 
0.010 
0.005 
2.000 
2.000 
3 
10 
20 
0.010 
0.020 
0.010 
0.020 
0.010 
2.000 
2.000 
4 
15 
30 
0.015 
0.030 
0.015 
0.031 
0.015 
2.000 
2.067 
5 
50 
100 
0.050 
0.100 
0.053 
0.111 
0.050 
2.000 
2.096 
6 
100 
200 
0.100 
0.200 
0.111 
0.250 
0.100 
2.000 
2.252 
7 
200 
400 
0.200 
0.400 
0.250 
0.667 
0.200 
2.000 
2.668 
8 
200 
700 
0.200 
0.700 
0.250 
2.333 
0.500 
3.500 
9.333 
9 
500 
200 
0.500 
0.200 
1.000 
0.250 
-0.300 
0.400 
0.250 
10 
500 
600 
0.500 
0.600 
1.000 
1.500 
0.100 
1.200 
1.500 
11 
500 
700 
0.500 
0.700 
1.000 
2.333 
0.200 
1.400 
2.333 
12 
500 
990 
0.500 
0.990 
1.000 
99.00 
0.490 
1.980 
99.00 
13 
900 
950 
0.900 
0.950 
9.000 
19.00 
0.050 
1.060 
2.111 
14 
998 
999 
0.998 
0.999 
499.0 
999.0 
0.001 
1.001 
2.002 </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5395/rde.2017.42.1.72 </p>



<p>www.rde.ac </p>

<p>Kim HY </p>

<p>OR has been used as a very popular estimate of effect in epidemiological studies. As the logistic regression has been 
frequently used in multivariate assessment of binary outcomes, OR which is the exponentiated regression coefficient from 
logistic regression has been popular, too. The logistic regression has a computational advantage that the convergence is 
efficient because the related logit link can convert risk (p) values, confined from 0 to 1, into log odds values ranging from 
negative infinity to positive infinity. Fortunately, lots of life-threatening diseases tend to have very low risk (or prevalence), 
e.g., lower than 0.1, therefore use of OR can be justified as a good estimator of RR. However, when we analyze data of 
prevalent diseases such as dental caries or periodontitis, we need to be careful not to interpret the strong association by OR 
as if it is by RR. Because the OR value is far from 1 than the corresponding RR value when the disease is not rare, to avoid 
possible mistake of overstating the effect, the resulting OR value can be converted into RR using following equation only 
when baseline risk can be appropriately assumed: </p>

<p>RR = 
OR 
1 -I 0 * (1 -OR) 
, where I 0 is baseline risk of control group. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>When the outcome is not rare, Poisson regression or log-binomial model are preferred to obtain RR instead of logistic 
regression. </p>

<p>Odds ratio as the measure of effects in case-control designs </p>

<p>When we are interested in a disease that is very rare, implementing a study with a cohort design is disadvantageous because 
not only it requires a long observation period and high cost but also it is very difficult to get sufficient information on 
occurrence of the disease. Case-control design offers a more efficient alternative in such a situation. In case-control design, 
subjects were selected from disease and no disease groups separately. The sample size of control group without disease is 
determined as appropriate, only considering the sample size of disease group. Therefore, there is no denominator which is 
needed to calculate a risk because information on the entire population is not collected. Computing both risk (p) and RR is 
impossible in the case-control design. 
However, odds and OR, ratio of odds in exposed and unexposed group, can be easily obtained in this design. When the 
disease is very rare, we can use OR as an approximation of RR. Also different size of no disease group is applicable as the 
study design is needed. Table 3 shows the value of RR can be easily changed by only arbitrarily changing the size of no 
disease group from 1.91 to 1.98, while OR shows consistency having the same value of 2. Therefore, you should not use 
risk or RR inappropriately in studies with case-control design. When the outcome of interest has very low prevalence, OR 
calculated in case-control studies can be used as an approximation of RR. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Relationship between odds ratio and relative risk at various levels of baseline risks in the control group (I 0 = 0.5, 
0.3, 0.2, 0.1, 0.05, and 0.01). 
1 I 0 , baseline risk of control group. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Odds ratio </p>

<p>Relative risk </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 </p>

<p>I 0 = 0.5 
I 0 = 0.2 </p>

<p>I 0 = 0.3 
I 0 = 0.1 </p>

<p>I 0 = 0.05 </p>

<p>I 0 = 0.01 </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5395/rde.2017.42.1.72 </p>

<p> 
www.rde.ac </p>

<p>The procedure of obtaining OR and RR using <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS Statistics</rs> for <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Windows Version 23.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA</rs>) </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of odds ratio (OR) and relative risk (RR) in two case-control designs with different size of no disease group </p>

<p>Disease 
No disease 
Total 
Disease 
No disease 
Total 
Exposure 
10 
100 
110 
Exposure 
10 
500 
510 
No exposure 
5 
100 
105 
No exposure 
5 
500 
505 
OR = (10/100) / (5/100) = 2.00 
OR = (10/500) / (5/500) = 2.00 
RR = (10/110) / (5/105) = 1.91 
RR = (10/510) / (5/505) = 1.98 </p>

<p>(a) Data (weight by freq) </p>

<p>(b) Analyze-Descriptive Statistics-Crosstabs 
(b-1) Statistics 
(b-2) Cells </p>

<p>(c) Crosstable 
(d) OR (95% CI) and RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5395/rde.2017.42.1.72 </p>



<p>www.rde.ac </p>



</text></tei>