<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5036010" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objective: To explore whether information regarding potentially alcohol-related health incidents 
recorded in electronic patient records might aid in earlier identification of alcohol use disorders. 
Design: We extracted potentially alcohol-related information in electronic patient records and 
tested if alcohol-related diagnoses, prescriptions of codeine, tramadol, ethylmorphine, and benzo-
diazepines; elevated levels of gamma-glutamyl-transferase (GGT), and mean cell volume (MCV); 
and new sick leave certificates predicted specific alcohol use disorder. 
Setting: Nine general practitioner surgeries with varying size and stability. 
Subjects: Totally 20,764 patients with active electronic patient record until data gathering and 
with a history of at least four years without a specific alcohol use disorder after turning 18 years 
of age. 
Methods: The Cox proportional hazard analysis with time-dependent covariates of potential accu-
mulated risks over the previous four years. 
Main outcome measures: Time from inclusion until the first specific alcohol use disorder, defined 
by either an alcohol specific diagnostic code or a text fragment documenting an alcohol 
problem. 
Results: In the unadjusted and adjusted Cox-regression with time-dependent covariates all varia-
bles were highly significant with adjusted hazard ratios ranging from 1.25 to 3.50. Addictive 
drugs, sick leaves, GGT, MCV and International Classification for Primary Care version 2 (ICPC-2), 
and International Classification of Diseases version 10 (ICD-10) diagnoses were analyzed. Elevated 
GGT and MCV, ICD-10-diagnoses, and gender demonstrated the highest hazard ratios. 
Conclusions: Many frequent health problems are potential predictors of an increased risk or vul-
nerability for alcohol use disorders. However, due to the modest hazard ratios, we were unable 
to establish a clinically useful tool. </p>

<p>KEY POINTS </p>

<p>Alcohol is potentially relevant for many health problems, but current strategies for identifica-
tion and intervention in primary health care have not been successful. 
Many frequent clinical problems recorded in electronic patient records may indicate an 
increased risk for alcohol related health problems. 
The hazard ratios were modest and the resulting predictive model was unsatisfactory for diag-
nostic purposes. If we accepted a sensitivity as low as 0.50, the specificity slightly exceeded 
0.75. With a low prevalent condition, it is obvious that the false positive problem will be vast. 
In addition to responding to elevated blood levels of liver enzymes, general practitioners 
should be aware of alcohol as a potentially relevant factor for patients with repeated events of 
many mental and psychosocial diagnoses and new sick leaves and repeated prescriptions of 
addictive drugs. </p>

<p>ARTICLE HISTORY </p>

<p>General practitioners (GPs) as health care providers for 
the general public are important actors in dealing with 
alcohol-related health problems.[1] The link between </p>

<p>alcohol consumption and numerous health problems is 
strong, and earlier identification of risky or harmful 
drinking is regarded essential, both in public health 
terms and for the individual patient.[2-4] The preferred </p>

<p>CONTACT Torgeir Gilje Lid 
giljelid@gmail.com 
Rasmus Risas Gate 54, N-4015 Stavanger, Norway </p>

<p>ß 2016 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &amp; Francis Group. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>SCANDINAVIAN JOURNAL OF PRIMARY HEALTH CARE, 2016 
VOL. 34, NO. 3, 215-223 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/02813432.2016.1207138 </p>

<p>method for identification and treatment of risky or 
harmful drinking has, for the past decades, been 
screening and brief intervention (SBI), but important 
questions concerning the effectiveness of SBI in rou-
tine health care settings remain unanswered.[5,6] 
Furthermore, recent large scale implementation studies 
have failed to show effect.[7-9] 
However, it is known that GPs regard dealing with 
alcohol-related health problems a legitimate part of 
their responsibility.[10-13] The recent recognition of 
the lack of robust evidence for SBI in routine health 
care settings necessitates further research. Recently, 
approaches based on clinical relevance instead of 
screening measures have been studied.[14-16] Health 
incidents or changes in the patient's life are used as 
indicators of potential relevance for addressing alcohol. 
These have been coined as pragmatic case finding [14] 
or semi-systematic method,[15] they not only focus pri-
marily on clinical signs, but also focus on targeted 
screening in some routine situations. These strategies 
focus on the present clinical situation and the aware-
ness that alcohol may be relevant for a patient's 
health, both as a possible cause and as a complicating 
factor for their health problems. GPs struggle with ask-
ing about alcohol out of context, as in general screen-
ing, but asking based on potential relevance in a 
specific clinical situation is probably a better founda-
tion for interventions.[17,18] 
In general practice, the patient records will often 
contain information gathered through many years. 
Almost all GPs in Norway use electronic patient records 
(EPR), but the systems are not highly functional in sys-
tematizing relevant information.[19] Not only the 
patient's present health problem, but also previous 
incidents may indicate relevance for talking about 
alcohol. 
The aim of this study was to explore whether infor-
mation regarding potentially alcohol-related health 
incidents recorded in EPRs might aid in earlier recogni-
tion of alcohol related health problems. </p>

<p>Design, methods, and material </p>

<p>Nine GP surgeries in the Stavanger region in south 
west of Norway were recruited. They were chosen on 
the basis of maximal variety in size (1-7 doctors) and 
stability (high turnover to high stability), and all had 
applied EPR for at least 10 years. The total number of 
doctors was 36. All 20,764 patients with an active EPR 
(alive and registered with a doctor the month prior to 
data gathering) were included. Gender, year of birth, 
name of registered doctor and surgery were registered, </p>

<p>and the patients were given a unique, non-reversible 
eight-digit code with letters and numbers. After com-
pletion of data gathering, the eight-digit code was 
replaced and the patients were consecutively num-
bered. Doctors and surgeries were also numbered. 
A vast majority of GP surgeries in the region at that 
time used the same EPR system, and a computer 
program designed to extract data from records in this 
system was made. We tested a pilot version of the 
computer program in the largest surgery during March 
2011, and then an automatized version was tested and 
applied a few months later. 
We extracted data that might be alcohol-related to 
test these data against comprehensive alcohol use dis-
order (c-AUD) as endpoint. C-AUD was defined as 
either an alcohol use disorder (AUD) according to 
ICPC-2 or ICD-10 [3,4] or a text fragment (AUD text 
fragment) documenting that an alcohol problem was 
dealt with. In Norway, ICPC-2 is applied in general 
practice, whereas the specialized health care system 
applies ICD-10. ICD-10-diagnoses for AUD were trans-
lated to ICPC-2 in 2010 applying standardized 
tables,[20] in order to identify ICPC-2-diagnoses for 
AUD. The diagnostic codes in ICD-10 are more specific 
(three to four figures) compared to ICPC-2 (two fig-
ures), thus to retain the specificity of AUD in ICD-10 
we used the corresponding ICPC-2-code solely if ''alco-
hol'' was included in the text-field of the ICPC-2-diag-
nosis. See Appendix A for all diagnoses included 
in AUD. 
Clinical experience indicates that the threshold for 
identifying an AUD with a formal diagnosis may be 
high in general practice. We wanted to include as out-
come situations where an AUD was documented in 
the running text of the EPR, but where no formal diag-
nosis was made. We identified the word ''alcohol'' in 
the running text, either alone or as a compound word 
(in Norwegian compound words are frequently used 
when the English expression would contain two or 
three words, e.g., ''alkoholmisbruk'', English: alcohol 
abuse). Compound words highly indicative of an AUD 
were defined as an AUD text fragment. All versions of 
compound words containing ''alcohol'' were assessed 
manually and either defined as an AUD text fragment 
or not. The validity of this AUD text fragment was 
tested by performing a second data collection in one 
surgery to explore the context of the AUD text frag-
ment by manually assessing a 12 word text fragment 
with the compound word with ''alcohol'' in the middle. 
This was done for a three-year period (January 2001 to 
December 2003) in one of the surgeries of medium 
size. We found 102 fragments which had been defined 
as AUD text fragments, and for 20 of these (20%) it </p>

<p> 
T. G. LID ET AL. </p>

<p>was evident that the alcohol problem in question was 
someone else's, most frequently a parent. We also 
identified 171 text fragments with ''alcohol'' originally 
not identified as an AUD text fragment. Of these, as 
many as 105 (60%) dealt with a real alcohol problem 
for the patient. Many of the patients had several such 
text fragments. This suggests that our method of defin-
ing an AUD text fragment is more prone to underesti-
mate than overestimate the prevalence of an AUD. 
The term c-AUD was defined as either an AUD or an 
AUD text fragment or both and used as outcome for 
the analyses. Censoring date was defined as the first of 
the month prior to data gathering, or the last predictor 
event if more recent. Start of follow-up (t ¼ 0) for all 
patients were defined after an observation period of 
four years free from c-AUD in the record. 
Predictors were firstly potentially alcohol-related 
ICD-10-diagnoses with attributable fractions larger than 
0.3.[3,4] These diagnoses were translated to ICPC-2, 
with a consequently lower precision level due to the 
wider categories of ICPC-2. We included other ICPC-
2-diagnoses where there is evidence of a potential 
causal relation with alcohol consumption.[15,21,22] See 
Appendix A for all diagnoses used as predictor events. 
Other predictors were number of new sick leaves, non-
narcotic controlled substances (class B-drugs in 
Norway) and elevated blood levels for GGT and 
MCV.[23-26] A new sick leave was defined as a full 
time (not partial) sick leave with at least 16 days since 
a previous sick leave. Class B-drugs were the non-
narcotic controlled substances codeine, tramadol, eth-
ylmorphine, and benzodiazepines, including z-drugs. 
Gender was included as predictor. 
All patients had a total history of 4-21 years, and all 
had an active patient record until data collection. For 
patients with a record prior to the age of 18, their 
observation period started from 1 January, the year 
they turned 18. Observations stopped at the age of 
80 years. All readable data in the EPRs were scanned 
by the program, including incoming reports. </p>

<p>Statistical methods </p>

<p>For descriptive statistics, we used mean, median, and 
range. Correlations were estimated by Spearman's 
rho.[27] Time from inclusion to c-AUD was analyzed 
applying the Cox proportional hazards model [28] 
including time-dependent covariates.[29,30] The covari-
ate values were updated at each time point for the fol-
lowing types of predictor events: B-drugs, new sick 
leaves, elevated blood levels for GGT and MCV, alco-
hol-related ICPC-2 and ICD-10 diagnoses. Thus, the fol-
lowing variables were included in the Cox-regression </p>

<p>models: gender, number of new sick leaves, number of 
prescriptions of class B drugs, number of elevated GGT 
and MCV levels, number of alcohol-related ICD-10 diag-
noses and number of alcohol-related ICPC-2 diagnoses. 
To do the analyses, the data file was organized in 
long format with one line per event date and varying 
number of lines per patient. Both simple and multiple 
Cox-regression were run. Results are reported as 
unadjusted and adjusted hazard ratios (HR), respect-
ively, with 95% confidence intervals (CI) and p values 
from Wald tests. The analyses were done using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Stata</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">13</rs> (College Station, TX) and all predictors were 
reported per 10 predictor events. We excluded from 
the model predictor events more than four years prior 
to the present predictor event.[31] Predictor events 
prior to t ¼ 0 were summed up and added to the 
events, however they were also gradually excluded 
during the first four years after t ¼ 0. 
From the final multiple Cox-regression model, a 
prognostic index was defined equal to the fitter linear 
predictor equation in the model. Receiver operator 
characteristics (ROC) of this index was evaluated 
against the patients' c-AUD status four years after each 
update of the index (i.e., new predictor event) by cal-
culating sensitivity and specificity and plotting the cor-
responding ROC curve.[27] </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The 20,764 patients, 43% of which were males, had fol-
low-up times of up to 17.0 years after t ¼ 0, with a 
median of 12.5 years (Table 1). The maximum number 
of events for each predictor is very high, though the 
medians are low, demonstrating that most patients 
have a small number of events for each predictor. 
2.9% of the patients had a positive end point (c-AUD), 
of which 53.3% male. When splitting up, we found that 
43% of these had an AUD (1.3% of all patients, 67.9% </p>

<p>Table 1. Descriptive statistics for n ¼ 20,764 patients from 
nine general practice surgeries in the Stavanger area in 
Norway accrued from March to August of 2011. </p>

<p>Variables 
Mean 
Median 
Range </p>

<p>Follow-up time, years 
6.5 
12.5 
0.0-17.0 
Age at start of follow-up, years 
43.4 
42.0 
22-79 
Born 
1956 
1957 
1916-1988 
No. of predictor events 
Class B drugs 
28.6 
5 
0-774 
New sick leave 
5.9 
3 
0-143 
Elevated laboratory test 
0.7 
0 
0-66 
ICD-10-diagnoses 
0.3 
0 
0-50 
ICPC-2-diagnoses 
2.4 
1 
0-130 
Cumulative predictor events 
37.8 
16 
0-870 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ICD-10: International Classification of Diseases, version 10; 
ICPC-2: International Classification of Primary Care, version 2. </p>

<p>SCANDINAVIAN JOURNAL OF PRIMARY HEALTH CARE </p>

<p>
male), whereas 57% had only AUD text fragment (1.6% 
of all patients, 41.1% male). 
In the simple Cox-regression, all variables were sig-
nificant, and only class B prescriptions and gender had 
an HR lower than 2 per 10 events (Table 2). In the 
adjusted Cox-regression the HR was highest for ele-
vated blood tests for GGT and MCV with 3.5 per 10 
events, and just below 2 for ICD-10 diagnoses, gender, 
and new sick leaves. All variables were highly signifi-
cant. The lowest estimates were class B drugs and 
ICPC-2 diagnoses. 
We made a prognostic index from all significant 
regression coefficients in the adjusted model. ROC of 
this index compared to status four years later gave a 
fairly modest area under the curve (AUC) of 0.72 </p>

<p>(Figure 1).[32,33] The curve reveals that with a sensitiv-
ity of 0.5, the corresponding specificity is slightly 
above 0.75. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our findings show that repeated incidents of many 
common clinical problems in general practice repre-
sent an increased risk of identifying an AUD later on, 
but the results are not strong enough to enable the 
development of a clinically relevant identification strat-
egy. Elevated blood tests of GGT and MCV, new sick 
leaves, prescriptions of class B drugs, and a wide var-
iety of diagnoses were significantly associated with 
increased risk of a future AUD, though the HRs were 
fairly modest. All predictors represent frequent inci-
dents in general practice, where the patient trajectories 
often are long. </p>

<p>Sample and methods </p>

<p>In this study, we have included all patients who had 
an active EPR until data collection and for at least four 
years after they turned 18 years of age instead of col-
lecting data on a sample of eligible patients. This 
ensures realistic data. The variables were chosen with 
adults in mind, and data prior to the year they turned 
18 was therefore not included in the material. In old 
age, the number of health problems rapidly increase, </p>

<p>Table 2. Results from Cox regression of alcohol use disorder 
with time-dependent covariates for 20,764 patients from nine 
general practice surgeries in the Stavanger area in Norway 
accrued from March to August of 2011. </p>

<p>Unadjusted estimates 
Adjusted estimates </p>

<p>Variables 
HR 
95% CI 
p 
HR 
95% CI 
p </p>

<p>Gender (male) 
1.71 (1.46, 2.01) &lt;0.001 1.94 (1.65, 2.29) &lt;0.001 
No. of predictor events 
Class B drugs a 
1.27 (1.24, 1.31) &lt;0.001 1.25 (1.21, 1.28) &lt;0.001 
New sick leave a 
2.16 (1.81, 2.58) &lt;0.001 1.81 (1.50, 2.19) &lt;0.001 
Elevated lab test a 3.62 (2.93, 4.46) &lt;0.001 3.50 (2.79, 4.39) &lt;0.001 
ICD-10-diagnoses a 2.51 (1.51, 4.18) &lt;0.029 2.00 (1.07, 3.72) 0.009 
ICPC-2-diagnoses a 2.29 (2.01, 2.61) 0.001 1.43 (1.16, 1.78) 0.002 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: HR: hazard ratio; CI: confidence interval; ICD-10: 
International Classification of Diseases, version 10; ICPC-2: International 
Classification of Primary Care, version 2. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Per 10 predictor events. </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>0.00 
0.25 
0.50 
0.75 
1.00 </p>

<p>1 -Specificity </p>

<p>Area under ROC curve = 0.7157 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Receiver operator characteristics (ROC) curve for prognostic index (gender, elevated lab tests, class B-drugs, new sick 
leaves, and alcohol-related ICPC-2 and ICD-10 diagnoses), for n ¼ 16,814 patients from the Stavanger area in Norway, for compre-
hensive alcohol use disorder. Abbreviations: ICD-10: International Classification of Diseases, version 10; ICPC-2: International 
Classification of Primary Care, version 2. </p>

<p> 
T. G. LID ET AL. </p>

<p>and collecting data for the prediction of future health 
problems is less relevant. 
Other data from the EPRs than the chosen variables 
were not collected, apart from gender, year of birth, 
doctor and surgery, and first and last entry in the EPR. 
We chose to exclude predictor events more than four 
years prior to a predictor event, because recent events 
in a patient's life, documented in the EPR, probably 
have a higher impact on present health. This view was 
supported by the fact that the HRs were lower when 
performing Cox-regressions without exclusion of pre-
dictor events more than four years prior (analyses not 
shown). </p>

<p>Significance of the results </p>

<p>We wanted to explore whether clinical information, as 
recorded in the EPR, might aid the doctors in establish-
ing relevance for addressing alcohol. Several HRs were 
around 2, though the analyses were done per 10 pre-
dictor events. But the number of such events for a 
patient may be very high, and all predictors represent 
frequent clinical problems in general practice. Many 
different kinds of events sum up the risk as the model 
indicates. Our validation of the AUD text fragment indi-
cated that our definition of c-AUD is underestimating 
the diagnosis. 
Gender was more strongly associated with AUD 
than with c-AUD, indicating a lower threshold for 
applying a specific diagnosis to a recognized alcohol 
problem if the patient is male. A gender difference in 
SBI is also described in a Cochrane review, but whether 
the gender difference is primarily caused by identifica-
tion or treatment differences is not known.[5,34] 
Elevated blood levels of GGT and MCV is a recognized 
starting point for alcohol talks in general practice, and 
their relevance has been tested in previous stud-
ies.[14,24,35] Such changes are late effects of too high 
alcohol consumption, and many psychosocial problems 
may occur much earlier.[15,36] We found low estimate 
for ICPC-2 diagnoses, perhaps because this is a com-
posite variable, composed by converted diagnoses 
from ICD-10,[3,4] pragmatic case finding,[14] and early 
clinical signs [15] (Appendix A). 
The AUC of the ROC-curve was fairly modest, and 
the direct clinical relevance is modest. We have chosen 
to exclude predictor events more than four years prior 
to the present event. Previous events sum up and con-
stitute an ever increasing risk, but previous difficulties 
and problems are also overcome and sometimes bal-
anced by positive experiences. While events early in 
life may have strong effects on present and future </p>

<p>health, information in the EPR will probably not be a 
strong indicator of relevant events in early lifetime.[37] 
If our choice of predictors has been adequate, the 
results indicate that using patient record data to estab-
lish a threshold value for identifying an AUD is futile 
because of lack of sensitivity and specificity. But our 
findings point to the fact that many frequent clinical 
problems normally not conceived as caused by alcohol 
consumption, over time may be related to alcohol con-
sumption. The predictor events constituting a potential 
risk, as well as the opportunities to intervene, increase 
over time in general practice. Even interventions 
with minor effect may potentially add up in the long 
run, when applied many times and for many 
patients.[38,39] 
SBI has shown a lack of diagnostic accuracy, inter-
vention efficacy, and feasibility.[8,11,17,40] Methods 
focusing on the present situation and the patient's 
problem will probably increase relevance and recogni-
tion for the patient.[14,15,18] We should bear in mind 
that alcohol use may represent attempts to master a 
challenging life as viewed from the patients' perspec-
tive.[41] An open and respectful dialogue is needed to 
explore how alcohol may be relevant for health, cop-
ing and well-being. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of the study </p>

<p>The large variety in size and stability for the surgeries 
supports external validity.[42] The extensive number of 
36 participating GPs and 20,764 patients together with 
the long observation period of 4-21 years further 
strengthens the external validity. 
Being an exploratory study in EPRs, the data is 
highly affected by everyday habits, flaws and inaccura-
cies in diagnostic work, interventions and documenta-
tion. Because of a maximum observation period of 21 
years, many doctors have been replaced over the 
years, thus several doctors may have been responsible 
for each patient's EPR. The resulting diagnostic variabil-
ity probably reduces the internal validity of the study, 
but strengthens the external validity.[42] When facing 
uncertainty, the result of the diagnostic process will 
vary greatly between doctors.[43] 
Many address alcohol and document the interven-
tions without proper diagnosis, but it is also likely that 
many interventions are not documented in the EPR. In 
addition, we have also demonstrated that c-AUD 
underestimated real alcohol problems in patients at 
least in the EPRs that were examined. Since we have 
no direct assessments of the patients, we know noth-
ing about the real prevalence of alcohol related health 
problems in the material. As the data are completely </p>

<p>SCANDINAVIAN JOURNAL OF PRIMARY HEALTH CARE </p>

<p>
anonymous, we are not able to test our data against 
registers as the Cause of Death Registry or the 
Norwegian Registry Database, nor may we trace a 
patient moving from one surgery to another. 
Sick leaves were difficult to trace uniformly by the 
data extraction software because of the extensive time 
frame, and many sick leaves, especially before 2000, 
had to be excluded. The results for sick leaves are 
therefore less robust. The composite variable of ICPC-2 
diagnoses obscures the potential relation between 
diagnoses or clusters of diagnoses and AUD. In future 
studies, ICPC-2-diagnoses should probably be grouped 
in clinically meaningful clusters in order to be able to 
detect stronger correlations than we have found. The 
screening of text fragments may also be more exten-
sively utilized in further studies, to explore relations 
between alcohol-related health problems and different 
clinical situations described but not diagnoses in the 
EPR. </p>

<p>Implications </p>

<p>We have shown that many everyday health problems 
may, over time, indicate an increased risk of a future 
AUD. The variables explored in this study may be just 
as important as vulnerability factors as they are poten-
tially early signs of an alcohol-related health problem. 
Our findings emphasize the importance of asking 
about alcohol consumption in many common clinical 
situations, exemplified by the variables in this study. 
The unsatisfactory diagnostic accuracy precludes the 
development of a clinically useful tool, but this is not a 
valid objection to asking about alcohol consumption 
based on potential relevance. 
Many patients may be aware of the possible relation 
between their health problem and alcohol consump-
tion.[38] Other patients may be unaware of such a rela-
tion. A GP addressing this possible relation in an open, 
non-judgmental manner may represent one of many 
important elements in a long and winding road to per-
manent change. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We wish to express our gratitude to all doctors at the partici-
pating surgeries, and especially Asgeir Haugedal for invalu-
able support and assistance in the initial process. We also 
wish to thank Alexander Løvik Stevenson, who helped put-
ting all the gathered data together, enabling further adapta-
tion and analysis. But most of all, we wish to thank Magne 
Rekdal, who designed the software that made this project 
possible. 
Ethical approval: The study was approved by the Regional 
Committee for Medical Research Ethics. </p>

<p>Disclosure statement </p>

<p>We are aware of no real, potential or perceived conflicts of 
interest for any of the authors. </p>

<p>Funding information </p>

<p>The study was funded by Research in General Practice, 
Norwegian Medical Association, and Centre for Alcohol and 
Drug Research, Stavanger University Hospital, Norway. </p>



<p> 
T. G. LID ET AL. </p>



<p>SCANDINAVIAN JOURNAL OF PRIMARY HEALTH CARE </p>

<p>
Appendix A: Alcohol use disorders and alcohol-
related disorders in ICD-10 and ICPC-2 </p>

<p>Outcome -alcohol use disorders ICD-10 [3] </p>

<p>E24.4 Alcohol-induced pseudo-Cushing's syndrome 
F10 
Mental and behavioural disorders due to use of 
alcohol 
F10.0 Acute intoxication 
F10.00-F10.07 
F10.1 Harmful use 
F10.2 Dependence syndrome F10.20-F10.26 
F10.3 Withdrawal state 
F10.30-F10.31 
F10.4 Withdrawal state with delirium F10.40-F10.41 
F10.5 Psychotic disorder 
F10.50-F10.56 
F10.6 Amnesic syndrome 
F10.7 Residual and late onset psychotic disorder 
F10.70-F10.75 
F10.8 Other mental and behavioural disorders 
F10.9 Unspecified mental and behavioural disorder 
G31.2 Degeneration of nervous system due to alcohol 
G62.1 Alcoholic polyneuropathy 
G72.1 Alcoholic myopathy 
I42.6 
Alcoholic cardiomyopathy 
K29.2 Alcoholic gastritis 
K70 
Alcoholic liver disease 
K70.1 Alcoholic hepatitis 
K70.2 Alcoholic fibrosis and sclerosis of liver 
K70.3 Alcoholic cirrhosis of liver 
K70.4 Alcoholic hepatic failure 
K70.9 Alcoholic liver disease, unspecified 
K85.2 Alcohol-induced acute pancreatitis 
K86.0 Alcohol-induced chronic pancreatitis 
O35.4 Maternal care for (suspected) damage to fetus 
from alcohol 
P04.3 Fetus and newborn affected by maternal use of 
alcohol 
Q86.0 Fetal alcohol syndrome (dysmorphic) 
R78.0 Finding of alcohol in blood 
T51 
Toxic effect of alcohol 
T51.0 Ethanol 
T51.1 Methanol 
T51.9 Alcohol unspecified 
X45 
Accidental poisoning by and exposure to alcohol 
X65 
Intentional self-poisoning by and exposure to 
alcohol 
Y15 
Poisoning by and exposure to alcohol, undeter-
mined intent </p>

<p>Outcome -Alcohol use disorders ICPC-2. Converted 
from ICD-10 [3] </p>

<p>P15 
Chronic alcohol abuse 
P16 
Acute alcohol abuse 
A23* Risk factor NOS 
A86* Toxic effect non-medicinal substance 
A90* Congenital anomaly nos/multiple 
A99* Disease/condition of unspecified nature/site 
D87* Stomach function disorders 
D97* Liver disease NOS 
D99* Disease digestive system other 
K84* Heart disease other 
N94* Peripheral neuritis/neuropathy </p>

<p>*Only when the word 'alcohol' in different versions is 
included in the diagnostic text </p>

<p>Predictor events -Alcohol-related diagnoses, 
ICD-10 [3] </p>

<p>C00-C14 
Malignant neoplasms of lip, oral cavity and 
pharynx 
C15 
Malignant neoplasm of esophagus 
C32 
Malignant neoplasm of larynx 
G40-G41 
Epilepsy and status epilepticus 
I10-I15 
Hypertensive diseases 
I47-I48 
Cardiac arrhythmias 
I60-I62, 
Hemorrhagic stroke 
I85 
Esophageal varices 
K22.6 
Gastro-oesophageal laceration-haemorrhage 
syndrome 
K73, K74 
Liver cirrhosis 
K85, K86.1 
Acute and chronic pancreatitis 
L40 exl L40.5 Psoriasis 
O03 
Spontaneous abortion </p>

<p>Predictor events -Alcohol-related diagnoses, ICPC-
2. Converted from ICD-10 [3] </p>

<p>D77 
Malignant digestive neoplasm other/NOS 
D87 
Stomach function disorder 
D97 
Liver disease NOS 
D99 
Disease digestive system other 
K78 
Atrial fibrillation/flutter 
K79 
Paroxysmal tachycardia 
K80 
Cardiac arrhythmia NOS 
K86 
Hypertension uncomplicated 
K87 
Hypertension complicated 
K99 
Cardiovascular disease other 
N88 
Epilepsy 
R85 
Malignant neoplasm respiratory other 
S91 
Psoriasis 
W82 Abortion spontaneous </p>

<p>Predictor events -Other potentially alcohol-
related diagnoses from ICPC-2, based on Rehm 
et al. and Reinholdz et al. [15,21] </p>

<p>D07 
Dyspepsia/indigestion 
N01 
Headache 
P01 
Feeling anxious/nervous/tense 
P06 
Sleep disturbance 
P18 
Medication abuse 
P74 
Anxiety disorder/anxiety state 
P76 
Depressive disorder 
Z12 
Relationship problem with partner 
Z13 
Partner's behaviour problem 
Z16 
Relationship problem with child 
Z20 
Relationship problem parent/family member 
Z21 
Behaviour problem parent/family member 
Z24-29 Relationship problem friend, assault/harmful event 
problem, fear of a social problem, limited function/ 
disability, social problem 
A80 
Trauma/injury NOS 
F75 
Contusion/hemorrhage eye </p>

<p> 
T. G. LID ET AL. </p>

<p>F77 </p>

<p>Injury eye other 
H78 
Superficial injury of ear 
H79 
Ear injury other 
L72-81, L96 Fractures, sprains, dislocations, etc. </p>

<p>N80 
Head injury other 
S16 
Bruise/contusion 
S18 
Laceration/cut 
S19 
Skin injury other </p>

<p>SCANDINAVIAN JOURNAL OF PRIMARY HEALTH CARE </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>