<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5023377" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Multiple sclerosis (MS) and its animal model, experimental auto-
immune encephalomyelitis (EAE), are inflammatory demyelinating 
disorders of the central nervous system (CNS). 
1,2 MS is thought to 
begin when peripherally activated myelin-reactive T cells infiltrate 
the CNS, followed by other immune cells, including monocytes, 
B cells, and neutrophils. In the CNS, these cells activate microglia 
and astrocytes and produce IFN-γ, IL-17, Granulocyte macrophage 
colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF), and IL-23, which promote 
inflammatory responses, 
3 while immunoregulatory cytokines like 
IL-4, IL-10, and IL-27 may be protective. 
4-6 Three major mecha-
nisms contribute to the chronic progression in MS: (i) persistent </p>

<p>CNS inflammation </p>

<p>7   ; (ii) loss of trophic support for both oligoden-
drocytes and neurons </p>

<p>8   ; and (iii) accumulation of CNS regeneration 
inhibitors such as Nogo-A, myelin-associated glycoprotein (MAG) 
and oligodendrocyte myelin glycoprotein (OMgp). 
9 Persistent 
CNS inflammation results in continuous CNS tissue damage, i.e., 
demyelination, axonal degeneration, and neuronal dysfunction, </p>

<p>10   while myelin proteins from the damaged tissue, in turn, perpetu-
ate chronic inflammation and the production of neuroregeneration 
inhibitors in the disease foci. 
8,9 This vicious cycle results in failure of 
spontaneous remyelination, axonal loss, and disease progression. </p>

<p>11   Current MS therapies mainly target dysfunctional immune 
response, one of the above-mentioned three pathogenic mecha-
nisms; they are thus only partially effective in mitigating disease 
progression and are less effective at the chronic stage. 
12 These 
immunomodulatory agents have little or no effect on the lack of 
neurotrophic factors and/or the accumulation of neuroregenera-
tion inhibitors in disease foci. On the other hand, delivery of a 
neurotrophic factor may primarily modulate myelination in the 
CNS and promote oligodendrocyte precursor (OPC) proliferation, 
survival, and differentiation, 
13 while its effects will likely be dimin-
ished by inflammation. Blocking neuroregeneration inhibitors in 
the CNS partially suppresses EAE, while having no impact on CNS 
inflammation. 
14 An MS therapy that targets these three pathogenic 
mechanisms at the same time would therefore be most beneficial. 
In view of the beneficial effects of neural stem cells (NSCs) 
in EAE treatment, including their capacity for neuroprotection, 
immunomodulation, trophic function, and possibly neuro-
repopulation, they appear to be an excellent candidate for cell-
based therapy. Indeed, NSCs, even without any modification, 
suppress EAE development. 
15-20 However, NSC therapy in EAE 
has resulted in only marginal improvement in clinical score for 
acute EAE, 
15,16,21,22 while their effect on the chronic stage of disease 
has not been studied. Our pilot experiments showed that unmodi-
fied NSCs failed to induce recovery from EAE when injected at 
day 60 postimmunization (p.i.) (data not shown). The main rea-
sons for this lack of therapeutic effect may be the poor survival 
and low differentiation potential of transplanted NSCs in CNS </p>

<p>The first two authors contributed equally to this work. 
Correspondence: Guang-Xian Zhang, Department of Neurology, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA. 
E-mail: Guang-Xian.Zhang@jefferson.edu </p>

<p>Neural Stem Cells Engineered to Express Three 
Therapeutic Factors Mediate Recovery from 
Chronic Stage CNS Autoimmunity </p>

<p>Xing Li </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Yuan Zhang </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Yaping Yan </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Bogoljub Ciric </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Cun-Gen Ma </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, Bruno Gran </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>, Mark Curtis </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, 
Abdolmohamad Rostami 
1 and Guang-Xian Zhang </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Neurology, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Key Laboratory of the Ministry of Education for Medici-
nal Resources and Natural Pharmaceutical Chemistry, Northwest China National Engineering Laboratory for Resource Development of Endangered 
Crude Drugs, College of Life Sciences, Shaanxi Normal University, Xi'an, China; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Institute of Brain Science, Department of Neurology, Shanxi Datong 
University Medical School, Datong, China; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Clinical Neurology Research Group, Division of Clinical Neuroscience, University of Nottingham School of 
Medicine, Nottingham, UK; </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Department of Neuropathology, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA </p>

<p>MT </p>

<p>Open </p>

<p>1456 </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org vol. 24 no. 8, 1456-1469 aug. 2016 </p>

<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>lesions, and their suboptimal immunoregulatory capacity. 
6,16,22 An 
approach that significantly enhances therapeutic capacity of NSCs 
in chronic stage of EAE is, therefore, crucial. Further, given that 
transplantated NSCs migrate only into the CNS inflamed foci, </p>

<p>23   these cells have been a useful vehicle to deliver therapeutic mol-
ecules to the disease foci for EAE treatment. </p>

<p>16,21   In the present study, we have tested the effect of a novel system 
on the chronic stage of EAE using adult NSCs that were engineered 
to simultaneously produce a therapeutic cocktail (cocktail-NSCs) 
containing IL-10, an effective immunoregulatory cytokine; neu-
rotrophin 3 (NT-3), a potent neurotrophic factor; and soluble 
LINGO-1 protein (LINGO-1-Fc), an antagonist of LINGO-1, a 
key part of the common receptor complex for neuroregeneration 
inhibitors, 
24 under the control of the Tet-On system. These NSCs 
target the three major mechanisms underlying the pathogenesis 
of chronic/progressive EAE and would thus be a highly effective 
approach for EAE therapy. This cocktail, continuously produced 
by autologous NSCs on the CNS disease foci, would also avoid 
potential side effects caused by repeated systemic administration 
of a large amount of drugs, or harmful local administration. </p>

<p>25   RESULTS 
Generation and characterization of bone marrow-
derived NSCs 
BM cells were isolated from femurs of adult B6 mice as described 
in Materials and Methods and our previous report. 
22 After 1 week </p>

<p>in culture, individual cells exhibited obvious proliferative ability, as 
shown in Supplementary Figure S1a. Two weeks later, individual cells 
proliferated to form various sizes of neurospheres (Supplementary 
Figure S1b) and, at 3-4 weeks, the neurospheres increased in 
size and gradually detached from the bottom of the culture plate 
(Supplementary Figure S1c). These neurospheres were collected, dis-
sociated to single cells, and reseeded at 1.0 × 10 
5 cells/ml for the next 
round of expansion. Neurospheres at the 5th passage were dissociated 
into single cells, transferred onto poly-D-lysine and laminin precoated 
coverslips and used in all in vitro experiments. These cells were posi-
tive for NSC markers Nestin and Sox2 (Supplementary Figure S1d,e), 
and their NSC nature was further confirmed by the capacity to prolif-
erate and differentiate into neural cell lineages (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Transduction of NSCs with inducible NT-3, IL-10, 
and/or LINGO-1-Fc 
The most recent Lenti-X Tet-On Advanced Inducible Expression 
System was used to transduce tetracycline-controlled transac-
tivator, NT-3, IL-10, LINGO-1-Fc and copGFP into NSCs cells. 
Innovatively, we inserted NT-3, IL-10, and LINGO-1-Fc genes 
individually into separate vectors and transduced them into cells 
sequentially. This method avoids the drawback of limited space for 
insertion of several genes in a lentiviral vector. We used neomycin, 
puromycin and hygromycin as selection markers in different vec-
tors to ensure that genes are transduced into the same cell. The 
structure of the vectors is shown in Supplementary Figure S2a. </p>

<p>Figure 1 NT-3/IL-10/LINGO-1-Fc promotes NSC proliferation and differentiation in vitro. (a) NSCs transduced with NT-3/IL-10/LINGO-1-Fc were 
plated on poly-D-lysine/laminin coated coverslips at a density of 2.0 × 10 
4 cell/ml in 24-well plates and cultured in NSC proliferation medium. After 48 
hours of culture with Dox (1.5 μg/ml), cells were stained with anti-Ki67 antibody. (b) Proliferation of NSCs was quantified as the percentage of Ki67-
positive cells in all GFP-positive cells. (c) Examples of NSCs that differentiated into mature oligodendrocytes (MBP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), neurons (NF-H </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), and astrocytes 
(GFAP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) in specific differentiation medium for 2 weeks. Scale bar = 100 μm. (d) Quantitative analysis of differentiated cells. Data are shown as mean 
values ± SD (n = 5 each group) and are representative of three experiments. Groups designated by the same letter are not significantly different, 
while those with different letters (A, B, C, D, E, or F) are significantly different (P &lt; 0.05-0.01), as determined by one-way analysis of variance with 
Tukey's multiple comparisons test. </p>

<p>Ctrl-NSCs </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs </p>

<p>GFP/Ki67/DAPI </p>

<p>MBP/DAPI </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>Ctrl-NSCs </p>

<p>NT-3-NSCs </p>

<p>IL-10-NSCs </p>

<p>LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs </p>

<p>NT-3/IL-10-NSCs </p>

<p>NT-3/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs </p>

<p>IL-10/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs </p>

<p>Ctrl-NSCs 
NT-3-NSCs 
IL-10-NSCs 
LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs 
NT-3/IL-10-NSCs 
NT-3/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs 
IL-10/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs 
Cocktail-NSCs </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>GFP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Ki67 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>cell (%) </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Mature oligodendrocyte/ 
neuron/astrocyte (%) </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>MBP 
NFH 
GFAP </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>B 
B </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A 
A 
A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>B 
B B 
B 
C </p>

<p>C C C 
C C </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>AB 
B </p>

<p>CD </p>

<p>DE 
E 
F </p>

<p>A 
A </p>

<p>A 
A </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>a 
c </p>

<p>b 
d </p>

<p>GFAP/DAPI 
NF-H/DAPI </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>



<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>To test the expression of these transduced genes in NSCs, we 
cultured the cells with or without Dox. 
26 After 24 hours, superna-
tants and cells were harvested and analyzed by ELISA and real-time 
PCR. NT-3, IL-10, and LINGO-1-Fc were strongly expressed only </p>

<p>in the presence of Dox (Supplementary Figure S2b). Meanwhile, 
cells transfected with a single gene (NT-3-NSCs, IL-10-NSCs, 
and LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs) or two genes (NT-3/IL-10-NSCs, 
NT-3/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs, and IL-10/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs) also </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>f 
g </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>b </p>



<p>www.moleculartherapy.org vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>

<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>produced significant levels of corresponding proteins. Withdrawal 
of Dox led to a decrease in the production of these proteins after 4 
days (Supplementary Figure S2b), confirming the efficacy of the 
Tet-On/Off system. Furthermore, Tet-On 3G mRNA was present, 
as detected by real-time PCR, in NSCs transduced with these len-
tiviruses (Supplementary Figure S2c). These results confirm the 
success of gene transduction and the Tet-On system. </p>

<p>Proliferation and differentiation potentials of 
cocktail-NSCs in vitro 
The proliferation capacity of cocktail-NSCs was tested by Ki67 
immunostaining. Interestingly, the number of Ki67 
+ cells was 
significantly increased in all NSCs that carried the NT-3 gene 
(NT-3-NSCs, NT-3/IL-10-NSCs, NT-3/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs, and 
cocktail-NSCs) (Figure 1a,b). Adding Dox to mock-transduced 
control NSCs did not change their proliferation. 
To investigate their effect on NSC differentiation, NT-3, IL-10, 
and/or LINGO-1-Fc-transduced NSCs were cultured in specific 
differentiation medium with or without Dox treatment. After 2-3 
weeks, a number of NSCs had differentiated into astrocytes, neu-
rons, or oligodendrocytes, while adding Dox to the control-NSCs 
did not change their differentiation profile. NSCs transduced with 
NT-3 and LINGO-1-Fc differentiated into higher numbers of neu-
rons and oligodendrocytes, but fewer astrocytes (Figure 1c,d). 
These results indicate that NT-3 and LINGO-1-Fc promote dif-
ferentiation of oligodendrocytes and neurons, while reducing dif-
ferentiation of astrocytes. </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs suppress acute EAE 
In order to evaluate the effect of cocktail-NSCs on the develop-
ment of EAE, we first i.v. injected cocktail-NSCs (1.0 × 10 
6 cell/ 
mouse) into mice at disease onset (day 10 p.i.). The group treated 
with PBS (Sham-EAE) showed a progressive increase in clini-
cal score from days 10 to 17 p.i., while mice treated with control 
NSCs, as well as those treated with NSCs transduced with one 
or two genes, showed a significant reduction in clinical scores at 
day 28 p.i. compared with the Sham-EAE group (P &lt; 0.05-0.01). 
Cocktail-NSC-treated mice exhibited the best recovery (P &lt; 
0.001), indicating that therapeutic effect of cocktail-NSCs was 
significantly more potent than that of NSCs transduced with a 
single gene (P &lt; 0.01) or with two genes (P &lt; 0.05) (Figure 2a,b). 
Consistent with the clinical score, sham-EAE mice showed severe 
EAE histological alterations, while only few inflammatory infil-
trates were present in the spinal cord white matter of the cocktail-
NSC-treated mice (P &lt; 0.01; Figure 2c,d), as measured in different 
white matter areas (Supplementary Figure S3). Meanwhile, mice </p>

<p>treated with NSCs transduced with a single gene or two genes also 
exhibited different degrees of recovery, and the treatment groups 
with NSCs producing IL-10 recovered better than those without 
IL-10 (P &lt; 0.05-0.01; Figure 2c,d). These results indicate that 
overexpression of IL-10 is necessary for the anti-inflammatory 
effects of cocktail-NSCs. 
To assess the therapeutic effect of cocktail-NSCs on the infil-
tration of pathogenic T cells into the CNS, MNCs were isolated 
from the CNS and analyzed by flow cytometry. The total number 
of MNCs was 6.3 × 10 
5 per mouse in the sham-EAE group versus 
1.9 × 10 
5 in the cocktail-NSC-treated group. The NT-3/IL-10-
NSC-treated group also showed fewer infiltrating cells (2.9 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>cell/mouse) compared with the sham-EAE group (Figure 2e). 
Significantly fewer CD4 
+ T cells and CD11c 
+ dendritic cells were 
observed in the CNS of cocktail-NSC-treated EAE mice than in 
other groups (Figure 2f, Supplementary Figure S4a). Further, 
cocktail-NSC treatment significantly reduced the percentages of 
Th1 (CD4 
+ IFN-γ 
+ ) and Th17 (CD4 
+ IL-17 
+ ) cells in the CNS com-
pared with control (P &lt; 0.01-0.001; Figure 2g, Supplementary 
Figure S4b). GM-CSF, a critical cytokine in Th17 cell pathoge-
nicity, 
27 was also significantly decreased by cocktail-NSC treat-
ment (P &lt; 0.001). Furthermore, the percentages and absolute 
numbers of IFN-γ 
+ CD4 
+ , IL17 
+ CD4 
+ , and GM-CSF 
+ CD4 
+ cells 
were also significantly decreased in all groups treated with NSCs 
producing IL-10. These results indicate that IL-10 in the cocktail 
plays an important role in the inhibition of CNS inflammatory 
infiltration. 
We and others have shown that NSCs, upon i.v. injection in 
EAE mice, were found in almost all peripheral organs within 
10 days, and subsequently completely disappeared from them by 
day 30 after transplantation. 
6,16,21,28 Injected NSC migrated exclu-
sively into the CNS inflammed foci. 
15 While in the periphery, these 
cells played an immunomodulatory role, primarily by inducing 
Th1, but not Th2 responses, and by induction of T-cell apoptosis </p>

<p>21   ; 
transduction with IL-10 significantly enhanced these effects. 
6 To 
study the autoantigen-induced cytokine production of cocktail-
NSC-treated mice, splenocytes were harvested 28 days p.i. and 
stimulated with MOG 35-55 . As shown in Supplementary Figure S5, 
concentrations of IFN-γ in cell culture supernatants were dramati-
cally decreased in all groups treated with NSCs overexpressing 
IL-10. Injection with NT-3/IL-10-NSCs and cocktail-NSCs signifi-
cantly decreased IL-17 production, and the GM-CSF level was also 
obviously decreased in mice treated with cocktail-NSCs. Treatment 
with NT-3-NSCs and NT-3/IL-10-NSCs showed a much higher 
IL-10 level than in other groups. There was no significant differ-
ence in proportions of various immune cell proportions among </p>

<p>Figure 2 Effect of cocktail-NSCs on the acute stage of EAE. (a) EAE mice were i.v. injected with various NSCs (1 × 10 
6 cells/mouse) at onset of 
disease (day 10 p.i.) and then i.p. injected with Dox every two days (n = 5 each group). Mice were scored blindly for disease severity daily by two 
researchers according to a 0-5 scale. (b) Accumulative score of EAE (sum of daily clinical scores from day 11 to day 28 p.i.). (c) Mice were sacrificed 
at day 28 p.i. (n = 5 each group), and spinal cords were harvested for H&amp;E stained spinal cord sections. The white matter of the lumbar spinal cord 
was analyzed to assess inflammation. (d) Mean score of inflammation in H&amp;E staining. (e-g) Spinal cords and brains were harvested and MNCs 
isolated (n = 5 each group). (e) Total MNC numbers in the CNS were counted under light microscopy. (f) Percentages of CD4 
+ , CD8 
+ , CD11b 
+ , and 
CD11c 
+ cells and (g) IFN-γ 
+ , IL-17 
+ , and GM-CSF 
+ CD4 
+ T cells were determined by flow cytometry. Absolute numbers of different subtypes of CNS 
infiltrating cells were calculated by multiplying the percentages of these cells (as shown in Supplementary Figure S4) by total numbers of MNCs 
obtained from each spinal cord and brain tissue. Groups designated by the same letter are not significantly different, while those with different let-
ters (A, B, C, D, E, or F) are significantly different (P &lt; 0.05-0.01) as determined by one-way analysis of variance with Tukey's multiple comparisons 
test. Data are presentative of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>



<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>splenocytes of these groups (data not shown). Overall, cocktail-
NSCs inhibited IFN-γ, IL-17, and GM-CSF production. </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs significantly alleviate chronic stage 
of EAE 
To define the effect of therapeutic cocktail-NSCs on the chronic 
stage of EAE, mice were transplanted with cocktail-NSCs by 
i.v. injection at day 60 p.i. PBS-injected mice exhibited a slight 
recovery at acute phase, and then remained stable up to day 120 
p.i. (Figure 3a), similar to described previously. 
29 While control 
NSCs showed no effect when treatment started at the chronic 
stage (Figure 3a), NSCs transduced with a single gene (NT-3-
or LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs alone, but not IL-10 alone) slightly halted 
disease progression compared with the sham-EAE group at day 
120 p.i. (P &lt; 0.05). The mean clinical score demonstrated that 
cocktail-NSCs and NT-3/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs significantly sup-
pressed EAE development at chronic stage EAE. In addition, 
the cocktail-NSC-treated group also showed significantly inhib-
ited EAE compared with mice treated with NT-3/IL-10-NSCs 
or IL-10/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs. These results indicate that, com-
pared to unmodified NSCs or cells transduced with one or two </p>

<p>therapeutic molecules, the cocktail-NSCs were the most effective 
at alleviating EAE when treatment was started at chronic stage, 
e.g., day 60 p.i. 
Given that the autologous property of BM-NSCs makes them 
of great interest for future clinical use, we focused on these cells 
in the current study. Similar results have also been observed in 
NSCs derived from the subventricular zone (SVZ) of brain (data 
not shown). </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs reduce CNS inflammation and promote 
an M2 phenotype in macrophages/microglia 
In order to determine the anti-inflammatory capacity of cocktail-
NSCs at the chronic stage of EAE, H&amp;E staining was performed 
to detect the extent of CNS inflammation. While IL-10-producing 
NSCs had stronger anti-inflammatory effects than those without 
IL-10, cocktail-NSC-treated mice showed the lowest inflammation 
score compared with all other groups (Figure 3b; Supplementary 
Figure S6a; P &lt; 0.05-0.01). 
Microglia/macrophages can exhibit either pro-or anti-inflam-
matory properties, depending on the disease stage and the signals 
they receive. 
30 Here, we determined expression of inducible nitric </p>

<p>Figure 3 Effect of cocktail-NSCs on the chronic stage of EAE. (a) EAE mice were i.v. injected with NSCs (1 × 10 
6 cells/mouse) at the chronic stage 
(60 p.i.) of disease and then i.p. injected with Dox every 2 days (n = 5 each group). Mice were scored blindly for disease severity by two researchers 
according to a 0-5 scale. (b) Spinal cords were harvested from EAE mice described in Figure 3a at day 120 p.i. for H&amp;E staining (photos as shown 
in Supplementary Figure S6a), and inflammation was scored in white matter of the lumbar spinal cord and data were expressed as mean ± SD. 
Spinal cords were immunostained against iNOS (c) and Arg1 (d) on infiltrating macrophages/microglia (Iba1 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>; photos as shown in Supplementary 
Figure S6b,c) and the numbers of double-positive cells were counted. Data represent mean ± SD; n = 5 mice per group. Groups designated by the 
same letter are not significantly different, while those with different letters (A, B, C, D, or E) are significantly different (P &lt; 0.05-0.01) as determined 
by one-way analysis of variance comparison with Tukey's multiple comparisons test. Data are presentative of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
c 
d </p>

<p>Sham-EAE </p>

<p>i.v. NSCs </p>

<p>Ctrl-NSCs 
NT-3-NSCs 
IL-10-NSCs 
LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs 
NT-3/IL-10-NSCs 
NT-3/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs 
IL-10/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs 
Cocktail-NSCs </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>Mean clinical scores </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Score of inflamation </p>

<p>3.0 
600 
250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B 
B 
B 
A 
AB </p>

<p>C 
CD 
D </p>

<p>A A </p>

<p>A A A 
A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>BC </p>

<p>D 
D </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>CD </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>E 
500 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>iNOS + </p>

<p>Iba1 + </p>

<p>cells/mm 2 </p>

<p>Arg1 + </p>

<p>Iba1 + </p>

<p>cells/mm 2 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>S h a m </p>

<p>-E A E 
C 
t r l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 \ I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 \ L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 \ L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>C 
o c k t a i l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>S h a m </p>

<p>-E A E </p>

<p>C 
t r l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 \ I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 \ L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 \ L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>C 
o c k t a i l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>S h a m </p>

<p>-E A E </p>

<p>C 
t r l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 \ I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 \ L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 \ L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>C 
o c k t a i l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>20 
40 
Days postimmunization </p>

<p>80 
100 
120 </p>

<p>A 
A 
B 
B 
C 
C </p>

<p>D 
D 
E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>0.0 
60 </p>



<p>www.moleculartherapy.org vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>

<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>oxide synthase (iNOS) and Arginase-1 (Arg1), primary mark-
ers of Type 1 (M1; proinflammatory) and Type 2 (M2; immu-
nomodulatory), respectively, by macrophages/microglia (Iba1 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) 
in the spinal cord. Higher numbers of iNOS </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Iba1 
+ (Figure 3c; 
Supplementary Figure S6b) and lower of Arg1 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Iba1 
+ cells 
(Figure 3d; Supplementary Figure S6c) were observed in the 
sham-EAE group compared to other groups, while cocktail-NSC-
treated mice had more Arg1 
+ and fewer iNOS </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Iba1 
+ cells. We also 
tested whether these engineered NSCs modulate microglial acti-
vation induced by lipopolysaccharide (LPS) treatment in vitro. In 
primary microglial cultures, cocktail-NSCs, as well as other IL-10-
producing NSC groups, effectively inhibited expression of major 
mediators of microglia activation, e.g., TNF-α, IL-1β, and iNOS 
(Supplementary Figure S7a). These results indicate that cocktail-
NSCs can inhibit the proinflammatory M1 phenotype of microg-
lia and switch it to anti-inflammatory or immunoregulatory M2 
phenotype, which can stimulate the remyelination process. </p>

<p>31   Cocktail-NSCs reduce axon degeneration and 
astrogliosis 
It is believed that damage to myelin sheaths in EAE greatly reduces 
axonal survival, 
32 and vice versa, axonal injury precludes remyelin-
ation due to the alteration of remyelination signals from axons. </p>

<p>33   Treatment that could preserve axonal integrity in EAE mice may 
therefore have potential as a neuropreotective agent. Here, axonal 
pathology of mice treated at the chronic stage of EAE was evaluated 
by the development of amyloid precursor protein (APP) deposits, a 
prototypical marker of axonal damage. 
34 In comparison with naive 
mice, sham-EAE mice exhibited a high intensity of APP staining in 
the white matter of the spinal cord (Figure 4a). Mice that received 
NSCs transduced with IL-10 or NT-3 alone showed a small but 
significant decrease in APP staining when compared with sham-
EAE mice. All groups treated with NSCs transduced with LINGO-
1-Fc had lower APP staining than those treated with NSCs without 
LINGO-1-Fc (P &lt; 0.05; Figure 4b). The lowest intensity of APP </p>

<p>Figure 4 Cocktail-NSCs reduced axon degeneration and astrogliosis at chronic stage of EAE. Mice described in Figure 3a were sacrificed and 
lumbar spinal cords were harvested at day 120 p.i. (a) APP staining in the white matter lesion of lumbar spinal cord for detection of axon damage. 
(b) APP intensity in white matter lesions (%) was quantified using <rs type="software">Image-Pro</rs>. APP intensity per field (%) was calculated using APP 
+ staining area 
divide the lesion area in the white matter. EAE lesions (lacking MBP labeling in Figure 5c) were delineated by dashed lines. (c) GFAP staining of spinal 
cord sections for detection of astrogliosis. (d) Quantitative analysis of GFAP expression using Image-Pro. Data represent mean ± SD; n = 5 mice per 
group. Groups designated by the same letter are not significantly different, while those with different letters (A, B, C, D, or E) are significantly differ-
ent (P &lt; 0.05-0.01) as determined by one-way analysis of variance comparison with Tukey's multiple comparisons test. Scale bar = 100 μm. Data are 
presentative of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>APP/DAPI </p>

<p>GFAP/DAPI </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>NAIVE </p>

<p>LINGO-1-Fc 
-NSCs </p>

<p>NT-3/IL-10 
-NSCs </p>

<p>NT-3/LINGO 
-1-Fc-NSCs </p>

<p>IL-10/LINGO 
-1-Fc-NSCs 
Cocktail-NSCs </p>

<p>Sham-EAE 
NT-3-NSCs 
IK-10-NSCs </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C 
C 
C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>CD 
DE D 
AE </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>APP Intensity per field (%) </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C 
C 
C </p>

<p>A 
A </p>

<p>AC 
A 
GFAP intensity per field (%) 
5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>N 
A I V E </p>

<p>S h a m 
-E A E 
C 
t r l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>C 
o c k t a i l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
A I V E </p>

<p>S h a m 
-E A E 
C 
t r l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>C 
o c k t a i l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>NSCs </p>

<p>NAIVE </p>

<p>LINGO-1-Fc 
-NSCs </p>

<p>NT-3/IL-10 
-NSCs </p>

<p>NT-3/LINGO 
-1-Fc-NSCs </p>

<p>IL-10/LINGO 
-1-Fc-NSCs 
Cocktail-NSCs </p>

<p>Sham-EAE 
NT-3-NSCs 
IK-10-NSCs 
NSCs </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>



<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>staining was observed in cocktail-NSC-treated EAE mice, indi-
cating beneficial effects of cocktail-NSCs in axonal protection, in 
which LINGO-1-Fc played a major role. 
Dense astrogliosis is an important factor in plaque formation 
and MS chronicity. 
35 We thus examined the effects of cocktail-NSCs 
on astrogliosis in EAE spinal cord sections using immunolabel-
ing for GFAP. There was a more than fivefold reduction in reac-
tive astrogliosis in mice that received cocktail-NSCs compared to 
sham-EAE. Astrogliosis was also significantly attenuated in mice 
treated with LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs (Figure 4c,d). These findings are 
in agreement with our in vitro data, which showed that LINGO-
1-Fc dramatically suppressed expression of astrocyte genes, 
GFAP, Vimentin, and N-cadherin, in response to LPS activation 
(Supplementary Figure S7b). Together, these results indicate that 
cocktail-NSCs effectively reduce axonal injury and astrogliosis. </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs promote remyelination 
To characterize possible remyelination, EAE mice were treated 
with different groups of NSCs starting on day 60 p.i., when 
chronic damage in the CNS was established. Lumbar spinal cords 
were harvested on day 60 p.i. (before treatment) for Luxol fast 
blue (LFB) and MBP stainings, which served as a baseline for 
demyelination. As shown in Figure 5a-d, a significant degree of 
demyelination had occurred by day 60 p.i. (baseline), and demy-
elination continued to progress in sham-EAE mice up to day 120 
p.i. EAE mice that received NSCs expressing either NT-3 or IL-10 
alone showed a similar demyelination level compared to the base-
line, indicating blockade of further demyelination without remy-
elination. Importantly, NSCs transduced with LINGO-1-Fc, or 
any two therapeutic genes, significantly reduced demyelination 
and enhanced MBP expression compared to the baseline (before 
treatment), and cocktail-NSCs had the strongest effects, provid-
ing evidence for not only blockade of further demyelination but 
also successful remyelination. Taken together, our data demon-
strate that the enhanced myelination observed in mice receiving 
cocktail-producing NSCs is due to both the blockade of further 
demyelination and the promotion of remyelination. 
Toluidine blue-stained sections were also used to visualize 
myelinated axons (Figure 6a). Loss of myelin was apparent in spinal 
cords of sham-treated mice, whereas a greater number of myelin-
ated and/or remyelinated axons was found in cocktail-NSC-treated 
mice. Newly formed myelin sheaths were thinner than in naive mice 
(Figure 6b). Consistent with the neuropathy phenotype, the g-ratio 
(measuring the size ratio between diameter of axon and total fibre) 
of the cocktial-NSC-treated group was significantly lower than that 
of the sham-EAE and other NSC-treated groups (Figure 6c), a fea-
ture of enhanced remyelination. 
6,8 These results clearly indicate that 
treatment with NSCs that produce a therapeutic cocktail not only 
prevents further CNS tissue damage but, importantly, also induces 
remyelination and neurorepair in chronic EAE. </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSC treatment increases the numbers of 
neurons and oligodendrocytes 
We then studied the effect of the cocktail on neural cell differ-
entiation of transplanted NSCs in demyelinated lesions by tri-
ple immunostaining. Colocalization of GFP (for transplanted 
NSCs) and neural specific markers in the striatum and corpus </p>

<p>callosum (as shown as Supplementary Figure S8a) revealed 
that some of the transplanted cells differentiated into NeuN </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>and Tuj1 
+ neurons (Supplementary Figure S8b,c), A2B5 
+ OPCs 
(Supplementary Figure S8d), APC 
+ and MBP 
+ mature oligo-
dendrocytes (Supplementary Figure S8e,f), GFAP 
+ astrocytes 
(Supplementary Figure S7g), while some NSCs remained undif-
ferentiated (Sox2 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>; Supplementary Figure S8h). Quantitative 
analysis showed that significantly higher percentages of neu-
rons, OPCs, and oligodendrocytes and a smaller percentage of 
GFAP 
+ astrocytes were derived from transplanted cocktail-NSCs 
than from control-NSCs (P &lt; 0.05-0.01) (Figure 7a-c). While 
up to 30.3 ± 1.1% of transplanted control NSCs (GFP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) retained 
undifferentiated Sox2 
+ morphological features (Supplementary 
Figure S8h), consistent with a previous report, 
16 a significantly 
smaller percentage (20.5 ± 2.0%) of these cells was observed in 
cocktail-NSCs (Figure 7a), indicating that a large proportion of 
cocktail-NSCs had differentiated into neural cells. Importantly, 
the majority of the MBP-stained area and neural cells were GFP </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>, 
indicating that the main mechanism of cocktail-induced remy-
elination and neural repair is via promotion of endogenous repair. 
We also hypothesized that a combination of NT-3 and LINGO-
1-Fc might enhance MBP synthesis. 
36,37 To test this, we used the tran-
swell system to determine their effects on OPC differentiation in vitro. 
OPCs treated with a combination of LINGO-1-Fc-and NT-3-NSCs 
had dramatically greater branch range of preoligodendrocytes (O4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>cells) (Supplementary Figure S9a-c) and mature oligodendrocytes 
(CNPase 
+ cells) with myelin sheaths (Supplementary Figure S9d,e). 
In the presence of NT-3/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs and cocktail-NSCs, the 
CNPase 
+ oligodendrocytes exhibited complex membrane morphol-
ogy compared with other groups (Supplementary Figure S9d), 
indicating that LINGO-1-Fc directly and strongly promoted OPC 
differentiation into mature oligodendrocytes and had the best 
effects in tandem with NT-3. A significantly decreased percentage of 
Ki67 
+ OPCs in cultures where NT-3 and LINGO-1-Fc were present 
(Supplementary Figure S9f,g) indicated an exit from cell cycle and 
the beginning of oligodendrocyte differentiation. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Treatment of chronic, progressive MS remains a major challenge 
due to the three major mechanisms that contribute to disease 
progression, including: (i) persistent CNS inflammation </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>; (ii) loss 
of trophic support for both oligodendrocytes and neurons 
8 ; and 
(iii) accumulation of CNS regeneration inhibitors. 
9 While unmod-
ified NSCs can suppress EAE when administered at the acute stage 
(e.g., day 22 p.i.), 
6,16 they failed to do so when administered at the 
chronic stage of disease (e.g., day 60 p.i.) as shown in the present 
study, most likely due to their weak anti-inflammatory capacity 
and low neurotrophin production. 
6,16,26 To simultaneously target 
the three major pathogenic mechanisms underlying the failure of 
neuroregeneration at the chronic stage of EAE, here we have for 
the first time engineered NSCs expressing a therapeutic cocktail 
that is triply-effective (Figure 8): (i) NT-3 supports NSC prolifera-
tion and their differentiation into neurons and oligodendrocytes; 
(ii) LINGO-1-Fc blocks the harmful effect of neuroregeneration 
inhibitors on OPCs/oligodendrocytes; and (iii) the inhibitory 
effect of IL-10 on CNS inflammation and the inductive effect 
on M2 phenotype of microglia/macrophages create a supportive </p>



<p>www.moleculartherapy.org vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>

<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>microenvironment for neuroregeneration. Although transplanted 
NSCs can differentiate into neural cells, the majority of MBP-
stained areas and neural cells were GFP </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>, indicating that promot-
ing development of endogenous cells is the main mechanism of 
cocktail-induced remyelination and neuroregeneration. </p>

<p>16,21,28   An important feature of chronic EAE and MS is the loss of 
both oligodendrocytes and neurons in damaged CNS tissues. 
38 An </p>

<p>effective treatment for these diseases at the chronic stage would 
therefore be capable of inducing proliferation and differentiation of 
endogenous neural precursor cells, e.g., NSCs and OPCs, thus sup-
plying sufficient neural cells for repair. NT-3 is an excellent candi-
date for this purpose, given its capacity to promote remyelination, 
axonal regeneration, and functional CNS recovery. 
39 Compared 
to other neurotrophic factors, NT-3 has a significantly greater </p>

<p>Figure 5 Cocktail-NSCs promote remyelination and MBP synthesis at chronic stage of EAE. Mice described in Figure 3a were sacrificed and 
spinal cords were harvested at day 120 p.i. (a) LFB staining of spinal cord sections for detection of demyelination. (b) Image-Pro Plus software was 
used to manually outline the total white matter area (red trace). Blue area indicates intact myelin, whereas pale areas indicate demyelinated areas. 
Demyelination is expressed as percentage of the total demyelinated area out of the total white matter area. (c) MBP staining in the sham-EAE group 
compared with NSC-treated groups. (d) Quantitative analysis of MBP expression. MBP intensity was measured in the lesion areas in the lumbar spinal 
cord using Image-Pro. Data represent mean ± SD; n = 5 mice per group. Groups designated by the same letter are not significantly different, while 
those with different letters (A, B, C, D, E, F, or G) are significantly different (P &lt; 0.05-0.01) as determined by one-way analysis of variance comparison 
with Tukey's multiple comparisons test. Scale bar = 100 μm. Data are presentative of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>EAE at 60 days </p>

<p>Ctrl-NSCs 
NT-3-NSCs </p>

<p>IL-10-NSCs 
LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs </p>

<p>NT-3/IL-10-NSCs 
NT-3/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs </p>

<p>IL-10/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs 
Cocktail-NSCs </p>

<p>Sham -EAE 
EAE at 60 days </p>

<p>MBP/DAPI </p>

<p>Ctrl-NSCs 
NT-3-NSCs </p>

<p>IL-10-NSCs 
LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs </p>

<p>NT-3/IL-10-NSCs 
NT-3/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs </p>

<p>IL-10/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs 
Cocktail-NSCs </p>

<p>Sham -EAE </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>



<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>capacity to provide neuroprotection and reduce astrogliosis, 
40 a 
main cause of MS plaque formation. 
35 NT-3 overexpression has 
been shown to enhance spinal cord injury recovery. 
41 Our previ-
ous studies showed that NSCs transduced with NT-3 significantly 
enhanced neuroregeneration in acute EAE. 
26 NT-3 acted on donor 
cells not only in an autocrine, but also in a paracrine fashion to 
enhance neuronal differentiation of both transplanted and endog-
enous cells, thus promoting neural repair. 
26 Here, NT-3-NSCs sig-
nificantly promoted NSC proliferation and differentiation towards 
neurons and oligodendrocytes, both of which are essential for neu-
ral repair in the chronic stage of EAE. 
42 Although using NT-3 alone 
at the chronic stage was somewhat effective, in combination with 
other therapeutic molecules such as IL-10 and/or LINGO-1-Fc, its 
effect was significantly enhanced. These results indicate that, while 
immunomodulation and blocking neuroregeneration inhibitors 
are important, NT-3, together with other therapeutic factors, helps 
to achieve the maximal therapeutic effect in chronic EAE. 
Another pathogenic mechanism underlying the failure of 
spontaneous remyelination in EAE and MS is the accumulation 
of neuroregeneration inhibitors, including Nogo, MAG, and 
OMgp. 
9,43 These inhibitors are generated from debris of damaged </p>

<p>CNS tissues, and they exert their effect on neural cells through 
the functional component of the NgR1/p75/LINGO-1 and NgR1/ 
TAJ(TROY)/LINGO-1 receptor complexes that mediate inhibi-
tory signals on axonal growth and oligodendrocyte differentia-
tion. 
14 LINGO-1 is a common, key factor in the above-mentioned 
complexes, and blocking LINGO-1 function using different 
approaches, including neutralizing antibodies, gene knockout, 
and LINGO-1-Fc administration, effectively promotes OPC 
maturation (Supplementary Figure S9a,d) and remyelination 
(Figure 5a-d), and protects these cells from CNS inflamma-
tion-or chemical-induced damage. 
14,34 In the present study, we 
showed that among three transduced molecules, overexpression 
of LINGO-1-Fc most effectively enhanced MBP intensity in vivo 
and induced oligodendrocyte maturation in vitro. The importance 
of blocking LINGO-1 signaling in the inhibition of astrogliosis 
is supported by significantly reduced expression levels of GFAP, 
Vimentin, and N-cadherin in LPS-activated astrocytes in vitro. 
Furthermore, adding LINGO-1-Fc significantly enhanced the 
therapeutic effects of NSCs transduced with IL-10 and/or NT-3, 
clearly demonstrating the nonredundant role of LINGO-1-Fc in 
the cocktail. </p>

<p>Figure 6 Toluidine blue staining for remyelination after NSC treatment at chronic stage of EAE. Mice described in Figure 3a were sacrificed 
and spinal cords were harvested at day 120 p.i. (a) Toluidine blue staining of 1-μm semi-thin sections was performed to visualize myelination in 
naïve and NSC-treated EAE mice. (b) All intact axons regardless of their myelination state, whose axoplasm was intercepted by a sampling line, were 
tagged and counted. (c) Mean g ratio (axon diameter divided by entire myelinated fiber diameter) was determined using <rs type="software">Image-Pro Plus</rs> software as 
described. 
6,59 Data represent mean ± SD; n = 5 mice per group. Groups designated by the same letter are not significantly different, while those with 
different letters (A, B, C, D, or E) are significantly different (P &lt; 0.05-0.01) as determined by one-way analysis of variance comparison with Tukey's 
multiple comparisons test. Data are presentative of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>1,000 
A </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>D 
D </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C 
CE 
DE </p>

<p>10 µm </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 
0.5 
0.0 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>Numbers of 
myelinated axon 
Mean g ratio </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>N 
a iv </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>S h a m 
-E A E </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>C 
o c k t a il -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>Naive 
Sham-EAE 
NT-3/IL-10-NSCs </p>

<p>NT-3/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs 
IL-10/LINGO-1-Fc-NSCs 
Cocktail-NSCs </p>

<p>N 
a iv </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>S h a m 
-E A E </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>C 
o c k t a il -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
c </p>



<p>www.moleculartherapy.org vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>

<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>Figure 8 Scheme of cocktail-producing NSCs in neural recovery in EAE. BBB: blood-brain barrier; Yellow: IL-10; Red: NT-3; Blue: LINGO-1-Fc. 
Arrow-headed or bar-headed line indicates promotion or inhibition, respectively. </p>

<p>In vitro and i.v. injection 
(Periphery) </p>

<p>BM-NSCs transduced with 
IL-10,NT-3, LINGO-1-Fc, 
and Tet-on/off </p>

<p>Immuno-
modulation 
BBB 
Astrogliosis </p>

<p>Oligodendrocyte </p>

<p>Immunomodulation </p>

<p>Blockade of 
new damage </p>

<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Axon </p>

<p>EAE 
(CNS parenchyma) </p>

<p>Blockade of 
neuroregeneration 
inhibitors </p>

<p>Remyelination 
Axonal outgrowth 
Neuron recovery 
(Exogenous 
Endogenous) </p>

<p>Figure 7 Quantitative analysis of neural cell differentiation of transplanted NSCs at chronic stage of EAE. Mice described in Figure 3a were sac-
rificed at day 120 p.i. and the brains were harvested for histological staining. Striatum and corpus callosum were examined by immunohistology for 
neurons, OPCs, oligodendrocytes and astrocytes as shown in Supplementary Figure S8b-h. (a) Percentages of transplanted NSC (GFP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>)-derived 
neurons (NeuN </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), OPCs (A2B5 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), mature oligodendrocytes (APC </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), astrocytes (GFAP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), and undifferentiated NSCs (Sox2 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) were shown. Data represent 
mean ± SD; n= 5 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01. (b) Quantification of total APC 
+ and (c) NeuN 
+ cell numbers. Data represent mean ± SD; 
n = 5 mice per group. Groups designated by the same letter are not significantly different, while those with different letters (A, B, C, D, E, F, or G) are 
significantly different (P &lt; 0.05-0.01) as determined by one-way analysis of variance comparison with Tukey's multiple comparisons test. Data are 
presentative of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>50 
Ctrl-NSCs </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs </p>

<p>* 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
* </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Transplanted GFP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>cells (%) </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
NeuN </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>B 
B 
B </p>

<p>B B 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C 
C </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>CE </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D 
D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>DE </p>

<p>1,200 
4,000 </p>

<p>3,000 </p>

<p>2,000 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>Number of APC </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>cells/mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Number of NeuN </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>cells/mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A2B5 
APC 
GFAP 
Sox2 </p>

<p>N 
a i v e </p>

<p>S h a m 
-E A E </p>

<p>E A E 
a t 6 0 </p>

<p>d a y s </p>

<p>C 
t r l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>C 
o c k t a i l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s 
N 
a i v e </p>

<p>S h a m 
-E A E </p>

<p>E A E 
a t 6 0 
d a y s C 
t r l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / I L -1 0 -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>N 
T -3 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>I L -1 0 / L I N </p>

<p>G 
O 
-1 -F c -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>C 
o c k t a i l -N </p>

<p>S C </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>



<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>Given that persistent CNS inflammation and microglia activa-
tion are considered the main cause of continuous neural tissue 
damage and EAE chronicity, 
44 treatment for neuroregeneration 
alone will be insufficient to ameliorate disease development, and 
it will need to be combined with an immunomodulation. Among 
immunomodulatory molecules used in EAE studies, IL-10, as 
the major product and common functional factor of regulatory 
T cells, tolerogenic DCs, and type 2 macrophages (M2), is consid-
ered highly potent in decreasing proinflammatory cytokine pro-
duction. 
30,45,46 While its systemic administration did not suppress 
EAE, IL-10 delivery by fibroblast cells into CNS inflamed foci 
effectively improved disease outcome. 
47 We have shown that i.v. 
transplanted brain tissue-derived NSCs suppressed ongoing acute 
EAE and that their effects were significantly enhanced by trans-
duction with IL-10. 
6 In the present study, we observed that in acute 
EAE levels of proinflammatory cytokines were markedly lower in 
IL-10-NSC-treated mice than in sham-treated or NT-3/LINGO-
1-Fc-NSC-treated EAE mice. Further, reduced pro-inflammatory 
cytokines and M1 response, together with enhanced M2 response, 
likely converted the CNS microenvironment in inflamed foci from 
hostile to supportive of neuroregeneration. Indeed, M2 cells are 
considered important for OPCs to mature into myelinating oligo-
dendrocytes. 
31 While IL-10 was a well-known anti-inflammatory 
molecular which ameliorate inflammation progressive in autoim-
mune disease, the clues from our results indicated IL-10 prob-
ably blockade demyelination by inhibited inflammatory cytokine 
expression and induced M2 macrophages/microglia response. 
An ideal combination of multiple therapeutic reagents would 
enhance the effect of each of them. Interestingly, when IL-10 and 
NT-3 were combined, microglia activation was markedly inhib-
ited compared with the group that was treated with IL-10 alone. 
Further, the combination of LINGO-1-Fc and NT-3 also mark-
edly halted disease progression. Our in vitro data demonstrated 
that LINGO-1-Fc could significantly promote OPC differentiation 
into mature oligodendrocytes. However, we also found that NT-3 
dramatically enhanced cell survival. A previous study showed 
that LINGO-1-Fc treatment promotes TrkB phosphorylation </p>

<p>14   and NT-3 combines with the Trk family receptor to activate its 
downstream pathway. 
39 Treatment with NT-3 and LINGO-1-Fc 
may, therefore, enhance their effect to boost OPC differentiation 
and improve the treatment results of each of them compared with 
a single gene treatment. Moreover, inflammation and demyelin-
ation are the two major elements of pathogenesis and exert their 
effects in parallel in chronic EAE. Our results show that IL-10 not 
only decreases pro-inflammatory cytokine production, but also 
dramatically inhibits microglial activation. Surprisingly, NT-3 had 
no effect on microglial activation, but when combined with IL-10 
it appeared to enhance the suppressive capacity of the latter. This 
enhancement might be attributable to the upregulation of IL-10 
production by NT-3 (Supplementary Figure S5e), although the 
exact mechanism is not clear. The superior effect of cocktail over 
single gene or combinations of any two of these genes indicates 
that these three therapeutic genes in the cocktail enhance the 
effects of one another in reversing CNS autoimmune damage. 
The safety issue of NSC transplantation has been a concern 
for clinical application. For example, coinjection of allogeneic 
adult NSCs with pancreatic islets resulted in NSC-derived tumor </p>

<p>formation. 
48 However, It has been found that NSCs, after trans-
plantation, survive in the CNS for up to 15 months, without any 
sign of deleterious outcomes such as tumor formation, adverse 
immune responses or inappropriate anatomical accumulation. </p>

<p>49   Safety of lentiviral vector as a tool for gene therapy has been 
widely tested in clinical trials. 
50,51 We in another series of experi-
ments observed that all cocktail-NSC-injected EAE mice survived 
up to 300 days p.i. without toxicity or tumor formation (data 
not shown). We, therefore, anticipate that the current system is 
an effective and safe method for the future therapy. Phase 1 and 
2 clinical trials using NSCs as therapies are ongoing to test their 
safety and practicability. </p>

<p>52   Taken together, our data demonstrate that NSCs engineered to 
produce a "cocktail" of three therapeutic molecules effectively tar-
get the three major mechanisms underlying EAE chronicity and 
convert the hostile environment into one supportive of the neuro-
regenerative process, thus significantly promoting endogenous oli-
godendrocyte/neuron differentiation and axonal integrity. Further, 
in addition to being a delivery vehicle, NSCs have intrinsic capac-
ity, albeit weak, for immunomodulation, 
21,23 neural protection 
53 and 
neural-repopulation, 
16,19 functions that can be greatly enhanced by 
this therapeutic cocktail. Thus, this study provides a new approach 
to break the vicious cycle of inflammation, myelin damage and neu-
roregeneration blockade, and paves the way to a novel, inducible, 
and highly effective therapy for chronic CNS inflammatory demy-
elination, for which there is currently no effective therapy. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Generation of NSCs and cell culture. NSCs were generated from bone 
marrow of the femurs of C57BL/6 mice (Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, 
ME), 6-8 weeks of age, as described previously. 
54 Cells were plated on poly-
D-lysine/laminin (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) coated 24-well plate 
and cultured in serum-free Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium: Nutrient 
Mixture F-12 (DMEM/F-12) (Invitrogen, Gaithersberg, MD) supplemented 
with 2% B27, 20 ng/ml epidermal growth factor, and 20 ng/ml basic fibro-
blast growth factor along with antibiotics. Cells were plated at a density of 
1 × 10 
6 cells/well, and media changed every four days. After 2 weeks, a pro-
portion of individual cells proliferated to form distinct neurosphere. After 
3-4 weeks, the neurospheres were collected, dissociated to single cells by 
accutase (Invitrogen), and replated at 1.0 × 10 
5 cells/ml for the next passage. 
Expression of neural specific markers Nestin and Sox2 was determined by 
immunocytochemistry. Cells at 5th to 10th passages were used in the follow-
ing in vitro and in vivo experiments. 
Primary astrocytes, microglial cells and oligodendrocyte progenitor 
cells (OPCs) were isolated from newborn mouse brain, dissociated with 
Neural Tissue Dissociation Kit (Miltenyi Biotech, San Diego, CA) and 
purified with either anti-ASCA-2, anti-CD11b, or anti-A2B5 microbeads 
(Miltenyi Biotech) respectively. Astrocytes were cultured in DMEM/10% 
fetal bovine serum (FBS) cell culture medium, microglia in DMEM/10% 
FBS plus 5 ng/ml M-CSF (PeproTech, Rochy Hill, NJ), and OPCs in 
DMEM/F12 supplemented with 2% B27, 2 mmol/l Glutamax, 20 ng/ml 
basic fibroblast growth factor, and 20 ng/ml PDGF-AA (Invitrogen). </p>

<p>Construction of vectors inducibly producing a therapeutic cocktail. To 
generate vectors inducibly expressing multiple therapeutic genes, we used 
the pLVX-EF1a-Tet3G and pLVX-TRE3G-IRES vectors (Clontech, Moutain 
View, CA). In brief, we cloned and inserted the NT-3 and IL-10 cDNA into 
multiple cloning sites (MCSs) of the pLVX-TRE3G-IRES-puro vector. 
Primer sequences are listed in Supplementary Table S1. The puromycin 
gene was replaced by the hygromycin gene in the pLVX-TRE3G-IRES-puro 
vector, which was then named pLVX-TRE3G-IRES-hyg. Next, we inserted </p>



<p>www.moleculartherapy.org vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>

<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>LINGO-1-Fc and copGFP cDNA into the MCS of pLVX-TRE3G-IRES-
hyg. The Lenti-X HTX Packaging System (Clontech) was used to produce 
the lentivirus of Lenti-X Tet-On 3G, LV-TRE3G-NT-3-IRES-IL-10, and 
LV-TRE3G-LINGO-1-Fc-IRES-copGFP (Supplementary Figure S2a). 
To establish the complete Tet-On Advanced System, we performed 
sequential transduction with the lentiviruses into NSCs following the 
user's manual for the Lenti-X Tet-On 3G inducible expression system. 
NSCs were first transduced with only the Lenti-X Tet-On 3G, followed by 
selection with G418 (500 µg/ml). Resistant clones were then screened for 
Tet-On expression and tested for inducibility. A favorable Tet-On-positive 
clone was then transduced with the LV-TRE3G-NT-3-IRES-IL-10 
lentivirus. Doubly transduced cells were selected using puromycin (5 µg/ 
ml), and the resulting puromycin-resistant clones were then screened for 
NT-3 and IL-10 inducibility. Afterwards, the neomycin and puromycin 
resistant clone was tranduced with the LV-TRE3G-LINGO-1-Fc-IRES-
copGFP lentivirus and, finally, triply-transduced cells were selected using 
hygromycin (500 µg/ml) and the resulting hygromycin-resistant clones 
screened for LINGO-1-Fc and copGFP inducibility. NSC-transduced 
with Lenti-X Tet-On 3G, LVX-TRE3G-IRES-puro and LVX-TRE3G-
IRES-copGFP-hyg were used as control NSCs. </p>

<p>Proliferation and differentiation of cocktail-NSCs. The proliferation 
capacity of NSCs was tested by staining for Ki-67 in vitro. NSCs were 
seeded at a density of 2.0 × 10 
4 cells/ml and incubated in NSC medium. 
After 24 hours, cells were fixed and stained using anti-Ki-67 antibody 
(Abcam, Cambridge, MA). The proliferation capacity was expressed as the 
percentage of Ki-67 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-positive cells among GFP 
+ cells. 
To evaluate the differentiation ability of engineered NSCs, dissociated 
single cells were plated on poly-D-lysine/laminin coated coverslip at a 
density of 2.0 × 10 
4 cells/ml and cultured in specific NSC differentiation 
medium. In brief, for neuron differentiation, Neurobasal medium was 
supplemented with 2% B-27, 2 mmol/l GlutaMax-I and 0.5 mmol/l cAMP. 
For astrocyte differentiation, DMEM was supplemented with 1% N-2, 
2 mmol/l GlutaMax-I and 1% FBS. The oligodendrocyte differentiation 
medium requires Neurobasl medium supplemented with 2% B-27, 2 mmol/l 
GlutaMax-I and 20 ng/ml T3. Over 2 weeks, NSCs in differentiation media 
changed morphology and developed markers of neurons, astrocytes and 
oligodendrocytes as determined by immunocytochemistry staining. To 
determine the number of cells expressing a specific antigen, five areas 
of each coverslip were examined, and the percentage of positive cells 
labeled for a specific neural marker in the total number of DAPI 
+ cells was 
expressed as the mean value of specific neural differentiation. </p>

<p>EAE induction and treatment. Female C57BL/6 mice, 7-8 weeks of age, 
were purchased from the Jackson Laboratory (Bar Harbor, ME). All 
experimental procedures and protocols were approved by the Institutional 
Animal Care and Use Committee of Thomas Jefferson University and 
were carried out in accordance with the approved institutional guidelines 
and regulations. Mice were immunized at two sites on the back with 200 
μg of myelin oligodendrocyte glycoprotein peptide 35-55 (MOG 35-55 ) 
(Genescript, Piscataway, NJ) in 200 μl of emulsion containing 50% com-
plete Freund's adjuvant with 5 mg/ml Mycobacterium tuberculosis H37Ra 
(Difco, Lawrence, KS). All mice were i.p. injected with 200 ng pertussis 
toxin (Sigma-Aldrich) in Phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) on days 0 and 
2 postimmunization (p.i.). Clinical EAE was scored daily in a blind man-
ner, according to a 0-5 scale as described previously </p>

<p>55   : 0, no clinical signs; 
0.5, stiff tail; 1, limp tail; 1.5, limp tail and wadding gait; 2, paralysis of one 
limb; 2.5, paralysis of one limb and weakness of another limb; 3, complete 
paralysis of both hind limbs; 4, moribound; and 5, death. 
NSCs transduced with different vectors were i.v. injected as single-
cell suspension (1.0 × 10 
6 cells in 150 μl PBS/each mouse) via the tail 
vein at the onset (day 10 p.i.) or chronic stage (day 60 p.i.) of disease. 
Upon cell injection, doxycycline (Dox; Sigma-Aldrich) was administered 
subcutaneously (s.c.) at a dose of 100 mg/kg/day. 
56 Mice injected with PBS 
only served as control. The group using unmodified NSCs was omitted </p>

<p>given that showed therapeutic effects similar to GFP-transduced NSCs 
(data not shown). In addition, given that injection of Dox alone did not 
affect the clinical course of EAE, 
26 a control group treated with Dox only 
was not included in the current study. </p>

<p>Histological analysis. Mice were sacrificed at day 28 (for acute EAE) or 
day 120 (for chronic EAE) p.i. and transcardially perfused with PBS. Brain 
and lumbar spinal cords were harvested for pathological assessment and 
spleen for immunological assessment. CNS tissues were cut into 7 μm sec-
tions, fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde and stained with hematoxylin and 
eosin (H&amp;E) for assessment of inflammation and Luxol fast blue (LFB) 
for demyelination. Slides were assessed and scored in a blinded fashion 
for inflammation </p>

<p>57   : 0, none; 1, a few inflammatory cells; 2, organization of 
perivascular infiltrates; and 3, abundant perivascular cuffing with exten-
sion into the adjacent tissue. For demyelination quantification, total white 
matter was manually outlined, and area (%) of demyelination was calcu-
lated by <rs type="software">Image-Pro Plus</rs> software. </p>

<p>58   For immunohistochemistry, brain and spinal cord tissues were fixed 
using 4% paraformaldehyde for 1 day and then cryo-protected using 
30% sucrose solution for 3 days. Fixed tissues were embedded in OCT 
compound (Tissue-Tek, Sakura Finetek, Japan) for frozen sections and 
then sectioned coronally at 12 μm. Transverse sections of brain and spinal 
cord were cut, and stained with different antibodies. Immunofluorescence 
controls were routinely generated by omitting primary antibodies. 
Results were visualized by fluorescent microscopy (Nikon Eclipse E600; 
Nikon, Melville, NY) or confocal microscopy (Zeiss LSM 510; Carl 
Zeiss, Thornwood, NY). For the quantifications of HE, FB, iNOS </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Iba1 
+ , 
Arg1 
+ Iba1 
+ , APP 
+ , GFAP 
+ and MBP 
+ , ten areas in the white matter at the 
lumbar spinal cord were selected (Supplementary Figure S3). </p>

<p>Toludine blue staining and analysis. For toluidine blue staining, spinal 
cords were dissected out and incubated in 2% paraformaldehyde plus 
2.5% glutaraldehyde overnight. Fixed tissues were then immersed in 
2% osmium tetroxide, dehydrated through a graded acetone series, and 
embedded into EPON following procedures described previously. 
34 Semi-
thin sections of 1 μm thickness were stained with 1% toluidine blue and 
images captured by light microscopy. A minimum of 10 micrographs per 
mouse were obtained, and 5 mice per group were evaluated. All axons in 
the area of ventral spinal cord were counted. To quantify myelinated axons, 
a line-sampling method was used in accordance with our previous study. </p>

<p>34   G ratio, i.e., axon diameter divided by the entire myelinated fiber diameter, 
was determined using Image-Pro Plus software. </p>

<p>6,59   Real-time RT-PCR. Total RNA was extracted from cells or tissues using RNeasy 
Plus Mini Kit (QIAGEN, Valencia, CA) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. Reverse transcription was conducted using QuantiTect Reverse 
Transcription Kit (QIAGEN). Real-time PCR was performed using the 
QuantiFast SYBR Green PCR Kit (QIAGEN), and detection was performed 
using the ABI Prism 7500 Sequence Detection System (Applied Biosystems, 
Foster City, CA). Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was 
used as an internal control. Neucleotide sequences of the primers were based 
on published cDNA sequences (Supplementary Table S2). </p>

<p>Mononuclear cell (MNC) preparation. Spleen was mechanically dissoci-
ated through a 70 µm cell strainer (Falcon, Tewksbury, MA) and incubated 
with red blood cell lysis buffer (Miltenyi) for 1 minute. Harvested cells were 
washed with cold PBS before in vitro stimulation. To acquire CNS cells, 
spinal cords and brains were mechnically dissociated and incubated with 
Liberase (Roche, Nutley, NJ) for 30 min, passed through a 70 µm cell strainer 
and washed with cold PBS. Cells were then fractionated on a 70/30% Percoll 
(Sigma-Aldrich) gradient by centrifugation at 2,000 rpm for 20 minutes and 
MNCs were collected from the interface and washed with PBS. </p>

<p>Cytokine production by ELISA. Splenocytes at 1.0 × 10 
6 cells/ml were cul-
tured in triplicates in RPMI 1640 supplemented with 10% FBS in 24-well 
plates and stimulated with 25 μg/ml MOG 35-55 for 72 hours. Supernatants </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>



<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>

<p>were collected and assayed for IFN-γ, IL-17, GM-CSF, IL-5, and IL-10 by 
ELISA Kits (R&amp;D System, Minneapolis, MN). </p>

<p>Flow cytometry analysis. For surface-marker staining, cells were incubated 
with fluorochrome-conjugated Abs to CD4, CD8, CD11b, and CD11c (BD 
Biosciences, San Jose, CA) or isotype control Abs for 30 minutes on ice. 
For intracellular staining, splenocytes or CNS-infiltrating MNCs were 
stimulated with 25 and 10 μg/ml MOG peptide for 72 hours or overnight, 
respectively, followed by stimulation with 50 ng/ml PMA and 500 ng/ml 
ionomycin in the presence of GolgiPlug for 5 hours. Cells were surface-
stained with mAbs against CD4 and CD8. Cells were then washed, fixed, 
and permeabilized with FIX&amp;PERM solution (Invitrogen), and intracel-
lular cytokines were stained with Abs against IL-17, IFN-γ, or GM-CSF 
(BD Biosciences). Flow cytometric analysis was performed on FACSAria 
(BD Biosciences) and data were analyzed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">FlowJo</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Treestar</rs>, 
Ashland, OR). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-5" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">6</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">GraphPad</rs>, La Jolla, CA). Data are presented as mean ± 
SD. When comparing multiple groups, data were analyzed by analysis of 
variance with Tukey's multiple comparisons test. A significance criterion 
of P &lt; 0.05 was used for all statistical analysis. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL </p>

<p>Figure S1. Generation of bone marrow-derived NSCs in vitro. 
Figure S2. Vector construction and NSC transduction. 
Figure S3. Schematic diagram of the measured area of spinal cord 
white matter. 
Figure S4. Cocktail-NSCs are the most efficient in suppressing CNS 
inflammation. 
Figure S5. Cytokine production of MNCs from NSC-treated mice dur-
ing acute EAE. 
Figure S6. Cocktail-NSCs reduce CNS inflammation and promote an 
M2 phenotype in macrophages/microglia. 
Figure S7. Cocktail-NSCs inhibit microglia and astrocyte activation 
in vitro. 
Figure S8. Neural cell differentiation of cocktail-NSCs in vivo. 
Figure S9. Cocktail-NSCs promoted primary OPC differentiation 
in vitro. 
Table S1. Primers used for pLV-TRE3G-NT-3-IRES-IL-10 and pLV-TRE3G-
LINGO-1-Fc-IRES-copGFP vector construction. 
Table S2. Primers used for real-time quantitative RT-PCR analysis. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant from the National Institutes of 
Health (1R01NS075260). X.L. and Y.Z. are partly supported by the 
Chinese National Natural Science Foundation (grant no. 81501062) 
and the Overseas Scholarship Program of Shaanxi Normal University. 
We thank Katherine Regan for editorial assistance. None of the authors 
have conflicts of interest. </p>





<p>www.moleculartherapy.org vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>

<p>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Cocktail-NSCs for the Chronic Stage of EAE </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 
International License. The images or other third party 
material in this article are included in the article's Creative 
Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit 
line; if the material is not included under the Creative 
Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from 
the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy 
of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc-sa/4.0/ </p>

<p>© X Li et al. (2016) </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy vol. 24 no. 8 aug. 2016 </p>



</text></tei>