<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5016906" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background and purpose -Total hip replacement (THR) is not 
recommended for children and very young teenagers because 
early and repetitive revisions are likely. We investigated the clini-
cal and radiographic outcomes of THR performed in children and 
teenage patients. 
Patients and methods -We included 111 patients (132 hips) 
who underwent THR before 20 years of age. They were identifi ed 
in the Norwegian Arthroplasty Register, together with informa-
tion on the primary diagnosis, types of implants, and any revi-
sions that required implant change. Radiographs and Harris hip 
score (HHS) were also evaluated. 
Results -The mean age at primary THR was 17 (11-19) years 
and the mean follow-up time was 14 (3-26) years. The 10-year sur-
vival rate after primary THR (with the endpoint being any revi-
sion) was 70%. 39 patients had at least 1 revision and 16 patients 
had 2 or more revisions. In the latest radiographs, osteolysis and 
atrophy were observed in 19% and 27% of the acetabulae and 
21% and 62% of the femurs, respectively. The mean HHS at the 
fi nal follow-up was 83 (15-100). 
Interpretation -The clinical score after THR in these young 
patients was acceptable, but many revisions had been performed. 
However, young patients with developmental dysplasia of the hip 
had lower implant survival. Moreover, the bone stock in these 
patients was poor, which could complicate future revisions. </p>

<p>■ </p>

<p>Total hip replacement (THR) is rarely recommended for 
children and young adults because several revisions can be 
expected. Young age and high activity levels are well-known 
risk factors for revision (Münger et al. 2006, Flugsrud et al.  2007). After revision, implant survival is poor and recovery of 
hip function is worse than after primary THR (Lie et al. 2004,   Bischel et al. 2012, Adelani et al. 2014). Besides, reduction in 
bone stock makes multiple revisions complicated (Bischel et  al. 2012). 
Assessment of the balance between risks and benefi ts of 
THR is therefore important in young patients. However, to 
date there have only been a few long-term reports on THR 
in young patients, especially those less than 20 years old 
(Cage et al. 1992, Torchia et al. 1996, Bessette et al. 2003,  Wroblewski et al. 2010). We therefore analyzed the long-term 
outcome from a large series of THRs in very young patients. </p>

<p>Patients and methods </p>

<p>Patients 
Using the Norwegian Arthroplasty Register (NAR) (Havelin  et al. 2000), we identifi ed patients who had undergone a pri-
mary THR before the age of 20 years in the period 1987-2010. 
We included 111 patients with 132 hips, reported from 15 hos-
pitals in Norway. 49 of the patients were male (56 hips). Infor-
mation on their revisions was obtained up to December 31, 
2013. We obtained written informed consent from 81 patients 
to obtain their medical records and radiographs (96 hips) 
(Figure 1). Perioperative medical records from 80 patients (95 
hips) were available, and there were postoperative radiographs 
from 80 patients (94 hips). </p>

<p>The Norwegian Arthroplasty Register (NAR) 
The NAR data include primary THRs and the following reop-
erations: changes of acetabular or femoral components, and 
of femoral head or liner, and removal of implants. From the 
NAR, we also obtained information on the date of surgery, 
previous surgeries, type of surgery, type of implant, diagno-</p>



<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 479-484 </p>

<p>sis at the primary THR, and indications for reoperations. We 
defi ned revision as removal or exchange of 1 or more compo-
nents, including liner. </p>

<p>Diagnosis 
In addition to data from the NAR, we obtained details of the 
diagnosis from the medical records, if available. Before 2011, 
Perthes' disease and slipped capital femoral epiphysis (SCFE) 
were registered as one common item. When the diagnosis 
was unclear in the medical records, SCFE was assumed if the 
patient had a history of fi xation for SCFE. If not, we kept the 
diagnosis as Perthes' disease /SCFE. </p>

<p>Causes of revision 
The NAR has 10 categories for the cause of revision (Table 1), 
and accepts multiple selections and free descriptions. To high-
light the main cause, we gave each patient 1 major diagnosis. 
If "Deep infection," "Dislocation," or "Fracture" was selected, 
we prioritized these diagnoses. "Loosening" without "Deep 
infection," was categorized as "Aseptic loosening." If "Oste-
olysis without loosening" was selected and the implant had 
been changed, we categorized it as "Osteolysis." If the proce-
dure was liner exchange only, we categorized it as "Wear." If 
"Pain" alone was selected, we categorized it as "Pain only." 
An implantation of a new implant following previous removal 
was categorized as "2-stage revision." </p>

<p>Radiographic analysis 
We obtained radiographs of 94 hips in 80 patients. 1 patient 
with informed consent was excluded because the patient had 
emigrated and the radiographs had not been stored. We evalu-
ated the latest radiographs for loosening, osteolysis, bone 
defects, atrophy, and ectopic calcifi cation. For assessment 
of migration or loosening of implants, we examined the fi rst 
postoperative radiographs of the implants, if available. All 
radiographs were analyzed by one of the authors (MT). 
The locations of radiographic fi ndings were recorded accord-
ing to the 3 acetabular zones described by Charnley and to the </p>

<p>7 femoral zones described by Gruen. Osteolysis was defi ned 
as a non-linear lucency of 3 mm or more around the prosthesis 
(Claus et al. 2003). Loosening of an acetabular component was 
determined from evidence of migration and a radiolucent line 
(Hodgkinson et al. 1988, Johnston et al. 1990). An acetabu-
lar component was diagnosed as "loose" when it had migrated 
more than 4 mm in either the horizontal or the vertical direc-
tion, or if it had tilted by more than 5°. Cemented acetabular 
components that had continuous radiolucent lines with any 
thickness in all 3 zones were categorized as being loose. Unce-
mented acetabular components that had radiolucent lines wider 
than 2 mm in all 3 zones were categorized as being loose. 
Loosening of an uncemented stem was defi ned by whether the 
stem was considered to be unstable according to the criteria of 
Engh et al. (1990). Loosening of a cemented stem was defi ned 
by whether we found a continuous radiolucent line around 
the stem, or stem subsidence of &gt; 5 mm. Bone defects were 
assessed using Paprosky's classifi cations (Paprosky et al. 1994,  Della Valle and Paprosky 2004). Bone areas with reduced den-
sity in the acetabulum and proximal femur were recorded as 
"atrophy" (Wangen et al. 2008). Thinning of the femoral cortex 
adjacent to a well-fi xed stem was recorded as "cortical atro-
phy" (Figure 2). Heterotopic ossifi cation was defi ned using the 
classifi cation of Brooker et al. (1973). In 3 hips, the proximal 
femur was replaced with a tumor prosthesis, so we evaluated 
the acetabular component only. In 1 hip, all the implants had 
been removed, so we assessed bone defects only. Leg-length 
discrepancy (LLD) was assessed by comparing the heights of 
greater or lesser trochanters relative to the line connecting the 
teardrops of the acetabulum. If the deformity was severe or if 
the proximal femur was replaced with a tumor prosthesis, we 
did not evaluate the patient's LLD. For analysis radiographs, 
we used <rs id="software-1" type="software">Mdesk Orthopaedics</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">RSA Biomedical</rs>, 
Umeå, Sweden). </p>

<p>Clinical score 
The 81 patients who consented to be part of this study were 
invited to an outpatient clinic of 1 author (VH) after 2011. </p>

<p>Primary THR before age 20 
during 1987-2010 from the 
Norwegian Arthroplasty Register 
n = 111 patients, 132 THRs </p>

<p>Consented to the study 
n = 81 patients, 96 THRs </p>

<p>Perioperative medical records, 80 patients, 95 THRs 
Radiographs, 
80 patients, 95 THRs 
Interview by one of the authors, 70 patients, 81 THRs </p>

<p>Excluded patients (n = 30): 
-dead, 8 
-declined, 22 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Flow of patient inclusion and data collection. </p>

<p>Table 1. Category of indications for revision </p>

<p>Register 
Current study </p>

<p>1 Loosening of 
Priority diagnosis 1 Infection 
acetabular component 
2 Dislocation 
2 Loosening of 
3 Fracture 
femoral component 
Other specifi ed 
4 Aseptic 
3 Dislocation 
loosening 
4 Deep infection 
5 Osteolysis 
5 Fracture in acetabulum 
6 Wear 
6 Fracture in femur 
7 Pain only 
7 Pain 
8 2-stage revision 
8 Osteolysis in acetabulum 
9 Other 
without loosening 
9 Osteolysis in femur 
without loosening 
10 Other (in text) </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 479-484 </p>



<p>70 patients (81 hips) came to the clinic, and Harris hip score 
(HHS) was obtained. </p>

<p>Statistics 
Kaplan-Meier survival analysis was used to determine the 
survival after the primary THR and the fi rst revision surgery. 
We performed time-trend analyses to assess changes in the 
revision rate between the periods 1987-1995 and 1996-2010. 
All calculations were performed using <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> Statistics. </p>

<p>Ethics 
The Regional Ethics Committee for Medical and Health 
Research deemed that approval was not necessary (2011/1125/ 
REK Vest). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The mean patient age at primary THR was 17 (11-19) years. 
8 patients with 9 THRs died after mean 5.3 (0.8-11) years. 
Among these, 2 patients with 3 hips had juvenile idiopathic 
arthritis (JIA) and one hip was operated on for acetabular 
tumor. For the surviving 103 patients (123 hips), the mean 
follow-up period was 14 (3-26) years. 
Pediatric hip diseases accounted for underlying diseases in 
54 hips, followed by systemic infl ammatory diseases (SIDs) 
(45 hips), sequelae of trauma (11 hips), and sequelae of infec-
tion (7 hips) (Table 3, see Supplementary data). </p>

<p>Primary THRs 
We identifi ed 24 different types of acetabular components and 
17 different types of femoral stems (Table 4, see Supplemen-
tary data). 89% of the acetabular components and 95% of the 
femoral stems were uncemented implants. Ceramic or metal-</p>

<p>on-polyethylene bearings were chosen for 89% of the THRs, 
and the most common head diameter (69%) was 28 mm (Table 
5, see Supplementary data). 
39 hips (30%) had undergone at least 1 revision. 32 acetabu-
lar components and 23 stems had been revised. The 10-year 
survival of the primary implant with the endpoint being any 
revision was 70%. It was 78% with the endpoint being a 
change of acetabular component and it was 90% with the end-
point being a change of stem. According to underlying dis-
ease, the 10-year survival with the endpoint being any revision 
was 77% for 45 hips with SID, 52% for 25 hips with devel-
opmental dysplasia of the hip (DDH), and 73% for 31 hips 
diagnosed as SCFE, Perthes' disease, or trauma. The 5-year 
survival of the THRs carried out in 1987-1998 was 84%, as 
compared to 97% in 1999-2010 (Figure 3). </p>

<p>Revisions 
69 revisions had been reported to the NAR. The greatest 
number of revisions performed on the same THR was 7. The </p>

<p>Figure 2. Example of cortical atrophy of fi xed stem (white arrow). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Survival curves. 
a. Primary THR with revision as 
endpoint. 
b. Primary THR operated during 
the periods 1987-1998 and 
1999-2010. 
c. Primary THR with cup change 
as endpoint. 
d. Primary THR with stem change 
as endpoint. 
e. First revision with second revi-
sion as endpoint. </p>



<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 479-484 </p>

<p>mean interval between the primary THR and the fi rst revi-
sion (n = 39) was 7.2 (0.3-17) years, it was 5.8 (0.4-13) years 
between the fi rst revision and the second (n = 16), 5.3 (0.1-
14) years between the second and the third (n = 7), and 2.2 
(0.3-6.1) years between the third and the fourth (n = 3). The 
survival rate of the 39 fi rst revision at 10 years with a second 
revision being the endpoint was 62% (Figure 3e). Aseptic 
loosening and infection accounted for 45% and 12% of the 
indications for all revisions (Table 2). </p>

<p>Radiographic results 
The last postoperative radiographs were taken at a mean of 12 
(2-27) years after the primary THR. 75 (80%) of the primary 
acetabular components and 86 (91%) of the primary femoral 
components survived. 1 patient had no implants. 
3 acetabular components and 1 femoral stem were found to 
be loose. Osteolysis and atrophy were observed in 19% and 
27% of the acetabulae and 21% and 62% of the femora, respec-
tively. Cortical atrophy was observed in 11 femora (12%) 
(Table 6, see Supplementary data). The status of bone defects 
in 2 acetabula and 9 femora was categorized as Paprosky class 
3A (Table 7, see Supplementary data). Structural bone grafts 
or augmentations in the acetabulum were identifi ed in 7 hips. 
The ectopic ossifi cation was categorized as Brooker grade 0 
in 53 hips, as grade 1 in 26, as grade 2 in 9, and as grade 3 in 
6. The LLD was measurable in 80 hips and was more than 10 
mm in 23 hips (29%) (Table 8, see Supplementary data). 15 
hips received at least 1 change of acetabular or femoral com-
ponent. LLD of more than 10 mm was observed in 9 of these 
15 hips, while in 14 of the other 65 hips. The opposite hip of 
the included 80 THRs was subjected to THR in 36 cases, had 
no deformity in 41 and had a deformity in 3. </p>

<p>Clinical results 
The HHS was evaluated at mean 12 (2-26) years after the pri-
mary THR. The mean pain score was 35 (10-44) and the mean 
total score was 83 (15-100). The mean total score for the 60 </p>

<p>hips without any revision was 85, while it was 77 for the 10 
hips with one revision and also for the 11 hips with 2 or more 
revisions. 17 hips had a total score of less than 70. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The 10-year survival of primary THR in our patients was 70%, 
which was worse than the rate of 89% for THRs in patients 
of all ages reported by the NAR (Lie et al. 2004). Patients 
with DDH had especially poor survival. These results confi rm 
that THR is still a challenging treatment for children and teen-
age patients. There have been few reports on THRs in such 
patients with a mean follow-up period of more than 10 years. 
Regarding cemented THRs in the 1970s, Cage et al. (1992)  observed gross implant loosening in 7 of the 22 cases at a 
mean follow-up of 11 years and Torchia et al. (1996) reported 
revision in 27 of 63 THRs and failure (revision or symptom-
atic loosening) in 29 hips at a mean follow-up of 13 years. 
Little is known about the long-term outcome of modern THR 
in very young patients. Bessette et al. (2003) reported the out-
come of 15 THRs performed between 1975 and 1990 with a 
mean follow-up of 14 years; 11 of the 15 were uncemented; 
5 hips were revised, and the mean HHS was 65. The THRs in 
our study were performed after 1987. The overall survival rate 
was similar to those in previous reports, but it is encourag-
ing that survival had improved in the later period of 11 years. 
Although our study cohort was too small for us to perform sta-
tistical evaluation, we assume that improvements in surgical 
techniques and implants contributed to this improvement-as 
well as the introduction of highly cross-linked polyethylene 
(Digas et al. 2007) and better control of juvenile idiopathic 
arthritis with biological agents (Gartlehner et al. 2008). 
Many different types of implants were used in our patients. 
We assume that surgeons chose new implants or tried them 
with good intention rather than using well-documented, rep-
resentative implants with which they had substantial experi-
ence in older patients. New implants are always released with 
the intention of achieving better outcome; however, not all can 
succeed, as has been the case with metal-on-metal bearings 
(Dunbar et al. 2014). In our series, the second (Tropic) and the 
third (Atoll) most frequently used acetabular components were 
later shown to have a 3-6 times higher risk of revision when 
compared with cemented Charnley cups (Havelin et al. 2002). 
They were used until 2000, and accounted for one-third of the 
primary components. They may have contributed to the poor 
survival during the earlier period of 11 years. We recommend 
that surgeons should not use poorly documented new implants 
in young patients, for whom long-time outcome matters most. 
We observed many revisions in our series. The 10-year 
survival rate for the fi rst revision was 62%, which was worse 
than the 10-year survival fi gure of 77% for the fi rst revision 
in all ages in the NAR (Lie et al. 2004). Complications led 
to the need for multiple revisions at short intervals. Our fi nd-</p>

<p>Table 2. Indications for revision </p>

<p>1st 2nd 3rd 4th 5th 6th 7th Total </p>

<p>Infection 
2 
3 
1 
1 
1 
8 
Dislocation 
2 
1 
1 
4 
Fracture 
1 
1 
Aseptic loosening 18 
9 
3 
1 
31 
Osteolysis 
3 
3 
6 
Wear 
11 
2 
1 
14 
Pain only 
1 
1 
2-stage revision 
1 
1 
Other 
1 a 
1 b 
1 c 
3 </p>

<p>Total number 
39 
16 
7 
3 
2 
1 
1 
69 </p>

<p>a Malposition of acetabular component. 
b Massive ectopic bone formation. 
c Loose locking ring. </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 479-484 </p>



<p>ing is consistent with the report by Bischel et al. (2012) that 
the number of previous revisions infl uenced the survival of 
acetabular cups. Repetitive hospitalization could confer a dis-
advantage on patients undergoing competitive education and 
developing their careers. It is therefore important to inform 
patients about the possibility of needing multiple revisions 
over a short period. 
Reduction of bone stock is a major concern in revision 
(Deirmengian et al. 2011, Sakellariou and Babis 2014). We 
observed reduced bone stock around both non-revised and 
revised implants. The reduction might arise from preopera-
tive deformities. However, regardless of the cause, poor bone 
stock implies many diffi culties in future revisions. 
The rate of osteolysis in our study was similar to previously 
reported rates (8-30%) in young adults (Wangen et al. 2008,  Kim et al. 2012). So far, patient age has not been reported as 
a risk factor in adults aged ≤ 50 years (Sandgren et al. 2014). 
We confi rmed that being a child or a teenager was not in itself 
an additional risk regarding osteolysis. 
Bone atrophy around components (Mueller et al. 2006,  Adolphson et al. 2009) is also a concern for future revisions. 
We observed a high incidence of atrophy in the proximal femur 
(62%). Cortical atrophy at the femoral diaphysis was observed 
in 11 hips (12%). 10 of the cortical atrophy cases occurred 
around stable and unrevised stems. As far as we understand, 
cortical atrophy is not common in elderly patients. We spec-
ulate that children and teenage patients are more vulnerable 
to stress shielding than older patients, presumably because 
of active bone remodeling. We suggest that implants with a 
high risk of stress shielding (Khanuja et al. 2011) should be 
avoided in young patients. 
LLD was common-especially after revision-and a large 
leg-length discrepancy was observed irrespective of the status 
of the opposite hip. LLD can have various causes, such as 
high positioning of the acetabular component and deep stem 
insertion. We could not determine the specifi c cause because 
most of the radiographs did not cover the whole pelvis, and 
we could not reasonably assess the height of the center of the 
acetabulum in patients with various statures. However, we 
assume that high positioning of the hip center had a substan-
tial effect on LLD because structural bone grafts or acetabular 
augmentations were identifi ed radiographically in only 7 hips, 
although the acetabular bone defect was graded Paprosky 
2B or more in 15 patients and the diagnosis was DDH in 25 
hips (14 of which had complete dislocation). More attention 
should be paid to restoring the original hip center in children 
and teenage patients (Schmitz et al. 2013). Centralization of 
these patients to limited specialized institutions would help to 
maintain the level of treatment of such rare patients. 
The fi nal HHS was favorable despite many revisions and 
radiographic changes. However, the mean HHS of revised 
hips was lower than that of non-revised hips. Our patients will 
defi nitely require additional revisions in the future. Even the 
oldest patient was still less than 50 at the end of this study. </p>

<p>Deterioration of hip function may occur in middle age. 
Continuous observation will be needed. 
One limitation of the present study was the small number 
of patients relative to the degree of heterogeneity. Neverthe-
less, to date this has been the largest study on modern THR 
to focus on children and teenage patients (Cage et al. 1992,  Torchia et al. 1996, Bessette et al. 2003). Although statisti-
cal analysis may be inappropriate, we believe that this study 
will give surgeons and patients a clinical overview of THR in 
children and teenagers and help in decision making. Another 
limitation was the low coverage of patients with bone tumors. 
THRs performed for tumors are often only reported to another 
registry: that of the Scandinavian Sarcoma Group (Aksnes et  al. 2008). However, such patients do not usually have alterna-
tives to THR. We therefore believe that the main purpose of 
our study-to help surgeons and patients in decision making 
for THR-could be accomplished without including tumors. 
In summary, we observed many revisions and reduced bone 
quality, but the clinical score has been favorable so far. We 
suggest that very young patients should be reminded about the 
possibility of frequent revisions at short intervals-and that 
future revisions will be challenging because of their reduced 
bone stock. </p>

<p>Supplementary data 
Tables 3-8, are available on the website of Acta Orthopaedica 
(www.actaorthop.org), identifi cation number 9820. </p>

<p>MT, SMR, and VH were responsible for the study design. VH measured HHS. 
MT, SMR, and AMF performed the analysis. MT drafted the manuscript. All 
the authors participated in interpretation of the results and in preparation of 
the manuscript. </p>

<p>This study was funded by Sophies Mindre Ortopedi A.S., Norway. The authors 
declare that there are no competing interests associated with this study. </p>

<p>Adelani M A, Crook K, Barrack R L, Maloney W J, Clohisy J C. What is 
the prognosis of revision total hip arthroplasty in patients 55 years and 
younger? Clin Orthop Relat Res 2014; 472(5): 1518-25. </p>



<p>
Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 479-484 </p>



</text></tei>