<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5406603" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The multicellular spheroid model partly mimics tumor microenvironments in vivo 
and has been reported in plenty of studies regarding radiosensitivity. However, 
clear isolation of quiescent and proliferating cells in live conditions has been 
quite difficult owing to technical limitations; therefore, comprehensive characteri-
zation could not be done thus far. In this study, we succeeded in separately iso-
lating different cell types using a fluorescent ubiquitination-based cell cycle 
indicator (Fucci) and determining their radiosensitivities. Unexpectedly, proliferat-
ing cells were more radioresistant than quiescent cells due to the contact effect 
when spheroids were disaggregated immediately after irradiation. However, the 
radiosensitivity of quiescent cells was not influenced by mild hypoxia (hypoxia-
inducible factor-1a-positive but pimonidazole-negative), but their radioresistance 
became similar to that of proliferating cells due to potentially lethal damage 
repair when disaggregated 24 h after irradiation. The Fucci system further 
allowed long-term observation of cell kinetics inside of the spheroid following 
irradiation using real-time confocal fluorescence scanning. Repeated cycles of 
recruitment from the quiescent to the proliferating phase resulted in cell loss 
from the outside of the spheroid toward the inside, causing gradual shrinkage. 
Interestingly, the central region of the spheroid entered a dormant stage approx-
imately 40 days after irradiation and survived for more than 2 months. Using the 
Fucci system, we were able to comprehensively characterize the radiosensitivity 
of spheroids for the first time, which highlights the importance of cell cycle 
kinetics after irradiation in determining the radiosensitivity under tumor 
microenvironments. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>ell cycle kinetics greatly influence radiosensitivity, as indi-
cated by in vitro analysis. Terasima and Tolmach were the 
first to report fluctuations in radiosensitivity during the cell 
cycle; cells in late S phase were the most radioresistant, 
whereas those in M phase were the most radiosensitive. 
(1) It 
has also been well recognized that cells stopping cell cycle 
progression show potentially lethal damage repair (PLDR). </p>

<p>(2)   Potentially lethal damage repair has been the operationally 
observed phenomenon that the surviving fraction (as deter-
mined by a clonogenic assay) significantly increases when pla-
teau phase cells with low growth activity are plated after a 
delay, as opposed to immediately after irradiation. 
(3) In addi-
tion to the aforementioned factors, when studying solid tumors, 
it is necessary to take into account features of the tumor 
microenvironment that are absent during in vitro conditions. 
For example, within tumors in vivo, hypoxic and quiescent cell 
fractions are generated because oxygen and nutrition are deliv-
ered by diffusion from tumor vessels, thereby varying their 
concentration throughout the tumor. 
(4) Considering that cells 
become radioresistant when oxygen tension is below 20-
30 mmHg, with an ED 50 (effective dose: pO 
2 required to 
achieve 50% of the radioresistance) =~3 mmHg, 
(4) such 
hypoxic cells in tumors have been thought to be a cause of 
cancer relapse after radiotherapy by in vitro studies. </p>

<p>The multicellular spheroid model includes 3-D anchorage-
independent growth conditions, quiescent and proliferating cell 
fractions, and hypoxia, thus partly mimicking in vivo condi-
tions, albeit with no vasculature. 
(5-7) This model has been used 
to study radiosensitivity in tumor microenvironments, and 
indeed, radioresistance was shown by 3-D cell-cell contact 
(contact effect) 
(8) and the existence of a hypoxic cell frac-
tion. 
(9) Concerning the latter, the existence of a very small 
fraction was contemplated due to the shape of cell survival 
curves detectable only at high doses. 
(9) Although coculture of 
fibroblasts with tumor cells was reported to increase the 
radioresistant hypoxic fraction, 
(10) sufficient radioresistance by 
hypoxia is unlikely to be detected in a simple spheroid model. 
Potentially lethal damage repair was also detected when irradi-
ated spheroids were disaggregated and prepared for a clono-
genic assay after a delay. 
(11) Structurally, mature spheroids are 
known to consist of the outer thin proliferating and inner 
hypoxic quiescent fraction, by demonstrating that only the 
outer fraction contains DNA synthesizing cells incorporating </p>

<p>3   H-thymidine or bromodeoxyuridine. 
(6) However, due to tech-
nical limitations, it has been quite difficult to separately isolate 
them in live conditions. Availability of such techniques should 
provide highly useful information regarding the effect of cell 
cycle kinetics on radiosensitivity. </p>

<p>To address this issue, we used the fluorescent ubiquitination-
based cell cycle indicator, Fucci. 
(12) This system takes advan-
tage of the cell cycle-specific properties of the E3 ligase activi-
ties of the APC 
Cdh1 and SCF 
Skp2 complexes, allowing us to 
visualize cell cycle progression in living cells: cells expressing 
Fucci emit red and green fluorescence in G 1 and S/G 2 /M 
phases, respectively. We previously reported that the radiation-
induced Fucci fluorescence change perfectly reflects the radia-
tion-induced G 2 arrest in HeLa-Fucci cells, 
(13,14) and such a 
G 2 arrest is prolonged in tumor microenvironments. 
(15,16) In 
this study, we newly established a human tongue carcinoma 
cell line expressing Fucci (SAS-Fucci cells) and forming 
spheroids. First, we characterized radiation-induced cell cycle 
kinetics of spheroids and separately isolated quiescent and pro-
liferating cells. Next, we determined their radiosensitivities by 
a clonogenic assay, and compared them to the survivors 
obtained from long-term observation of the spheroid following 
irradiation when its structure was maintained. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Cell lines and culture conditions. A human tongue squamous 
cell carcinoma cell line, SAS, was obtained from the Health 
Science Research Resources Bank (Sendai, Japan) and main-
tained in DMEM (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) contain-
ing a high concentration of glucose (4500 mg/L) with 100 units/ 
mL penicillin and 100 lg/mL streptomycin, supplemented with 
10% FBS, at 37°C in a humidified 5% CO 2 atmosphere. 
Establishment of SAS-Fucci cells. Fucci plasmids (CFII-EF-
mKO2-hCdt1 [30/120]) and CFII-EF-mAG-hGeminin [1/110]) 
were provided by the Riken Bio-Resource Center through the 
National Bio-Resource Project of the Ministry of Education, 
Culture, Sports, Science and Technology, Japan. Packaging 
plasmids (pLV-IVSV-G and pLV-HELP) (LENTI-Smart; Invi-
voGen, San Diego, CA, USA) and Fucci plasmids were trans-
fected into 293T cells (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA). 
Supernatants were added to SAS cells, which were then cul-
tured in serum-free medium for 72 h in the presence of 8 lg/ 
mL infection reagent, Polybrene (Sigma-Aldrich). To purify 
double-transduced cells, green fluorescent cells were first iso-
lated using a MoFlo XDP cell sorter (Beckman Coulter, Brea, 
CA, USA) at ice-cold temperature. One week after the first 
cell-sorting procedure, red fluorescent cells were isolated. After 
the two-step sorting, six clones were isolated, and one clone 
showing strong fluorescence in both colors was designated as 
SAS-Fucci cells. This experiment was approved by Genetically 
Modified Organisms Safety Committee of Tokyo Medical and 
Dental University (2012-006C3). 
Time-lapse imaging. Time-lapse images of monolayer cells 
were acquired at 1-h intervals for 72 h on a BIOREVO BZ-9000 
fluorescence microscope (Keyence, Osaka, Japan). Images of 
spheroids were acquired at 1-h intervals for 72 h using an 
FV10i-LIV confocal laser scanning microscope (Olympus, 
Tokyo, Japan) in an agar-spread culture dish containing growth 
medium. During imaging, cells and spheroids were kept at 37°C 
in a humidified atmosphere containing 95% air and 5% CO 2 . For 
quantitative analysis, fluorescent areas were measured using the 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">ImageJ</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version">1.44</rs> software (available at <rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij</rs>/). 
Flow cytometry analysis. All samples were fixed in 4% 
paraformaldehyde to detect DNA contents and the fluorescence 
intensity of monomeric Azami Green (mAG) or monomeric 
Kusabira Orange 2 (mKO2). After washing in PBS, cells were 
stained with PBS containing 10 lg/mL Hoechst 33342 (Invitro-
gen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) for 30 min. Samples were analyzed </p>

<p>using a FACSCanto II (BD Bioscience, Franklin Lakes, NJ, 
USA) with FlowJo software (Tree Star, Ashland, OR, USA). 
Spheroid formation. A Hydrocell 96-well plate (CellSeed, 
Tokyo, Japan) was used to generate spheroids. One thousand 
cells were plated in each well and incubated for approximately 
7 days. After the spheroids became visible to the naked eye, 
the culture medium was replaced with fresh medium every 
2 days. Spheroids approximately 700 lm in diameter were 
transferred to the agar-spread culture dish containing growth 
medium, which was originally prepared for observation on an 
FV10i-LIV confocal laser scanning microscope (Olympus). 
Cell sorting. To assess the radiosensitivity of cells grown in 
tumor microenvironments, spheroids were disaggregated after 
irradiation. Spheroids were incubated for 15 min in Spheroid 
Dispersion Solution (SCIVAX Life Sciences, Kawasaki, Japan) 
for preparation of single-cell suspensions immediately or 24 h 
after irradiation. To distinguish viable from non-viable cells, 
cells were incubated in 200 nM DAPI (Sigma) solution for 
15 min at room temperature under light-shielded conditions. 
After aspiration of the DAPI solution, cells were washed twice 
in PBS. The DAPI-positive cells were excluded as non-viable 
cells, and only DAPI-negative cells were analyzed further. To 
enrich quiescent cells relative to G 1 cells, cells with higher red 
fluorescence intensity were sorted according to Fucci fluores-
cence intensity. Equal numbers of proliferating cells expressing 
green fluorescence were sorted at the same time. Fluorescence 
analysis and cell sorting were carried out using a MoFlo XDP 
flow cytometer (Beckman Coulter). After sorting, cells were 
subjected to colony-forming assays as described below. 
Hypoxic treatment. To investigate the effect of oxygen ten-
sion on radiosensitivity, spheroids formed as described above 
were treated using the AnaeroPack-Anaero 5% (Mitsubishi 
Gas Chemical, Tokyo, Japan) as described previously. 
(17) Incu-
bation time was 9 h, which was sufficient to generate severe 
hypoxia (pO 2 &lt; 0.1% = 0.78 mmHg) in the liquid phase after 
equilibration with the air phase. Irradiation was given under 
this condition and then the spheroids were returned to normox-
ia. Twenty-four hours after reoxygenation, the spheroids were 
disaggregated and red and green cells were sorted as described 
above. Radiosensitivity was determined by a colony-forming 
assay as described below. 
Immunohistochemistry. To detect DNA-synthesizing cells, 
spheroids were incubated for 48 h in growth medium contain-
ing 10 lM 5-ethynyl-2 
0 -deoxyuridine (EdU), and sections were 
stained using the Click-iT Plus EdU Imaging kit (Invitrogen). 
Pimonidazole and hypoxia-inducible factor-1a (HIF-1a) were 
used as hypoxic markers and 53BP1 was used to detect DNA 
double-strand breaks (DSBs). Spheroids were incubated in 
200 lM pimonidazole-HCl (Hypoxyprobe-1; Hypoxyprobe, 
Burlington, MA, USA) for 8 h. Samples were fixed in PBS 
containing 4% paraformaldehyde for 24 h. Fixed samples were 
embedded in OCT compound (Sakura, Tokyo, Japan) and 
stored at À80°C. Frozen samples were cut with a cryostat into 
10-lm sections, and then boiled in Target Retrieval Solution 
(Dako, Glostrup, Denmark) for 20 min at 70°C. After antigen 
retrieval, non-specific antigens were blocked in Protein Block 
Serum-Free (Dako) for 20 min. Sections were incubated with 
anti-pimonidazole (1:50; Hypoxyprobe), anti-HIF1a (1:150; 
Novus Biologicals, Littleton, CO, USA), or anti-53BP1 (1:500; 
Abcam, Cambridge, UK) for 60 min at room temperature. 
After washing, samples were incubated with secondary anti-
bodies conjugated with Alexa Fluor 488, 555, or 647 (1:500; 
Invitrogen) for 30 min at room temperature. After immunore-
action, samples were counterstained with Hoechst 33342 </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | April 2017 | vol. 108 | no. 4 | 705 
© 2017 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Original Article 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas 
Onozato et al. </p>

<p>(1:1000; Invitrogen). All sections were mounted with ProLong 
Gold Antifade Reagent (Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, USA). 
For quantitation of the 53BP1 foci number per cell, 50 cells 
were randomly selected from outer and inner regions of the 
spheroids and foci were counted. Experiments were repeated 
three times and results were expressed as mean AE SE. 
Irradiation. Monolayer cells and spheroids were irradiated 
using an RX-650 Cabinet X-radiator system (Faxitron, Lin-
colnshire, IL, USA) at a dose rate of 0.75 Gy/min (130 kVp, 
5 mA, 0.5 mm Al filtration). 
Clonogenic assay. To assess radiosensitivity, an appropriate 
number of prepared single cells following irradiation were plated 
on dishes and incubated for approximately 10 days. Colonies 
were fixed and stained with crystal violet. Colonies consisting of 
more than 50 cells were counted, and surviving fractions (SFs) 
were determined as described previously. 
(16) Data were fitted to 
the following equation (linear-quadratic [LQ] model) by Kalei-
daGraph 3.6 (Synergy Software, Reading, PA, USA): </p>

<p>SF ¼ exp ðÀaD À bD 
2 Þ </p>

<p>Parameters of a, b, and D10 (dose obtaining SF at 10%) 
were determined by the curve fitting. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Mean values were statistically compared 
using one-way ANOVA with post hoc Tukey's multiple compar-
ison test or Student's t-test. P-values &lt;0.05 were considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Establishment of SAS-Fucci cells. A schematic diagram of the 
fluorescence colors emitted by the Fucci system over the 
course of the cell cycle is shown in Figure 1(a). To establish 
SAS cells expressing the Fucci probes, the Fucci plasmids 
were virally transduced into SAS cells, and Fucci-expressing 
cells were isolated through two-step cell sorting (Fig. S1). 
Ultimately, a clone expressing high levels of fluorescence was 
isolated and designated as SAS-Fucci. Fucci function was 
assessed by time-lapse imaging: red fluorescence gradually 
shifted to green fluorescence, and then back to red fluorescence 
after mitosis (Fig. 1b). Two-dimensional flow cytometry analy-
sis revealed the inverted U-phase (Fig. 1c) of exponentially 
growing cell populations. 
(12) After 10 Gy irradiation, the num-
ber of green cells gradually increased, reaching a peak approx-
imately 16 h after irradiation, and then red cells appeared 24 h </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Functional examination of SAS-Fucci cells. (a) Schematic diagram of fluorescence colors emitted by the Fucci system during the cell cycle. 
(b) Time-lapse imaging of Fucci fluorescence during cell cycle progression. Arrowheads indicate the same SAS-Fucci cell nucleus. (c) Time course 
of cell population during cell cycle progression following 10 Gy irradiation. Upper panels, time-lapse imaging of Fucci fluorescence. Middle pan-
els, time course of 2-D flow cytometric analysis of fluorescence intensities of monomeric Azami Green (mAG; green) and monomeric Kusabira 
Orange 2 (mKO2; red). Proportions of cells in each cell fraction are shown as percentages. Lower panels, time course of DNA content analysis. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | April 2017 | vol. 108 | no. 4 | 706 </p>

<p>Original Article 
Radiosensitivity of tumor spheroids 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas </p>

<p>after irradiation. By 72 h after irradiation, most cells had 
returned to their original distribution, although a small fraction 
of green cells persisted (Fig. 1c, upper and middle panels). 
These kinetics reflected G 2 arrest kinetics, as shown by DNA 
content analysis (Fig. 1c, lower panels). Overall, the fluores-
cence kinetics were similar to that of HeLa-Fucci cells 
reported previously. 
(13,14) Thus, we confirmed that the Fucci 
system expressed in SAS cells was fully functional. 
Structures of spheroids. We next formed multicellular spher-
oids (diameter,~700 lm). First, we observed the inner regions 
of the spheroids using histology sections (Fig. 2a). Green cells 
were concentrated in the outer layer, with a thickness of 
70 lm, whereas red cells were present inside the spheroid. 
DNA-synthesizing (S-phase) cells were labeled with EdU 
(Fig. 2a). The EdU staining overlapped with the outer layer, 
which mainly contained green cells. Confocal laser scanning 
images of the spheroid (Fig. S2) confirmed that the outer layer 
consisted mainly of green cells, whereas the interior consisted 
mainly of red cells. When using this method, deeper regions 
(&gt;100 lm from the surface) appear dark due to the optical 
conditions of the confocal scanning microscope system used. 
Furthermore, we examined hypoxic conditions inside the 
spheroids by immunostaining for HIF-1a and pimonidazole. 
The inner region was positive for HIF-1a, but not for 
pimonidazole (Fig. 2b), indicating that the interior was mildly, 
but not severely, hypoxic. 
(18,19) Taken together, these results 
indicated that the outer rim, rich in green cells, represented the 
growing fraction, whereas the interior, rich in red cells, was a 
quiescent fraction under mild hypoxia. 
Cell cycle kinetics in spheroids following irradiation. Figure 3 
shows time-lapse images of Fucci fluorescence at different 
depths in the absence (Fig. 3a) or presence (Fig. 3b) of irra-
diation. In addition, the time course of the ratio of green to </p>

<p>red fluorescent areas in the same plane is shown in the 
absence (Fig. 3c) or presence (Fig. 3d) of irradiation. Essen-
tially, in the absence of irradiation, the ratio did not change 
at any depth (Fig. 3c). At a depth of 25 lm, corresponding 
to the growing fraction, a mixture of red and green cells 
was observed. After irradiation, the proportion of green cells 
gradually increased, reaching a peak approximately 24 h after 
irradiation; thereafter, it decreased and went back to the orig-
inal distribution by 72 h, which was thought to reflect G 2 
arrest kinetics. The time required to reach the peak was 
somewhat longer than for cells in monolayer cultures 
(Fig. 1c). At a depth of 50 lm, only a small part of the qui-
escent fraction was included in the plane, whereas at a depth 
of 100 lm, the quiescent fraction accounted for the majority 
of the plane. Considering that quiescent red cells remained 
red even after irradiation, it is reasonable that the peak 
height decreased as the depth increased, as shown in Fig-
ure 3(d). </p>

<p>Isolation of cells in outer and inner regions grown as spheroids </p>

<p>after irradiation. We next tried to sort cells by flow cytometry 
according to Fucci fluorescence under sterile conditions to iso-
late cells in the outer proliferating and inner quiescent regions. 
As a control, red and green cells isolated from each fraction I 
and II (Fig. 4a, upper panel) showed essentially the same 
radiosensitivity in monolayer cultures (Fig. 4a, lower panel). 
Two-dimensional FACS revealed that the red fraction con-
sisted of cells with a wide range of red fluorescence intensities 
immediately after irradiation (Fig. 4b, upper panel), but pri-
marily of cells with higher intensities 24 h after irradiation 
(Fig. 4c, upper panel). These results indicate that, during the 
24 h after irradiation, cells with lower red fluorescence inten-
sity in the growing fraction reached G 2 phase (green) and 
stopped there, whereas quiescent cells remained in G 0 phase </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Histological analysis of spheroids consisting 
of SAS-Fucci cells. (a) Fucci fluorescence and 
staining 
of 
5-ethynyl-2 
0 -deoxyuridine 
(EdU) 
incorporated into DNA-synthesizing cells. EdU was 
incorporated into spheroids for 48 h, and thin 
sections were prepared. After EdU staining, 
fluorescence was observed. Bar = 100 lm. (b) 
Hypoxic conditions within spheroids. Spheroids 
were incubated with pimonidazole (Pimo) for 8 h, 
and thin sections were prepared. The sections were 
immunostained for hypoxia-inducible factor-1a 
(HIF-1a) and pimonidazole and counterstained with 
Hoechst. Bar = 100 lm. </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | April 2017 | vol. 108 | no. 4 | 707 
© 2017 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Original Article 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas 
Onozato et al. </p>

<p>(red) with higher intensity. The green fraction also shifted to 
the right, indicating that intensity increased due to the time 
spent in G 2 phase. Twenty-four hours after irradiation, the 
majority of cells in the growing fraction became green; conse-
quently, sorting by red and green fluorescence was assumed to 
almost perfectly separate growing and quiescent fractions. 
However, immediately after irradiation, a non-negligible pro-
portion of G 1 cells were present in the growing fraction. Given 
that all red cells were sorted, this fraction still contained part 
of the growing fraction. To overcome this issue, only cells 
with high intensity of red fluorescence, presumably corre-
sponding to G 0 phase, were sorted to avoid contamination by 
the growing fraction. </p>

<p>Determination of radiosensitivity in isolated quiescent and pro-</p>

<p>liferating cells from spheroids following irradiation. We finally 
tried to determine the radiosensitivities of isolated cells as 
described above by a clonogenic assay. Parameters fitted to the 
LQ model are summarized in Table S1. Surprisingly, the 
radiosensitivity of red cells sorted immediately after irradiation 
was the same as that of monolayer-cultured cells, and only 
green cells became markedly radioresistant (Fig. 4b, lower 
panel), clearly showing that this was due to the so-called con-
tact effect. 
(8) However, the surviving fractions of red cells </p>

<p>sorted 24 h after irradiation increased and became comparable 
to that of green cells (Fig. 4c, lower panel). This phenomenon 
is known as PLDR. 
(3) One could argue that the radioresistance 
stems from cells that survived the massive cell death that 
occurred during the 24 h after irradiation. The percentage of 
cells in the dead fraction, as judged by DAPI-positivity, did 
not significantly increase in the 24 h after irradiation (Fig. S3). 
Therefore, we were able to exclude this possibility and attri-
bute the radioresistance to PLDR. 
Radiosensitivity was the same between the outer and inner 
cells prepared from spheroids 24 h after irradiation. Next, we 
sought to determine whether such cells would show more 
radioresistance when irradiated under severe hypoxia. Because 
inner cells experienced mild hypoxia within the spheroid 
(Fig. 2b), we placed spheroids in a severely hypoxic condition 
(pO 2 &lt; 0.1% = 0.78 mmHg) and irradiated them. Remarkable 
radioresistance was observed in both outer and inner cells, 
which had comparable surviving fractions (Fig. 4d, lower 
panel). These results indicate that most of the inner cells were 
not in severely hypoxic conditions within spheroids, which do 
not significantly influence radiosensitivity. </p>

<p>Double-strand break content in outer and inner cells of spher-</p>

<p>oids following irradiation. It is well-established that DSB repair </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Time-lapse imaging inside of spheroids in live conditions. Time-lapse imaging of Fucci fluorescence at various depths from the bottom 
of the spheroid in the absence (a) or presence (b) of irradiation. Fucci fluorescence inside the spheroid for up to 72 h after sham or 10 Gy irradi-
ation was determined at each depth using a confocal laser scanning microscope. Bar = 200 lm. Time course of ratio of monomeric Azami Green 
(mAG; green) to monomeric Kusabira Orange 2 (mKO2; red) area at each depth in the absence (c) or presence (d) of irradiation. Areas of red or 
green fluorescence at each depth were quantitated using <rs id="software-7" type="software">ImageJ</rs> <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version">1.44</rs> software. Ratios were plotted as a function of time after start of the 
observation or irradiation. Representative values are shown. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | April 2017 | vol. 108 | no. 4 | 708 </p>

<p>Original Article 
Radiosensitivity of tumor spheroids 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas </p>

<p>activity is closely associated with clonogenic radiosensitiv-
ity. 
(20) Therefore, we examined the time course of DSB con-
tents in outer and inner cells following irradiation (Fig. 5). 
Immunofluorescence staining for 53BP1 recognizes DSB sites 
and therefore a decrease in 53BP1 foci reflects DSB repair 
kinetics. 
(21) Many 53BP1 foci were observed in outer cells 
0.5 h after irradiation, but significantly fewer foci in inner 
cells. Mild hypoxia was possibly sufficient to reduce the DSB 
number in inner cells. Until 72 h after irradiation, the foci 
number gradually decreased and inner cells always showed a 
significantly lower number of foci. These results indicate that 
simple DSB yield or DSB rejoining does not explain the dif-
ference in clonogenic radiosensitivity between quiescent and 
proliferating cells. </p>

<p>Determination of surviving cells in spheroids following irradia-</p>

<p>tion. We next tried to identify cells surviving when the struc-
ture of spheroids is maintained following irradiation. For this 
purpose, long-term observation of Fucci fluorescence was 
undertaken in the same way as Figure 3. Fucci fluorescence 
images at the indicated days after irradiation are shown in </p>

<p>Figure 6(a). Like Fig. 3b, radiation-induced G 2 arrest kinetics 
in the outer region was observed again. Judging from the 
spheroid size, the growing outer cells were first released from 
G 2 arrest followed by cell loss. Then, sequentially, from the 
outside towards the inside, red quiescent cells shifted to green 
growing cells followed by cell loss, and the spheroid gradually 
shrank. Forty-five days after irradiation, the shift stopped and 
red cells, presumably having constituted the core of the spher-
oid, entered a dormant state (Fig. 6b). The cells survived until 
76 days after irradiation, after which they were transferred to 
monolayer culture conditions. Cells started to regrow and 
showed clonogenicity (data not shown). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we separately isolated quiescent and proliferating 
cells from spheroids and determined their radiosensitivities 
using SAS-Fucci cells. Furthermore, this system enabled us to 
monitor long-term changes in cell kinetics inside the spheroid 
following irradiation. Novel major findings are as follows: (i) </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Isolation of outer and inner cells grown in spheroids and determination of their radiosensitivities. (a) Upper panel, FACS fractions of 
cells grown in monolayers sorted by flow cytometry: I, red cells; II, green cells. Lower panel, dose-survival curves for sorted red and green cells 
immediately after indicated doses of irradiation. Data represent mean AE SE of three independent determinants. (b) Upper panel, FACS fractions 
of cells grown in spheroids sorted by flow cytometry immediately after 10 Gy irradiation: I, red cells; II, green cells. Lower panel, dose-survival 
curves for red and green cells from spheroids obtained immediately after indicated doses of irradiation. Data represent mean AE SE of three inde-
pendent experiments. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01. (c) Upper panel, FACS fractions of cells grown in spheroids sorted by flow cytometry 24 h after 
10 Gy irradiation: I, red cells; II, green cells. Lower panel, dose-survival curves for red and green cells 24 h after indicated doses of irradiation. 
Data represent mean AE SE of three independent experiments. Some error bars cannot be seen because they would be smaller than the symbols. 
(d) Upper panel, FACS fractions of cells grown in spheroids sorted by flow cytometry 24 h after 10 Gy of irradiation under severe hypoxia: I, red 
cells; II, green cells. Spheroids were subjected to severe hypoxia for 9 h and then irradiated at the indicated doses. After irradiation, spheroids 
were returned to normoxia and incubated for 24 h. The spheroids were then disaggregated and red and green cells were sorted by flow cytome-
try. Lower panel, dose-survival curves for red and green cells 24 h after indicated doses of irradiation under severe hypoxia. Data represent 
mean AE SE of triplicate determinants. Some error bars cannot be seen because they would be smaller than the symbols. **P &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | April 2017 | vol. 108 | no. 4 | 709 
© 2017 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Original Article 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas 
Onozato et al. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Time course of DNA double-strand break contents in spheroids following irradiation. (a) Representative measured sites for outer (I) and 
inner (II) regions of spheroids after irradiation. Bar = 200 lm. (b) Immunofluorescence staining for 53BP1 at the indicated times after 10 Gy irra-
diation. Bar = 10 lm. (c) Quantitative analysis of 53BP1 foci number. Fifty cells were randomly selected from outer and inner regions and foci 
numbers were counted. Data represent mean AE SE of three independent experiments. **P &lt; 0.01. N.S., not significant. </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Long-term observation of a spheroid following irradiation. (a) Confocal scanning fluorescence images of a spheroid at indicated times 
after irradiation. A spheroid was irradiated with 10 Gy and a plane at a depth of 100 lm from the bottom was observed at the indicated times 
up to 76 days (d) after irradiation. Images were acquired by time-lapse imaging up to 3 days; thereafter, they were manually acquired every 3-
4 days on a confocal scanning microscope. Bar = 200 lm. (b) Time course of ratio of monomeric Azami Green (mAG; green) to monomeric Kus-
abira Orange 2 (mKO2; red) area following 10 Gy irradiation. Areas of red or green fluorescence were quantitated using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> 1.44 software. 
Ratios were plotted as a function of time after irradiation. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | April 2017 | vol. 108 | no. 4 | 710 </p>

<p>Original Article 
Radiosensitivity of tumor spheroids 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas </p>

<p>green cells containing DNA-synthesizing cells were concen-
trated in the outer layer, with a thickness of~70 lm, whereas 
red quiescent cells were present inside the spheroid; (ii) the 
inside quiescent fraction was HIF-1a-positive but pimonida-
zole-negative; (iii) proliferating cells, but not quiescent cells, 
showed more radioresistance compared to monolayer-cultured 
cells due to the contact effect; (iv) quiescent cells, but not pro-
liferating cells, showed PLDR 24 h after irradiation and the 
surviving fractions for the former reached the same level as 
those for the latter; (v) DSB contents were always significantly 
lower in quiescent cells within spheroids after irradiation; (vi) 
cell loss was observed after the shift from the quiescent to the 
proliferating stage within the spheroid following irradiation; 
and (vii) the central region of the spheroid entered a dormant 
stage and finally survived for at least 2.5 months. 
The contact effect, the radioresistance observed in spheroids 
independent of hypoxia, has been known for more than 
40 years; 
(8,9) however, its mechanisms remain elusive. An 
alteration in chromatin packaging influencing DNA repair effi-
ciency is a possible promising candidate. 
(8) The present study 
clearly shows that the contact effect occurs only in proliferat-
ing cells (Fig. 4a,b), consistent with the report that drugs stop-
ping cell cycle progression attenuated the contact effect. </p>

<p>(22)   Mild hypoxia was not sufficient for inducing hypoxia-asso-
ciated radioresistance in quiescent cells, but PLDR finally 
made them catch up with contact effect-induced radioresis-
tance in proliferating cells when disaggregated 24 h after irra-
diation (Fig. 4c). Notably, these phenomena were not simply 
correlated with DSB yield or DSB rejoining after irradiation 
(Fig. 5). Liu et al., 
(23) using the premature chromosome con-
densation method and FISH, reported that PLDR occurring in 
G 0 cells is due to enhanced fidelity of DSB repair through 
non-homologous end joining, but not due to enhanced rejoin-
ing. Taken together, a possible DSB repair mechanism might 
be postulated for the contact effect, as fidelity of DSB repair is 
somehow enhanced through alteration in chromatin packaging 
specifically occurring in growing cells within the spheroid. 
By observing the long-term cell cycle kinetics of the spher-
oid following irradiation, we found that cell loss occurred </p>

<p>during the release from G 2 arrest or recruitment from quiescent 
phase to growing phase (Fig. 6). Presumably, cell loss of outer 
cells subsequently caused reoxygenation of inner quiescent 
cells, thereby activating a switch from the quiescent to the pro-
liferating stage, 
(3) and in turn, cell death was induced. How-
ever, entering a dormant stage allowed cells to escape from 
the cycle, enabling them to survive. It is evident that this pro-
cess was not reproduced in the clonogenic assay because the 
spheroid structure was broken after disaggregation and tumor 
environments were lost. However, the question as to why dor-
mancy occurred in the spheroid after irradiation, remains to be 
addressed. This kind of dormancy is known to emerge in 
tumors after cancer therapy and is regarded as one of the 
mechanisms underlying the failure of cancer therapies. </p>

<p>(24-27)   Cancer stem cells are thought to be involved in it, 
(24,25) and it 
is intriguing to speculate the existence of such cancer stem 
cells at the center of the spheroid. Further study is required to 
shed light on this issue. 
In this study, the Fucci system enabled us to separately 
determine the radiosensitivity of quiescent and proliferating 
cells grown as multicellular spheroids, and made it possible to 
comprehensively characterize the radiosensitivity of spheroids 
for the first time. Our study highlighted the importance of cell 
cycle kinetics occurring in tumor microenvironments following 
irradiation as a factor influencing tumor radiosensitivity. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Dr. A. Miyawaki and Dr. A. Sakaue-Sawano for 
their permission to obtain Fucci plasmids through Riken BRC. This 
study was supported in part by the Japan Society for the Promotion of 
Science (Kakenhi grant nos. 26861569, 26293399, 16K20436, and 
16K15784) to A.K. and M.M. </p>

<p>Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>The authors have no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Cancer Sci | April 2017 | vol. 108 | no. 4 | 711 
© 2017 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Original Article 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas 
Onozato et al. </p>



<p>Supporting Information </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found online in the supporting information tab for this article: </p>

<p>Fig. S1. Two-step cell sorting of SAS cells transduced with Fucci plasmids. </p>

<p>Fig. S2. Fluorescence images of a spheroid consisting of SAS-Fucci cells, at varying depths from the bottom, obtained by confocal laser scanning 
microscopy. </p>

<p>Fig. S3. Fraction of dead cells following irradiation, as determined by FACS analysis. </p>

<p>Table S1. Parameters fitted to the LQ model regarding cell survival. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | April 2017 | vol. 108 | no. 4 | 712 </p>

<p>Original Article 
Radiosensitivity of tumor spheroids 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas </p>

</text></tei>