<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5339831" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Pyruvate kinase M2 isoform (PKM2) catalyzes the last step of glycolysis and plays an important role in tumor cell 
proliferation. Recent studies have reported that PKM2 also regulates apoptosis. However, the mechanisms under-
lying such a role of PKM2 remain elusive. Here we show that PKM2 translocates to mitochondria under oxidative 
stress. In the mitochondria, PKM2 interacts with and phosphorylates Bcl2 at threonine (T) 69. This phosphoryla-
tion prevents the binding of Cul3-based E3 ligase to Bcl2 and subsequent degradation of Bcl2. A chaperone protein, 
HSP90α1, is required for this function of PKM2. HSP90α1's ATPase activity launches a conformational change of 
PKM2 and facilitates interaction between PKM2 and Bcl2. Replacement of wild-type Bcl2 with phosphorylation-de-
ficient Bcl2 T69A mutant sensitizes glioma cells to oxidative stress-induced apoptosis and impairs brain tumor for-
mation in an orthotopic xenograft model. Notably, a peptide that is composed of the amino acid residues from 389 to 
405 of PKM2, through which PKM2 binds to Bcl2, disrupts PKM2-Bcl2 interaction, promotes Bcl2 degradation and 
impairs brain tumor growth. In addition, levels of Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation, conformation-altered PKM2 and Bcl2 
protein correlate with one another in specimens of human glioblastoma patients. Moreover, levels of Bcl2 T69 phos-
phorylation and conformation-altered PKM2 correlate with both grades and prognosis of glioma malignancy. Our 
findings uncover a novel mechanism through which mitochondrial PKM2 phosphorylates Bcl2 and inhibits apoptosis 
directly, highlight the essential role of PKM2 in ROS adaptation of cancer cells, and implicate HSP90-PKM2-Bcl2 
axis as a potential target for therapeutic intervention in glioblastoma. 
Cancer cells exhibit increased level of reactive oxygen 
species (ROS) than normal cells partly due to oncogenic </p>

<p>stimulation, increased metabolic activity and mitochon-
drial malfunction [1-3]. Under persistent oxidative stress, 
cancer cells become well-adapted to such stress through 
a set of mechanisms, which not only activate ROS-scav-
enging systems but also inhibit apoptosis [4]. A number 
of studies have suggested that such adaptation contrib-
utes to malignant transformation, metastasis and resis-
tance to anticancer drugs [5-7]. Therefore, understanding 
mechanisms of ROS adaptation is important to efficiently 
kill cancer cells and overcome drug resistance. </p>



<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>

<p>Pyruvate kinase (PK) catalyzes the final step of gly-
colysis and is comprised of four isoenzymes encoded by 
two distinct genes in mammals, PKLR and PKM. Alter-
native splicing of PKM pre-mRNA results in the gener-
ation of pyruvate kinase M1 (PKM1) and M2 (PKM2) 
by the inclusion of exon 9 and exon 10, respectively [8, 
9]. PKM2, but not PKM1, is upregulated in most human 
cancers. Replacement of PKM2 with PKM1 in lung can-
cer cells inhibits aerobic glycolysis and tumor growth 
in nude mouse xenograft [10]. Activation of epidermal 
growth factor receptor (EGFR) in human glioma cells 
leads to increased glucose uptake and lactate production 
in a PKM2 expression-dependent manner [11]. Mediated 
by extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK)-dependent 
phosphorylation, PKM2 is capable of translocating to 
the nucleus upon EGRF activation [12]. In the nucleus, 
PKM2 binds to c-Src-phosphorylated β-catenin and en-
hances β-catenin's transactivation activity, promoting the 
expression of downstream oncogene cyclin D1 and the 
progression of cell cycle [13]. Under hypoxic conditions, 
prolyl-hydroxylated PKM2 interacts with HIF1a to in-
duce glycolytic gene expression, which in turn enhances 
glucose metabolism in cancer cells [14]. These findings 
demonstrate the crucial roles of PKM2 in tumor cell pro-
liferation. 
Besides its important roles in promoting cell prolifera-
tion, PKM2 is also involved in the regulation of apopto-
sis. It has been shown that depletion of PKM2 expression 
by small interfering RNAs specifically against PKM2 
results in decreased viability and increased apoptosis in 
multiple cancer cell lines [15]. Silencing of PKM2 in rat 
and human glioma spheroids enhances both apoptosis 
and differentiation [16]. In non-small cell lung cancer 
(NSCLC), PKM2 deficiency enhances ionizing radia-
tion-induced apoptosis and autophagy in vitro and in vivo 
[17]. In addition to its anti-apoptotic function, PKM2 has 
been reported to translocate to the nucleus and induce 
a caspase-independent cell death in response to TT-232 
[18]. These results indicate that PKM2 also plays instru-
mental roles in cell survival. However, the mechanism 
underlying such roles of PKM2 remains elusive. 
B-cell lymphoma 2 (Bcl2) is an anti-apoptotic mem-
ber of the Bcl-2 family and is amplified in many human 
cancers [19]. The role of Bcl2 in ROS adaptation has 
been investigated in various laboratories. Ling et al. [20] 
demonstrated that ROS generation plays a vital role in 
the initiation of apoptotic cascade by proteasome inhib-
itor bortezomib. Overexpression of Bcl2 in prostate car-
cinoma cells diminishes bortezomib-induced apoptosis. 
Hildeman et al. [21] found that superoxide dismutase 
(SOD) mimetic MnTBAP decreases intracellular ROS 
and prevents apoptosis of activated T cells in vitro. Their 
study showed that MnTBAP increases the expression of </p>

<p>Bcl2, which is normally decreased by T-cell activation 
[21]. These findings indicate that Bcl2 plays an important 
role in ROS adaptation in different cell types. However, 
the mechanism through which Bcl2 is regulated during 
such adaptation is not well understood. 
In this study, we report that PKM2 translocates to 
the mitochondria under oxidative stress. Mitochondrial 
PKM2 interacts with and phosphorylates Bcl2, which 
then prevents Cul3-RBX1 ligase-mediated degradation 
of Bcl2, enhances apoptosis resistance of tumor cells and 
promotes gliomagenesis. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>PKM2 translocates to the mitochondria and inhibits hy-
drogen peroxide-induced Bcl2 degradation and apopto-
sis 
To investigate PKM2's role in ROS adaptation, we 
depleted endogenous PKM2 in U87 or U251 human 
glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) cells through the infec-
tion of a lentivirus expressing a specific shRNA against 
PKM2 (Supplementary information, Figure S1A). After 
hydrogen peroxide (H 2 O 2 ) or diamide (a thiol-oxidizing 
compound) treatment, U87 or U251 cells with PKM2 
depletion (U87/shPKM2 or U251/shPKM2) had much 
more apoptotic cells than those cells expressing non-tar-
geting shRNA (U87/shNT or U251/shNT), as determined 
by flow cytometry analysis of Annexin V-positive cells 
(Figure 1A and Supplementary information, Figure S1B). 
Similarly, caspase 3 activity was much more robust in 
U87/shPKM2 or U251/shPKM2 cells than that in U87/ 
shNT or U251/shNT cells after H 2 O 2 treatment (Figure 
1B). Cytochrome c is released from the mitochondria to 
the cytosol, where it binds to Apaf1 to activate caspase 
cascades, during the early stage of mitochondria-de-
pendent apoptosis [22]. Figure 1C showed that more 
cytochrome c was detected in cytosolic fraction in U87/ 
shPKM2 or U251/shPKM2 cells than that in the cells 
expressing shNT after H 2 O 2 treatment. Immune cells, 
such as Jurkat T cells, also express high levels of PKM2. 
To determine whether PKM2 has similar anti-apoptot-
ic function in Jurkat T cells, we depleted endogenous 
PKM2 in Jurkat T cells and examined the effect of PKM2 
depletion on H 2 O 2 -induced apoptosis. PKM2 depletion 
did not significantly increase the percentage of apoptotic 
cells in Jurkat T cells after H 2 O 2 treatment (Supplementary 
information, Figure S1C), suggesting the cell-type spec-
ificity of PKM2 anti-apoptotic function. Taken together, 
these results demonstrate that PKM2 is essential for the 
resistance of glioma cells to oxidative stress-induced and 
mitochondria-dependent apoptosis. 
To understand the mechanism of PKM2 regulation of 
such apoptosis, we examined subcellular localization of </p>

<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>



<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>

<p>PKM2 after H 2 O 2 treatment. Immunofluorescent analysis 
with anti-PKM2 or anti-VDAC (ubiquitously expressed 
and located in the outer mitochondrial membrane) an-
tibody showed that ~15% of PKM2 was translocated 
to the mitochondria in U87 cells upon H 2 O 2 treatment 
(Figure 1D), which was supported by a subcellular frac-
tionation analysis, showing that more PKM2 was detect-
ed in mitochondrial fraction of U87 or U251 cells after 
H 2 O 2 treatment (Figure 1E). More thorough experiments 
of submitochondrial fractionation were also performed, 
showing that PKM2 was translocated to outer membrane 
of mitochondria upon H 2 O 2 treatment (Supplementa-
ry information, Figure S1D). Thus, we speculated that 
PKM2 might regulate apoptosis via modulation of mito-
chondrial proteins. To test this possibility, we performed 
a mass spectrometry analysis of proteins associated with 
mitochondrial PKM2. Among them, three Bcl2 family 
proteins, including Bcl2, Bcl-xl and Bax, were identified 
(Supplementary information, Table S1). These proteins 
have been reported to regulate apoptosis by controlling 
mitochondrial membrane permeability [19]. Interactions 
between PKM2 and these proteins were further validat-
ed by co-immunoprecipitation analyses. Both Bcl2 and 
Bax could interact with PKM2, whereas Bcl-xl failed to 
do so (Supplementary information, Figure S1E). How-
ever, only Bcl2 protein level was markedly decreased in 
H 2 O 2 -treated U87/shPKM2 cells, whereas levels of Bcl-
xl or Bax proteins were not (Figure 1F). mRNA levels 
of Bcl2 showed no significant difference between U87/ 
shNT and U87/shPKM2 cells with or without H 2 O 2 
treatment, suggesting that PKM2 post-transcriptionally 
regulated Bcl2 (Figure 1G). Furthermore, treatment of a 
potent proteasome inhibitor MG132 abrogated H 2 O 2 -in-
duced decrease of Bcl2 protein level in U87/shPKM2 
cells (Figure 1H). These data confirmed that PKM2 
depletion enhanced a proteasome-mediated degradation </p>

<p>of Bcl2 induced by H 2 O 2 treatment. Consistently, H 2 O 2 
induced more Bcl2 polyubiquitination in U87/shPKM2 
cells than in U87/shNT cells (Figure 1I). These findings 
demonstrate that PKM2 translocates to the mitochondria 
and sustains Bcl2 protein stability, therefore enhancing 
the resistance of tumor cells to oxidative stress. 
In addition to H 2 O 2 treatment, we examined whether 
PKM2 depletion can enhance Bcl2 degradation under 
treatments of tumor necrosis factor α (TNFα; inflamma-
tory cytokine), paclitaxel (PTX; anti-cancer cytotoxic 
drug) or temozolomide (TMZ; an alkylating agent used 
for glioma treatment). As shown in Supplementary infor-
mation, Figure S1F, PKM2 depletion enhanced TNFα-
and PTX-induced, but not TMZ-induced, Bcl2 degra-
dation. More types of tumor cells, such as A549 lung 
cancer cells and HT29 colon cancer cells, were examined 
for PKM2's ability to stabilize Bcl2 protein. Consistent 
results were obtained, showing that PKM2 depletion pro-
moted H 2 O 2 -induced degradation of Bcl2 in both A549 
and HT29 cells (Supplementary information, Figure 
S1G). 
To avoid the overexpression of target proteins, much 
less exogenous PKM2 or Bcl2 was expressed than those 
endogenous proteins in tumor cells through limiting in-
fection efficiency (Supplementary information, Figure 
S1H). </p>

<p>PKM2 interacts with and stabilizes Bcl2 
To investigate the mechanism through which PKM2 
regulates Bcl2, a co-immunoprecipitation assay was 
performed to validate their interaction. Immunoblotting 
analyses of immunoprecipitated Bcl2 with an anti-PKM2 
antibody (Figure 2A) or immunoprecipitated PKM2 
with an anti-Bcl2 antibody (Supplementary information, 
Figure S2A) showed that endogenous PKM2 interacted 
with endogenous Bcl2 reciprocally, but not with succi-</p>

<p>Figure 1 PKM2 translocates to the mitochondria and inhibits H 2 O 2 -induced Bcl2 degradation and apoptosis. Immunoprecip-
itation and immunoblotting analyses were performed with the indicated antibodies. Data are representative of at least three 
independent experiments. (A, B) U87 (top panel) or U251 (bottom panel) cells that stably express control shRNA (shNT) or 
shRNA against PKM2 (shPKM2) were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 24 h). The cells were harvested for apoptosis 
analysis using Annexin V-Cy5 Apoptosis Kit (A) or caspase 3 activity analysis (B). Data represent the means ± SD of three 
independent experiments. CON, control. (C) U87 or U251 cells with or without PKM2 depletion were treated with H 2 O 2 (0.5 
mM, 24 h) and harvested for cytosolic (Cyto) and mitochondrial (Mito) fractionation. (D) U87 cells were treated with or without 
H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). Immunofluorescence analyses were performed using anti-PKM2 or anti-VDAC antibodies. Representa-
tive images were shown in left panel. Co-localization of two proteins in 300 cells was quantified using the software of <rs id="software-2" type="software">Volocity</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">PerkinElmer</rs>, right panel). (E) U87 or U251 cells were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). Cytosolic and mitochondrial 
fractions of the cells were prepared. (F) U87/shNT or U87/shPKM2 cells were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 4 h). (G) 
U87/shNT or U87/shPKM2 cells were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 4 h). Quantitative RT-PCR was performed to ex-
amine mRNA levels of Bcl2. Data represent the means ± SD of three independent experiments. (H) U87/shPKM2 cells were 
pretreated with or without MG132 for 0.5 h, followed by treatment of H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM) for 4 h. (I) U87/shNT or U87/shPKM2 
cells were infected with a lentivirus expressing SFB-Bcl2. The cells were pretreated with MG132 for 0.5 h and then treated 
with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 4 h). Pull-down of SFB-Bcl2 was performed with streptavidin agarose beads. PD, pull-down. </p>

<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>



<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>

<p>nate dehydrogenase (SDHA; used as a negative control) 
in both U87 and U251 cells upon H 2 O 2 treatment. These 
observations were further supported by an immunofluo-
rescence staining, showing that PKM2 colocalized with 
Bcl2 after H 2 O 2 treatment (Figure 2B). We also examined 
the interaction between PKM2 and Bcl2 under various 
treatments or in various types of tumor cells. TNFα or 
PTX could induce the interaction between PKM2 and 
Bcl2, whereas TMZ failed to do so (Supplementary in-
formation, Figure S2B). Consistently, PKM2 interacted 
with Bcl2 in A549 and HT29 cells, but not in Jurkat T 
cells, upon H 2 O 2 treatment (Supplementary information, 
Figure S2C). We further explored the location of PKM2 
interaction with Bcl2, as PKM2 and Bcl2 also locate in 
the nucleus besides the mitochondria. Subcellular frac-
tionation experiments were performed, showing that 
PKM2 interacted with Bcl2 in the mitochondria, but not 
in the nucleus (Supplementary information, Figure S2D). 
PKM1 shares high homology with PKM2 in protein 
sequence, as they differ from each other in only one 
exon. PKM2 contains exon 10, whereas PKM1 contains 
exon 9 [9]. To narrow searching range for Bcl2-in-
teracting region on PKM2, we tested whether PKM1 
interacts with Bcl2. U87 cells were infected with a len-
tivirus expressing Flag-tagged PKM2 (Flag-PKM2) or 
Flag-PKM1. Immunoblotting analyses of immunopre-
cipitated Flag-PKM2 or Flag-PKM1 with an anti-Bcl2 
antibody showed that PKM1, unlike PKM2, did not 
interact with Bcl2 after H 2 O 2 treatment (Figure 2C), 
suggesting that PKM2 may interact with Bcl2 through 
the region encoded by exon 10 of PKM2. According to 
secondary structure of PKM2 exon 10, we constructed 
four S-Flag-Streptavidin-binding peptide (SFB)-tagged 
PKM2 mutants with the deletion of the indicated amino </p>

<p>acid residues, including PKM2 Δ370-388, PKM2 Δ389-
405, PKM2 Δ406-423 and PKM2 Δ424-435. Immuno-
blotting analyses of precipitated SFB-PKM2 proteins 
with anti-Bcl2 antibody showed that only PKM2 Δ389-
405 failed to bind to Bcl2 among PKM2 mutants (Figure 
2D). Bcl2 has been reported to interact with other pro-
teins through hydrophobic or ionic bonds [23]. Accord-
ing to amino acid properties, we constructed two PKM2 
mutants, PKM2 ILLL, in which hydrophobic amino 
acids (isoleucine 389, leucine 392, leucine 394 and leu-
cine 398) were mutated to alanine, and PKM2 EERR, 
in which ionic amino acids (glutamic acid 396, glutamic 
acid 397, arginine 399, and arginine 400) were mutated 
to alanine. Both PKM2 WT and PKM2 EERR interacted 
with Bcl2, whereas PKM2 ILLL failed to do so (Figure 
2E and Supplementary information, Figure S2E). 
To investigate whether PKM2-Bcl2 interaction is 
required for Bcl2 protein stability, we generated en-
dogenous PKM2-depleted U87 cells with reconstituted 
expression of shRNA-resistant (r) PKM2 WT or rPKM2 
ILLL (Figure 2F). Immunoblotting analyses of immuno-
precipitated Bcl2 with anti-ubiquitin antibody showed 
that H 2 O 2 treatment resulted in more polyubiquitination 
of Bcl2 in U87 cells expressing rPKM2 ILLL than in the 
cells expressing rPKM2 WT (Figure 2G). Consistently, 
Bcl2 protein levels were decreased in the cells express-
ing rPKM2 ILLL, but not in the cells expressing rPKM2 
WT, after H 2 O 2 treatment (Figure 2H). 
To test the specificity of PKM2 ILLL mutation, we 
examined pyruvate kinase and protein kinase activities 
of PKM2 ILLL mutant. As shown in Supplementary 
information, Figure S2F, PKM2 ILLL has comparable 
pyruvate kinase activity to PKM2 WT. We further exam-
ined the glycolytic activities of the corresponding PKM2 </p>

<p>Figure 2 PKM2 interacts with and stabilizes Bcl2. Immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting analyses were performed with the 
indicated antibodies. Data are representative of at least three independent experiments. (A) U87 or U251 cells were treated 
with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). Succinate dehydrogenase (SDHA) that has not been reported to interact with PKM2 or 
Bcl2 was used as a negative control. (B) U87 cells were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). Immunofluorescence was 
performed using anti-PKM2 and anti-Bcl2 antibodies. Representative images were presented in left panel. Co-localization of 
two proteins in 300 cells was quantified using the software of <rs type="software">Volocity</rs> (right panel). (C) U87 cells were infected with a lenti-
virus expressing Flag-PKM1 or Flag-PKM2 and then treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). (D) U87 cells were infected 
with a lentivirus expressing SFB-PKM2 WT or the indicated deletion mutants and then treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 
1 h). Pull-down of SFB-PKM2 proteins was performed with streptavidin agarose beads. (E) U87 cells stably expressing SFB-
PKM2 WT or ILLL were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). Pull-down of SFB-PKM2 proteins was performed with 
streptavidin agarose beads. (F-H) U87 cells were depleted of endogenous PKM2 and then reconstituted with the expression 
of rPKM2 WT or rPKM2 ILLL (F). The cells were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM) for 4 h (G, H). The cells were pretreat-
ed with MG132 for 0.5 h before H 2 O 2 treatment (G). (I) U87 cells that stably express SFB-Bcl2 were treated with or without 
H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). SFB-Bcl2 complex was precipitated using streptavidin agarose beads. A peptide competition assay was 
performed by mixing precipitated SFB-Bcl2 complex with 1.0 µg synthesized Flag or PKM2 389-405 peptides. (J, K) U87 
cells that stably express SFB-Bcl2 were infected with a lentivirus expressing HA-tagged PKM2 389-405 peptide or Flag pep-
tide and then treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM) for 1 (J) or 4 h (K). SFB-Bcl2 complex was precipitated using streptavidin 
agarose beads (J). Expression of Flag or PKM2 peptides was examined using dot blot assay with anti-HA antibody. </p>

<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>ILLL-reconstituted cells. The data showed that similar 
glucose consumption and lactate production were detect-
ed in both PKM2 WT-and ILLL-reconstituted U87 cells 
(Supplementary information, Figure S2G). We previous-
ly reported that PKM2 could phosphorylate Histone H3 
at threonine (T) 11 [24]. Thus, we examined the phos-
phorylation of Histone H3 T11 by PKM2 WT or ILLL. 
The data showed that both PKM2 WT and ILLL could 
phosphorylate Histone H3 T11 at similar levels (Supple-
mentary information, Figure S2H). Together, these data 
suggested that PKM2 ILLL only lost the binding to Bcl2, 
but still reserved its pyruvate kinase and protein kinase 
activities. 
Peptide medicine is recognized for being highly selec-
tive and efficacious, and at the same time, relatively safe 
and well tolerated. We next investigated the possibility of 
the peptide that is composed of amino acids ranging from 
389 to 405 of PKM2 as an anti-tumor drug. U87 cells 
were infected with a lentivirus expressing SFB-Bcl2. 
Precipitated SFB-Bcl2 complex was incubated with syn-
thesized Flag or PKM2 389-405 peptides. PKM2 389-
405 peptide remarkably disrupted H 2 O 2 -induced inter-
action between PKM2 and Bcl2, whereas Flag peptides 
could not (Figure 2I). 
To confirm actual binding of PKM2 peptides to Bcl2, 
biotinylated PKM2 or Flag peptides were synthesized 
and incubated with U87 lysates or bacteria-purified 
recombinant Bcl2. As shown in Supplementary infor-
mation, Figure S2I and S2J, endogenous Bcl2 or recom-
binant Bcl2 could be co-precipitated with biotinylated 
PKM2 peptides, but not with biotinylated Flag peptides, 
in a dose-dependent manner. In addition, the more PKM2 
was expressed, the less Bcl2 was pulled down by bioti-
nylated PKM2 peptides (Supplementary information, 
Figure S2K). 
Inhibition of PKM2-Bcl2 interaction by PKM2 pep-
tides was further examined in cells. U87 cells that stably 
express SFB-Bcl2 were infected with a lentivirus ex-
pressing PKM2 389-405 or Flag peptides. Expression 
of PKM2 peptides significantly inhibited H 2 O 2 -induced 
interaction between PKM2 and Bcl2, and caused subse-
quent degradation of Bcl2 (Figure 2J and 2K). Expres-
sion levels of PKM2 or Flag peptides were examined us-
ing dot blot assay, showing that PKM2 and Flag peptides 
had similar expression levels (Figure 2J and 2K). These 
results implicate a therapeutic potential of PKM2 389-
405 peptide as an anti-cancer drug. </p>

<p>HSP90α1 alters PKM2 conformation and facilitates in-
teraction between PKM2 and Bcl2 
To investigate mechanism through which PKM2 inter-
acts with Bcl2, we tested whether PKM2 interacts with </p>

<p>Bcl2 directly. Recombinant His-Bcl2 and GST-PKM2 
were purified from bacteria. Purities of two proteins 
were examined by gel staining with Coomassie Blue 
(Supplementary information, Figure S3A). GST pull-
down assays were performed by mixing PKM2 and Bcl2 
or PKM2 and commercial Histone H3 (NEB) that has 
been reported to interact with PKM2 in vitro [24]. The 
data showed that Bcl2 could not bind to PKM2 in vitro, 
whereas Histone H3 could do so (Figure 3A). Analysis of 
PKM2 structure implied that PKM2 389-405 fragment, 
especially four hydrophobic amino acids (I389, L392, 
L394 and L398) of PKM2 that are essential for PKM2-
Bcl2 interaction, are mostly buried inside (Supplementary 
information, Figure S3B). Thus, we proposed that PKM2 
structure should be altered to expose those critical amino 
acids. To search for potential isomerase, we performed a 
mass spectrum analysis of proteins associated with total 
PKM2 after H 2 O 2 treatment. HSP90α1 was identified 
to be the only associated protein that can alter protein 
conformation (Supplementary information, Table S2). 
Interaction between HSP90α1 and PKM2 was further 
validated by a co-immunoprecipitation assay, showing 
that HSP90α1 interacted with PKM2 after H 2 O 2 treat-
ment (Figure 3B). 
HSP90α1, an isoform of HSP90, is a chaperone pro-
tein that assists other proteins to fold properly, stabilizes 
proteins against heat stress and aids in protein degra-
dation. To determine whether HSP90α1 is required for 
PKM2-Bcl2 interaction, we depleted HSP90α1 in U87 
cells with a shRNA against HSP90AA1 (Supplementa-
ry information, Figure S3C). Immunoblotting analyses 
of immunoprecipitated Bcl2 with anti-PKM2 antibody 
showed that HSP90α1 depletion abrogated the interac-
tion between PKM2 and Bcl2 (Figure 3C). To map the 
interacting region of HSP90α1 and PKM2, three deletion 
mutants of HSP90α1 were constructed (Figure 3D), in-
cluding N-terminal deletion mutant (ΔN), middle domain 
mutant (MD) and C-terminal deletion mutant (ΔC). 
Among three HSP90α1 mutants, only HSP90α1 MD 
could bind to PKM2 (Figure 3E). To further pinpoint the 
exact interacting region on HSP90α1, three more dele-
tion mutants of HSP90α1 were constructed according to 
crystal structure of HSP90α1 [25], including HSP90α1 
1-293, 1-360 and 1-469. Co-immunoprecipitation anal-
yses of HSP90α1 WT and mutants showed that only 
HSP90α1 1-293 lost the binding to PKM2 among the 
mutants under H 2 O 2 treatment (Figure 3F). The region 
spanning amino acids 327-340 of HSP90β, which is ho-
mologous to the region spanning amino acids 347-360 of 
HSP90α1, has been reported to be involved in the bind-
ing to its client protein AKT [26]. Thus, we tested wheth-
er amino acids 347-360 of HSP90α1 are required for its </p>



<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>

<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>binding to PKM2. HSP90α1 deletion mutant, HSP901 
Δ347-360 lost the binding to PKM2 after H 2 O 2 treatment 
(Figure 3G). Meanwhile, we also mapped the region of 
HSP90α1-PKM2 interaction on PKM2. Supplementary 
information, Figure S3D showed that both PKM2 Δ389-
405 and PKM2 Δ406-423 lost their binding to HSP90α1. 
Ionic bonds are often involved in HSP90 substrate bind-
ing [26]. Considering simultaneous surface exposure of 
the interacting amino acids of PKM2, four ionic amino 
acids (R399, R400, D407 and E410) of PKM2, which are 
located on the surface of PKM2 protein, were mutated to 
alanine (PKM2 RRDE). Co-immunoprecipitation anal-
yses showed that PKM2 WT interacted with HSP90α1 
upon H 2 O 2 treatment, whereas PKM2 RRDE mutant 
failed to do so (Supplementary information, Figure 
S3E). Together, these results demonstrated that amino 
acids 347-360 of HSP90α1 are involved in the binding 
to PKM2, and that PKM2 is likely a client protein of 
HSP90α1. 
HSP90α1's ATPase activity often induces conforma-
tional change in client proteins, thereby causing their 
activation [27]. To determine whether HSP90α1 alters 
PKM2 conformation, we performed chaperon assay by 
mixing recombinant GST-PKM2 with HSP90α1 WT or 
HSP90α1 G97D (ATPase activity dead mutant), in which 
glycine 97 was mutated to aspartic acid. Immunoblot-
ting analyses of precipitated GST-PKM2 with a PKM2-
389 antibody, which specifically recognizes PKM2 389-
405 fragment that is buried inside the protein before 
H 2 O 2 treatment, showed that GST-PKM2 could only 
be recognized by PKM2-389 antibody in the presence 
of HSP90α1 WT, but not HSP90α1 G97D (Figure 3H), 
suggesting that PKM2 conformation was altered by </p>

<p>HSP90α1 to expose PKM2 389-405 fragment. We further 
examined this result in cells. U87 cells were depleted 
of endogenous HSP90α1 and reconstituted with the ex-
pression of rHSP90α1 WT or rHSP90α1 G97D (Supple-
mentary information, Figure S3F). Inhibition of HSP90 
activity by HSP90α1 G97D expression was confirmed by 
examining the expression of HSP90α1 substrate proteins, 
AKT1 and Chk1. rHSP90α1 G97D expression signifi-
cantly inhibited the expression of AKT1 and Chk1 (Sup-
plementary information, Figure S3G). Immunoblotting 
analyses of the precipitated SFB-PKM2 with PKM2-
389 antibody showed that H 2 O 2 -induced alteration of 
PKM2 conformation could only be detected in the cells 
expressing rHSP90α1 WT, but not in the cells expressing 
rHSP90α1 G97D (Figure 3I). 
To determine whether HSP90α1-mediated conforma-
tional change of PKM2 is required for PKM2-Bcl2 in-
teraction, co-immunoprecipitation assay was performed 
using Bcl2 antibody in HSP90α1-depleted U87 cells that 
were reconstituted with the expression of rHSP90α1 WT 
or G97D. As shown in Figure 3J, PKM2 interacted with 
Bcl2 in cells expressing rHSP90α1 WT, but not in cells 
expressing rHSP90α1 G97D, after H 2 O 2 treatment. This 
result was further supported by an HSP90α1-mediated 
chaperon assay followed by a GST pull-down assay, 
showing that PKM2 could only interact with Bcl2 in the 
presence of HSP90α1 WT, but not HSP90α1 G97D (Fig-
ure 3K). Consistently, H 2 O 2 treatment induced more deg-
radation of Bcl2 in the cells expressing rHSP90α1 G97D 
than in the cells expressing rHSP90α1 WT (Figure 3L). 
HSP90α1-mediated conformational change of PKM2 
was also confirmed using an HSP90 inhibitor (17-AAG), 
which could efficiently inhibit expression of AKT1 </p>

<p>Figure 3 HSP90α1 alters PKM2 conformation and facilitates the interaction between PKM2 and Bcl2. Immunoprecipitation 
and immunoblotting analyses were performed with the indicated antibodies. Data are representative of at least three inde-
pendent experiments. (A) GST pull-down assay was performed by mixing bacteria-purified recombinant GST-PKM2 and 
His-Bcl2, or GST-PKM2 and Histone H3 at 4 °C for 4 h. GST-PKM2 was precipitated using glutathione agarose beads. (B) 
U87 cells that stably express SFB-PKM2 were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). SFB-PKM2 was pulled down us-
ing streptavidin agarose beads. (C) U87 cells that stably express shNT or shHSP90α1 were treated with or without H 2 O 2 
(0.5 mM, 1 h). (D) Flag-HSP90α1 WT and Flag-HSP90α1 deletion mutants, HSP90α1 ∆C(1-224), MD(1-544) and ∆N(545-
731), used in the experiments are represented as black bars. (E) U87 cells were infected with a lentivirus expressing Flag-
HSP90α1 WT or Flag-HSP90α1 deletion mutants and then treated with H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). (F) U87 cells were infected with 
a lentivirus expressing Flag-HSP90α1 WT or Flag-HSP90α1 1-293 or Flag-HSP90α1 1-360 or Flag-HSP90α1 1-469 (bottom 
panel). Flag-HSP90α1 WT and Flag-HSP90α1 truncation mutants, HSP90α1 1-293, 1-360 and 1-469, used in the experi-
ments are represented as black bars (top panel). (G) U87 cells were infected with a lentivirus expressing Flag-HSP90α1 WT 
or Flag-HSP90α1 ∆347-360. (H) Chaperone assay was performed by mixing GST-PKM2 and recombinant HSP90α1 WT or 
G97D. After the reaction, GST-PKM2 was pulled down using glutathione agarose beads. (I) U87 cells were depleted of en-
dogenous HSP90α1 and then reconstituted with the expression of rHSP90α1 WT or G97D. The cells were further infected 
with a lentivirus expressing SFB-PKM2 and then treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). (J) HSP90α1-depleted U87 cells 
were reconstituted with the expression of rHSP90α1 WT or G97D and then treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). (K) 
Chaperone assay was performed by mixing recombinant HSP90α1 WT or G97D and GST-PKM2. After the reaction, GST-
PKM2 were pulled down using glutathione agarose beads and incubated with His-Bcl2 at 4 °C for 4 h. (L) HSP90α1-depleted 
U87 cells that were reconstituted with the expression of rHSP90α1 WT or G97D were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 4 h). </p>



<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>

<p>and Chk1 (Supplementary information, Figure S3H). 
As shown in Supplementary information, Figure S3I 
and S3J, pretreatment of 17-AAG markedly inhibited 
H 2 O 2 -induced alteration of PKM2 conformation and 
PKM2-Bcl2 interaction. Consistently, H 2 O 2 -induced 
degradation of Bcl2 was markedly enhanced by 17-AAG 
treatment (Supplementary information, Figure S3K). </p>

<p>PKM2 phosphorylates Bcl2 at T69 
It has been reported that Bcl2 stability could be reg-
ulated by phosphorylation [28]. To investigate whether 
PKM2 regulates Bcl2 phosphorylation, we performed 
mass spectrometry analysis of Bcl2 phosphorylation in 
U87 cells after H 2 O 2 treatment, showing that threonine (T) 
69 and serine (S) 70 of Bcl2 were phosphorylated after 
H 2 O 2 treatment. Immunoblotting analyses of the precipi-
tated SFB-Bcl2 with anti-Bcl2 pT69 and anti-Bcl2 pS70 
antibodies showed that PKM2 depletion significantly 
blocked Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation, but not Bcl2 S70 
phosphorylation (Figure 4A and Supplementary infor-
mation, Figure S4A). Regulation of Bcl2 T69 phosphor-
ylation by PKM2 was further verified in more types of 
tumor cells or under more treatments. Both TNFα-and 
PTX-induced Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation were significant-
ly inhibited by PKM2 depletion, whereas TMZ treatment 
could not even induce Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation (Sup-
plementary information, Figure S4B). H 2 O 2 -induced Bcl2 
T69 phosphorylation was blocked by PKM2 depletion in 
A549 or HT29 cells, whereas Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation 
could not even be induced in Jurkat T cells after H 2 O 2 
treatment (Supplementary information, Figure S4C). 
Previous studies from our and other groups have 
reported that PKM2 is capable of phosphorylating pro-
teins as a protein kinase [24]. We next tested whether 
PKM2 phosphorylates Bcl2. In vitro kinase assays were 
performed by mixing 32 p-labeled PEP with recombinant 
PKM2 or PKM1 and Bcl2 WT or phosphorylation-de-
ficient Bcl2 mutants. Figure 4B and 4C showed that 
PKM2, but not PKM1, could phosphorylate Bcl2, and 
that Bcl2 T69A was resistant to phosphorylation, where-
as Bcl2 S70A could still be phosphorylated. Phosphor-
ylation of Bcl2 T69 by PKM2 was further validated by 
LC-MS/MS analyses, showing that Bcl2 T69 was the 
only residue phosphorylated by PKM2 (Figure 4D and 
Supplementary information, Figure S4D). To further 
verify Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation by PKM2 in cells, U87 
cells with depleted PKM2 and reconstituted expression 
of rPKM2 WT or ILLL were infected with a lentivirus 
expressing SFB-Bcl2. Immunoblotting analyses of the 
precipitated SFB-Bcl2 with anti-Bcl2 pT69 antibody 
showed that Bcl2 T69 was phosphorylated in cells ex-
pressing rPKM2 WT, but not in cells expressing rPKM2 </p>

<p>ILLL, after H 2 O 2 treatment (Figure 4E). Together, these 
data clearly indicated that PKM2 phosphorylated Bcl2 at 
T69 after H 2 O 2 treatment. 
We further tested whether PKM2-dependent Bcl2 
phosphorylation is required to sustain Bcl2 protein lev-
el. U87 cells were infected with a lentivirus expressing 
SFB-Bcl2 WT or T69A. Immunoblotting analyses of the 
precipitated SFB-Bcl2 with an anti-ubiquitin antibody 
showed that Bcl2 T69A had more polyubiquitination 
than Bcl2 WT after H 2 O 2 treatment (Figure 4F). Consis-
tently, H 2 O 2 treatment resulted in more degradation of 
Bcl2 T69A than that of Bcl2 WT (Figure 4G). </p>

<p>PKM2-dependent Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation prevents the 
binding of Cul3-based E3 ligase to Bcl2 
It has been reported that Bcl2 could be ubiquitinated 
by Cul3-based E3 ligase and subsequently degraded [29]. 
To investigate the mechanism through which PKM2 sta-
bilizes Bcl2 protein, we examined whether PKM2 inter-
feres with recruitment of Cul3-based E3 ligase to Bcl2. 
U87 cells were depleted of PKM2 and reconstituted with 
expression of rPKM2 WT or ILLL. Immunoblotting 
analyses of immunoprecipitated Bcl2 with anti-Cul3 
and anti-Rbx1 antibodies showed that Bcl2 interacted 
with both Cul3 and Rbx1 in cells expressing rPKM2 
ILLL, but not in cells expressing rPKM2 WT, after H 2 O 2 
treatment (Figure 5A), suggesting that PKM2 interacts 
with Bcl2 and prevents binding of E3 ligase to Bcl2. We 
next examined whether Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation is re-
quired to prevent the recruitment of E3 ligase. Figure 5B 
showed that Bcl2 T69A was associated with more Cul3 
and Rbx1 than Bcl2 WT after H 2 O 2 treatment. In con-
trast, phosphorylation-mimic mutant of Bcl2, Bcl2 T69E, 
interacted with much less Cul3 and Rbx1 than Bcl2 WT 
in H 2 O 2 -treated U87 cells with PKM2 depletion (Figure 
5C). 
To further demonstrate whether Cul3-based E3 ligase 
is involved in H 2 O 2 -induced Bcl2 degradation, we de-
pleted Cul3 using siRNA against CUL3 (siCul3) in U87 
cells with depleted PKM2 and reconstituted expression 
of rPKM2 ILLL, or in U87 cells expressing Bcl2 T69A. 
Immunoblotting analyses of immunoprecipitated Bcl2 
or precipitated SFB-Bcl2 with anti-ubiquitin antibod-
ies showed that Cul3 depletion remarkably inhibited 
H 2 O 2 -induced polyubiquitination of Bcl2 in cells express-
ing rPKM2 ILLL or H 2 O 2 -induced polyubiquitination of 
Bcl2 T69A (Figure 5D and 5E). Consistently, Cul3 deple-
tion blocked H 2 O 2 -induced degradation of Bcl2 in cells 
expressing rPKM2 ILLL or H 2 O 2 -induced degradation of 
Bcl2 T69A (Figure 5F and 5G). Taken together, these re-
sults demonstrate that PKM2-dependent phosphorylation 
of Bcl2 T69 prevents the binding of Cul3-Rbx1 ligase to </p>

<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>



<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>

<p>Bcl2, therefore inhibiting Bcl2 degradation. </p>

<p>Phosphorylation of Bcl2 T69 by PKM2 enhances resis-
tance of tumor cells to oxidative stress and promotes gli-
omagenesis 
To explore the biological function of PKM2-depen-
dent Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation, U87 or U251 cells were 
depleted of PKM2 and reconstituted with the expression 
of rPKM2 WT or ILLL (Figure 2F and Supplementary 
information, Figure S5A); U87 or U251 cells were de-
pleted of Bcl2 and reconstituted with the expression of 
rBcl2 WT or T69A (Supplementary information, Figure 
S5B and S5C). Apoptosis analysis using Annexin V-Cy5 
staining showed that more apoptotic cells were detected 
in cells expressing rPKM2 ILLL or rBcl2 T69A than in 
cells expressing rPKM2 WT or rBcl2 WT after H 2 O 2 
treatment (Figure 6A and 6B, Supplementary informa-
tion, Figure S5D and S5E, top panel). Consistently, H 2 O 2 
treatment led to the stronger caspase 3 activity in cells 
expressing rPKM2 ILLL or rBcl2 T69A than that in cells 
expressing rPKM2 WT or rBcl2 WT after H 2 O 2 treat-
ment (Figure 6A and 6B, Supplementary information, 
Figure S5D and S5E, bottom panel). In addition, effects 
of phosphorylation-mimic Bcl2 T69E on apoptosis were 
examined. As shown in Supplementary information, Fig-
ure S5F, expression of rBcl2 T69E markedly abrogated 
H 2 O 2 -induced apoptosis of PKM2-depleted U87 cells. 
Together, these data demonstrate that PKM2-dependent 
Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation is essential for oxidative stress 
adaptation of glioma cells. 
To further explore the cellular functions of PKM2-de-
pendent Bcl2 phosphorylation, apoptosis analyses were 
performed in U87 cells under various types of treatments. 
As shown in Supplementary information, Figure S5G and </p>

<p>S5H, more apoptotic cells were observed in PKM2-de-
pleted U87 cells with reconstituted expression of rPKM2 
ILLL or Bcl2-depleted U87 cells with reconstituted ex-
pression of rBcl2 T69A than those in the cells expressing 
rPKM2 WT or rBcl2 WT after TNFα or PTX treatment. 
It has been extensively reported that the treatment of 
TNFα or PTX induces significant ROS production and 
ROS plays an essential role in TNFα-or PTX-induced 
apoptosis [30, 31]. Thus, PKM2-dependent Bcl2 regu-
lation induced by TNFα or PTX is very likely mediated 
by increased ROS after the treatment. This hypothesis 
was simply tested by using the antioxidant N-acetyl-cys-
teine (NAC) to decrease intracellular ROS levels. The 
data showed that NAC treatment significantly abrogated 
TNFα-or PTX-induced apoptosis in PKM2-depleted 
U87 cells, and that TNFα-or PTX-induced Bcl2 phos-
phorylation at T69 was also inhibited by NAC treatment 
(Supplementary information, Figure S5I and S5J). These 
results indicate that TNFα-or PTX-induced Bcl2 regula-
tion by PKM2 was ROS dependent, suggesting a specific 
role of PKM2 under oxidative stress. 
PKM2-dependent Bcl2 phosphorylation was also in-
vestigated in other types of tumor cells. A549 or HT29 
cells were depleted of endogenous PKM2 and recon-
stituted with rPKM2 WT or ILLL, or were depleted of 
endogenous Bcl2 and reconstituted with rBcl2 WT or 
T69A. Consistently, H 2 O 2 treatment induced more apop-
tosis in A549 or HT29 cells expressing rPKM2 ILLL 
or rBcl2 T69A than in the cells expressing rPKM2 WT 
or rBcl2 WT (Supplementary information, Figure S5K-
S5N). 
Conditions associated with tumorigenesis (including 
gliomagenesis) such as hypoxia, matrix detachment, mi-
tochondrial dysfunction and inflammation can all lead </p>

<p>Figure 4 PKM2 phosphorylates Bcl2 at T69. Immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting analyses were performed with the indi-
cated antibodies. Data are representative of at least three independent experiments. (A) U87 cells that stably express shNT 
or shPKM2 were infected with a lentivirus expressing SFB-Bcl2 and then treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). SFB-
Bcl2 was pulled down using streptavidin agarose beads. (B) Chaperon assay was performed with recombinant HSP90α1 and 
GST-PKM2. After reaction, GST-PKM2 was pulled down using glutathione agarose beads. In vitro kinase assays were per-
formed by mixing isomerized GST-PKM2 and His-Bcl2 WT or Bcl2 T69A or Bcl2 S70A. (C) Chaperon assay was performed 
with recombinant HSP90α1 and GST-PKM2 or GST-PKM1. GST-PKM2 or GST-PKM1 was pulled down using glutathione 
agarose beads. In vitro kinase assay was performed by mixing His-Bcl2 and isomerized GST-PKM2 or GST-PKM1. (D) 
Chaperon assay was performed with recombinant HSP90α1 and GST-PKM2. GST-PKM2 was pulled down using glutathione 
agarose beads. In vitro kinase assays were performed by mixing isomerized GST-PKM2 and His-Bcl2. After reaction, His-
Bcl2 was pulled down using Nickel agarose beads and analyzed by mass spectrometry. Mass spectrometric analysis of a 
tryptic fragment at m/z 182.054 (mass error was 0.10 p.p.m.) matched to the doubly charged peptide 69-pho-tSPLQTPAAP-
GAAAGPALSPVPPVVHLTLR-98, suggesting that T69 was phosphorylated. The Sequest score for this match was Xcorr = 2.18; 
Mascot scores were 27, and expectation value was 5.1 × 10 −4 . The Best score evidence ID was 460, and site probability was 
78.4%. (E) PKM2-depleted U87 cells that were reconstituted with the expression of rPKM2 WT or ILLL were infected with a 
lentivirus expressing SFB-Bcl2 and then treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). (F, G) U87 cells that stably express SFB-
Bcl2 WT or T69A were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 4 h). The cells were pretreated with MG132 for 0.5 h before 
H 2 O 2 treatment (F). </p>

<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>Figure 5 PKM2-dependent Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation prevents the binding of Cul3-based E3 ligase to Bcl2. Immunoprecip-
itation and immunoblotting analyses were performed with the indicated antibodies. Data are representative of at least three 
independent experiments. (A) PKM2-depleted U87 cells were reconstituted with the expression of rPKM2 WT or ILLL and 
then treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). (B) U87 cells that stably express SFB-Bcl2 WT or T69A were treated with or 
without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). SFB-Bcl2 was pulled down using streptavidin agarose beads. (C) PKM2-depleted U87 cells were 
infected with a lentivirus expressing SFB-Bcl2 WT or T69E and then treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 1 h). SFB-Bcl2 
was pulled down using streptavidin agarose beads. (D, F) PKM2-depleted U87 cells were reconstituted with the expression 
of rPKM2 ILLL and then transfected with or without siRNA against CUL3 (siCul3). The cells were treated with or without H 2 O 2 
(0.5 mM, 4 h). The cells were pretreated with MG132 for 0.5 h (D). (E, G) U87 cells that stably express SFB-Bcl2 T69A were 
transfected with or without siCul3 and then treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 4 h). The cells were pretreated with MG132 
before H 2 O 2 treatment (E). </p>



<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>

<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>Figure 6 Phosphorylation of Bcl2 T69 by PKM2 enhances the resistance of tumor cells to oxidative stress and promotes 
gliomagenesis. Immunoblotting analyses were performed with the indicated antibodies. Data are representative of at least 
three independent experiments. (A) U87 cells were depleted of endogenous PKM2 and then reconstituted with the expres-
sion of rPKM2 WT or ILLL. The cells were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 24 h). The cells were harvested for analyses 
of apoptosis using Annexin V staining (top panel) or caspase 3 activity (bottom panel). Data represent the means ± SD of 
three independent experiments. (B) U87 cells were depleted of endogenous Bcl2 and then reconstituted with the expression 
of rBcl2 WT or T69A. The cells were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 24 h). The cells were harvested for analyses of 
apoptosis using Annexin V staining (top panel) or caspase 3 activity (bottom panel). Data represent the means ± SD of three 
independent experiments. (C, D) U87 cells were depleted of endogenous Bcl2 and reconstituted with the expression of rBcl2 
WT or T69A (C). U87 cells were depleted of endogenous PKM2 and reconstituted with expression of rPKM2 WT or ILLL (D). 
Endogenous PKM2-depleted U87 cells with reconstituted expression of rPKM2 ILLL were further infected with the lentivirus 
expressing Flag-Bcl2 WT or T69E (D). All genetically-modified U87 cells above were harvested and intracranially injected 
into randomized athymic nude mice (seven mice per group). After 40 days, the mice were euthanized and tumor growth was 
examined. H&amp;E-stained coronal brain sections show representative tumor xenografts (top panel). Representative images of 
tumor boundaries were presented in middle panel with 200× magnification. Tumor volumes were measured using length (a) 
and width (b) and calculated using the equation: V = ab 2 /2 (bottom panel). Data represent the means ± SD of seven mice. 
(E) Kaplan-Meier survival curves for the mice intracranially injected with Bcl2-depleted U87 cells reconstitutively expressing 
rBcl2 WT or T69A, or PKM2-depleted U87 cells reconstitutively expressing rPKM2 WT or ILLL, or Bcl2 WT-or T69E-express-
ing U87 cells that were depleted of PKM2 and reconstituted with the expression of rPKM2 ILLL (10 mice per group). (F, G) 
Tumor tissues derived from the mice injected with PKM2-depleted U87 cells reconstitutively expressing rPKM2 WT or ILLL 
(F), or Bcl2-depleted U87 cells reconstitutively expressing rBcl2 WT or T69A (G) were dissected for immunoblotting analyses. 
(H, J) U87 cells were intracranially injected into randomized athymic nude mice. After 15 days, 7 mice were sacrificed to ex-
amine tumor growth; the remaining mice were intratumorally injected with the lentivirus expressing Flag or PKM2 (389-405) 
peptides, and then sacrificed on day 40. H&amp;E-stained coronal brain sections show representative tumor xenografts (H, top 
panel). Representative images of tumor boundaries were presented in middle panel with 200× magnification. Tumor volumes 
were calculated (H, bottom panel). Data represent the means ± SD of 7 mice. Tumor tissues derived from the mice injected 
with the lentivirus expressing Flag or PKM2 389-405 peptides were dissected for immunoblotting analyses (J). (I) U87 cells 
were intracranially injected into randomized athymic nude mice. After 15 days, the mice were intracranially injected with the 
lentivirus expressing Flag or PKM2 (389-405) peptides. Kaplan-Meier survival curves were then plotted. </p>

<p>to excess production of ROS [32-34]. Therefore, cancer 
cells are particularly challenged while dealing with ox-
idative stress [35, 36]. To evaluate the contribution of 
PKM2-dependent Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation to brain tu-
mor development, we intracranially injected (1) Bcl2-de-
pleted U87 cells with reconstituted expression of rBcl2 
WT or T69A, (2) PKM2-depleted U87 cells with recon-
stituted expression of rPKM2 WT or ILLL, or (3) Bcl2 
WT-or T69E-expressing U87 cells that were depleted of 
PKM2 and reconstituted with the expression of rPKM2 
ILLL (Supplementary information, Figure S5O) into ran-
domized athymic nude mice. Analyses of hematoxylin 
and eosin (H&amp;E) staining and tumor volume showed that 
cells expressing rPKM2 WT or rBcl2 WT elicited rapid 
tumorigenesis. In contrast, brain tumor development was 
markedly dampened by the expression of rPKM2 ILLL 
or rBcl2 T69A. Notably, rPKM2 ILLL expression-sup-
pressed tumorigenesis was restored by Bcl2 T69E expres-
sion, but not Bcl2 WT expression (Figure 6C and 6D). 
Clear boundaries between tumor cells and normal cells 
without obvious inflammatory lesions were observed in 
the brain sections from the mice inoculated with genet-
ically-modified U87 cells (Figure 6C and 6D, middle 
panel). Kaplan-Meier survival curves showed that mice </p>

<p>injected with the cells expressing rBcl2 T69A or rPKM2 
ILLL survived longer time than mice injected with the 
cells expressing rBcl2 WT or rPKM2 WT. Consistently, 
the expression of Bcl2 T69E, but not Bcl2 WT, could sig-
nificantly shorten the survival time of the mice inoculated 
with PKM2 ILLL-reconstituted U87 cells (Figure 6E). 
Further, the contribution of PKM2-dependent Bcl2 
T69 phosphorylation to gliomagenesis was evaluated 
using luciferase-labeled U87 cells. Quantification of re-
al-time imaging of tumor growth showed that PKM2-de-
pleted U87 cells expressing rPKM2 WT or Bcl2-depleted 
cells expressing rBcl2 WT expanded quickly in mice 15 
days after implantation and reached maximum number 
after 40 days, whereas cells expressing rPKM2 ILLL 
or rBcl2 T69A failed to do so (Supplementary informa-
tion, Figure S5P and S5Q). Consistent results were also 
obtained in mice implanted with (1) PKM2-depleted 
U251 cells with reconstituted expression of rPKM2 
WT or rPKM2 ILLL, and (2) Bcl2-depleted U251 cells 
with reconstituted expression of rBcl2 WT or T69A. 
Kaplan-Meier survival curves showed that mice injected 
with U251 cells expressing rPKM2 ILLL or rBcl2 T69A 
had longer survival time than mice injected with U251 
cells expressing rPKM2 WT or rBcl2 WT (Supplementary </p>



<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>

<p>information, Figure S5R). Furthermore, immunoblotting 
analyses of the dissected tumor tissues showed that de-
creased levels of Bcl2 and increased levels of cleaved 
caspase 3 were detected in tumor tissues derived from the 
mice injected with U87 cells expressing rPKM2 ILLL or 
rBcl2 T69A compared to those in the counterpart tissue 
derived from the mice injected with U87 cells expressing 
rPKM2 WT or rBcl2 WT (Figure 6F and 6G). Together, 
these results demonstrate that Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation 
by PKM2 is crucial for brain tumor development. 
We next investigated therapeutic effects of PKM2 
389-405 peptide on gliomagenesis. U87 cells were in-
tracranially injected into randomized nude mice. After 
15 days, the mice bearing relatively small tumors were 
intratumorally injected with a lentivirus expressing Flag 
or PKM2 389-405 peptides. On day 40, analyses of H&amp;E 
staining and tumor volume showed that expression of 
PKM2 389-405 peptide, but not Flag peptide, signifi-
cantly impaired tumor growth (Figure 6H). Kaplan-Mei-
er survival curves showed the mice injected with the 
lentivirus expressing PKM2 389-405 peptide had much 
longer survival time than the mice injected with the lenti-
virus expressing Flag peptides (Figure 6I). Luciferase-la-
beled U87 cells were also used to evaluate therapeutic 
potential of PKM2 peptides. As shown in Supplementary 
information, Figure S5S, luciferase-expressing U87 cells 
grew into a small tumor 15 days after implantation. On 
day 40, the mice injected with the lentivirus expressing 
PKM2 389-405 peptide bear much smaller tumor than 
the mice injected with the lentivirus expressing Flag 
peptides. Consistent results were obtained in mice im-
planted with U251 cells followed by the injection of the 
lentivirus expressing Flag peptide or PKM2 389-405 
peptide, showing that the expression of PKM2 peptide 
markedly prolonged mouse survival (Supplementary 
information, Figure S5T). Immunoblotting analyses of 
the dissected tumor tissues showed decreased level of 
Bcl2 and increased level of cleaved caspase 3 in tumor 
tissues derived from the mice injected with the lentivirus 
expressing PKM2 389-405 peptide compared to those 
in the counterpart tissues derived from the mice injected 
with the lentivirus expressing Flag peptides (Figure 6J). 
Together, these results demonstrate that PKM2 389-405 
peptide could inhibit gliomagenesis effectively, high-
lighting therapeutic potential of PKM2 peptide as an an-
ti-tumor drug. </p>

<p>Bcl2 pT69 levels positively correlate with levels of con-
formation-altered PKM2 and grades of glioma malig-
nancy and prognosis 
To investigate clinical significance of PKM2-depen-
dent Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation, immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>(IHC) analyses were performed with 40 specimens from 
human primary GBM patients (World Health Organiza-
tion (WHO) grade IV) using antibodies of anti-Bcl2, an-
ti-Bcl2 pT69 or anti-PKM2-389, which specifically rec-
ognizes PKM2 with conformational change. Specificities 
of the antibodies used for IHC staining were validated 
by a blocking peptide/recombinant protein competition 
assay (Supplementary information, Figure S6). As shown 
in Figure 7A, Bcl2 protein levels correlated with levels 
of conformation-altered PKM2 or Bcl2 pT69. Pearson 
correlation analysis of the staining on a scale of 0-8.0 
showed that these correlations were significant (Figure 
7B and 7C). 
We next examined the correlation of survival of 80 
GBM patients, all of whom received standard adjuvant 
radiotherapy after surgery and the following treatment 
with an alkylating agent (TMZ in most cases), with lev-
els of Bcl2 pT69 (low, 0-4.5 staining score; high, 4.6-8 
staining score) or levels of PKM2 with conformational 
change (low, 0-3.9 staining score; high, 4.6-8 staining 
score). Patients whose tumors had low levels of confor-
mation-altered PKM2 (22 cases) had a median survival 
of 169.58 weeks, whereas those whose tumors had high 
levels of conformation-altered PKM2 (58 cases) had 
a significantly lower median survival of 69.33 weeks 
(Figure 7D). Patients whose tumors had low levels of 
Bcl2 pT69 (28 cases) had a median survival of 166.66 
weeks, whereas those whose tumors had high levels of 
Bcl2 pT69 (52 cases) had a significantly lower median 
survival of 59.34 weeks (Figure 7E). Correlations of lev-
els of Bcl2 pT69 and conformation-altered PKM2 with 
grades of glioma malignancy were also explored. Levels 
of conformation-altered PKM2 or Bcl2 pT69 in samples 
from patients with low-grade diffuse astrocytoma (WHO 
grade II; median survival time &gt; 5 years) were compared 
with those from patients with high-grade GBM [37]. 
IHC analyses showed that levels of conformation-altered 
PKM2 or Bcl2 pT69 in low-grade tumors were signifi-
cantly lower than those in GBM tumors (Figure 7F and 
7G). 
Taken together, these results clarify the importance of 
PKM2-dependent Bcl2 phosphorylation and stabilization 
in the clinical behavior of human GBM and reveal a rela-
tionship between Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation or conforma-
tion alteration of PKM2 and clinical glioma malignancy. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>PKM2 is upregulated in many human cancers and pro-
motes tumor cell proliferation through multiple mecha-
nisms. Recent studies reported that PKM2 also regulates 
apoptosis. However, mechanisms underlying such a role </p>

<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>Figure 7 Bcl2 pT69 levels positively correlates with levels of conformation-altered PKM2 and grades of glioma malignancy 
and prognosis. (A-C) Immunohistochemical analyses of 40 specimens from GBM patients using anti-PKM2-389, anti-Bcl2 
pT69 and anti-Bcl2 antibodies were performed. Representative images of two GBM specimens (A). Semi-quantitative scor-
ing (using a scale from 0 to 8) was carried out (Pearson product moment correlation test; B, r = 0.76, P &lt; 0.001; C, r = 0.81, 
P &lt; 0.001). (D, E) Survival of 80 patients with low (0-4.5 staining scores, blue curve) versus high (4.6-8 staining scores, red 
curve) conformation-altered PKM2 levels (low, 22 patients; high, 58 patients) was analyzed (D). Survival of 80 patients with 
low (0-3.9 staining scores, blue curve) versus high (4.0-8 staining scores, red curve) Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation levels (low, 
28 patients; high, 52 patients) was compared (E). Empty circles represent the deceased patients, and filled circles represent 
the censored (alive at last clinical follow-up) patients. (F, G) Forty diffuse astrocytoma specimens were immunohistochemi-
cally stained using PKM2-389 antibody (F) or anti-Bcl2 pT69 antibody (G). Staining scores of the specimens were compared 
with 40 (F) or 80 (G) stained GBM specimens (Student's t-test, two tailed, P &lt; 0.001). (H) Schematic representation of the 
PKM2-mediated Bcl2 stabilization and apoptosis resistance. PKM2 translocates to the mitochondria under oxidative stress, 
where PKM2 interacts with and phosphorylates Bcl2 at T69. Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation that requires HSP90α1-mediated 
PKM2 isomerization prevents the binding of Cul3-based E3 ligase to Bcl2, which stabilizes Bcl2 and therefore inhibits apop-
tosis and promotes tumorigenesis. </p>



<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>

<p>of PKM2 remains unknown. Here we domonstrate that 
oxidative stress induces mitochondrial translocation of 
PKM2. In the mitochondria, PKM2, functioning as a 
protein kinase, interacts with and phosphorylates Bcl2 at 
T69, which disrupts assocation of Cul3-based E3 ligase 
with Bcl2, and blocks proteasome-mediated Bcl2 degra-
dation, thereby inhibiting oxidative stress-induced apop-
tosis (Figure 7H). These results reveal a novel mecha-
nism by which PKM2 regulates apoptosis directly, and 
highlight the critical role of PKM2 in ROS adaptation of 
tumor cells. Importantly, levels of Bcl2 T69 phosphor-
ylation and conformation-altered PKM2 correlate with 
grades of glioma malignancy and prognosis of GBM pa-
tient, suggesting that Bcl2 T69 phosphorylation and con-
formational change of PKM2 could be two biomarkers to 
predict brain tumor malignancy and prognosis. Further-
more, the finding that PKM2 389-405 peptide disrupts 
PKM2-Bcl2 interaction, promotes Bcl2 degradation, and 
hampers brain tumor development points to the potential 
of this peptide as an anti-cancer drug. 
Elevated levels of ROS have been detected in almost 
all cancer types. Cancer cells can adapt to such stress 
through multiple mechanisms [38]. Here we demonstrate 
that PKM2 is involved in such adaptation by inhibiting 
apoptosis. Our data show that increased level of ROS 
induced mitochondrial translocation of PKM2. Mito-
chondrial PKM2 interacts with and phosphorylates Bcl2. 
PKM2-dependent Bcl2 phosphorylation prevents Bcl2 
degradation and thereby inhibits ROS-induced apopto-
sis. In addition to apoptosis inhibition, cancer cells also 
activate ROS-scavenging systems to cope with increased 
ROS levels [4]. PKM2 is also involved in this process. 
Increased intracellular ROS level causes inhibition of 
glycolytic activity of PKM2 through oxidation of cys-
teine 358, which diverts glucose flux into the pentose 
phosphate pathway, thereby generating sufficient reduc-
ing potential for detoxification of ROS [39]. Thus, PKM2 
can promote the adaptation of cancer cells to ROS at 
two levels, suggesting therapeutic potential of targeting 
PKM2. 
PKM2 can be regulated at multiple levels, such as 
posttranslational modification and subcellular local-
ization. It has been shown in our previous studies that 
PKM2 is phospohorylated at serine 37 by ERK 1 and 
2 upon EGFR activation [12]. PKM2 S37 phosphory-
lation promotes nuclear translocation of PKM2. In the 
nucleus, PKM2 interacts with β-catenin and thereby 
enhances transactivation activity of β-catenin, which 
enhances downstream oncogene expression [13]. Nu-
clear translocation of PKM2 was also observed by Lv 
et al. [40], showing that PKM2 K433 acetylation that 
was mediated by the p300 acetyltransferase prevents the </p>

<p>binding of FBP to PKM2 and thereby facilitates nuclear 
translocation of PKM2 and its switch from a cytoplas-
mic metabolic enzyme to a nuclear protein kinase. Both 
studies demonstrated nuclear localization and functions 
of PKM2. In this study, we showed for the first time that 
PKM2 translocates to the mitochondria under oxidative 
stress. Submitochondrial fractionation analyses showed 
that PKM2 translocated to outermembrane of mitochon-
dria (Supplementary information, Figure S1D). It is like-
ly that PKM2-Bcl2 interaction bridges PKM2 to mito-
chondrial outermembrane, which remains to be clarified. 
Protein kinase activity of PKM2 has been extensively 
reported. PKM2 phosphorylates Histone H3 or STAT3 
in the nucleus and regulates various gene expression 
[24, 41]. Bub3 and myosin light chain 2 are also phos-
phorylated by PKM2 to promote mitosis and cytokinesis 
in the context of cell cycle [42, 43]. Moreover, protein 
kinase activity of PKM2 on Histone H3 can be enhanced 
by succinyl-5-aminoimidazole-4-carboxamide-1-ri-
bose-5′-phosphate (SAICAR) and over 100 proteins were 
identified to be phosphorylated by PKM2 [44]. Notably, 
protein kinase activity of PKM2 was further supported 
by two recent publications, showing (1) that yeast PKM2 
homolog directly phosphorylates histone H3 at T11 both 
in vivo and in vitro, and (2) that nuclear PKM2 phos-
phorylates Stat3 and promotes proinflammatory pheno-
type of macrophages in coronary artery disease through 
boosting IL-6 and IL-1β production [45, 46]. Together, 
these studies demonstrate the protein kinase activity of 
PKM2 in the nucleus. Here we showed that oxidative 
stress stimulates the protein kinase activity of PKM2 to 
phosphosrylate Bcl2 at T69 in the mitochondria, which is 
essential for the anti-apoptotic function of PKM2. 
Roles of Bcl2 can be regulated by phosphorylation. 
SLAMF1 deficiency in chronic lymphocytic leukemia 
(CLL) increased ROS accumulation and induced Bcl2 
phosphorylation, thereby promoting autophagic flux [31]. 
Flubendazole (a potent inducer of autophagy) activates 
JNK1, leading to Bcl2 phosphorylation at S70 and sub-
sequent release of Beclin1 from Bcl2-Beclin1 complex 
for autophagy induction [30]. During mitotic arrest, sus-
tained JNK activation dramatically increases Bcl2 phos-
phorylation, resulting in the inactivation of anti-apoptotic 
function of Bcl2 [47]. Mimicking phosphorylation of 
the putative mitogen-activated protein (MAP) kinase 
sites of Bcl2 protein (T56, T74 and S87) abolishes TN-
Fα-induced Bcl2 degradation and apoptosis [48]. Bcl2 
phosphorylation (T69, S70 and S87) confers resistance 
of CLL cells to the BH3 mimetic ABT-737 by impeding 
direct binding [49]. Together, these studies elaborated 
that Bcl2 phosphorylation is a pivotal mechanism for the 
regulation of Bcl2 functions. However, role of the phos-</p>

<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>phorylation in regulation of Bcl2 anti-apoptotic function 
is controversial and upstream kinase that phosphorylates 
Bcl2 at T69 remains elusive. In this study, we revealed 
that PKM2 phosphorylates Bcl2 at T69 in the mitochon-
dria, which prevents the binding of Cul3-based E3 ligase 
to Bcl2 and stabilizes Bcl2, thereby inhibiting oxidative 
stress-induced apoptosis. Notably, Bcl2 T69 phosphor-
ylation by PKM2 has been confirmed by in vitro kinase 
assay and mass spectrometry analyses. 
HSP90 plays a number of important roles, such as 
assisting folding, intracellular transport, maintenance 
and degradation of proteins as well as facilitating cell 
signaling [50]. In cancer cells, it can stabilize some pro-
teins encoded by oncogenes, such as EGFR, PI3K and 
AKT [51-53]. HSP90 possesses ATPase activity and in-
duces conformational changes in client proteins, thereby 
causing activation of such proteins [54]. In this study, 
we demonstrate that HSP90 interacts with and isomer-
izes PKM2 upon oxidative stress. Isomerized PKM2 is 
required for Bcl2 phosphorylation and the inhibition of 
oxidative stress-induced apoptosis. Our finding identifies 
PKM2 as a new substrate of HSP90 and uncovers a nov-
el mechanism of HSP90 regulating apoptosis via modu-
lation of PKM2. 
Our findings demonstrate that PKM2-dependent Bcl2 
phosphorylation and stabilization plays an essential role 
in resistance of tumor cells to oxidative stress-induced 
apoptosis and gliomagenesis, which not only reveal a 
novel mechanism of PKM2-mediated ROS adaptation 
of tumor cells, but also provide a molecular basis for 
treating rapid proliferating tumors by interfering with the 
HSP90-PKM2-Bcl2 axis. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>Rabbit monoclonal antibodies against PKM2, Bcl2 pS70, cy-
tochrome c, AKT1, Bcl-xl, Bax, Tom20, MnSOD2 and HSP90α1, 
and mouse monoclonal antibodies against Bcl2 and Chk1, and 
polyclonal antibodies against VDAC, Cul3 and Rbx1, and mouse 
anti-rabbit IgG (Conformation Specific; L27A9) were obtained 
from Cell Signaling Technology (Danvers, MA, USA). Rabbit 
polyclonal antibody against Bcl2 pT69 was obtained from Thermo 
Fisher Scientific. Mouse monoclonal antibody against ubiquitin 
and GST were purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa 
Cruz, CA, USA). Rabbit polyclonal antibody recognizing PKM2-
389 (a customer antibody) was obtained from Signalway Antibody 
(College Park, MD, USA). Mouse monoclonal antibodies for Flag, 
His and tubulin, and rabbit polyclonal antibody for TIMM22 were 
purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA). Hygromycin, pu-
romycin, and G418 were purchased from EMD Biosciences (San 
Diego, CA, USA). PolyJet in vitro DNA transfection reagent was 
from Signagen Laboratories (Rockville, MD, USA). GelCode Blue 
Stain Reagent was obtained from Pierce (Rockford, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>U87 and U251 GBM cells and 293T cells were maintained in 
Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) supplemented 
with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and antibiotics. The protein 
expression and reconstitution experiments were conducted using 
the established stable cell lines. Transfection was performed as in-
structed by manufacturer. </p>

<p>DNA constructs and mutagenesis </p>

<p>PCR-amplified human PKM2 and Bcl2 were cloned into 
pcDNA3.1, pCDH, pCDH-Flag, pCDH-SFB, pCold I, pLOC or 
pGEX-KG vectors. PCR-amplified human HSP90α1 was cloned 
into pCMV-Flag, pCDH-Flag or pGEX-KG. Synthesized 3× 
PKM2 389-405 fragments or 3× Flag fragments were cloned into 
pCDH-Flag. pCDH-SFB-PKM2 ∆370-388, pCDH-SFB-PKM2 
∆389-405, pCDH-SFB-PKM2 406-423, pCDH-SFB-PKM2 
∆424-435, pCDH-SFB-PKM2 ILLL, pCDH-SFB-PKM2 EERR, 
pLOC-rPKM2, pLOC-rPKM2 ILLL, pCDH-SFB-Bcl2 T69A, 
pCold I-Bcl2 T69A, pCMV-Flag-HSP90α1 G97D, pCMV-Flag-
HSP90α1 ∆C, pCMV-Flag-HSP90α1 MD, pCMV-Flag-HSP90α1 
∆N, pCDH-Flag-HSP90α1, pCDH-Flag-HSP90α1 1-293, pC-
DH-Flag-HSP90α1 1-360, pCDH-Flag-HSP90α1 1-469, pLOC-
rHSP901, pCDH-Flag-rHSP90α1 G97D and pGEX-KG-HSP90α1 
G97D were made using the QuickChange site-directed mutagen-
esis kit (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA, USA). pLOC-rPKM2 contains 
nonsense mutations of C1170T, C1173T, T1174C and G1176T. 
pCDH-Flag-rHSP90α1 contains nonsense mutations of C2433T, 
A2434C and G2436T. 
The pGIPZ control was generated with the control oligonucle-
otide 5′-GCTTCTAACACCGGAGGTCTT-3′. pGIPZ PKM2 shR-
NA was generated with 5′-CATCTACCACTTGCAATTA-3′ oligo-
nucleotide targeting exon 10 of the PKM2 transcript. pGIPZ Bcl2 
shRNA was generated with 5′-AGGTTCACTAAAGCAGTAG-3′ 
oligonucleotide targeting noncoding region of the Bcl2 transcript. 
pGIPZ HSP90α1 shRNA was generated with 5′-AGGATCTA-
CAGGATGATCA-3′. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence analysis </p>

<p>Cells were fixed and incubated with primary antibodies, Alexa 
Fluor dye-conjugated secondary antibodies and Hoechst 33342 
according to the standard protocols. Cells were examined using 
a deconvolution microscope (Zeiss, Thornwood, NY, USA) with 
a 63-Å oil immersion objective. <rs id="software-4" type="software">Axio Vision</rs> software from <rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Zeiss</rs> 
was used to deconvolute Z-series images. </p>

<p>Subcellular fractionation analyses </p>

<p>U87 or U251 cells were harvested and washed three times with 
cold PBS. Cytosolic or mitochondrial fractions were prepared us-
ing the Mitochondria/Cytosol Fraction Kit (BioVision). 
Mitochondrial subfractionation was performed as described 
previously [55]. Briefly, isolated mitochondria were resuspended 
in 10 µM KH 2 PO 4 (pH 7.4) for 20 min on ice. An equal volume of 
iso-osmotic solution (32% sucrose, 30% glycerol, 10 mM MgCl 2 ) 
was added and spun at 10 000× g for 10 min at 4 °C. The superna-
tant were centrifuged at 15 000× g for 1 h at 4 °C; the pellet and 
supernatant contained outer membrane and intermembrane space 
proteins, respectively. Then, the pellet from the first time centri-
fuge was resuspended in 10 µM KH 2 PO 4 (pH 7.4) for 20 min on 
ice, and iso-osmotic solution was added, followed by centrifuge </p>



<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>

<p>at 15 000× g for 1 h at 4 °C; the pellet and supernatant contained 
inner membrane and matrix proteins, respectively. </p>

<p>Apoptosis assay </p>

<p>U87 or U251 cells were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 
24 h). The cells were harvested and stained as described in the 
protocol of Annexin V-Cy5 Apoptosis Kit (BioVision). </p>

<p>ROS measurement </p>

<p>Total ROS in tumor tissues were measured using the Oxiselect 
In Vitro ROS/RNS Assay Kit (Cell Biolabs), following the manu-
facturer's instructions. Briefly, tumor tissues were homogenized in 
cold PBS solution (20 mg/ml) and centrifuged at 10 000× g for 5 
min. The supernatant was collected for the assay. The fluorescence 
(Ex480 nm/Em530 nM) was measured using the Synergy HT 
Multi-Mode Microplate Reader (Bio-Tek instruments, Inc). </p>

<p>Caspase 3 activity assay </p>

<p>U87 or U251 cells were treated with or without H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM, 
24 h). The cells were harvested and washed three times with cold 
PBS. Caspase 3 activity was measured as described in the protocol 
of the Caspase-3 Activity Assay Kit (Cell Signaling Technology). </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting analyses </p>

<p>Extraction of proteins with a modified buffer from cultured 
cells was followed by immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting 
with corresponding antibodies, as described previously [56]. </p>

<p>Dot blot assay </p>

<p>Cell lysate was spotted on a nitrocellulose membrane (0.2 µm 
pore size) and then dried for several hours at room temperature. 
Membranes were blocked with 3% (w/v) nonfat dry milk in PBS 
for 30 min at room temperature and probed with the indicated an-
tibodies for 1 h at room temperature. Membranes were washed 2 
times for 3 min with PBS and subsequently incubated with a sec-
ondary antibody (HRP-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG,) in 3% (w/ 
v) nonfat dry milk-PBS for 1 h at room temperature. Membranes 
are washed 2 times with PBS. Following the last wash, the mem-
brane is exposed to chemiluminescence detection system (Tanon 
5200 Multi) and developed using a Pierce ECL Plus Substrate 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific). </p>

<p>Purification of recombinant proteins </p>

<p>Wild-type and mutant GST-PKM2, His-Bcl2 and GST-
HSP90α1 were expressed in bacteria and purified as described 
previously [57]. Non-tagged HSP90α1 was obtained by thrombin 
cleavage of GST. The purities of the recombinant proteins were 
verified by gel staining with Coomassie Blue. </p>

<p>Chaperone assay </p>

<p>Purified HSP90α1 (0.5 µg) and GST-PKM2 (0.5 µg) were incu-
bated at 30 °C for 30 min with 2 mM ATP in a total volume of 20 
µl, containing 40 mM HEPES-KOH (pH 7.5) and 2 mM MgCl 2 . </p>

<p>Pyruvate kinase assay </p>

<p>The activity of bacterially purified PKM2 WT (0.1 µg) and 
PKM2 ILLL (0.1 µg) toward PEP was measured with a pyruvate 
kinase assay (BioVision, Mountain View, CA, USA) according to 
the manufacturer's instruction. Data represent the mean ± SD of </p>

<p>three independent experiments. </p>

<p>In vitro kinase assay </p>

<p>The PKM2-mediated kinase reactions were performed as de-
scribed previously [24]. In brief, the bacterially purified recom-
binant PKM2 (200 ng) was incubated with Bcl2 (100 ng) with 
kinase buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 100 mM KCl, 50 mM 
MgCl 2 , 1 mM Na 3 VO 4 , 1 mM DTT, 5% glycerol, 0.05 mM FBP, 
0.5 mM PEP or 5 µCi 32 P-labeled PEP) in 25 µl at 25 °C for 1 h. 
The reactions were terminated by the addition of SDS-PAGE load-
ing buffer and heated to 100 °C. The reaction mixtures were then 
subjected to SDS-PAGE analyses. 32 P-labeled PEP was prepared 
as described previously [25]. Briefly, reactions were carried out 
at 25 °C for 5 min. Reaction mixtures contained 50 mM HEPES, 
pH 7.5, 12.5 mM KF, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM oxaloacetate, 0.5 units 
PEPCK/ml and 32 P-PEP. The reactions were diluted by 10-fold 
with water and applied to Vivapure Q columns (Sartorius) to puri-
fy 32 P-labeled PEP. </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted with RNeasy Plus Kit (Qiagen, Va-
lencia, CA, USA). cDNA was prepared by a QuantiTect Reverse 
Transcription Kit (Qiagen) using oligonucleotide (dT) and random 
primers. Quantitative real-time PCR analysis was performed under 
the following conditions: 5 min at 95 °C followed by 40 cycles at 
95 °C for 30 s, 55 °C for 40 s, and 72 °C for 1 min using an ABI 
Prism 7700 sequence detection system. Data were normalized to 
expression of a control gene (β-actin) for each experiment. 
The following primer pairs were used for quantitative real-time 
PCR: Bcl2, 5′-GGTGGGGTCATGTGTGTGG-3′ (forward) and 
5′-CGGTTCAGGTACTCAGTCATCC-3′ (reverse); β-actin, 
5′-CATGTACGTTGCTATCCAGGC-3′ (forward) and 5′-CTCCT-
TAATGTCACGCACGAT-3′ (reverse). </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry analysis </p>

<p>An in vitro PKM2-phosphorylated recombinant Bcl2 was ex-
haustively acetylated with acetic anhydride and triethylamine in 
acetonitrile, evaporated to dryness, then resuspended in 50 mM 
ammonium bicarbonate buffer containing Rapigest (Waters Corp, 
MA, USA). The sample was heated to 95 °C for 10 min and then 
allowed to cool; 100 ng of sequencing-grade modified trypsin 
(Promega, Madison, WI, USA) was added. The digestion proceed-
ed overnight at 37 °C and was analyzed by LC-MS/MS on an Obi-
trap-XL mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, 
MA, USA). 
Proteins were identified by a database search of the fragment 
spectra against the National SwissProt protein database (EBI) 
using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Mascot</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">v.2.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Matrix Science, London, UK</rs>) and <rs id="software-11" type="software">Sequest</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-11" type="version-number">v.1.20</rs>) via <rs id="software-3" type="software">Proteome Discoverer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">v.1.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Thermo Fisher Scientific</rs>). 
Phosphopeptide matches were analyzed by using <rs type="software">PhosphoRS</rs> im-
plemented in <rs type="software">Proteome Discoverer</rs> and manually curated [58]. </p>

<p>Intracranial injection </p>

<p>We intracranially injected U87 or U251 cells (2 × 10 5 in 5 µl 
of DMEM per mouse) with depletion of endogenous PKM2 and 
reconstituted expression of rPKM2 WT or ILLL, or the cells with 
depletion of endogenous Bcl2 and reconstituted expression of 
rBcl2 WT or T69A into randomized 4-week-old female athymic 
nude mice. Intracranial injections were performed as described in </p>

<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>a previous publication [59]. Seven mice per group in each experi-
ment were included. Mice injected with U87 cells were sacrificed 
40 days after implantation. U87 cells were intracranially injected 
into randomized athymic nude mice. After 15 days, 7 mice were 
sacrificed to examine tumor growth; the remaining mice were in-
tracranially injected with the lentivirus-expressing Flag or PKM2 
(389-405) peptides, and then sacrificed on day 40. The brain of 
each mouse was collected, fixed in 4% formaldehyde and embed-
ded in paraffin. Tumor formation and phenotype were determined 
by histologic analysis of H&amp;E-stained sections. Kaplan-Meier sur-
vival curves for the mice intracranially injected with the indicated 
U87 or U251 cells were performed with ten mice per group. The 
use of mice was in compliance with ethical regulations and was 
approved by the institutional review board at the Institute of Bio-
chemistry and Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Bioluminescence imaging with IVIS </p>

<p>Mice were anaesthetized with isoflurane inhalation, and were 
subsequently intraperitoneally injected with 100 µl of 7.5 mg/ml 
D-luciferin (Xenogen). Bioluminescence imaging with a CCD 
camera (IVIS, Xenogen) was initiated 10 min after injection with 
2 min exposure time. Bioluminescence from the region of interest 
was defined manually. Background was defined using a region of 
interest from a mouse that was not given an intraperitoneal injec-
tion of D-luciferin. All bioluminescent data were collected and 
analyzed using IVIS. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical analysis </p>

<p>The tissue sections from paraffin-embedded human GBM and 
astrocytoma specimens were stained with antibodies. We quanti-
tatively scored the tissue sections according to the percentage of 
positive cells and staining intensity, as previously defined [60]. 
We rated the intensity of staining on a scale of 0-3: 0, negative; 1, 
weak; 2, moderate; and 3, strong. We assigned the following pro-
portion scores: 0 if 0% of the tumor cells showed positive staining, 
1 if 0%-1% of cells were stained, 2 if 2%-10% were stained, 3 if 
11%-30% were stained, 4 if 31%-70% were stained, and 5 if 71%-
100% were stained. We then combined the proportion and inten-
sity scores to obtain a total score (range, 0-8), as described previ-
ously [60]. Scores were compared with overall survival, defined 
as the time from the date of diagnosis to death or last known date 
of follow-up. All patients received standard adjuvant radiotherapy 
after surgery, followed by treatment with an alkylating agent (TMZ 
in most cases). The use of human brain tumor specimens and the 
database was approved by the Institutional Review Board at Fudan 
University Shanghai Cancer Center and the Institutional Review 
Board at First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical College. In-
formed consent was obtained from all patients. Data represent the 
mean ± SD of 80 stained GBM specimens and 40 stained astrocy-
toma specimens. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>We determined the significance of differences in the human gli-
oma data using Pearson's correlation test and Student's t-test (two-
tailed). P &lt; 0.05 was considered to be significant. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Tech-</p>

<p>nology of China (2014CB943101) to WY, the National Natural 
Science Foundation of China (31471324 and 31422034 to WY, and 
81402457 to JL), the Strategic Priority Research Program of the 
Chinese Academy of Sciences (XDB19000000) to WY and the 
Thousand Talents Plan-Youth to WY. </p>

<p>Author Contributions </p>

<p>This study was conceived by WY; WY and JL designed the 
study; JL, RC, XW, PW, YZ and HG performed the experiments; 
FY, PW, DL and WL provided pathology assistance; CL and RZ 
provided technical assistance of mass spectrometry analyses; WY 
wrote the manuscript with comments from all authors. </p>

<p>Competing Financial Interests </p>

<p>The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>





<p>Mitochondrial PKM2 regulates apoptosis </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 27 No 3 | March 2017 </p>



<p>Ji Liang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 Unported 
License. The images or other third party material in this article are 
included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated 
otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the 
Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from 
the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>© The Author(s) 2017 </p>

</text></tei>