<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5015293" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T19:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Methods and Results--We evaluated the Sodium-Sensitivity Index (SS-Index) in 71 white normotensives after 5 days of high-and 
low-sodium diets. We measured BP continuously at the end of each period, estimating hemodynamic indices from BP waveform 
analysis, and autonomic indices from heart rate (HR) and BP variability. According to the SS-Index distribution, we defined 
1 sodium-sensitive group (SS, with SS-Index &gt;15 mm Hg/[mmolÁday]), 1 sodium-resistant group, (unresponsive to sodium load 
with À15≤ SS-Index ≤+15), and 1 inverse sodium-sensitive group, responsive to sodium by decreasing BP, with SS-Index &lt;À15). 
We compared the effects of the diets among groups, and correlated autonomic/hemodynamic indices with the SS-Index. After 
sodium loading, a significant decrease in systemic peripheral resistances, HR, spectral indices of BP modulation, and a significant 
increase of indices of HR vagal modulation were found in the inverse sodium-sensitive group but not in SS normotensives. 
Moreover, the highest SS-Indices were associated with the lesser vagal HR decelerations. </p>

<p>Conclusions--Our data suggest that salt sensitivity in white normotensive individuals is associated with impaired vasodilation 
and altered autonomic response to dietary salt. Such dysfunction may critically contribute to induce a BP response to dietary salt. 
( J Am Heart Assoc. 2016;5:e003736 doi: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736) </p>

<p>Key Words: autonomic function • baroreflex • blood pressure spectral analysis • heart rate variability • peripheral resistance 
• salt intake • salt-sensitive </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>alt-sensitive hypertensive individuals display a higher rate 
of cardiovascular events than salt-resistant hypertensive 
individuals. 
1 A similar trend characterizes salt-sensitive nor-</p>

<p>motensives, who also have a significant increase in mortality </p>

<p>rate over time. 
2 However, few studies investigated the </p>

<p>mechanisms relating the increased cardiovascular risk to 
sodium sensitivity. Sodium loading/depletion maneuvers may 
unveil alterations in cardiovascular control associated with 
sodium sensitivity possibly involved in the increased rate of 
cardiovascular events. In this regard, while it has been shown 
that salt-sensitive hypertensive patients respond to sodium 
loading with either a blunted sympathetic deactivation 
3 or an </p>

<p>impaired cardiac parasympathetic activation, 
4,5 limited evi-</p>

<p>dence of an altered autonomic cardiovascular modulation is 
available in normotensive subjects. 
A study in mostly normotensive black Americans, under-
going a few days of dietary salt loading, showed a significant 
decrease in systemic vascular resistance in sodium-resistant 
individuals, while such a response was largely impaired in 
sodium-sensitive individuals. 
6 This finding suggests the </p>

<p>hypothesis that an autonomic-mediated reduction in periph-
eral vascular resistance, in response to sodium loading, might 
be weakened or absent in sodium-sensitive normotensives. 
However, to the best of our knowledge, no data are available 
on the dependence of hemodynamic or autonomic responses </p>

<p>From the IRCCS Fondazione Don C. Gnocchi, Milan, Italy (P.C.); Department of 
Cardiovascular, Neural and Metabolic Sciences, Istituto Auxologico Italiano, 
Milan, Italy (G.P., A.F.); Department of Health Sciences, University of Milano-
Bicocca, Milan, Italy (G.P.); Fondazione Don Carlo Gnocchi, Parma, Italy (D.L., 
L.B., V.B.); Department of Clinical and Experimental Medicine, University of 
Parma, Italy (M.B., P.C.). </p>

<p>Accompanying Data S1 through S3, Table S1, and Figure S1 are available at 
http://jaha.ahajournals.org/content/5/8/e003736/DC1/embed/inline-
supplementary-material-1.pdf </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Gianfranco Parati, MD, Department of Cardiovascular 
Neural and Metabolic Sciences, S. Luca Hospital, Istituto Auxologico Italiano 
and University of Milano-Bicocca, Piazzale Brescia 20, Milan 20149, Italy. 
E-mail: gianfranco.parati@unimib.it </p>

<p>Received April 21, 2016; accepted July 7, 2016. 
ª 2016 The Authors. Published on behalf of the American Heart Association, 
Inc., by Wiley Blackwell. This is an open access article under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, 
distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is 
properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>to salt loading on the degree of sodium sensitivity in white 
normotensive individuals. 
The present study specifically addressed the above open 
issue. We tested the hypothesis that an altered hemodynamic 
or autonomic response to dietary salt manipulation is 
detectable in white normotensive individuals as a function 
of their sensitivity to sodium. This was done by deriving 
information on hemodynamic control from pulse waveform 
analysis and by assessing spontaneous heart rate (HR) and 
blood pressure (BP) variability during different levels of 
sodium intake in healthy normotensives with different degrees 
of sodium sensitivity, as quantified in a continuous fashion by 
the sodium sensitivity index (SS-Index). </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Subjects and Data Collection </p>

<p>The experimental protocol conformed to the Declaration of 
Helsinki and was approved by the ethics committee of Don C. 
Gnocchi Foundation. Seventy-one normotensive volunteers 
(45 females), recruited among medical students and residents 
attending our University Hospital, were included. Inclusion 
criteria were a normotensive status, confirmed by clinic BP 
measurements and 24-hour ambulatory BP monitoring, and 
the absence of history and of any physical or laboratory 
evidence of cardiovascular disease. No endurance or profes-
sional athletes were enrolled. Volunteers received a detailed 
explanation of the study and gave informed consent. All 
participants followed a low-sodium (30 mmol NaCl per day) 
and a high-sodium (200 mmol NaCl per day) diet, each for 
5 days, in random order. They were instructed on how to 
prepare their meals at home, and received the total amount of 
sodium to be used in their food during the high-sodium diet 
from the hospital pharmacy, in separate 1-g sachets. During 
both diets, they were asked to refrain from intense physical 
exercise. On the last day of each diet, the 24-hour urinary 
sodium excretion rate (UNaV) was quantified. In the morning 
of the same day, body weight was assessed and brachial BP 
was measured on the right arm with subjects in a sitting 
position for 2 hours, with readings every 15 minutes with an 
oscillometric ambulatory BP monitoring device (Spacelabs 
90207; Spacelabs Healthcare, Redmond, WA). Mean arterial 
pressure (MAP) was averaged over the 2-hour recording 
period. The difference between average MAP values at the 
end of the high-salt and low-salt diets (DMAP) was divided by 
the difference between the corresponding urinary sodium 
excretion rates (DUNaV) to obtain the SS-Index, 
7 defined as 
DMAP/DUNaV ratio and expressed in mm Hg/(molÁday). 
Finger BP was recorded beat-by-beat for 2 hours from the 
mid finger of the left hand by the Portapres model-2 device 
(Finapres Medical Systems B.V., Amsterdam, the Netherlands) </p>

<p>simultaneously with the brachial right-arm cuff. Finger BP was 
obtained in 68 of the 71 volunteers; technical problems 
prevented the recording in 3 cases. Finger BP waveforms 
were sampled at 100 Hz. Beat-by-beat values of systolic BP, 
diastolic BP, and pulse interval (PI) were derived from the 
finger BP waveforms. Since we previously observed a 
significant proportional bias between finger and brachial BP 
measures associated with the sodium depletion maneuver, </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>the brachial measures of systolic and diastolic BP, averaged 
over the 2-hour recordings, were used to calibrate the finger 
BP waveform. After such calibration, the average of systolic 
and diastolic beat-by-beat BP series from Portapres coincided 
with the corresponding brachial BP measures. The beat-by-
beat BP series were visually inspected by an expert operator 
to remove premature beats and artifacts, and the recordings 
of 1 subject were discarded because a high number of 
artifacts made them unsuitable for spectral analysis. Thus, 
data of 67 volunteers (41 females) were available for BP 
waveform and for HR and BP variability analysis. 
Hemodynamic parameters were derived from BP waveform 
analysis through Model-Flow analysis (see details of the 
Model-Flow method and of validation studies versus "gold 
standard" methods in Data S1). Hemodynamic parameters 
were the following: left ventricular ejection time, systemic 
vascular resistances (SVR), aortic characteristic impedance, 
arterial compliance, stroke volume, and cardiac output. 
Autonomic indices were calculated from the analysis of HR 
and BP variability (Data S1). Frequency-domain indices of HR 
variability were the high-frequency power of PI (PI HF), index 
of vagal modulations of HR, and the ratio between low-
frequency (LF) and HF powers of PI (PI LF/HF powers ratio), 
which is an index of the cardiac sympatho/vagal balance. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Frequency-domain indices of BP variability were the LF power 
of diastolic BP, reported to reflect sympathetically mediated 
vasomotor oscillations generally assumed to be induced by 
baroreflex resonance 
10,11 ; the very-low frequency power of </p>

<p>diastolic BP that quantifies long-term fluctuations mainly of 
vasomotor origin; and the sensitivity of baroreflex control of 
HR estimated by the transfer function method over the LF 
(BRS LF) and HF (BRS HF) bands. Additionally, we calculated 
the number of PI increases per minute larger than 50 ms 
(NN50+, time-domain index of cardiac parasympathetic 
modulation under the hypothesis that bursts of vagal outflow 
on the sinus node produce PI lengthening of more than 
50 ms) 
12 ; and the short-term scale coefficient a 1 through </p>

<p>detrended fluctuation analysis of PI, which is a complexity-
domain index of cardiac sympatho/vagal balance. </p>

<p>13,14 </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>The association between SS-Index and hemodynamic or 
autonomic indices was assessed by the nonparametric </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Response to Salt in Normotensives 
Castiglioni et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Kendall's rank correlation coefficient, s, separately after each 
diet. 
Traditionally, individuals are classified on the basis of their 
response to sodium tests in those that increase BP, or sodium 
sensitive (SS), and in those that do not increase BP, even if 
this latter group has a heterogeneous response, with some 
individuals presenting even a marked depressor response to 
salt loading. 
15 Table S1 (see Data S2) summarizes results </p>

<p>following this dichotomous approach. More recently, it has 
been proposed to further divide individuals who do not 
increase BP after sodium loading in a genuine sodium-
resistant (SR) group, actually unresponsive to sodium, and in 
an inverse sodium-sensitive (ISS) group, that respond to high 
dietary salt decreasing BP. 
16 Following this trichotomous </p>

<p>approach, we defined SR as those individuals with SS-Index 
between À15 and +15 mm Hg/(molÁday), ISS those with SS-
Index lower than À15 mm Hg/(molÁday), and SS those with 
SS-Index greater than 15 mm Hg/(molÁday). Figure S1 (see 
Data S3) illustrates the SS-Index distribution and the 3 
sodium-sensitivity classes in our normotensive population. 
The effects of sodium loading on ISS, SR, and SS groups 
were assessed by longitudinal analysis of mean response 
profiles, assuming no specific covariance structure of the 
repeated measures. 
17 Analysis factors were the "SS condi-</p>

<p>tion" (ie, ISS, SR, and SS) and "diet," the latter with 2 repeated 
measures, 1 at the low-salt diet and 1 at the high-salt diet. 
Statistical significance of the difference between diets was 
evaluated with "a posteriori" contrasts after correction for 
multiple comparisons with the false discovery rate proce-
dure. 
18 A proper transformation was applied if the hypothesis </p>

<p>of normality was rejected (Shapiro-Wilk test). Frequency </p>

<p>domain indices were log-transformed, reducing their skew-
ness. 
19 Cardiac output and stroke volume were also log-</p>

<p>transformed. No transformation was required for NN50+ and 
a 1 , as previously reported in healthy volunteers. 
20 Analysis </p>

<p>was performed with "R: A Language and Environment for 
Statistical Computing" software package (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">R Core Team, R Foundation for Statistical Computing</rs>, Vienna, Austria, 2015), 
setting the statistical significance threshold at P=0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Table 1 reports the general characteristics of our population. 
The 3 groups had similar age and 24-hour ambulatory BP level 
during habitual diet. Female sex was more common, with their 
prevalence at 69%, 60%, and 59% in the ISS, SR, and SS 
groups, respectively, without significant differences among 
groups. The body mass index was slightly higher in SS than in 
ISS. The percentage of individuals with positive family history 
for hypertension was almost double in the SS (41%) than in 
the ISS (21%) group, although this difference did not reach 
statistical significance. 
Figure 1 shows the effect of the sodium loading/depletion 
maneuver on BP and HR. With respect to the low-salt diet, the 
high-salt diet decreased BP in the ISS group (systolic BP: 
from 115.3AE11.0 to 108.5AE11.2; MAP: from 85.1AE9.3 to 
78.7AE9.2; diastolic BP: from 71.3AE9.5 to 64.9AE8.3 mm Hg, 
meanAESD), increased BP in the SS group (systolic BP: from 
112.8AE9.2 to 119.0AE9.2; MAP: from 80.7AE7.7 to 87.2AE8.2; 
diastolic BP: from 67.0AE6.9 to 72.6AE7.6), and did not affect 
the SR group (systolic BP: from 114.7AE10.4 to 114.2AE11.4; 
MAP: from 82.3AE7.2 to 82.2AE7.8; diastolic BP: from </p>

<p>Table 1. General Characteristics of Normotensive Volunteers by SS-Index Classes: Mean (SD) </p>

<p>Classes 
ISS (N=29) 
SR (N=25) 
SS (N=17) 
P Value </p>

<p>SS-Index range, mm Hg/(molÁday) 
À98.2: À15.3 
À14.5: +14.3 
+15.1: +123.0 </p>

<p>DMAP, mm Hg* 
À6.4 (3.7) 
0.0 (2.0) 
6.5 (3.9) </p>

<p>Sex, F/M 
20/9 
15/10 
10/7 
0.72 </p>

<p>Age, y 
27.3 (6.4) 
26.0 (3.8) 
29.6 (6.8) 
0.053 </p>

<p>Body mass index, kg/m </p>

<p>2 † </p>

<p>21.4 (2.6) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>22.1 (2.4) 
23.9 (2.5) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>DWeight, kg </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>1.4 (1.1) 
1.2 (1.6) 
0.9 (1.4) 
0.34 </p>

<p>Family history of hypertension 
21% 
36% 
41% 
0.28 </p>

<p>24-h systolic BP, mm Hg </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>115.0 (7.7) 
116.5 (8.6) 
116.2 (11.7) 
0.82 </p>

<p>24-h diastolic BP, mm Hg </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>68.6 (5.6) 
69.2 (6.1) 
69.8 (8.6) 
0.84 </p>

<p>24-h HR, bpm </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>73.5 (9.0) 
70.7 (9.2) 
71.5 (10.5) 
0.53 </p>

<p>BP indicates blood pressure; HR, heart rate; ISS, inverse sodium-sensitive; SR, sodium resistant; SS, sodium sensitive. 
*DMAP, difference between high-salt and low-salt conditions in mean arterial pressure averaged over the 2-h recording period at the end of the diet. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Measures at the end of the low-sodium diet. </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Means a significant difference vs SS (Tukey's post-hoc). </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>DWeight, difference between body weights at the end of the high-salt and low-salt diets. </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>Data from 24-h ambulatory BP monitoring during habitual diet; P calculated by v 
2 test for sex and family history of hypertension, by 1-way ANOVA for all the other variables. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Response to Salt in Normotensives 
Castiglioni et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>68.9AE6.2 to 68.8AE6.7). The high-salt diet also decreased HR 
significantly in ISS (from 71.9AE10.9 to 67.0AE8.6 bpm) and 
SR (from 73.2AE10.9 to 69.6AE13.4) groups, but not in the SS 
group (from 69.1AE12.1 to 67.9AE9.5). 
Figure 2 shows left ventricular ejection time and other 
hemodynamic parameters from model-flow analysis. The 
high-salt diet increased left ventricle ejection time in all 
groups (+10.8, +17.8, and +13.8 ms in ISS, SR, and SS, 
respectively). However, it induced opposite changes of SVR 
and arterial compliance in ISS and SS, without affecting SR </p>

<p>(P&lt;0.001 for factors interaction). In fact, after the high-
salt diet, SVR decreased in ISS (from 1.22AE0.34 to 
1.07AE0.20 mm Hg9s/mL), tended to increase in SS (from 
1.00AE0.27 to 1.12AE0.31) without substantial changes in SR 
(from 1.03AE0.19 to 1.07AE0.26), while arterial compliance 
increased in ISS (from 2.16AE0.43 to 2.33AE0.45 mL/ 
mm Hg) and decreased in SS (from 2.45AE0.56 to 
2.31AE0.58), also in this case without substantial changes 
in SR (from 2.35AE0.38 to 2.38AE0.41). Aortic characteristic 
impedance decreased in ISS only. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Brachial measures of blood pressure (BP) and heart rate (HR). Mean (SEM) after low-salt (open </p>

<p>circles) and high-salt (solid circles) diets in 3 groups of normotensive volunteers, defined on the basis of SS-
Index: a sodium-sensitive group, SS, with SS-Index &gt;15 mm Hg/(mmolÁday), and 2 sodium-resistant 
groups: 1 unresponsive to sodium load, SR, with À15≤ SS-Index ≤15; and 1 responding to sodium load with 
a BP decrease, ISS, with SS-index &lt;À15. ISS indicates inverse sodium sensitive; MAP, mean arterial 
pressure. The "*" marks significant differences between diets. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Response to Salt in Normotensives 
Castiglioni et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Considering HR variability (Figure 3), the high-salt diet 
decreased spectral and complexity-based indices of car-
diac sympatho/vagal balance (PI LF/HF decreased by À21%, 
À20%, and À16% and a 1 decreased by À6%, À4%, and À7% 
in ISS, SR, and SS groups, respectively). The high-salt diet also 
increased time-domain and spectral indices of vagal HR 
modulation (+32%, +36%, and +24% for NN50+, +51%, +54%, 
and +38% for PI HF, in ISS, SR, and SS groups, respectively). 
The vagal HR modulation tended to decrease with the severity 
of sodium sensitivity and the effect of sodium loading 
appeared less marked in the SS group. 
Figure 4 shows that the high-salt diet increased the 
baroreflex sensitivity in all groups (BRS LF: +22%, +38%, 
and +23%; BRS HF: +29%, +48%, and +28% in ISS, SR, and SS 
groups). The high-salt diet also decreased the LF power of 
diastolic BP in ISS (À24%), in SR (À52%), and in SS (À24%) 
groups, with the change reaching the significance threshold in 
ISS and SR groups only. Sodium loading also decreased the 
diastolic BP fluctuations of longer term (very-low frequency </p>

<p>power), significantly in the ISS group (À32%), and close to the 
significance level in the SR group (À26%). By contrast, very-
low frequency power of diastolic BP was only marginally 
influenced by the sodium diets in the SS group (À6%). 
The SS-Index also allows describing the severity of sodium 
sensitivity in a continuous fashion, without introducing 
predefined classes of salt sensitivity. In this regard, Figure 5 
shows mean values of SVR, cardiac output, and MAP by 
quintiles of SS-Index, separately after the 2 diets. Interest-
ingly, SVR progressively decreased and cardiac output 
progressively increased from the lower to the upper quintile 
after the low-salt diet while, after the high-salt diet, SVR 
appeared uniformly distributed and the increase of cardiac 
output with SS-Index was much less pronounced. MAP was 
substantially higher in the 2 upper quintiles after the high-salt 
diet while, after the low-salt diet, the highest value was 
associated with the lower quintile. Table 2 reports the 
Kendall's associations between SS-Index and all the other 
variables of the study by diets. As expected, BP increased with </p>

<p>Figure 2. Hemodynamic parameters. Mean (SEM) after low-salt and high-salt diets in inverse sodium-sensitive (ISS), sodium-resistant (SR), </p>

<p>and sodium-sensitive (SS) individuals; SVR indicates systemic vascular resistances. The "*" marks significant differences between diets. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Response to Salt in Normotensives 
Castiglioni et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>SS-Index after the high-salt diet. Indices of cardiovascular 
hemodynamics were also associated with SS-Index but only 
after the low-salt diet: stroke volume, cardiac output, and 
arterial compliance increased while SVR and aortic charac-
teristic impedance decreased with SS-Index. As regards HR 
and BP variability, SS-Index was negatively associated with 
vagal HR modulation after the high-salt diet: NN50+ 
decreased significantly with SS-Index, and the same trend, </p>

<p>close to the significance threshold (P=0.07), characterized the 
frequency-domain index of vagal HR modulation, PI HF. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study investigated whether hemodynamic and autonomic 
responses to salt intake depend on the degree of salt 
sensitivity, for the first time in a population of white, young, </p>

<p>Figure 3. Autonomic indices of HR variability. Left: frequency-and complexity-domain indices of cardiac </p>

<p>sympatho/vagal balance (PI LF/HF and a 1 ); right: frequency-and time-domain indices of vagal modulations 
of HR (PI HF and NN50+), in inverse sodium-sensitive (ISS), sodium-resistant (SR), and sodium-sensitive 
(SS) individuals. a 1 indicates short-term scale coefficient of PI; HF indicates high frequency; HR, heart rate; 
LF, low frequency; NN50+, number of PI increases per minute larger than 50 ms; PI, pulse interval. Spectral 
indices are represented in logarithmic scale. The "*" marks significant differences between diets. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Response to Salt in Normotensives 
Castiglioni et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>normotensive volunteers and by adopting a classification in 3 
rather than in 2 classes: ISS, SR, and SS. In fact, the SS-Index 
distribution emphasized the oversimplification of the tradi-
tional dichotomous approach in sensitive/resistant individu-
als to sodium loading, because normotensive subjects 
traditionally classified as sodium resistant do not all respond 
to sodium loading in the same way. 
The BP decrease induced by sodium loading in the ISS 
group appeared to be a consequence of a dramatic decrease 
of vascular resistances. By contrast, vascular resistances did 
not decrease in SR and SS groups. In this regard, SR 
normotensives seemed more similar to SS than to ISS 
individuals, and after the low-salt diet peripheral resistances </p>

<p>in both SR and SS groups were about 20% lower than in the 
ISS group. 
Our findings support the notion that the disproportion 
between cardiac output and vascular resistances in SS 
subjects is determined by their failure to adequately lower 
vascular resistances during sodium repletion, 
21 and confirm </p>

<p>data collected in a mostly normotensive population of black 
individuals dichotomously classified in salt-sensitive and salt-
resistant groups, 
6 in whom vascular resistances increased in </p>

<p>salt-sensitive and decreased in salt-resistant individuals after 
5 days of high-salt diet without significant changes in cardiac 
output. However, by splitting salt-resistant individuals into the 
ISS and SR subgroups, we provide evidence that only in ISS </p>

<p>Figure 4. Autonomic indices of BP variability. Indices of baroreflex sensitivity (BRS LF and BRS HF) and of </p>

<p>sympathetic modulations of vascular tone (diastolic BP VLF and LF) represented in logarithmic scale, in 
inverse sodium sensitive (ISS), sodium resistant (SR), and sodium sensitive (SS) individuals. BP indicates 
blood pressure; HF, high frequency; LF, low frequency; VLF, very-low frequency. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Response to Salt in Normotensives 
Castiglioni et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>normotensives was the unchanged cardiac output after the 
high-salt diet the result of a significantly lower HR level, which 
acted as a compensatory factor against a substantially higher 
stroke volume. 
The role of peripheral resistances in mediating salt-induced 
increases of blood pressure is still a matter of lively 
debate. 
22,23 The Guyton's theory concluded that salt loading </p>

<p>induces hypertension causing transient large increases in 
cardiac output, whereas systemic vascular resistance initially 
remains normal or unchanged. 
24,25 A recent review chal-</p>

<p>lenged this view, proposing that direct response to sodium 
load in SS individuals is attributable to an initial inhibitory 
effect on arteriolar vasodilation that is able to prevent 
vascular resistance decrease. 
26 Our observation that the </p>

<p>initial hemodynamic pattern after sodium loading is a lack of 
vasodilation in SS individuals seems to confirm this vasodys-
function theory. However, we also showed that during low-salt 
diet the SS-Index is positively associated with cardiac output 
and arterial compliance and negatively associated with SVR 
and characteristic impedance, suggesting a residual positive </p>

<p>salt balance in SS subjects during salt depletion and giving 
support to Guyton's physiology. We may also hypothesize a 
role played by altered modulations of the renin-angiotensin-
aldosterone system or of the sympathetic nervous system, 
reported to occur in hypertensive SS individuals. 
3,27 However, </p>

<p>studies in normotensive humans revealed that an increased 
dietary salt intake (5-7 days of high-salt regimen) induces a 
profound reduction in vascular nitric oxide bioavailability, 
which limits endothelium-dependent vasodilation. 
28,29 Thus, a </p>

<p>reduced bioavailability of nitric oxide after 5 days of high-salt 
diet might determine the altered response of vascular 
resistances in SS and SR normotensive subjects. Future 
studies could validate this speculation by measuring plasma 
levels of nitric oxide and of interacting cytokines, such as 
transforming growth factor b1, 
28 in ISS, SR, and SS groups </p>

<p>undergoing a high-salt diet. 
Our data also indicate effects of the sodium loading/ 
depletion maneuver on the autonomic cardiovascular modula-
tion. First, sodium loading increased vagal modulation of HR (PI 
HF and NN50+) and the HR BRS (Figure 4), with these changes </p>

<p>Figure 5. Dependence of SVR, cardiac output, and MAP on SS-Index. Mean and SEM by quintiles of the </p>

<p>SS-Index distribution, plotted separately after the low-salt diet (upper panels) and the high-salt diet (lower 
panels). SS-Index range for each quintile is reported on the lower right panel. MAP indicates mean arterial 
pressure; SVR, systemic vascular resistances. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Response to Salt in Normotensives 
Castiglioni et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>appearing less pronounced in SS individuals, and decreased HR 
significantly, but not in SS normotensives (Figure 1). These 
findings suggest an increased vagal modulation of HR after a 
high-salt diet, partially blunted in the SS group. 
Second, sodium loading decreased indices reflecting 
cardiac sympatho/vagal balance (PI LF/HF and a 1 ) and 
vasomotor oscillations considered to reflect sympathetic 
vascular modulation associated with a baroreflex resonance 
(diastolic BP LF in Figure 4). In line with these findings, it was 
observed that a low-salt diet increases the muscle sympa-
thetic nerve traffic in hypertensive individuals. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Third, sodium loading significantly decreased slow vaso-
motor components of diastolic BP variability (Figure 4), likely 
generated by sympathetic modulation of SVR, only in the ISS </p>

<p>group, in which the high-salt diet also dramatically decreased 
SVR. This suggests that the preserved adaptation of vascular 
resistances to dietary sodium intake in ISS individuals may 
reflect the preserved ability of the autonomic nervous system 
to modulate SVR. 
The effects of sodium diets we reported in normotensive 
individuals are similar to changes described in hypertensive 
patients. 
4,5 Increased BRS, increased cardiac vagal index, and </p>

<p>decreased HR and cardiac sympatho/vagal balance have 
been reported in hypertensive patients after a high-salt diet, 
with these changes being blunted in those hypertensive 
patients with the more severe degree of sodium sensitivity. 
Therefore, our results indicate that the same type of cardiac 
autonomic alterations characterizing sodium sensitivity in 
hypertensive patients are already detectable in a population of 
young, healthy, white normotensive individuals, with possible 
clinical implications for prevention of the adverse cardiovas-
cular effects of sodium loading as well as of an increased 
sodium sensitivity. 
We also identified associations between SS-Index and 
several hemodynamic variables, but only after the low-salt 
diet (Table 2). This was not reported by Schmidlin et al, 
probably because of the dichotomous classification of sodium 
sensitivity, or of the lower sample size. 
6 We found that after </p>

<p>5 days of a low-salt diet, individuals with the lowest degree of 
sodium sensitivity had the highest SVR, the highest aortic 
impedance, and the lowest arterial compliance. These trends 
were responsible for a reduction in cardiac afterload with 
increased sodium sensitivity, and for an increase in the 
Windkessel effect with increased sodium sensitivity under 
reduced sodium loading. In this condition of sodium depletion, 
BP levels did not depend on the SS-Index significantly, as for 
systolic and diastolic BP, or even decreased with the severity 
of sodium sensitivity, as for MAP. By contrast, the high-salt 
diet uncoupled SS-Index from cardiac afterload and Wind-
kessel effect, and concomitantly BP increased significantly 
with SS-Index. 
We also detected a negative association between SS-Index 
and NN50+, but only after sodium loading (Table 2), indicating 
a partially blunted vagal control of HR in individuals with the 
higher degree of sodium sensitivity, when facing a high-salt 
diet. Interestingly, this hypothesis is supported by previous 
evidence of a blunted vagal modulation of HR in SS 
normotensive individuals following their habitual diet. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>Our results might also help to clarify recent controversial 
findings that indicate a U-shaped association between sodium 
intake and health outcomes. 
32 In fact, our findings seem to </p>

<p>suggest that an ideal healthy sodium diet, valid for all 
normotensive individuals, might not exist. In a fraction of our 
volunteers, the diet with a very low sodium content induced 
hemodynamic adaptations that are generally associated with 
increased risk of cardiovascular events. Volunteers with </p>

<p>Table 2. Correlation Between SS-Index and Hemodynamic or 
Autonomic Variables (Kendall's s and Significance P) at the 
End of Each Diet </p>

<p>Low-Salt Diet 
High-Salt Diet </p>

<p>s 
P Value 
s 
P Value </p>

<p>Systolic BP 
À0.09 
0.29 
0.24* 
0.003 </p>

<p>Diastolic BP 
À0.14 
0.08 
0.31* 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>MAP 
À0.18 
0.02* 
0.29* 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Pulse pressure 
À0.08 
0.29 
0.08 
0.30 </p>

<p>HR 
À0.09 
0.27 
0.03 
0.68 </p>

<p>Model flow analysis </p>

<p>Left ventricular 
ejection time </p>

<p>À0.02 
0.77 
0.03 
0.76 </p>

<p>Stroke volume 
0.19* 
0.02 
0.05 
0.51 </p>

<p>Cardiac output 
0.17* 
0.04 
0.10 
0.23 </p>

<p>SVR 
À0.21* 
0.01 
0.03 
0.68 </p>

<p>Arterial compliance 
0.18* 
0.03 
0.02 
0.82 </p>

<p>Aortic 
characteristic 
impedance </p>

<p>À0.19* 
0.02 
À0.14 
0.10 </p>

<p>HR and BP variability analysis </p>

<p>PI HF 
À0.09 
0.26 
À0.15 
0.07 </p>

<p>PI LF/HF 
0.08 
0.33 
0.13 
0.12 </p>

<p>Diastolic BP LF 
À0.05 
0.53 
0.03 
0.70 </p>

<p>Diastolic BP VLF 
À0.06 
0.45 
À0.05 
0.53 </p>

<p>BRS HF 
À0.025 
0.77 
À0.04 
0.65 </p>

<p>BRS LF 
À0.07 
0.38 
À0.12 
0.16 </p>

<p>NN50+ 
À0.12 
0.15 
À0.21* 
0.013 </p>

<p>a 1 
0.10 
0.22 
0.10 
0.24 </p>

<p>a 1 indicates short-term scale coefficient of PI; BP, blood pressure; BRS, baroreflex 
sensitivity; HF, high frequency; HR, heart rate; LF, low frequency; MAP, mean arterial 
pressure; NN50+, number of PI increases per minute larger than 50 ms; PI, pulse 
interval; SVR, systemic vascular resistances; VLF, very-low frequency. 
*Correlations significant at P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Response to Salt in Normotensives 
Castiglioni et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>SS-Index lower than À30 mm Hg/(molÁday) even had higher 
MAP values after the low-salt diet, as a consequence of a 
remarkable increase of BP induced by salt restriction 
(Figure 5). This would imply that a very low-sodium diet, 
likely beneficial or at least not harmful for most normotensive 
individuals, should be recommended only if inverse sensitivity 
to sodium can be excluded. Future epidemiological and 
prospective studies might clarify whether the ISS individuals 
described in our study significantly contribute to the observed 
greater incidence of cardiovascular events in populations 
exposed to extremely low dietary sodium intakes. 
Two study limitations should be considered. First, partici-
pants in our study, enrolled among students and young medical 
doctors of our University Hospital on a voluntary basis, might 
not be fully representative of a white normotensive population, 
due to their educational level, lifestyle habits, and sex 
distribution. In case the BP response to sodium intake might 
depend on sex, the higher prevalence of females among our 
participants might have biased our results. Therefore, to 
evaluate whether the imbalance between males and females 
might have influenced our results, we have also quantified the 
SVR response to dietary salt by sex in Table 3. The table 
suggests that differences between sexes may affect the 
absolute values of SVR (higher in females than in males), but 
are unlikely to affect the response to dietary salt, because in 
both sexes SVR decreased in the ISS group and increased in the 
SS group. 
Second, the salt-sensitivity test, based on high-and low-
salt diets, lasted several days. Therefore, we cannot extend 
our results to individuals classified as ISS, SR, or SS by the 
sodium loading/depletion maneuver based on saline infusion 
and diuretics (the so-called "Indiana protocol") 
15 because this </p>

<p>maneuver lasts only a few hours and might not elicit the same 
autonomic and hemodynamic adaptations observed in our 
study. 
In conclusion, our study provides evidence that in SS 
normotensive subjects, an impaired vasodilatory response to </p>

<p>dietary salt loading can be a major pathogenetic factor in 
determining the pressor effect of dietary salt intake. This 
alteration seems to be associated with a dysfunction in 
autonomic cardiovascular regulation, as suggested by a 
blunted vagal cardiac modulation and a reduced vascular 
sympathetic inhibition in SS normotensives during high salt 
intake. </p>

<p>Sources of Funding </p>

<p>This study funded by the Italian Ministry of Health. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>None. </p>



<p>Table 3. SVR (mm Hg9s/mL) at the End of Each Diet in the 
3 Sodium Sensitivity Classes (ISS, SR, and SS) by Sex: Mean 
(SEM) </p>

<p>ISS 
SR 
SS </p>

<p>Females (N=41) </p>

<p>Low-salt 
1.28 (0.07) 
1.09 (0.04) 
1.16 (0.08) </p>

<p>High-salt 
1.12 (0.04) 
1.16 (0.06) 
1.31 (0.08) </p>

<p>Males (N=26) </p>

<p>Low-salt 
1.10 (0.13) 
0.95 (0.07) 
0.79 (0.06) </p>

<p>High-salt 
0.95 (0.06) 
0.95 (0.09) 
0.87 (0.06) </p>

<p>ISS indicates inverse sodium-sensitive; SR, sodium resistant; SS, sodium sensitive; SVR, 
systemic vascular resistances. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Response to Salt in Normotensives 
Castiglioni et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>



<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003736 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Response to Salt in Normotensives 
Castiglioni et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL </p>

<p>Data S1. Hemodynamic parameters from BP waveform analysis and autonomic indices from HRV and </p>

<p>BP variability analysis. </p>

<p>Frequency domain analysis of HRV and BP variability. Beat-by-beat series of systolic BP, diastolic BP </p>

<p>and PI were resampled at 5 Hz. The Welch periodogram was estimated over the 2-hour recording by </p>

<p>90%-overlapped Hann data windows of 1638.4 s, and smoothed by a broadband procedure. 
1 Power </p>

<p>spectra were integrated over a very low frequency (VLF) band, between 0.001 and 0.04 Hz; a low </p>

<p>frequency (LF) band, between 0.04 and 0.15 Hz; and a high-frequency (HF) band, between 0.15 and 0.50 </p>

<p>Hz. In this way, the HF power of PI (PI HF), the ratio between LF and HF powers of PI (PI LF/HF powers </p>

<p>ratio), the LF power of diastolic BP and the VLF power of diastolic BP, were estimated. The sensitivity of </p>

<p>baroreflex control of HR was estimated by the transfer function method separately over the LF (BRS LF) </p>

<p>and HF (BRS HF) bands. This was done by calculating systolic BP and PI spectra and cross-spectra over </p>

<p>120-s long, 50% overlapped, Hann data windows, considering reliable only spectral lines with squared </p>

<p>coherence modulus between systolic BP and PI greater than 0.25. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Time-domain and complexity-domain analysis of HRV. Increases larger than 50 ms between </p>

<p>consecutive PI values were counted over the whole 2-hour recording and expressed as rate of increases </p>

<p>per minute (NN50+). 
3 The self-similar characteristics of PI were assessed by the short-term scale </p>

<p>coefficient  1 through detrended fluctuation analysis, considering blocks of PI data not greater than 12 </p>

<p>beats. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>BP waveform analysis. Hemodynamic parameters were derived through the <rs type="software">Beatscope</rs> software, </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>that analyzed finger BP waveforms beat-by-beat for the whole 2-hour recording. The software was </p>

<p>initialized by entering sex, height and body weight of each individual as measured at the end of each </p>

<p>diet. The shape of the brachial BP waveform was reconstructed from the finger BP waveform by </p>

<p>applying a proper filtering procedure implemented in Beatscope. The left ventricular ejection time was </p>

<p>estimated as time interval between systolic upstroke and dicrotic notch on the pulse waveform. </p>

<p>Systemic vascular resistances (SVR), aortic characteristic impedance and arterial compliance were </p>

<p>estimated by a nonlinear three-element model of the aortic input impedance called Model Flow. 
6 Stroke </p>

<p>volume was estimated integrating the flow simulated by the model during systole; cardiac output was </p>

<p>calculated multiplying stroke volume and HR. Values associated to valid BP waveforms (i.e., with </p>

<p><rs type="software">Beatscope</rs> artifact code = 10000000) were averaged over the 2 hours recording at the end of each diet. </p>

<p>Limitations. The "Model Flow" method, originally designed for analyzing invasive aortic BP </p>

<p>waveforms, has some limits when applied to noninvasive finger BP, like all noninvasive methods for </p>

<p>determining cardiac output. 
7 Stroke volume is calculated as output of a 3-element Windkessel model, </p>

<p>with the BP waveform as input, and both characteristic impedance and compliance of the model depend </p>

<p>on the level of the measured BP. Therefore, discrepancies between invasive and non-invasive measures </p>

<p>of BP may influence the estimation of stroke volume and, consequently, cardiac output. </p>

<p>When invasive BP measures were used, the model flow showed good agreement with the </p>

<p>thermodilution technique, 
8, 9 the difference between model-flow and thermodilution measures of </p>

<p>cardiac output being 0.70 (1.08) L/min, as mean (SD), in 25 awake patients in sitting position. As </p>

<p>expected, the model-flow method applied to the noninvasive finger BP was less precise in estimating </p>

<p>absolute values, 
8 nevertheless it tracked precisely relative changes of cardiac output and stroke </p>

<p>volume. 
9, 10 Stroke volumes estimated from noninvasive BP by model flow and from Doppler ultrasound </p>

<p>measures in the aorta were compared in 6 healthy subjects resting supine, and the percent error </p>

<p>between the two methods was 0% (4.2%). </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>It should be considered, however, that calibration of the peripheral finger BP with an arm cuff BP </p>

<p>measure and application of a proper filtering procedure to reconstruct the central BP waveform from </p>

<p>the peripheral BP waveform greatly reduced the discrepancies between model-flow estimates of stroke </p>

<p>volume based on finger BP and on invasive brachial BP 
12 . In our study brachial BP waveforms were not </p>

<p>only reconstructed from the finger BP waveform with the same filtering procedure, but the </p>

<p>reconstructed BP waveforms were calibrated with brachial BP measures, in order to greatly reduce </p>

<p>discrepancies between finger and brachial BP levels responsible for the errors due to use of a peripheral </p>

<p>pulse wave. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Another possible source of errors in the model-flow analysis is that characteristic impedance and </p>

<p>compliance also depend on age, sex, weight and height of the subject. The model flow method takes </p>

<p>this dependence into account through a statistical fitting of the aorta mechanical properties. 
6 Since in </p>

<p>our study the ISS, SR and SS groups had substantially similar age, body mass index and sex distribution, </p>

<p>possible inaccuracies in the statistical fitting should have affected similarly the three groups, with </p>

<p>limited impact on the quantification of differences among groups. </p>

<p>Data S2. Hemodynamic and autonomic indices in salt-resistant and salt-sensitive groups as classified 
by traditional criteria. </p>

<p>Traditionally, individuals are classified in only two classes of salt-sensitivity. The dichotomous </p>

<p>classification as salt-resistant or salt-sensitive is done on the base of the increase in mean arterial </p>

<p>pressure after a high sodium diet compared to the mean arterial pressure level after a low sodium diet. </p>

<p>Unlike criteria based on the SS-index, this classification does not take into account the actual intake of </p>

<p>dietary salt as quantified by 24-hour urinary sodium excretion rate. Usually, the threshold for classifying </p>

<p>an individual as salt-sensitive is an increase in mean arterial pressure ≥ 5% after the high-salt diet. </p>

<p>Table S1 shows hemodynamic and autonomic indices in salt-resistant and salt-sensitive groups classified </p>

<p>following this traditional criterion. Including all normotensive individuals that do not increase BP after </p>

<p>sodium loading in a single "salt resistant" class, the dramatic fall of SVR after sodium loading that </p>

<p>characterizes the ISS group only cannot be detected. By contrast, autonomic changes induced by dietary </p>

<p>salt that similarly affect ISS and SR groups appear clearly in the traditionally defined "salt resistant" </p>

<p>class. </p>

<p>Data S3. SS-Index distribution in normotensives and definition of sodium-sensitivity groups </p>

<p>The frequency histogram of SS-Index for the 71 normotensive individuals (figure S1) shows a relative </p>

<p>maximum at 0 mmHg/(mol/day), with symmetric tails on the left and right contiguous bins, and an </p>

<p>absolute maximum at -20 mmHg/(mol/day). This distribution suggests classifying normotensive </p>

<p>individuals into three groups: a sodium sensitive (SS) group that increases blood pressure in response to </p>

<p>sodium loading; a sodium resistant (SR) group, unresponsive to sodium; and an inverse sodium sensitive </p>

<p>(ISS) group that decreases blood pressure in response to sodium loading. The symmetry of the </p>

<p>distribution around SS-Index=0 suggests to set the thresholds for separating the SR group from the </p>

<p>other two groups at +15 and -15 mmHg/(mol/day). In this way, the histogram peak at -20 </p>

<p>mmHg/(mol/day) is associated with the ISS group. </p>

<p>It is worth noting that the ISS phenomenon does not regard only the sodium sensitivity test based on </p>

<p>high-and low-salt diets. In fact, sodium loading also induced negative blood pressure responses, lower </p>

<p>than -5 mmHg, in about 20% of a normotensive population tested for sodium sensitivity according to the </p>

<p>Indiana protocol (saline infusion vs. diuretics) </p>

<p>
Table S1. Hemodynamic and autonomic indices in traditionally defined salt resistant and salt sensitive groups: </p>

<p>mean (standard error of the mean). </p>

<p>Salt Resistant (N=57) 
Salt Sensitive (N=10) </p>

<p>Low-Salt 
High-Salt 
p 
Low-Salt 
High-Salt 
p </p>

<p>HR (bpm) 
76.6 (9.9) 
73.0 (9.5) 
** 
70.9 (12.2) 
70.0 (7.7) 
n.s. </p>

<p>Left ventricle ejection time (ms) 
296 (21) 
309 (24) 
** 
300 (19) 
317 (23) 
** </p>

<p>Stroke Volume (mL) 
63.5 (18) 
65.6 (16.7) 
n.s. 
78.3 (18.7) 78.1 (26.2) 
n.s. </p>

<p>Cardiac Output (L/s) 
4.76 (1.22) 
4.69 (1.14) 
n.s. 
5.42 (1.19) 5.29 (1.25) 
n.s. </p>

<p>SVR (mmHg ×s /mL) 
1.13 (0.29) 
1.09 (0.23) 
n.s. 
0.92 (0.28) 1.04 (0.35) 
n.s. </p>

<p>Aortic characteristic impedance 
(mmHg ×s /L) 
60.7 (9.4) 
60.1 (9.5) 
n.s. 
54.1 (9.6) 
54.7 (10.3) 
n.s. </p>

<p>Arterial Compliance (mL/mmHg) 
2.24 (0.4) 
2.32 (0.42) 
** 
2.64 (0.62) 2.50 (0.66) 
** </p>

<p>PI LF/HF 
4.7 (3.5) 
3.7 (2.4) 
** 
5.0 (2.0) 
3.8 (1.0) 
n.s. </p>

<p> 1 
1.00 (0.15) 
0.95 (0.16) 
** 
1.06 (0.06) 0.97 (0.06) 
** </p>

<p>PI HF (ms </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
739 (1268) 
1072 (1907) 
** 
536 (557) 
603 (346) 
n.s. </p>

<p>NN50+ (n/min) 
6.3 (4.4) 
8.4 (4.6) 
** 
6.4 (4.6) 
7.9 (4.6) 
n.s. </p>

<p>BRS LF (ms/mmHg) 
11.7 (6.0) 
14.8 (7.7) 
** 
10.4 (4.8) 
11.9 (2.8) 
n.s. </p>

<p>BRS HF (ms/mmHg) 
12.1 (8.7) 
16.4 (11.7) 
** 
9.1 (4.6) 
11.3 (3.2) 
n.s. </p>

<p>Diastolic BP VLF (mmHg </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
12.0 (9.2) 
9.3 (5.9) 
** 
10.1 (4.9) 
13.0 (12.0) 
n.s. </p>

<p>Diastolic BP LF (mmHg </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
7.3 (5.1) 
5.4 (3.2) 
** 
6.6 (3.1) 
6.0 (4.0) 
n.s. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis by means profiles, with False Discovery Rate post-hoc comparison; p is the significance of the 
difference between low-salt and high-salt diets; ** indicates p&lt;0.01; n.s.= not significant (p&gt;0.05). BP=blood pressure; 
HR= heart rate; SVR=systemic vascular resistances; PI=pulse interval; HF= high frequency; LF=low frequency; VLF= very-
low frequency; BRS=baroreflex sensitivity; NN50+=number of PI increases per minute larger than 50 ms;  1 =short-term 
scale coefficient of PI. </p>

<p>Figure S1: SS-Index distribution over 71 normotensive volunteers. The distribution was decomposed </p>

<p>into three groups representing inverse sodium sensitive (ISS), sodium sensitive (SS) and sodium resistant </p>

<p>(SR) individuals by setting the thresholds for identifying SR individuals at -15 and +15 mmHg/(mol/day). </p>

<p>This choice, although arbitrary, defines an SR distribution symmetrically centred on 0, and associate the </p>

<p>distribution peak occurring at a negative SS-Index value, to the ISS group. </p>



</text></tei>