<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5089945" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Aims/Introduction: Our previous study found that dexamethasone-induced insulin resis-
tance (IR) was involved in 5-hydroxytryptamine (5-HT) synthesis and 5-hydroxytryptamine 2 
receptor (5-HT 2 R) in the periphery. The present study examined the effects of inhibitions of 
both peripheral 5-HT synthesis and 5-HT 2 R on dexamethasone-induced IR. 
Materials and Methods: Male rats were exposed to dexamethasone for 10 days, then 
treated with or without a 5-HT 2 R antagonist, sarpogrelate, a 5-HT synthetic inhibitor, 
carbidopa, alone or in combination for 20 days. 
Results: Dexamethasone-induced whole-body IR, with glucose intolerance, decreased 
insulin sensitivity, hyperglycemia, hyperinsulinemia and dyslipidemia, could be effectively 
abolished by sarpogrelate or/and carbidopa, whereas IR-related actions of dexamethasone 
in tissues were accompanied by increased 5-HT synthesis in the liver and visceral adipose, 
and upregulated 5-HT 2 R (5-HT 2A R and 5-HT 2B R) expression in these two tissues as well as 
in skeletal muscle. Sarpogrelate or/and carbidopa treatment significantly abolished dexam-
ethasone-caused tissue-specific IR. In the liver, increased gluconeogenesis, triglycerides and 
very low-density lipoprotein syntheses with steatosis, and downregulated expression of 
plasmalemmal glucose transporter-2 were markedly reversed. In the visceral adipose and 
skeletal muscle, downregulated expression of plasmalemmal glucose transporter-4 was sig-
nificantly reversed, and increased lipolysis was also reversed in the visceral adipose. Dex-
amethasone-induced activations of hepatic mammalian target of rapamycin serine </p>

<p>2448 </p>

<p>, 
and S6K threonine 
389/412 phosphorylation were also abolished markedly by sarpogrelate </p>

<p>or/and carbidopa. Co-treatment with sarpogrelate and carbidopa showed a synergistic 
effect on suppressing dexamethasone actions. 
Conclusion: Inhibitions of both peripheral 5-HT synthesis and 5-HT 2 R are expected to 
be a dependable target for treatment of steroid-induced diabetes. </p>

<p>side-effect profile, such as development of type 2 diabetes, 
ischemic heart diseases, dyslipidemia, osteoarthritis, depression 
and especially whole-body insulin resistance (IR) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>. Chronically 
elevated GC levels have been linked to fatty liver development, 
and as a result, could contribute to hepatic steatosis </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Insulin-
resistant and glucose-intolerant patients have an elevated GC </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally to this work. 
Received 25 November 2015; revised 24 February 2016; accepted 16 March 2016 </p>

<p>ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by Asian Association for the Study of Diabetes (AASD) and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 </p>

<p>833 </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution 
in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E </p>

<p>level </p>

<p>3,4 </p>

<p>, and GC is also associated with the fatty liver phenotype 
in non-alcoholic fatty liver disease </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, myotonic dystrophy 
6 and 
metabolic obesity in normal-weight subjects </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>. The liver is an 
important player in the diabetogenic effects induced by GC 
treatment </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>, whereas pathophysiological accumulation of lipids 
in the liver has been identified as an independent risk factor 
for IR and metabolic syndrome </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>. In addition, GC is also 
involved in IR in adipose tissue and skeletal muscle </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>. 
Serotonin, also called 5-hydroxytryptamine (5-HT), is synthe-
sized by a two-step enzymatic pathway, in which tryptophan is 
first converted to 5-hydroxy-tryptophan (5-HTP) by the enzyme 
tryptophan hydroxylase (Tph), and 5-HTP is next converted to 
5-HT by aromatic L-amino acid decarboxylase (AADC) </p>

<p>10,11 </p>

<p>. 
There are two subtypes of Tph, Tph1 and Tph2, presenting in 
the periphery (Tph1) and center (Tph2), respectively </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>. As to 5-
HT receptors (5-HTR), seven receptor classes, including 14 sub-
types of 5-HTR belonging to seven subfamilies (5-HT 1 R to 5-
HT 7 R), have been identified to date, reflecting the diversity of 
serotoninergic actions </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>. The 5-HT 2 R family including three sub-
types, named 5-HT 2A, 2B, 2C receptors, are expressed predomi-
nantly in peripheral tissues, with similar structure, 
pharmacological properties and signaling pathways </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>. It has been 
found that serum levels of 5-HT are elevated in diabetic patients, 
and the increasing concentration in serum is a marker of diabetic 
complications </p>

<p>14-16 </p>

<p>. Therefore, glucose metabolism and obesity 
might be etiologically associated with 5-HT </p>

<p>17,18 </p>

<p>, as well as adipo-
cyte differentiation mediated by 5-HT 2 Rs in vitro </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>. Upregulation 
of the 5-HT 2A R is often found in obesity and diabetes, which 
leads to high blood sugar level </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>, and GC treatment can increase 
density of serotonin 5-HT 2A R in humans </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>. 
In a previous study </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>, we found that 5-HT is synthesized in 
both the liver and visceral adipose tissues, which are enhanced 
by chronic GC exposure, and is important for GC-induced IR 
in both organs and whole body; GC also upregulates expres-
sions of 5-HT 2A R and 5-HT 2B R in both organs, which might 
be another reason for GC-induced IR. To examine the hypoth-
esis that GC-induced IR can be effectively treated by inhibition 
of both peripheral tissue's 5-HT synthesis and 5-HT 2 R, insulin-
resistant rats induced by long-term exposure to dexamethasone 
(Dex) were treated with an AADC inhibitor, carbidopa (CDP), 
or/and a 5-HT 2 R antagonist, sarpogrelate (Sar). The parameters 
related with whole-body IR, and IR-related abnormality in the 
liver, visceral adipose and skeletal muscle tissue were examined. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Animal experiments 
All studies were carried out in accordance with the Laboratory 
Animal Care Committee at China Pharmaceutical University. 
Animals were kept on a standard 12-h light/dark cycle with 
access to water and food ad libitum throughout the experiment. 
First, male Sprague-Dawley rats (10-weeks-old, purchased from 
B&amp;K Universal Group Limited Shanghai, China; license num-
ber: SCXK [Hu] 2013-0006) were subcutaneously given normal 
saline (control rats) or 0.75 mg/kg bodyweight Dex </p>

<p>(Dexamethasone Sodium Phosphate Injection; Cisen Pharma-
ceutical Co., Ltd, Jining, China; diluted with normal saline) 
twice daily on the morning and afternoon with a 12-h interval 
for 10 days, to make a model of Dex-induced IR. We found 
that long-term treatment with 2.0 mg/kg bodyweight Dex twice 
daily, as had been carried out in another investigation </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>, easily 
led to increased mortality of rats, whereas a dose of 0.75 mg/kg 
bodyweight twice daily was safer, and also induced a marked 
IR in these rats. The consequences of hyperglycemia and hyper-
insulinemia were judged by measuring the levels of fasting 
blood glucose and blood insulin on day 10 after initiating Dex 
exposure. Then, the Dex-exposed rats were divided into four 
groups randomly (n = 8 per group): model group, Dex-exposed 
with Sar (sarpogrelate hydrochloride; Mitsubishi Tanabe 
Pharma Corporation, Osaka, Japan), a broad-spectrum antago-
nist of 
5-HT 2 R, -treated group (Sar group), Dex-exposed with CDP 
(Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA), an inhibitor of AADC, -treated 
group (CDP group), and Dex-exposed with Sar and CDP co-
treated group (Sar+CDP group). The treatments were twice-
daily, carried out for 20 days with an oral administration at 
1 h before Dex exposure. In the Sar group, Sar at 25 mg/kg 
bodyweight was given twice daily before Dex exposure, which 
was lower than previously reported </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>. In order to execute a par-
allel comparison between Sar and CDP treatment, 25 mg/kg 
bodyweight CDP treatment twice daily was also carried out in 
the CDP group, whereas that in the Sar+CDP group was of a 
mixture with both (Sar : CDP = 2:1) as an equal dose with 
both the Sar and CDP group. The drugs were all dissolved with 
a vehicle 0.5% CMC-Na, and were made to the same concen-
tration of 5.0 mg/mL with the same delivery volume (0.50 mL/ 
kg bodyweight), whereas rats in the control and model group 
were given 0.5% CMC-Na (0.50 mL/kg bodyweight). 
On day 16 and day 18 of treatment, the glucose tolerance 
test (GTT) and insulin tolerance test (ITT) were carried out at 
12 h after fasting, and 5 h after the drug and Dex treatment. 
At the end of the experiment, animals were deprived of food 
(free to take water) for 12 h, and then were anesthetized by 
amobarbital sodium (45 mg/kg) intraperitoneal injection and 
euthanized. Collected blood samples were centrifuged (600 g, 
for 10 min) for obtaining serum. Liver tissue, intra-abdominal 
adipose tissue, including mesenteric, bilateral perirenal and epi-
didymal adipose tissue, and hind thigh muscle were removed 
immediately. Liver tissue and intra-abdominal adipose tissue 
were weighed. The tissues were washed in cold phosphate-buf-
fered saline. Samples of serum and the tissues were stored at -
80°C immediately for subsequent further measurement. </p>

<p>GTT and ITT 
Randomly selected five of eight rats in each group were used to 
carry out GTT and ITT. A dose of 2 g/kg glucose injection 
(Hunan Kelun Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd, Yueyang, China) was 
intraperitoneally injected. Approximately 20 lL of blood was 
sampled at 0, 30, 60, 90 and 150 min by tail bleeding before </p>



<p>J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 
ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Ma et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>and after glucose was given. Blood glucose was measured using 
a LifeScan Blood Glucose Meter (Johnson &amp; Johnson, Milpitas, 
CA, USA). The GTT was evaluated by the total area under the 
blood glucose curve (AUC) using the trapezoidal method </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>. 
A dose of 0.5 IU/kg insulin injection (Eli Lilly Inc., Suzhou, 
China) was intraperitoneally injected. Approximately 20 lL of 
blood was sampled at 0, 30, 60, 90 and 120 min by tail bleed-
ing before and after insulin was given. Blood glucose was mea-
sured, and the ITT was evaluated by AUC like GTT. </p>

<p>Serum and hepatic biochemical analysis 
The 0.4-g tissues were sliced and homogenized in 4 mL cold 
phosphate-buffered saline buffer, and the homogenate was then 
used for measurement. Levels of 5-HT, insulin, dopamine and 
very low-density lipoprotein (VLDL) in the tissue or serum 
were measured by using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
assay kit (Abcam, Sha Tin, Hong Kong). Serum levels of 
triglyceride (TG), total cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein 
cholesterol (LDL-c), high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-c), 
free fatty acids (FFA) and glucose, and glycerol content in the adi-
pose tissue were measured by using a spectrophotometer kit (Nan-
jing Jianchen, Nanjing, China). TG content in the liver tissue was 
measured using a TG enzyme-test kit (Applygen Technologies 
Inc., Beijing, China). Serum VLDL-c level was calculated by 
VLDL-c = total cholesterol -LDL-c -HDL-c. Homeostasis 
model of assessment for IR index was calculated by serum glu-
cose 9 serum insulin / 22.5 </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Oil red O staining in the liver tissue 
The liver tissue stored in a -80°C freezer was placed in an 
optimal cutting temperature chamber and a 6-lm thick section 
was made. Tissue slices were rinsed with phosphate-buffered 
saline, raised with 60% isopropanol and stained with fresh Oil 
Red O working solution for 15 min. Tissue slices were rinsed 
with 60% isopropanol again, and hematoxylin was used to 
counterstain for showing the nucleus. </p>

<p>Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction 
Total ribonucleic acid (RNA) was extracted from intra-abdom-
inal adipose tissue or liver tissue using RNAiso Plus Isolation 
Reagent (TAKARA, Otsu, Shiga, Japan) according to the manu-
facturer's instructions. Total RNA was reserve transcribed and 
amplified in a GeneAmp PCR system (Eppendorf, Hamburg, 
Germany). Primers used in the reverse transcription polymerase 
chain reaction were of: adipose triglyceride lipase (ATGL; for-
ward TTC AAG TTT CCT TGC AGA GT; reverse CTC CCA 
AAC TGA CCC TTA AA) in visceral adipose tissue, acetyl-
CoA carboxylase (ACCase; forward GCC AGC AGA ATT 
TGT TAC TC; reverse AGA CGA TGC AAT CTT ATC CC) 
in liver tissue, and glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase 
(forward TAT CGG ACG CCT GGT TAC; reverse TGC TGA 
CAA TCT TGA GGG A). Data analysis was carried out using 
a <rs id="software-0" type="software">GeneGenius</rs> automatic gel imaging and analysis system (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Syn-gene</rs>, Cambridge, UK), and scanned by densitometry for </p>

<p>quantitation. To exclude variations as a result of RNA quantity 
and quality, the data for genes were adjusted to glyceraldehyde 
3-phosphate dehydrogenase, and the relative expression levels 
of ATGL and ACCase were calculated as: (relative gray value 
of the gene / mean of relative gray value in the con-
trol) 9 100%. </p>

<p>Western blotting 
Liver tissue, intra-abdominal adipose tissue or skeletal muscle 
tissue were homogenized in lysis buffer, then sonicated and 
incubated on ice for 15 min. Extraction of cytosol or mem-
brane protein used a Cytosol or Membrane Protein Extraction 
Kit (Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology, Shanghai, China). 
Proteins were separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacry-
lamide gel electrophoresis, and electrophoretically transferred 
onto nitrocellulose membrane. After being blocked, the mem-
branes were then incubated with appropriate primary antibod-
ies, including antibodies with anti-Tph1 and anti-AADC 
(Epitomics-Abcam, Sha Tin, Hong Kong), anti-glycerin-3-phos-
phate acyltransferase 1 and microsomal triglyceride transfer 
protein (Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA), 
anti-glucose transporter 2 (GLUT2) and GLUT4 (Epitomics-
Abcam), anti-5-HTR 2A R and 5-HT 2B R (GeneTex Inc., Irvine, 
CA, USA), anti-phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase-1, anti-ser-
ine (Ser) 
2448 phospho-mTOR, anti-mTOR, anti-threonine 
(Thr) 
389/412 phospho-p70S6K and anti-p70S6K (Signalway Anti-
body, College Park, MD, USA), and anti-b-actin (Bioworld 
Technology Inc., St. Louis Park, MO, China). Then the mem-
branes were incubated with the HRP-coupled secondary anti-
bodies (HuaAn Biotechnology Co. Ltd, Hangzhou, China). 
Detection was carried out by densitometry using the enhanced 
chemiluminescence detection system (Tanon-5200; Tanon 
Science &amp; Technology Co., Ltd, Shanghai, China). The relative 
expressions levels of each protein were calculated as: (relative 
gray value of each protein / mean of relative gray value in the 
control) 9 100%. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data are shown as mean -standard deviation. The differences 
among the groups were evaluated by one-way analysis of vari-
ance (ANOVA) followed by Fisher's least significant differences 
tests under the homogeneity of variances or Tamhane's T2 tests 
under the non-homogeneity of variances, whereas the differ-
ences of tissue protein expression levels of Tph1, AADC, 
5-H 2A R, and 5-HT 2B R between the control and Dex-exposed 
group were tested by using Student's t-test. P &lt; 0.05 was con-
sidered significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Effects of Sar or/and CDP treatment on Dex-induced whole-
body IR and decrease in bodyweight and food intake 
Bodyweight in the rats exposed to Dex for 10 days was signifi-
cantly decreased compared with the control rats, whereas subse-
quent treatment with Sar or/and CDP for 20 days significantly </p>

<p>ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 </p>



<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Treating GC-induced IR through 5-HT </p>

<p>reversed Dex-caused bodyweight loss with a significant body-
weight gain compared with the Dex-exposed rats. In addition, 
the bodyweight between in Sar-or/and CDP-treated groups 
was not different, which was also not different compared with 
that before drug treatment in each group (Figure 1a, left), 
showing that the Sar or/and CDP treatment completely sup-
pressed Dex-caused weight loss. Food intake was also decreased 
by Dex, which was not reversed significantly by Sar or/and 
CDP treatment, with a slight attenuation by the drug treatment, 
especially in the CDP and Sar+CDP groups (Figure 1a, right). 
Fasting blood glucose level (Figure 1b, left) at the beginning 
of GTT was minimally but significantly, increased in the Dex-
exposed rats (model group) compared with the control rats, 
and was lower in the Sar, CDP and Sar+CDP groups than in 
the model group. A more glucose-stimulated increase in blood 
glucose level (Figure 1b, left) within 150 min in the Dex-
exposed rats was found compared with the control, and AUC 
(Figure 1b, right), a marker of glucose intolerance, was mark-
edly elevated by Dex, both of which were significantly sup-
pressed by Sar or CDP treatment, and were more effectively 
suppressed by both co-treatment, suggesting a synergistic effect 
between Sar and CDP. We also detected a Dex-induced impair-
ment of insulin tolerance examined by ITT, in which both 
insulin-stimulated decrease in blood glucose level (Figure 1c, 
left) within 120 min and AUC (Figure 1c, right) in the Dex-
exposed rats were blunted compared with the control, whereas 
both were markedly improved by Sar or/and CDP treatment 
with a synergistic effect between Sar and CDP. 
In the end of the experiment, hyperglycemia (Figure 1d, left) 
and hyperinsulinemia (Figure 1d, middle) with an increased 
homeostasis model of assessment for IR index (Figure 1d, 
right) induced by Dex were found, which were attenuated sig-
nificantly by Sar or/and CDP treatment with a synergistic effect 
between them. Dyslipidemia with increased levels of serum TG 
(Figure 1e, left), LDL-c and VLDL-c (Figure 1e, middle), and 
decreased serum level of HDL-c (Figure 1e, right) was also 
detected in the Dex-exposed rats, which was also attenuated by 
Sar or/and CDP treatment with a synergistic effect between 
them. More importantly, higher serum HDL-c level in the 
Sar+CDP group than the control group were detected. The 
results suggested that Dex-induced whole-body IR could be 
markedly improved by Sar or CDP treatment, whereas co-treat-
ment with Sar and CDP has a strong abolishment with a syn-
ergistic effect on Dex-induced IR. </p>

<p>Effects of Sar or/and CDP on Dex-induced energy metabolic 
disorder in the liver 
Liver weight (Figure 2a, left up) was significantly decreased in 
the model group compared with the control, whereas the liver 
to bodyweight ratio, namely hepatic index (Figure 2a, left 
down), was markedly increased. Either Sar or CDP treatment 
showed a reversed tendency on Dex-induced decrease in liver 
weight and increase in hepatic index, whereas the co-treatment 
markedly reversed Dex effect on hepatic index, and had a 
reversed tendency on liver weight. Significant hepatic steatosis 
(Figure 2a, right) examined by using Oil Red O staining was 
found in the model group, which was inhibited by Sar or CDP 
treatment, and was strongly inhibited by the co-treatment, indi-
cating a synergistic effect between both. 
TG synthesis detected by assessing glycerin-3-phosphate acyl-
transferase 1 expression (Figure 2b, left), a rate-limiting enzyme 
of hepatic TG synthesis 
27 and VLDL assembly detected by 
assessing microsomal triglyceride transfer protein expression 
(Figure 2b, left), a key factor of hepatic VLDL assembly </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>, both 
were upregulated by Dex. Sar or CDP treatment obviously sup-
pressed Dex-induced upregulations of glycerin-3-phosphate 
acyltransferase 1 and microsomal triglyceride transfer protein, 
whereas the co-treatment showed strong suppression on Dex 
effects. Accordingly, increased content of TG (Figure 2b, right 
upper) and VLDL (Figure 2b, right lower) in the liver tissue of 
the model group were detected, both of which were signifi-
cantly decreased by Sar or CDP treatment and strongly 
decreased by the co-treatment. By assessing hepatic ACCase 
gene expression (Figure 2b, middle), a rate-limiting enzyme of 
fatty acids (FAs) synthesis </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>, we also detected increased hepatic 
FAs synthesis with markedly upregulated expression of the 
ACCase gene in the liver of the model group, which was mark-
edly inhibited by Sar or CDP treatment, but was not further 
inhibited by the co-treatment. These results suggested that Dex-
stimulated TG and VLDL syntheses, showing increased hepatic 
TG and VLDL content, and steatosis, could be abolished effec-
tively by Sar or CDP treatment and strongly abolished by the 
combination of both. Sar or CDP treatment also attenuated the 
Dex-induced FAs synthesis in the liver, but did not have a syn-
ergistic effect. 
Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase-1 (Figure 2c), a rate-lim-
iting enzyme of gluconeogenesis </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, was upregulated by Dex, 
whereas GLUT2 expression (Figure 2c) on the cell membrane 
was downregulated by Dex, and both were significantly </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Effects of sarpogrelate (Sar) or/and carbidopa (CDP) treatment on dexamethasone (Dex)-induced alterations in bodyweight, food intake 
and whole-body insulin resistance in the rats. (a) Bodyweight (left) and food intake (right, only mean value), (b) glucose tolerance test with blood 
glucose levels (left) and area under the blood glucose curve (AUC; right), and (c) insulin tolerance test with blood glucose levels (left) and (c) AUC 
(right) were shown in the control (Ctrl), model with Dex-exposed (Dex), and Dex-exposed with Sar (Dex+Sar), CDP (Dex+CDP), or Sar and CDP 
(Dex+Sar+CDP)-treated group. (d) Levels of serum glucose (left) and insulin (middle), homeostasis model of assessment for insulin resistance 
(HOMA-IR) index (right), and (e) levels of serum TG (left), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-c) and very low-density lipoprotein cholesterol 
(VLDL-c; middle), and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-c; right) are shown in each group. Data are presented as the mean -standard 
deviation. Except for five of eight per group in the glucose and insulin tolerance tests, the others were from all eight rats per group. (b,c) 
*P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 in the blood glucose compared the model group with each group, or in other data. </p>



<p>J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 
ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Ma et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>Before modeling </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>450 </p>

<p>Blood glucose (mM) </p>

<p>Blood glucose (mM) </p>

<p>Blood glucose (mM) </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>0 
30 
60 
90 
150 </p>

<p>200 
Body weight (g/rat) 
Average food intake 
(g/rat/day) </p>

<p>Modeling with Dex Modeling and drug 
45 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 
AUC 
(mmol.h/L) </p>

<p>AUC 
(mmol.h/L) </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>Serum HDL-c 
(mM) 
1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>HOMA-IR index </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 0 </p>

<p>Time/days </p>

<p>Time/min </p>

<p>Ctrl 
Dex 
Dex+Sar Dex+CDP 
Dex+Sar+CDP </p>

<p>Ctrl Dex 
Dex+Sar 
Dex+CDP Dex+Sar+CDP </p>

<p>30 
60 
90 
120 
Time/min 
Ctrl 
Dex 
Dex+Sar Dex+CDP 
Dex+Sar+CDP </p>

<p>5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 </p>

<p>Modeling and drug treatment 
Modeling 
treatment for 20 days 
for 10 days </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** ** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** ** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** ** </p>

<p>** 
** ** ** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** ** 
** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>LDL-c 
VLDL-c </p>

<p>Serum TG (mM) </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Serum LDL-c and VLDL-c </p>

<p>Serum insulin 
(mU/L) </p>

<p>(mM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>** ** ** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>** 
* 
** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>** 
** 
** </p>

<p>** ** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* 
* 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** ** ** </p>

<p>** ** ** ** </p>

<p>* * * </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 
6 
4 </p>

<p>2 
0 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>(d) </p>

<p>(e) </p>

<p>ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 </p>



<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Treating GC-induced IR through 5-HT </p>



<p>** ** </p>

<p>** ** ** ** 
* </p>

<p>** ** </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Liver weight 
(g/rat) </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2.5 
PEPCK1 </p>

<p>PEPCK1 </p>

<p>GLUT2 </p>

<p>p-mTOR </p>

<p>mTOR </p>

<p>p-S6K </p>

<p>S6K </p>

<p>GLUT2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
Fold increase above basal </p>

<p>p-mTOR/mTOR 
p-S6K/S6K </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>** ** ** ** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** ** 
** ** 
** </p>

<p>** ** ** ** 
** ** ** ** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** 
* 
* </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>** ** ** 
** 
** </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 
HI (%) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>GPAT1 </p>

<p>ACCase </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>GPAT1 </p>

<p>MTTP </p>

<p>MTTP </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P </p>

<p>D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>** 
** ** 
** </p>

<p>** ** </p>

<p>** ** ** ** </p>

<p>** ** </p>

<p>Protein expression 
(Fold-increase) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 
Hepatic TG </p>

<p>Hepatic VLDL 
ACCase gene expression 
(Fold-increase) </p>

<p>Protein expression 
(Fold-increase) </p>

<p>(mg/g liver) </p>

<p>(μMol/g liver) 
40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 
** ** ** ** </p>

<p>** 
* </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>(d) </p>

<p>Ctrl 
Dex 
Dex+Sar </p>

<p>Dex+Sar+CDP 
Dex+CDP </p>



<p>J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 
ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Ma et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>reversed by Sar or CDP treatment and strongly reversed by the 
co-treatment, showing that the combination of Sar and CDP 
also had a synergistic effect on abolishing Dex-stimulated 
increase in gluconeogenesis and decrease in glucose uptake in 
the liver. 
Activations of mTOR Ser 
2448 and S6K Thr 
389/412 phosphoryla-
tion are very important in inducing IR with the regulation of 
lipogenesis in liver </p>

<p>30,31 </p>

<p>. We found that the expressions of mTOR 
and S6K in the liver (Figure 2d) were not obviously changed by 
Dex exposure or Dex exposure with Sar or/and CDP treatment, 
whereas Ser 
2448 phosphorylation of mTOR, and Thr 
389/412 phos-
phorylation of p70S6K (Figure 2d) were upregulated markedly 
by Dex exposure, both of which were abolished significantly by 
Sar or CDP treatment, and abolished further by the co-treatment, 
showing a synergistic effect between Sar and CDP. These results 
suggested that Sar or/and CDP's effect on Dex-induced IR in the 
liver is closely involved in suppressing Dex-induced activation of 
the mTOR-S6K pathway. </p>

<p>Effects of Sar or/and CDP on Dex-induced decrease in 
plasmalemmal GLUT4 expression in the skeletal muscle and 
visceral adipose tissue, and lipolysis in the visceral adipose 
tissue 
GLUT4 is the most important transporter of glucose from 
extracellular into intracellular sites in the muscle and adipose 
tissue, which is translocated by insulin stimulation from intra-
cellular sites to the plasma membrane </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>. Dex-induced downreg-
ulation of GLUT4 expression on the cell membrane in the 
skeletal muscle and visceral adipose tissues were detected, which 
was reversed by Sar or CDP treatment, and more effectively 
reversed by the combination of Sar and CDP (Figure 3a, left), 
showing a synergistic effect of them on abolishing Dex-caused 
decrease in glucose uptake. 
GC promotes lipolysis in the adipose tissue </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>. ATGL is a key 
enzyme in controlling lipolysis, which can be upregulated by 
GC </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>. We detected Dex-stimulated lipolysis in the visceral adi-
pose tissue of the model group, with increased serum FFA 
levels (Figure 3a, right), decreased visceral adipose weight (Fig-
ure 3b, left), upregulated expression of the ATGL gene (Fig-
ure 3b, middle) and increased glycerol content (Figure 3b, 
right) in the visceral adipose tissue. Co-treatment with Sar and 
CDP showed more significant amelioration than alone on Dex-</p>

<p>induced lipolysis in visceral adipose tissue (Figure 3b). The co-
treatment was more effective than CDP alone on decreasing 
Dex-caused enhancement in the serum FFA level, ATGL 
expression and glycerol content, which was also more effective 
than Sar on reversing glycerol increase. In addition, either Sar 
or CDP treatment merely showed a reversing tendency on 
Dex-caused decrease in visceral adipose weight, whereas the co-
treatment showed significant reversion on that (Figure 3b). </p>

<p>5-HT Synthesis was upregulated by Dex in the liver and 
visceral adipose tissue, whereas expressions of 5-HT 2A and 
5-HT 2B were also upregulated by Dex in the liver, visceral 
adipose and skeletal muscle tissue 
To examine whether 5-HT is synthesized and is influenced by 
Dex in the liver, visceral adipose and skeletal muscle tissue of 
rats, we assessed Tph1 and AADC expression by western blot, 
and 5-HT levels in these three tissues and serum. In agreement 
with a previous study </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>, the expressions of Tph1 and AADC 
(Figure 4a,b) were detected in the liver and visceral adipose tis-
sues, but were not detected in the skeletal muscle (data not 
shown), whereas rats' chronic exposure to Dex showed mark-
edly upregulated Tph1 and AADC expression in both tissues. 
Accordingly, 5-HT levels in the serum and three tissues (Fig-
ure 4d) were increased significantly by Dex, which were inhib-
ited by CDP in a dose-dependent manner in the CDP or Sar 
and CDP co-treatment rats, whereas Sar alone did not obvi-
ously change 5-HT levels in the serum or in the three tissues. 
More importantly, the fold increases of 5-HT levels in the liver 
and visceral adipose tissue in the model group were higher than 
that in the serum, whereas that in the serum and skeletal mus-
cle tissue were similar, showing that increased 5-HT by Dex in 
the liver and visceral adipose tissue come from 5-HT synthesis 
in the tissue itself rather than serum, which was different with 
5-HT inside the skeletal muscle, which comes from the serum. 
Upregulated expressions of 5-HT 2A R and 5-HT 2B R by Dex in 
the three tissues were also detected (Figure 4a-c). In addition, 
we found very low content of dopamine in the liver, skeletal 
muscle and visceral adipose tissue, which was not altered by 
Dex exposure with or without CDP or/and Sar treatment (data 
not shown), suggesting that Dex-induced IR and CDP or/and 
Sar effects in the liver, skeletal muscle and visceral adipose tis-
sue were not associated with dopamine. </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Effects of sarpogrelate (Sar) or/and carbidopa (CDP) treatment on dexamethasone (Dex)-induced alterations in hepatic lipid and glucose 
metabolism in the rats. (a) Liver weight (left upper), hepatic index (HI) (left lower) and hepatic steatosis with a representative image (magnification: 
9100) using Oil-red O staining (right). (b) Expressions of glycerin-3-phosphate acyltransferase 1 (GPAT1) and microsomal triglyceride transfer protein 
(MTTP) (left), messenger ribonucleic acid expression of acetyl-CoA carboxylase (ACCase; middle), hepatic contents of triglyceride (TG; right upper) 
and very low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (VLDL; right lower). (c) expressions of phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase-1 (PEPCK1) and glucose 
transporter 2 (GLUT2), and (d) expressions of serine 
2448 phospho-mammalian target of rapamycin (p-mTOR), mTOR, threonine 
389/412 phospho-
p70S6K(p-S6K), and p70S6K (S6K) are shown in the liver tissues of the control (Ctrl), model with Dex-exposed (Dex) and Dex-exposed with Sar 
(Dex+Sar), CDP (Dex+CDP), or Sar and CDP (Dex+Sar+CDP)-treated groups. Data are presented as the mean -standard deviation. Except for four 
of eight per group in the examining protein or gene expression, the others were from all eight rats per group. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01. GAPDH, 
glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase. </p>

<p>ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 </p>



<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Treating GC-induced IR through 5-HT </p>

<p>These results suggested that Dex-induced upregulations of 
5-HT 2 R and 5-HT synthesis in the liver and visceral adipose 
tissues, and upregulation of 5-HT 2 R in the skeletal muscle are 
very likely important for Dex-caused whole-body IR with 
tissue-specific IR. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
GC-induced whole-body IR involves the liver, adipose tissue 
and skeletal muscle. In the liver, GC stimulates hepatic gluco-
neogenesis through induction of phosphoenolpyruvate </p>

<p>carboxykinase-1 and glucose-6-phosphatase </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, enhances insulin-
stimulated hepatic de novo lipogenesis by upregulation of 
ACCase and FA synthase </p>

<p>34,35 </p>

<p>, and increases VLDL production 
and secretion </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>. Several indirect mechanisms also likely play a 
role in GC-induced hepatic lipid accumulation, including 
increased lipolysis in visceral adipose tissue, which results in 
more FFA to be delivered to the liver through the blood, and 
systemic hyperinsulinemia and hyperglycemia, which drive hep-
atic de novo lipogenesis </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>. Ectopic lipid accumulation in the 
liver have been strongly associated with hepatic IR with whole-</p>

<p>Visceral adipose </p>

<p>Visceral adipose </p>

<p>Skeletal muscle </p>

<p>Skeletal muscle 
** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** ** ** 
** 
750 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>Serum FFA 
(μM) </p>

<p>(μmol/g adipose) 
Glycerol </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>In visceral adipose tissue </p>

<p>In visceral adipose tissue 
ATGL 
GAPDH </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
* 
** 
** 
2.5 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Visceral adipose weight </p>

<p>(g/rat) </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 
ATGL gene expression 
(Fold-increase) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** 
* </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>** 
** 
* 
* 
** 
* 
* * 
* * </p>

<p>0.5 
GLUT4 expression 
(Fold-increase) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 
GLUT4 </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>GLUT4 </p>

<p>β-actin 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Effects of sarpogrelate (Sar) or/and carbidopa (CDP) treatment on dexamethasone (Dex)-induced alterations in skeletal muscle and 
visceral adipose glucose uptake and visceral adipose lipolysis in the rats. Expression of (a) plasmalemmal glucose transporter 4 (GLUT4) in the 
visceral adipose and skeletal muscle tissue (left), serum free-fatty acids (FFA) level (right), (b) visceral adipose weight (left), and messenger 
ribonucleic acid expression of adipose triglyceride lipase (ATGL; middle) and glycerol content (right) in the visceral adipose tissue are shown in the 
control (Ctrl), model with Dex-exposed (Dex), and Dex-exposed with Sar (Dex+Sar), CDP (Dex+CDP), or Sar and CDP (Dex+Sar+CDP)-treated groups. 
Data are presented as the mean -standard deviation. Except for four of eight per group in examining GLUT4 and ATGL expression, the others 
were from all eight rats per group. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01. GAPDH, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase. </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Examinations of tryptophan hydroxylase 1 (Tph1), aromatic L-amino acid decarboxylase (AADC), 5-hydroxytryptamine 2A receptor 
(5-HT 2A R) and 5-HT2B receptor (5-HT 2B R) expression. Expressions of Tph1, AADC, 5-HT 2A R and 5-HT 2B R in the (a) liver and (b) visceral adipose tissue, 
expressions of (c) 5-HT 2A R and 5-HT 2B R in the skeletal muscle tissue were shown in the control (Ctrl) and model with Dex-exposed (Dex) groups. 
(d) Fold-increases of 5-HT levels in the serum, tissues of liver, visceral adipose, and skeletal muscle were shown in the Ctrl, Dex and Dex-exposed 
with Sar (Dex+Sar), CDP (Dex+CDP), or Sar and CDP (Dex+Sar+CDP)-treated groups. Data are presented as the mean -standard deviation. Except 
for eight per group in examining 5-HT levels, the others were from four of eight rats per group. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01. </p>



<p>J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 
ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Ma et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>Tph1 </p>

<p>In 
Liver 
Tissue </p>

<p>Adipose 
In 
Visceral </p>

<p>Skeletal </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>Tissue 
Muscle 
In </p>

<p>Tph1 </p>

<p>Tph1 </p>

<p>Protein expression 
(Fold-increase) </p>

<p>Protein expression 
(Fold-increase) </p>

<p>AADC </p>

<p>AADC </p>

<p>5-HT 2A R 5-HT 2B R </p>

<p>5-HT 2A R </p>

<p>5-HT 2A R 
5-HT 2B R </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** </p>

<p>** ** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** 
* </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** ** 
* </p>

<p>** 
2 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>Visceral adipose 
Skeletal muscle 
Liver 
Serum </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5-HT 2B R </p>

<p>5-HT 2B R </p>

<p>5-HT 2A R </p>

<p>5-HT 2B R </p>

<p>5-HT (Fold-increase) </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Tph1 
AADC </p>

<p>AADC </p>

<p>5-HT 2A R </p>

<p>5-HT 2B R </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
Protein expression 
(Fold-increase) </p>

<p>5-HT 2A R </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
C t r l 
D e x 
C t r l 
D e x 
C t r l 
D e x </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P 
C t r l 
D e x 
D e x + S a r 
D e x + C D P 
D e x + S a r + C D P </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x </p>

<p>C t r l 
D e x 
C t r l 
D e x 
C t r l 
D e x </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>(d) </p>

<p>ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 </p>



<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Treating GC-induced IR through 5-HT </p>

<p>body IR, and to represent an important marker of cardiovascu-
lar risk, such as atherosclerosis, possibly even more so than vis-
ceral fat </p>

<p>38,39 </p>

<p>. Though GC-induced lipolysis in white adipose 
tissue is controversial, GC promotes lipolysis by increasing mes-
senger RNA expression of the two key lipolytic enzymes, hor-
mone-sensitive lipase and ATGL, and has been found in 
adipose tissue through investigations of rats exposed to GC 
in vivo and adipocytes exposed to GC in vitro </p>

<p>33,40,41 </p>

<p>, and Cush-
ing syndrome patients through microdialysis </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>. Increased lipoly-
sis will result in elevated circulating FFA, which in turn can 
induce IR </p>

<p>40,43 </p>

<p>. Though it is controversial as to whether glucose 
uptake is inhibited by GC in adipose tissue, one study showed 
that in the omental, but not in the subcutaneous, adipocytes in 
humans, GC decreases insulin-stimulated glucose uptake </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>. GC 
is also found to decrease insulin-mediated glucose uptake in 
the skeletal muscle, which can occur through stimulation of ser-
ine kinases, resulting in phosphorylation and inactivation of 
insulin receptor and insulin receptor substrate molecules </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>. In 
the present study, we found that GC-induced whole-body IR, 
and tissue-specific IR in the liver, visceral adipose and skeletal 
muscle are involved in enhanced 5-HT synthesis in the liver 
and visceral adipose, and upregulated 5-HT 2A R and 5-HT 2B R 
in these tissues. Dex-induced IR can be abolished effectively by 
inhibition of both 5-HT 2 R with Sar and peripheral 5-HT syn-
thesis with CDP, and be strongly abolished by the combination 
of Sar and CDP in a synergistic manner, suggesting that the 
combination of Sar and CDP might be a dependable method 
for curing steroid-induced diabetes. Furthermore, the Sar or 
CDP effect was not owing to their impact on bodyweight or 
food intake, as Sar or/and CDP treatment resulted in a reversal 
to Dex-caused weight loss with a complete suppression to Dex-
induced weight loss, but no reversal with a further decrease to 
the food intake in the rats. In addition to decreased food 
intake, the mechanisms of GC-caused weight loss are reduction 
in overall protein synthesis while promoting muscle proteolysis, 
and enhanced gluconeogenesis to result in hyperglycemia and 
glucose lost through urine </p>

<p>46,47 </p>

<p>. Thus, we presume that Sar or/ 
and CDP treatment also attenuates Dex-stimulated effects on 
protein metabolism, as well as suppressing gluconeogenesis. 
Additionally, though CDP is expected to lower dopamine pro-
duction, Dex or CDP did not lead to a change in dopamine 
level in the present study, showing that dopamine is not the 
cause for GC-induced IR. We presume that a major action of 
AADC in the liver and visceral adipose is to assist 5-HT syn-
thesis rather than dopamine. 
It is presumed that the majority of 5-HT in the periphery is 
produced by the entero-chromaffin cells in the gut </p>

<p>48,49 </p>

<p>, and 
5-HT is then majorly taken up and stored in platelets in circu-
lation </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>. Dex-induced production of 5-HT in the entero-chro-
maffin cells has been observed in the small intestine, especially 
in the duodenum of rats </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>. However, both our previous study </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>and present study found that 5-HT is also synthesized in the 
liver and visceral adipose tissues, which were upregulated by 
Dex with upregulated expressions of both Tph1 and AADC, </p>

<p>and that increased 5-HT levels by Dex in both tissues came 
from tissue itself rather than the blood. 5-HT by acting on 
5-HT 2A R mediates hepatic steatosis and IR has been shown in 
several studies </p>

<p>24,52 </p>

<p>, whereas activation of the mTOR-S6K path-
way has been shown to be the mechanism of 5-HT action in 
the liver </p>

<p>53 </p>

<p>, and in the adipocytes and C2C12 myotubes by inhi-
bition of insulin-stimulated activation of the IRS-1-AKT 
signaling pathway with glucose uptake </p>

<p>54 </p>

<p>. The present study 
showed that Dex-induced activations of mTOR Ser 
2448 and 
S6K Thr 
389/412 phosphorylation in the liver tissue were accom-
panied by upregulations of hepatic 5-HT synthesis, and 
5-HT 2A R and 5-HT 2B R expression, followed by hepatic IR, such 
as increased gluconeogenesis, downregulation of GLUT2 expres-
sion on the cell membrane, and increased TG and VLDL synthe-
sis with steatosis in the liver tissue. More importantly, the 
aforementioned liver-IR markers induced by Dex could be abol-
ished significantly by inhibition of 5-HT 2A R and 5-HT 2B R with 
Sar or 5-HT synthesis with CDP, and were more effectively abol-
ished by the combination of Sar and CDP, suggesting that GC-
induced hepatic IR is closely involved in increased hepatic 5-HT 
synthesis and 5-HT 2 R. In addition, the present study also sug-
gested that Dex-stimulated lipolysis in the visceral adipose tissue 
resulted in increased serum FFA level, and downregulation of 
plasmalemmal GLUT4 expression in the visceral adipose and 
skeletal muscle tissue, and might very likely be involved in adi-
pose-specific upregulation in 5-HT synthesis and 5-HT 2 R expres-
sion, and muscle-specific upregulation in 5-HT 2 R expression. 
We also found that it is both 5-HT 2A R and 5-HT 2B R instead of 
5-HT 2A R alone 
24,52 that mediate 5-HT-stimulated IR in the three 
tissues, both of which were upregulated by Dex. The precise 
mechanisms need to be studied further. 
Taken together, peripheral 5-HT synthesis and 5-HT 2 R 
(5-HT 2A R and 5-HT 2B R) are very important for GC-induced 
whole-body IR, and both of which can be upregulated by GC 
in the liver and visceral adipose with upregulated 5-HT 2 R in 
the skeletal muscle. Inhibitions of both peripheral 5-HT synthe-
sis and 5-HT 2 R can be used in the treatment of GC-induced 
IR with diabetes. In addition, great elevation of HDL-c level in 
serum by the combination of Sar and CDP in the Dex-exposed 
rats, with great suppression on Dex-caused enhancement of 
LDL-c level in serum, showed that inhibition of both peripheral 
5-HT synthesis and 5-HT 2 R might also be an effective method 
for the treatment of atherosclerosis, as the goal of lowering total 
cholesterol and LDL-c, and raising HDL-c in blood has become 
a very important health issue for preventing or treating 
atherosclerosis </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
The authors are grateful to Professor Rong Hu (China Pharma-
ceutical University) for her contribution in manuscript revision; 
and Hongbao Yang and Yong Yang, associate researchers 
(Safety Evaluation of Drugs in China Pharmaceutical Univer-
sity, China) for their contribution to histopathological examina-
tions. This study was supported by the National Natural </p>



<p>J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 
ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Ma et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>Science Foundation of China (no. 81570720), and the Students' 
Innovation and Entrepreneurship Training Program in China 
Pharmaceutical University (no. SY15094). </p>

<p>DISCLOSURE 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>





<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Treating GC-induced IR through 5-HT </p>





<p>J Diabetes Investig Vol. 7 No. 6 November 2016 
ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Ma et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

</text></tei>