<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5458115" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>progression is driven by these stromal cells 1 that secrete trophic fac-
tors 34-36 and mediate the desmoplastic deposition of extracellular 
matrix (ECM), tumor vascularization, and the epithelial-mesen-
chymal transition (EMT) enabling metastatic capacity. 37 Tumor 
stroma also mutes anti-cancer immune response. 38-42 Progression 
of many types of cancer is promoted by obesity, hallmark of which 
is WAT overgrowth and high BMI. 2,16,43 The mechanisms underly-
ing increased risk of cancer mortality in obese patients remain 
unclear. Whereas diet 44 and the metabolic syndrome 45 appear to 
underlie cancer initiation, different mechanisms account for the ef-
fect of obesity on cancer progression. A growing body of evidence 
indicates that the key determinant of cancer progression in obesity 
is WAT. 43,46 Consistent with that observation, breast cancer survi-
vors that undergo WAT transplantation for breast augmentation 
have a higher chance of relapse, as we have reported. 15-17 Factors 
secreted by ASCs, adipocytes, and infiltrating leukocytes, collectively 
called adipokines, have been considered as the mechanistic link 
between obesity and cancer. 47 ASCs also secrete MCP-1 and 
other chemokines recruiting macrophages 48 that accumulate in 
the crown-like structures associated with breast cancer risk and 
progression. 49,50 </p>

<p>At present, there are no therapies aimed at ASCs available due to the 
lack of validated molecular targets specific for these cells. Previously, 
we reported non-glycanated DDCN as the marker of ASC differenti-
ating into white adipocytes in mice. 29 Here, we demonstrate that 
human ASC express also non-glycanated DCN recognized by 
CSWKYWFGEC peptide. We show that this peptide can be used as 
an imaging probe or a vehicle directing cytotoxic therapeutics to 
ASCs and enabling their targeted depletion. We had previously 
reported that, in mice, ngDCN-homing hunter killer peptides 
D-WAT and D-CAN target PDGFRa-negative/PDGFRb-positive 
ASCs serving as progenitors of white adipocytes, whereas they spare 
the PDGFRa-positive/PDGFRb-negative brown/beige adipocyte pro-
genitors. 25,29 Our data presented here indicate that both D-WAT and 
D-CAN also target human ASCs with comparable selectivity. As we 
had demonstrated in animal studies, ASCs with higher PDGFRa/ 
lower PDGFRb signaling give rise to beige adipocytes, whereas 
ASCs with higher PDGFRb/lower PDGFRa signaling give rise to 
white adipocytes. It remains to be determined whether ngDCN spe-
cifically marks white adipocyte progenitor cells in humans. </p>

<p>Decorin is a ubiquitously expressed proteoglycan secreted into the 
extracellular matrix molecules. Its main function is modulation of fi-
brillogenesis through interaction with collagens and fibronectin. 51 
Based on the DCN cleavage site resulting in DDCN, we have pre-
dicted that it is generated post-translationally. 26 The protease gener-
ating DDCN remains to be identified. Our data showing that ngDCN 
added to cell culture medium binds to human ASCs (Figure S5) sug-
gest that proteolysis occurs extracellularly. The function of ngDCN 
remains to be determined. Both DCN and ngDCN have been re-
ported to suppress adipogenesis; 26 however, the mechanism of their 
effects on specific pre-adipocyte lineages has not been analyzed. It 
has been shown that DCN suppresses PDGFR signaling by inter-
fering with PDGF activity. 52 In mice, PDGFRa À PDGFRb + ASCs 
are perivascular/mural cells, whereas the PDGFRa + PDGFRb À cells 
are localized deeper in the stroma. 29 Our data demonstrate that, 
in human WAT, the two corresponding stromal populations exist 
and have the same relative perivascular localization. It is possible 
that DCN and ngDCN regulate adipogenesis by suppressing 
signaling specifically through PDGFRa or PDGFRb. The function 
of DCN and ngDCN interactors, including PDGFs, transforming 
growth factor b (TGF-b), and resistin, which serves as a DDCN re-
ceptor in WAT, 26,51 in modulating ASC fate remains to be tested. 
Studies in mouse models provide evidence that DCN suppresses 
PDGFRa signaling in liver cancer. 52 Establishing how DCN and 
ngDCN modulates PDGFRa and PDGFRb signaling in the context 
of white and brown adipose tissue, tumors, and other fibrotic condi-
tions may delineate new approaches to disease prevention and 
treatment. </p>

<p><rs type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs>We thank Zhanguo Gao and Angielyn Rivera for technical assistance. 
We thank Renato Iozzo and Jane Grande-Allen for sharing DCN-null 
MEFs. We thank Askar Kuchumov, Eugene Shevchenko, and Andrew 
Makarovskiy for many helpful discussions. This work was supported 
in part by CTSA award UL1 TR000371. </p>



<p> 
Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 </p>





<p>Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>