<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5452632" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs><rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 21</rs>End Stage Renal Disease (ESRD) undergoing hemodialysis 
(HD) is one of the chronic diseases with effects on patient's qual-
ity of life. Patients undergoing hemodialysis must adhere to a very 
restricted diet and fluid intake. These patients require four hours 
of dialysis sessions three times a week at dialysis unit. These 
results in a loss of time that affects employment, leisure and social 
relationships (Ikonomou et al., 2015). Patients undergoing HD 
experience multiple problems such as sodium and water retention 
(Lee, 2012), hyperphosphatemia (Karamanidou, Clatworthy, 
Weinman, &amp; Horne, 2008), hyperkalemia (Bellizzi et al., 2016), 
hypertension, anemia (Erlingmark, Hedström, &amp; Lindberg, 2016), 
fatigue (Zyga et al., 2015) heart disease (Segall, Nistor, &amp; Covic, 
2014) or diabetes mellitus (van der Meer, Ruggenenti, &amp; 
Remuzzi, 2010). The management of such health issues involves 
several variations in the patient's lifestyle. The success of treat-
ment depends largely on patient adherence to stringent recom-
mended regimen. Non-adherence to therapeutic recommendations 
can have untoward effects on quality of life (Ibrahim, Hossam, &amp; 
Belal 2015), increased morbidity, healthcare costs and mortality. 
Overall, it is estimated that approximately 50% of patients on dial-
ysis are poorly compliant with their treatment (Kammerer, Garry, 
Hartigan, Carter, &amp; Erlich, 2007). </p>

<p>Background </p>

<p>According to the National Kidney Foundation and Kidney 
Disease Outcomes Quality Initiative (Estrella et al., 2013) non-
adherence among patients undergoing HD include: failure or 
shorten the session b) excessive intake of fluids and foods contain-
ing potassium and phosphorus and c) non-adherence to medica-
tion treatment. Non-adherence to attendance at HD session, pre-</p>

<p>Correspondence: Victoria Alikari, Nursing Department, Faculty of 
Human Movement and Quality of Life, University of Peloponnese, 
Sparta, Laconia, Greece. 
Tel.: +30.693.6168825. 
E-mail: vicalikari@gmail.com </p>

<p>Key words: adherence; SMAQ; hemodialysis; validity. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements: the authors would like to thank patients on 
hemodialysis, nursing staff and the Scientific Councils of the Dialysis 
Unit "Medifil", Athens, "Molaoi" Hospital, and Hospital of Tripolis 
"Evagelistria", Peloponnese, Greece. </p>

<p>Contributions: AV, study conception, design and coordination, inter-
views undertaking, literature review, paper writing; VM, project lead-
ing, design and coordination; MT, design and coordination; NK, data 
analysis, manuscript drafting; PT, interviews undertaking, design and 
coordination; AA, interviews undertaking, literature review; EF, inter-
views undertaking, manuscript drafting, literature review; SZ, project 
leading, manuscript drafting. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest: the authors declare no potential conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Received for publication: 14 February 2017. 
Revision received: 18 April 2017. 
Accepted for publication: 27 April 2017. </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC 4.0). </p>

<p>©Copyright V. Alikari et al., 2017 
Licensee PAGEPress, Italy 
Health Psychology Research 2017; 5:6647 
doi:10.4081/hpr.2017.6647 </p>

<p>A modified version of the Greek Simplified Medication Adherence 
Questionnaire for hemodialysis patients </p>

<p>Victoria Alikari, 1 Vasiliki Matziou, 2 Maria Tsironi, 1 Natasa Kollia, 3 Paraskevi Theofilou, 1 
Adamantia Aroni, 1 Evangelos Fradelos, 1 Sofia Zyga 1 </p>

<p>1 Department of Nursing, University of Peloponnese; 2 Department of Nursing, National and 
Kapodistrian University of Athens; 3 Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, School of Health 
Science and Education, Harokopio University, Athens, Greece </p>

<p>[Health Psychology Research 2017; 5:6647] 
[page 1] </p>

<p>2017; volume 5:6647 </p>

<p>[page 2] </p>

<p>[Health Psychology Research 2017; 5:6647] </p>

<p>scribed medications, fluid restrictions, and dietary intake range 
from 0% to 32.3%, 1.2% to 81%, 3.4% to 74%, and 1.2% to 
82.4%, respectively (Durose, Holdsworth, Watson, &amp; 
Przygrodzka, 2004; Kutner, Zhang, &amp; McClellan, 2002). </p>

<p>The effect of non-adherence in hemodialysis regimen </p>

<p>Adherence to prescribed hemodialysis regimen is a critical fac-
tor for obtaining good therapeutic results for patients undergoing 
HD and contributes to reducing morbidity, mortality and hemodial-
ysis side effects (muscle cramps, malnutrition, sepsis, infections) 
(Lòpez-Gòmez, Villaverde, Jofre, &amp; Pérez-García, 2005). 
Nonadherence to fluid restriction can cause anxiety, panic, dysp-
nea, hypertension and pulmonary edema. Repeated excessive fluid 
intake periods burden on the cardiovascular system. Although 
hypertension is a risk factor for cardiovascular disease, the results 
of studies on the relationship between the nonadherence to fluid 
restriction and mortality were positive (Szczech et al., 2003) or 
negative (Lòpez-Gòmez, et al., 2005). These results may indicate 
that other variables, such as nutritional status and age may act as 
mediators (Szczech et al., 2003; Lòpez-Gòmez et al., 2005). 
Non-adherence to diet and medication regimen can lead to 
chronically elevated serum phosphorus levels, which play a main 
role in the development of secondary hyperparathyroidism and 
renal osteodystrophy. Elevated phosphate levels may, also, 
increase the risk for coronary heart disease even in young patients 
(Goodman, 2002) leading to a significantly increased risk of mor-
tality (Block et al., 2004). Severe hyperkalemia is common among 
patients undergoing HD with an inclination to suicide or who 
ignore proper dietary regimen. 
The skipping or shortening of the hemodialysis session reduces 
the adequacy of dialysis. The skipping of at least one dialysis ses-
sion per month has been associated with 25-30% higher risk of 
death while the abbreviation for more than 10 minutes (≥3 times 
per month) has, also, been associated with increased mortality 
(Leggat et al., 1998). </p>

<p>Measures of patient adherence </p>

<p>Patient adherence is measured in various ways in clinical prac-
tice. The measurement methods used may be objective or subjec-
tive. Pills counting are usually carried out in patient's home or dur-
ing his visit to the clinic but cannot determine the discharge, accu-
mulation or movement of the pills to another container. The meas-
urement of prescriptions or prescriptions renewed in right time 
provides us information for adherence but no information is given 
whether the patient actually takes the medication or not. The direct 
observation may seem the most precise method; however, patients 
can hide their drugs in their mouths and reject them when they are 
not visible. The method of direct observation is most useful in 
measuring adherence through the presence to the appointment with 
the therapist. The electronic devices are accurate and a degree of 
patient cooperation is required. Blood and urine tests are expensive 
and impractical for use in the routine. Therefore, health profession-
als should be based on less direct and less sensitive methods. 
Interviews and questionnaires are flexible and practical methods to 
obtain information on the adherence to the treatment. However, the 
questionnaires may be difficult to use for patients with low levels 
of literacy. The Hill-Bone Compliance Scale (Hill-Bone) consists 
of three subscales (medication taking behavior, attendance in 
appointments and sodium intake) but it has limited generalization 
as it aims only to patients taking antihypertensive agents. Due to 
its high reliability (Cronbach's a 0.84) in populations of the black 
race, its use is recommended for studies in these populations (Kim, </p>

<p>Hill, Bone, &amp; Levine 2000; Krousel-Wood et al., 2013). The Eight-
Item Morisky Medication Adherence Scale (MMAS-8) focuses on 
medication behavior and particularly in reduced use and negli-
gence of taking medication (Tan, Patel, &amp; Chang 2014). The 
Medication Adherence Report Scale (MARS) focuses on beliefs 
and compliance barriers (Nguyen, Caze, &amp; Cottrell, 2014). It is 
based on the scale Drug Attitude Inventory (DAI) and explores the 
medication behavior and attitudes towards medication of patients 
with psychosis with high validity and reliability (Cronbach's a 
0.75) (Thompson, Kulkarni, &amp; Sergejew, 2000). 
In conclusion, each method, either objective or subjective, has 
strengths and limitations while some methods are more useful for 
some types of therapeutic recommendations than others (Achieng 
et al., 2013; Jimmy &amp; Jose, 2011). 
In order to measure HD patient adherence, self-report instru-
ments such as reliable and validates questionnaires are often used. 
Literature review revealed a small number of scales which can be 
used especially for hemodialysis patients. The Renal Adherence 
Attitudes Questionnaire (RAAQ) is a scale consisted of 26 items 
measuring attitudes toward adherence while the Renal Adherence 
Behaviour Questionnaire (RABQ) is a scale consisted of 25 items 
evaluating self-reported dietary and fluid adherence (Rushe &amp; 
McGee, 1998). The Dialysis Diet and Fluid Non-Adherence 
Questionnaire (DDFQ) (Vlaminck, Maes, Jacobs, Reyntjens, &amp; 
Evers, 2001) is a 4-item scale that assesses the level of adherence 
to fluid and dietary restriction for the past 14 days. However, the 
above tools do not explore the levels of attendance in HD session 
and medication use (Vlaminck et al., 2001). The End Stage Renal 
Disease Adherence Questionnaire (ESRD-AQ) is a 46 item ques-
tionnaire that addresses all aspects of adherence in HD. 
Nevertheless, the large number of questions should be considered 
(Kim, Evangelista, Phillips, Pavlish, &amp; Kopple, 2010). Finally, the 
Fluid Control in Hemodialysis Patients Scale (FCHPS) is a tool 
conducted on 2010 by Albayrak Cosar &amp; Cinar Pakyuz to focus on 
knowledge, behaviors, and attitudes of HD patients about the 
aspect of fluid restriction (Albayrak Cosar &amp; Cinar Pakyuz, 2010). 
As a result, there is need of a reliable questionnaire to be 
addressed exclusively to patients undergoing HD measuring all 
aspects of adherence to HD regimen. 
The aim of this study was to modify the Greek version of 
Simplified Medication Adherence Questionnaire (GR-SMAQ) for 
patients undergoing hemodialysis and explore its validity and reli-
ability. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Study design </p>

<p>This study was a methodological study. </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>The GR-Simplified Medication Adherence Questionnaire is a 
self-administered questionnaire that consists of 6 items of which 
four are dichotomous (Yes/No), one is Likert-type while one is 
open: (1) "Do you always take your medication at the appropriate 
time?" (2) "When you feel bad, have you ever discontinued taking 
your medication?" (3) "Have you ever forgotten to take your med-
ication?" (4) "Have you ever forgotten to take your medications 
during the weekend?" (5) "In the last week, how many times did 
you fail to take your prescribed dose?" (6) "Since your last visit, 
how many whole days have gone by in that you did not take your </p>

<p>Article </p>

<p>medication?" (Theofilou, 2012). 
In order to modify the GR-SMAQ for patients undergoing HD, 
a group of experts (5 patients undergoing HD, 3 hemodialysis 
nurses and 3 nephrologists) was asked about the degree of under-
standing, appropriateness and relevance of the scale. The follow-
ing changes were made by the group: item 4 was amended as fol-
lows: "Have you ever forgotten to take your medications during 
the time interval between two dialysis sessions?" as patients under-
going HD may visit dialysis clinics on Saturday or on Sunday, also. 
Item 1 was removed as the right time of taking medication is likely 
to coincide with HD sessions. Finally, item 6 was, also, not includ-
ed because patients undergoing HD visit dialysis clinics day by 
day. Four additional items were introduced to achieve the modifi-
cation of the GR-SMAQ for patients undergoing HD. The above 
modifications were made with the consensus of Theofilou P. by 
whom the GR-SMAQ was translated into Greek language 
(Theofilou, 2012) for patients with lung cancer. Score range from 
0-8. Higher scores indicate greater adherence to HD regimen. It 
takes only 4 minutes to complete. The SMAQ was, firstly, con-
structed by Knobel et al. (2010) to measure adherence levels 
among HIV patients. It has, also, been used for evaluating adher-
ence to phosphate binders among patients undergoing HD (Arenas, 
et al., 2010a; 2010b) and patients with early breast cancer 
(Oberguggenberger et al., 2012) respectively. 
Finally, patients were given questionnaire related to demo-
graphic data (gender, age, educational level, job, marital status). </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>All 139 patients undergoing hemodialysis from three Dialysis 
Units of Athens and Peloponnese region, Greece, were asked to 
participate in this study. The inclusion criteria were: (a) age &gt; 18 
years, (b) diagnosis of chronic kidney disease undergoing 
hemodialysis for at least 6 months (c) ability to write and read flu-
ently the Greek language. The exclusion criteria were: history of 
mental illness and serious eye problems. Ultimately, a convenience 
sample of 107 patients met the mentioned criteria (response rate 
76.9%). The study was carried out during the period June 2016 -
November 2016. </p>

<p>Ethical considerations </p>

<p>The study was approved by the scientific councils of Dialysis 
Units (25/11/2015 and 24/10/13) and the Hellenic Data Protection 
Authority (Approval Number 1618, 11/02/2016). Patients, who 
met the criteria, after being informed about the aim of the study, 
gave their written consent and completed the above-mentioned 
questionnaires. Participants' anonymity was protected and safety 
of the material was maintained. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>Content Validity Index (CVI) was used to assess the relevance 
of each question using a 4-point scale: 4=highly relevant, 3=rele-
vant with minor adjustments, 2=minimally relevant and 1=not rel-
evant. For the construct validity of the questionnaire the technique 
of factor analysis with the rotation method of axes was applied 
(Equamax by normalizing by Kaiser). Repeatability was evaluated 
by the method McNemar-Bowker. Internal consistency of the 
questionnaire was calculated through Cronbach's a coefficient 
while the significance level was set up at 5%. Quantitative vari-
ables are described as mean (± Standard Deviation) and qualitative 
variables as absolute frequencies and relative frequencies. The sta-
tistical analysis was performed using IBM <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> Statistics <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version20</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2003</rs>, Chicago, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Participants' characteristics </p>

<p>In current study, 107 patients undergoing hemodialysis took 
part. Of these, 69% were males and 31% females. The mean age 
was 62 (±13) years old (Table 1). The frequency distribution of 
participants' responses to the GR-SMAQ-HD items is presented in 
Table 2. </p>

<p>Construct validity of the GR-SMAQ-HD </p>

<p>CVI was 0.40 for item 1 ("Do you always take your medication 
at the appropriate time?") and item 6 ("Since your last visit, how 
many whole days have gone by in that you did not take your med-
ication?"). Therefore, these items were removed. For the additional 
items (5-8) and the amended item (4) CVI was 0.90. Factor analysis 
of GR-SMAQ-HD items showed that all questions had a satisfactory 
correlation (r&gt;0.4) with at least one of the remaining questions. Also, 
all items were satisfactory sampling adequacy measures (&gt;0.6 -
Measures of Sampling Adequacy) and communalities (&gt;0.5). For the 
evaluation of partial correlation coefficient the value of the Kaiser-
Meyer-Olkin statistical criterion was 0.708 that is, also, considered 
satisfactory. Of the 8 questions, three factors emerged with eigenval-
ue greater than unity: "Medication adherence" (items 1, 2, 3, and 4), 
"Attendance at the HD session" (items 5 and 6) and "Diet/Fluid 
restrictions" (items 7 and 8). These three factors explain cumulative-
ly the 63% of the total dispersion (Table 3). </p>

<p>Reliability of GR-SMAQ-HD </p>

<p>Test-retest reliability </p>

<p>The test-retest method was implemented for the reliability of 
the questionnaire. From the total of 107 patients, 17 of them com-</p>

<p>[Health Psychology Research 2017; 5:6647] 
[page 3] </p>

<p>Article </p>

<p>Table 1. Participants' characteristics (N=107). </p>

<p>Characteristic 
N. (%) </p>

<p>Age (years), mean (±SD) 
62 (±13) 
Gender 
Males 
72 (69) 
Females 
33 (31) 
Marital status 
Unmarried 
24 (23) 
Married 
6 (6) 
Divorced 
74 (71) 
Widowed 
-
Number of children 
None 
27 (26) 
1 
34 (32) 
2 
15 (14) 
≥3 
30 (28) 
Educational level 
Primary school 
42 (40) 
Secondary school 
29 (27) 
High school 
18 (17) 
Undergraduate student 
3 (3) 
University 
14 (13) 
Job 
Unemployed 
17 (16) 
Employed 
29 (27) 
Retired 
60 (57) </p>

<p>SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>[page 4] </p>

<p>[Health Psychology Research 2017; 5:6647] </p>

<p>pleted the GR-SMAQ-HD two weeks after the first administration. 
The repeatability evaluation was performed by controlling the 
McNemar-Bowker. No statistically significant difference was 
shown between the responses of the first and second reference to 
any question (P≥0.005) (Table 4). </p>

<p>Internal consistency </p>

<p>Internal consistency was tested through Cronbach's alpha coef-
ficient. The factor "Attendance at HD session" seems to have the 
highest Cronbach's alpha (0.856) while the factor "Medication 
adherence" follows with Cronbach's alpha 0.750 and "Diet/fluid 
restrictions" with Cronbach's alpha 0.717. The internal consisten-
cy of the overall GR-SMAQ-HD scale consisting of 8 questions 
was: Cronbach's alpha = 0.742. The whole scale and the subscales 
had Cronbach's alpha up to 0.71 that means that GR-SMAQ-HD 
has satisfactory internal consistency. Furthermore, the analysis 
showed that no substantial increase in Cronbach's alpha yet hap-
pened even if an item is deleted from the subscales. In conclusion, 
we could argue that all items had significant internal consistency 
each other. 
The basic descriptive measures of location and dispersion and 
internal consistency of three factors (dimensions) of GR-SMAQ-
HD are presented in Table 5. The mean GR-SMAQ-HD score was 
6.29 (±1.82). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study was carried out in Athens and Peloponnese region 
and aimed to modify the GR-SMAQ scale for hemodialysis 
patients. The GR-SMAQ-HD is a modified form of GR-SMAQ 
and contains items to cover all aspects of adherence in hemodialy-
sis. The initial form of SMAQ shows sufficient internal consisten-
cy among Spanish patients undergoing HD (Cronbach's alpha 
0.70) (Arenas et al., 2010) and HIV patients (Cronbach's 
alpha=0.75) (Knobel et al., 2002). </p>

<p>Measures of patient adherence </p>

<p>Several measures have been constructed for the evaluation of 
patient adherence. Most of them focus on measure of medication 
and behavioral barriers to adherence (Lam &amp; Fresco, 2015). The 
Hill-Bone Compliance Scale has limited generalization as it aims 
only to patients taking antihypertensive agents (Kim et al., 2010). 
The Brief Medication Questionnaire can detect different types of 
non-adherence to the treatment (recurring or sporadic) (Svarstad, 
Chewning, Sleath, &amp; Claesson, 1999). The Medication Adherence 
Questionnaire is, also, known as the 4-Morisky Medication 
Adherence Scale (MMAS) and Morisky Scale is the most widely 
used scale. It has been used in a wide range of diseases and patients 
with low educational level (Culig &amp; Leppee, 2014). The 
Medication Adherence Report Scale (MARS) focuses on beliefs of 
adherence (Thompson, Kulkarni, &amp; Sergejew, 2000). 
Regarding the questionnaires related to adherence among 
hemodialysis patients, the literature research refers to reliable 
scales: i) the Dialysis Diet and Fluid Non-Adherence 
Questionnaire (DDFQ) (Vlaminck et al., 2001) assess the frequen-
cy and degree of adherence to fluid and dietary restriction ii) the 
Renal Adherence Attitudes Questionnaire (RAAQ) measuring atti-
tudes toward adherence and iii) the Renal Adherence Behavior 
Questionnaire (RABQ) measuring self-reported dietary (diet and 
fluid) adherence (Rushe &amp; McGee, 1998) and, finally, the End 
Stage Renal Disease Adherence Questionnaire (ESRD-AQ) (46 </p>

<p>items) that explores all the aspects of adherence on HD, patients </p>

<p>Article </p>

<p>Table 2. The GR-SMAQ-HD scale (N=107). </p>

<p>GR-SMAQ-HD Items 
N. (%) </p>

<p>If you feel worse, do you stop taking yours medicines? 
Yes 
29 (27) 
No 
78 (73) 
Do you ever forget to take you medicines? 
Yes 
46 (43) 
No 
61 (57) 
Have you ever forgotten to take your medications during the time interval 
between two dialysis sessions? 
Yes 
24 (22) 
No 
83 (78) 
How often did you not take your medicine over the last week? 
6-10 times 
2 (2) 
3-5 times 
2 (2) 
1-2 times 
28 (26) 
Never 
75 (70) 
Last month, how often did you shorten the session on your own initiative? 
4-5 times 
1 (1) 
3 times 
2 (2) 
2 times 
7 (6) 
1 time 
18 (17) 
I did not shorten the session 
79 (74) 
Last month, on average how many minutes did you shorten the session with 
your own initiative? 
&gt;30 
1 (1) 
21-30 
8 (7.5) 
11-20 
7 (6.5) 
≤10 
13 (12) 
I did not shorten the session 
78 (73) 
During the last week, how often did you follow the instructions on fluid 
restrictions? 
Never 
2 (2) 
Rarely 
12 (11) 
Half of the time 
15 (14) 
Most of the time 
38 (36) 
Every time 
40 (37) 
During the last week, how often did you follow the instructions on diet? 
Never 
4 (4) 
Rarely 
7 (6) 
Half of the time 
14 (13) 
Most of the time 
45 (42) 
Every time 
37 (35) </p>

<p>Table 3. Loadings of the variables on the Factor Analysis of GR-
SMAQ-HD scale. </p>

<p>Factors 
Medication 
Attendance at 
Diet/Fluid 
HD session 
restrictions </p>

<p>Item 1 
0.621 
-0.203 
0.398 
Item 2 
0.775 
0.285 
0.022 
Item 3 
0.860 
-0.092 
0.131 
Item 4 
0.692 
0.348 
0.167 
Item 5 
0.057 
0.901 
0.178 
Item 6 
0.078 
0.912 
0.113 
Item 7 
0.157 
0.107 
0.871 
Item 8 
0.085 
0.213 
0.821 </p>

<p>Method of extracting factors: Method of Principal Component; Rotation method of axes: Equamax by 
Kaiser normalization. </p>

<p>beliefs and factors of non-adherence (Kim et al., 2010). None of 
these scales was designed exclusively for the study of adherence 
behavior in hemodialysis. On the contrary, the above scales focus 
more on identifying other aspects of adherence such as patients' 
attitudes, factors of nona-dherence or knowledge on hemodialysis 
regimen, (Kim et al., 2010; Rushe &amp; McGee, 1998). 
In conclusion, several scales have been designed to assess 
adherence and, especially, its factors. However, we cannot support 
that there is an easy and short tool for measuring all views of 
adherence among patients undergoing HD (Smyth, Hartig, Hayes, 
&amp; Manickam, 2015). 
In our study, we conducted factor analysis to identify possible 
items correlations. The factor analysis revealed three subgroups in 
the GR-SMAQ-HD. The first subgroup consisted of four items 
(items 1, 2, 3 and 4) that measure medication adherence and, 
already, exist in the first form of GR-SMAQ. The two items of the 
second group cover the aspect of attendance at HD session (items 
5 and 6) while the last two items of the third group focus on 
Fluid/Diet restrictions (items 7 and 8). The three factors 
(Attendance to HD session, Diet/Fluid restrictions) revealed from 
this study are similar to those of the study of Kim and Evangelista 
(2013) using the Spanish version (End Stage Renal Disease 
Adherence Questionnaire, ESRD-AQ) and Portuguese (PESRD-
AQ) version of the End Stage Renal Disease Adherence 
Questionnaire (Poveda et al., 2016) while one factor (Diet/Fluid 
restrictions) is similar to the studies of Vlaminck et al. (2001) and 
Albayrak Cosar &amp; Cinar Pakyuz (2016). 
The removal of items 1 and 6 of the initial GR-SMAQ allowed 
the factorial structure become simpler and more powerful. In par-
ticular, a group of experts (10 patients undergoing HD, 5 
hemodialysis nurses and 3 nephrologists) suggested that item 1 
("Do you always take your medication at the appropriate time?") 
should be removed because the words "at the appropriate time" 
confuse patients because the correct hour of taking medication 
may coincides in time with the HD session. As far as item 6 is con-
cerned ("Since your last visit, how many whole days have gone by 
in that you did not take your medication?"), the group of experts 
referred that it is not relevant to the specific group of dialysis 
patients. These changes reduced the obstacles for patients undergo-
ing HD to complete the questionnaire and made it easier to inter-
pret because all items can be considered reliable and study adher-
ence. 
Factor analysis confirms that the GR-SMAQ-HD fits the data 
well and explains 63% of the variance in all dimensions of adher-
ence to HD regimen that is good for a brief, self-administered 
questionnaire. 
The test-retest method was performed in order to check the 
repeatability. According to the literature (Streiner, Norman, &amp; 
Cairney, 2003), two to fourteen days are required between the first 
and second time of administration. Patients found the question-
naire easy to complete, understandable and none required any 
explanation of questions. </p>

<p>Implication for practice </p>

<p>The main benefit of using GR-SMAQ-HD is to identify the 
levels of adherence in order to target for intervention. Moreover, a 
clinician could identify especially the dimension in that a patient 
on hemodialysis is not adherent. The need for early identification 
and assessment of non-adherence is vital for patients undergoing 
hemodialysis (Ghimire, Castelino, Lioufas, Peterson, &amp; Zaidi, 
2016; Karamanidou et al., 2008). However, given the complexity 
of adherence's pathogenesis and the lack of multidimensional 
tools, the effective intervention by HD nurses is difficult. </p>

<p>Therefore, nurses and health care professionals of hemodialysis 
units and renal clinics should be suspicious in the detection of non-
adherence in order to improve the health care plan and help 
patients to develop coping strategies (Davison &amp; Cooke, 2015). 
Due to their contact with patients undergoing HD, hemodialysis 
nurses could improve adherence levels building a trusting relation-
ship with patients through patient-center approach. It is well 
known that interventions should focus on patient education and 
counseling and that the higher the knowledge level the highest the 
adherence and quality of life levels (Barnes, Hancock, &amp; Dainton, 
2013; Cowperthwaite, Schutt-Aine, Herranen, &amp; Sorribes, 2012; 
Sandlin, Bennett, Ockerby, &amp; Corradini, 2013).The GR-SMAQ-
HD can be used in future research as a short, multidimensional 
adherence scale to successfully recognize the most useful areas for 
intervention aiming at improving patient outcomes. In addition, it 
could be beneficial if GR-SMAQ-HD compared with other more 
objective measures in order to investigate sensitivity and specifici-
ty more. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations </p>

<p>GR-SMAQ-HD is a short tool that can be completed within 
minutes, while it is easily assessed, thus allowing health profes-
sionals to measure and evaluate adherence easily. Also, it is the 
first scale for Greek patients undergoing HD measuring adherence 
levels. As already mentioned, the study was conducted in Dialysis 
Units of Athens and Peloponnese region. Therefore, results cannot 
be generalized for patient undergoing HD. Moreover, the question-
naires were administered during HD session so the presence of 
physicians, nurses and others may have influenced the responses of 
participants. </p>

<p>[Health Psychology Research 2017; 5:6647] 
[page 5] </p>

<p>Article </p>

<p>Table 4. Test-retest reliability of GR-SMAQ-HD (two week peri-
od between test-retest, n=17). </p>

<p>GR-SMAQ-HD 
Test (A), 
Re-test (Β), 
P-value 
Items 
mean (±SD) 
mean (±SD) </p>

<p>Item 1 
0.88 (±0.5) 
0.89 (±0.41) 
1.000 
Item 2 
0.87 (±0.3) 
0.87 (±0.33 
1.000 
Item 3 
0.85 (±0.24) 
0.88 (± 0.22) 
1.000 
Item 4 
0.90 (±0.21) 
0.89 (±0.19) 
1.000 
Item 5 
0.98 (±0.10) 
0.97 (±0.11) 
1.000 
Item 6 
0.97 (± 0.11) 
0.97 (± 0.10) 
1.000 
Item 7 
0.89 (±0.12) 
0.88(±0.13) 
0.368 
Item 8 
0.88 (±0.11) 
0.87 (±0.10) 
0.317 </p>

<p>Table 5. Descriptive characteristics and internal consistency of 
the GR-SMAQ-HD (N=107). </p>

<p>Min. Max. Mean SD Cronbach's a </p>

<p>Total score 
1 
8 
6.29 1.82 
0.742 
Medication 
0 
4 
3.04 1.15 
0.750 
Attendance at HD session 
0 
2 
1.76 0.58 
0.856 
Diet/Fluid restriction 
0 
2 
1.50 0.74 
0.717 </p>

<p>SD, Standard Deviation. </p>

<p>[page 6] </p>

<p>[Health Psychology Research 2017; 5:6647] </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Through the study of the psychometric properties of the GR-
SMAQ-HD, its validity was found to be highly satisfactory. This 
questionnaire seems to be an easy and appropriate tool to conduct 
studies exploring adherence to HD regimen. Therefore, it would be 
useful for widespread use in future studies to validate this ques-
tionnaire with a larger sample of patients undergoing HD. </p>



<p>Article </p>



<p>Article </p>

</text></tei>