<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5360361" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Oxidative stress-induced cell injury has been 
linked to the pathogenesis of neurodegenerative disorders 
such as spinal cord injury, Parkinson's disease, and multiple 
sclerosis. Morroniside is an antioxidant derived from the 
Chinese herb Shan-Zhu-Yu. The present study investigated 
the neuroprotective effect of morroniside against hydrogen 
peroxide (H 2 O 2 )-induced cell death in SK-N-SH human neuro-
blastoma cells. H 2 O 2 increased cell apoptosis, as determined 
by flow cytometry and Hoechst 33342 staining. This effect was 
reversed by pretreatment with morroniside at concentrations 
of 1-100 µM. The increase in intracellular reactive oxygen 
species (ROS) generation and lipid peroxidation induced by 
H 2 O 2 was also abrogated by morroniside. H 2 O 2 induced a 
reduction in mitochondrial membrane potential, increased 
caspase-3 activity, and caused downregulation of B cell 
lymphoma-2 (Bcl-2) and upregulation of Bcl-2-associated 
X protein (Bax) expression. These effects were blocked by 
morroniside pretreatment. Thus, morroniside protects human 
neuroblastoma cells against oxidative damage by inhibiting 
ROS production while suppressing Bax and stimulating Bcl-2 
expression, thereby blocking mitochondrial-mediated apop-
tosis. These results indicate that morroniside has therapeutic 
potential for the prevention and treatment of neurodegenera-
tive diseases. </p>

<p>Neurodegenerative disorders are characterized by loss or 
dysfunction of neurons in the central nervous system (1,2). 
Oxidative stress and consequent mitochondrial dysfunc-</p>

<p>tion contribute to the pathology of spinal cord injury (3,4), 
stroke (5,6), Parkinson's disease (7), and Alzheimer's 
disease (8) via production of reactive oxygen species (ROS), 
which include hydrogen peroxide (H 2 O 2 ), superoxide, singlet 
oxygen, and the hydroxyl radical (9). 
ROS play an important role in intracellular signal trans-
duction and gene expression in cell survival and organism 
development (10). However, excess accumulation of ROS can 
damage proteins, DNA and cell membranes (11). ROS induce 
cell death via the mitochondrial apoptosis pathway (12). Neurons 
are thought to be more susceptible to ROS owing to increased 
oxidative metabolism and fewer antioxidative enzymes (13,14). 
Suppression of ROS generation and inhibition of apoptosis can 
therefore potentially prevent neurodegeneration. 
Cornus officinalis is among the most commonly used 
Chinese medical herbs and has been used to treat kidney-and 
brain-related diseases (15). Its biological activities include 
antioxidant (16,17), anti-inflammatory (18) and antimicro-
bial (19) effects. Morroniside is the major active ingredient 
of C. officinalis extract (20) (Fig. 1) and has been shown to 
reduce blood glucose, mitigate cerebral ischemia-reperfusion 
injury, and modulate the immune response (21). However, little 
is known concerning the effects of morroniside on oxidative 
stress-induced cell damage. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Cell culture and treatment. SK-N-SH human neuroblastoma 
cells (Type Culture Collection of the Chinese Academy of 
Sciences, Shanghai, China) were cultured in Dulbecco's modi-
fied Eagle's medium (DMEM) supplemented with 10% (v/v) 
fetal bovine serum, 100 U/ml penicillin/streptomycin (all 
from Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) in plastic 25-cm 
2 flasks 
at 37˚C and under 5% CO 2 , 95% air. Culture medium was 
changed every other day and the cells were subcultured once 
attaining 70-80% confluency. Morroniside (Phytomarker Ltd., 
Tianjin, China) was dissolved in D-PBS (Invitrogen) and H 2 O 2 
(Sinopharm Chemical Reagent Co. Ltd., Shanghai, China) 
was dissolved in sterile distilled water. SK-N-SH cells were 
pretreated with different concentrations of morroniside for 
24 h, followed by incubation with H 2 O 2 (200-400 µM) for 24 h 
to induce injury. </p>

<p>Morroniside protects SK-N-SH human neuroblastoma 
cells against H 2 O 2 -induced damage </p>

<p>JING-XING ZHANG 
1,2 , RUI WANG 
2 , JIN XI 
2 , LIN SHEN </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, AN-YOU ZHU 
1 , QI QI 
2 , QI-YI WANG 
2 , </p>

<p>LUN-JUN ZHANG 
1 , FENG-CHAO WANG 
1 , HE-ZUO LÜ 
1,2 and JIAN-GUO HU </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Clinical Laboratory, The First Affiliated Hospital of Bengbu Medical College; 
2 Anhui Key Laboratory of Tissue Transplantation, Bengbu Medical College, Bengbu, Anhui 233004, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received September 22, 2016; Accepted January 31, 2017 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/ijmm.2017.2882 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Professor Jian-Guo Hu or Professor He-Zuo </p>

<p>Lü, Department of Clinical Laboratory, The First Affiliated Hospital 
of Bengbu Medical College, 287 Chang Huai Road, Bengbu, 
Anhui 233004, P.R. China 
E-mail: jghu9200@163.com 
E-mail: lhz233003@163.com </p>

<p>Key words: morroniside, SK-N-SH cells, reactive oxygen species, </p>

<p>apoptosis, neuroprotection </p>

<p>ZHANG et al: MORRONISIDE PROTECTS SK-N-SH CELLS AGAINST H 2 O 2 -INDUCED DAMAGE </p>



<p>Cell viability assay. The viability of the cells was assessed by 
3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide 
(MTT) assay. Briefly, SK-N-SH cells were plated into 96-well 
plates at the density of 5x10 
3 cells/well. Cells were preincubated 
with morroniside (1, 10 and 100 µM) for 24 h before 200 µM 
H 2 O 2 was administered. After a 24-h incubation, 20 µl of a 
5 mg/ml stock solution of MTT (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) 
was added to the culture medium and incubated in the dark 
for 4 h at 37˚C to allow for formazan formation. Then MTT 
formazan crystals were dissolved in 100 µl dimethyl sulfoxide 
(DMSO; Sigma) and spectrophotometrically determined at an 
absorbance of 570 nm. The percentage of cell viability was 
measured by normalization of all values to the control group 
(=100%). </p>

<p>Morphological observation. SK-N-SH cells were seeded into 
6-well plates at the density of 2x10 
5 cells/well. When cell 
confluency achieved 70-80%, the cells were pre-incubated 
with morroniside for 24 h before H 2 O 2 (200 µM) was added to 
induce cell damage for another 24 h. The growth and morpho-
logical changes in each group were observed under an inverted 
phase contrast microscope. </p>

<p>Cytotoxicity assay. Lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) assay was 
used to assay H 2 O 2 -induced cytotoxicity. SK-N-SH cells were 
seed into 96-well plates at a density of 5x10 
3 cells/well. After 
cells were exposed to H 2 O 2 (200 µM) for 24 h, a total of 120 µl 
of cell medium was collected for LDH analysis according 
to the manufacturer's protocol included in the cytotoxicity 
assay kit (Beyotime Biotechnology, Nantong, China). The 
absorbance of each group was read at 490 nm. Each group 
had five duplicate wells and the experiments were repeated at 
least three times. Data are expressed as the percentage of LDH 
release of the injury group (H 2 O 2 -induced group). </p>

<p>Apoptosis analysis. In order to determine whether morroni-
side protects against H 2 O 2 -induced apoptosis, Hoechst 33342 
(Sigma), a fluorescent nuclear dye, was used to detect cell 
apoptosis by observing the cell morphology. Briefly, SK-N-SH 
cells were treated as described above and then washed 
with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and incubated with 
Hoechst 33342 (10 µg/ml in PBS; Sigma) for 15 min at 37˚C 
in the dark. The cells were washed with PBS, fixed with cold 
4% paraformaldehyde for another 15 min in room temperature, 
washed with PBS again, and then examined by fluroescence 
microscopy. The percentage of apoptotic cells was calculated 
as the ratio of apoptotic cells to the total cells counted. At least 
500 cells were counted from more than 3 random microscopic 
fields. 
Moreover, in order to confirm the anti-apoptotic effect of 
morroniside, flow cytometry with Annexin V-FITC and prop-
idium iodide (PI) double staining (Beyotime Biotechnology) 
was performed. After SK-N-SH cells were treated with 
H 2 O 2 (200 µM), 5x10 
5 cells were collected and counted for 
Annexin V-FITC and PI double staining. Briefly, cells in 
different groups were washed three times with cold PBS and 
stained with Annexin V-FITC for 15 min in the dark. After 
cells were washed another three times, PI was added and the 
fluorescence of each group was immediately analyzed by flow 
cytometry. </p>

<p>Assessment of intracellular ROS production. For visualiza-
tion and analysis of intracellular ROS, the oxidation sensitive 
probe DCFH-DA (Beyotime Biotechnology) was used. After 
the treatment of H 2 O 2 , SK-N-SH cells were exposed to 10 µM 
DCFH-DA for 20 min at 37˚C in the dark. The cells were 
washed with PBS for 3 times, and then DCF fluorescence was 
observed using fluorescence microscopy and quantified by 
fluorescence multi-well plate reader (BioTek, Highland Park, 
VT, USA) with an excitation wavelength of 488 nm and emis-
sion wavelength of 525 nm. </p>

<p>Measurement of intracellular superoxide anion production. 
Superoxide anion was detected with dihydroethidium probes. 
Cells were treated with 2 µM dihydroethidium (Beyotime 
Biotechnology) for 30 min at 37˚C in dim light after incuba-
tion with H 2 O 2 . Each well was washed with cold PBS and 
then DMEM to remove the remaining probes. Then cells were 
observed using fluorescence microscopy and the fluorescence 
intensity was quantified by a fluorescence multi-well plate 
reader. </p>

<p>Lipid peroxidation assay. Lipid peroxidation was monitored by 
measuring malondiadehyde (MDA; Beyotime Biotechnology), 
a stable end product of lipid peroxidation cascades using an 
MDA assay kit. SK-N-SH cells were washed with ice-cold 
PBS and then harvested with RIPA lysis buffer (Beyotime 
Biotechnology) after the treatment of H 2 O 2 . Cell homogenates 
were centrifuged at 16,000 x g at 4˚C for 10 min. The superna-
tant was used for MDA assay and protein determination. The 
total protein concentrations were measured using BCA Protein 
assay kit (Beyotime Biotechnology). For MDA measurement, 
100 µl samples were added into a 15-ml tube followed by 
addition of 200 µl MDA working solution. The mixture was 
heated at 100˚C for 15 min, chilled to room temperature, and 
centrifuged at 1,000 x g for 10 min. Supernatants of 200 µl 
were transferred to 96-well plates, and the absorbance of each 
group was read at 532 nm. </p>

<p>Determination of activity of superoxide dismutase (SOD). 
Cellular SOD levels were determined using a Superoxide 
Dismutase assay kit (Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, 
Nanjing, China). SK-N-SH cells were pretreated with different 
concentrations of morroniside for 24 h prior to exposure to </p>

<p>Figure 1. Chemical structure of morroniside. </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 39: 603-612, 2017 </p>



<p>H 2 O 2 (200 µM) for another 24 h. Cells were washed twice with 
ice-cold PBS and harvested in RIPA lysis buffer, and then total 
protein contents were determined with the BCA protein assay 
kit (Beyotime Biotechnology). Samples were collected and 
analyzed according to the manufacturer's instructions. SOD 
levels were normalized to the protein concentrations. </p>

<p>Monitoring mitochondrial membrane potential (MMP). 
SK-N-SH cells were treated with various dose of morroniside 
in a 12-well plate for 24 h before H 2 O 2 (200 µM) for 24 h. A 
fluorescent dye JC-1 (Beyotime Biotechnology) was added to 
achieve final concentration of 10 µg/ml. Then cells were incu-
bated for 30 min at 37˚C in dim light. Cells were washed with 
PBS to remove the excess dye, and then images were captured 
using fluorescence microscopy within 30 min. For the JC-1 
monomer, excitation wavelength was 514 nm and maximum 
emission wavelength was 529 nm. For the JC-1 polymer, the 
maximum excitation and emission wavelength were 585 and 
590 nm, respectively. </p>

<p>Measurement of caspase-3 activity. Activity of caspase-3 
was measured with a commercial caspase-3 activity assay 
kit (Beyotime Biotechnology), using Ac-DEVD-pNA as 
the specific substrate. The cell pellets were lysed on ice in 
lysis buffer for 15 min, and then the lysate was centrifuged 
at 20,000 x g for 10 min at 4˚C. Supernatant of 10 µl was 
collected and incubated with 10 µl Ac-DEVD-pNA (2 mM) 
at 37˚C for another 1-2 h in the dark. The absorbance values 
were measured with a spectrofluorometer at 405 nm and were 
corrected as protein content in the lysate. Protein concentra-
tion was determined by Bradford protein assay kit (Beyotime 
Biotechnology) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>Reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR). 
The mRNA expression levels of B cell lymphoma-2 (Bcl-2) 
and Bcl-2-associated X protein (Bax) were determined by 
RT-PCR. Briefly, SK-N-SH cells were treated as mentioned 
above, and the total RNA of each group was extracted using 
TRIzol agent (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. Two micrograms of total RNA was first reverse 
transcribed into cDNA, and then routine PCR was performed 
as previously described (22). Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate 
dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was used as an internal control and 
products were analyzed on 1% agarose gel. <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageJ</rs> software </p>

<p>(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">NIH</rs>, Bethesda, MD, USA) was used to quantify the optical 
density value of each band. The sequences of specific primers 
(Sangon Biotech Inc., Shanghai, China) used for RT-PCR are 
listed in Table I. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis. Cells were collected at 24 h after expo-
sure to H 2 O 2 . In order to detect the expression of Bcl-2 and 
Bax, SK-N-SH cells were washed with PBS and lysed using 
a lysis buffer for 30 min on ice. Lysates were centrifuged at 
16,000 x g for 10 min at 4˚C, and the supernatant was saved 
for the total protein determination. Protein concentrations 
were determined using a commercially available BCA protein 
assay kit (Beyotime Biotechnology). For western blot analysis, 
equivalent amounts of protein of each sample (20 µg) were 
electrophoresed using sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide 
gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE), and transferred to polyvinyl-
idene difluoride membranes (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA). 
After the membranes were blocked with 5% non-fat dry milk 
in Tris-buffered saline (TBS) for 1 h at room temperature, 
primary antibodies (in TBST-5% BSA) against Bcl-2 (1:2,000; 
12789-1-AP) and Bax (1:5,000; 60267-1-Ig) (both from 
ProteinTech Group Inc, Chicago, IL, USA) were added and 
incubated overnight at 4˚C for determining signal transduction 
events. The membranes were rinsed three times with TBST 
and incubated with an appropriate HRP-conjugated secondary 
antibody (1:2,000; #04-15-06 and #04-18-06) (both from 
KPL, Gaithersburg, MD, USA) for 1 h at 37˚C. An ECL kit 
(Millipore) was used to visualize membrane immunoreactivity. 
Quantification was performed using a computerized imaging 
program <rs id="software-1" type="software">Quantity One</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Bio-Rad</rs>, Hercules, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. All data are presented as mean ± stan-
dard deviation of the mean (SD). Statistical analyses were 
performed by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with 
post hoc Tukey's t-test to determine statistical significance. 
A value of P&lt;0.05 was considered to indicated statistically 
significant differences. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Morroniside attenuates H 2 O 2 -induced cell death. 
H 2 O 2 -induced cell injury was evaluated using the MTT assay. 
H 2 O 2 reduced cell viability in a dose-and time-dependent 
manner, with a survival rate of 50% after 24 h in the presence </p>

<p>Table I. Sequences of the primers and PCR product sizes used in RT-PCR. </p>

<p>Gene 
Primer 
Sequence 
Size (bp) </p>

<p>GAPDH 
Sense 
5'-AGAAGGCTGGGGCTCATTTG-3' 
258 
Antisense 
5'-AGGGGCCATCCACAGTCTTC-3' </p>

<p>Bax 
Sense 
5'-CCAAGGTGCCGGAACTGA-3' 
57 
Antisense 
5'-CCCGGAGGAAGTCCAATGT-3' </p>

<p>Bcl-2 
Sense 
5'-CATGTGTGTGGAGAGCGTCAAC-3' 
187 
Antisense 
5'-CTTCAGAGACAGCCAGGAGAAATC-3' </p>

<p>GAPDH, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase; Bax, Bcl-2-associated X protein; Bcl-2, B cell lymphoma-2. </p>

<p>ZHANG et al: MORRONISIDE PROTECTS SK-N-SH CELLS AGAINST H 2 O 2 -INDUCED DAMAGE </p>



<p>of 200 µM H 2 O 2 relative to the untreated controls (Fig. 2A). 
Cells were treated with various concentrations of morroniside 
for 24 h to determine whether the H 2 O 2 -induced decrease 
in viability would be mitigated. Morroniside had no effect 
on the survival of SK-N-SH cells that were not treated with 
H 2 O 2 (Fig. 2B). However, pretreatment with morroniside 
attenuated the H 2 O 2 -induced decrease in cell survival in a 
dose-dependent manner, with the greatest effect observed at 
10 µM (Fig. 2C). </p>

<p>Morroniside reverses H 2 O 2 -induced morphological changes. 
SK-N-SH cells treated for 24 h with 200 µM H 2 O 2 showed 
morphological changes including loss of cell projections; </p>

<p>a round, swollen, or shrunken cell body; and aggregation. 
These changes were blocked by pretreatment with morroni-
side (Fig. 2D). </p>

<p>Morroniside inhibits H 2 O 2 -induced LDH release. The LDH 
release assay showed that H 2 O 2 increased LDH activity in the 
supernatant of the SK-N-SH cell cultures relative to the control 
group. This effect was suppressed upon treatment with 1, 10 
and 100 µM morroniside (P&lt;0.05) (Fig. 2E). </p>

<p>Morroniside protects SK-N-SH cells from H 2 O 2 -induced apop-
tosis. We investigated whether the H 2 O 2 -induced decrease in 
SK-N-SH cell survival was due to apoptosis by Hoechst 33342 </p>

<p>Figure 2. (A) Effects of H 2 O 2 on SK-N-SH cell viability. Cell viability was reduced in a dose-and time-dependent manner by treatment with H 2 O 2 (200 µM for 
24). (B) Effects of morroniside on SK-N-SH cell viability. Morroniside treatment did not affect cell viability at concentrations of 1, 10 and 100 µM. (C) Effects 
of morroniside on H 2 O 2 -induced SK-N-SH cell death. Pretreatment with morroniside (1-100 µM) for 24 h restored viability in cells exposed to H 2 O 2 (200 µM) 
in a dose-dependent manner. (D) Morroniside inhibits morphological changes resulting from H 2 O 2 treatment. Scale bar, 20 µM. (E) Morroniside suppresses 
H 2 O 2 -induced lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) release in SK-N-SH cells. Cells were pretreated with indicated concentrations of morroniside (1-100 µM) for 24 h 
following treatment with 200 µM H 2 O 2 or no treatment for 24 h. LDH activity in the medium was measured. Data represent mean ± SD (n=3). 
# P&lt;0.05, 
## P&lt;0.01 
and 
### P&lt;0.001 vs. control group; </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 and </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 vs. H 2 O 2 -treated group. </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 39: 603-612, 2017 </p>



<p>and Annexin V/PI staining. Control cells stained with 
Hoechst 33342 had large, oval-shaped nuclei (Fig. 3A). H 2 O 2 
(200 µM) treatment increased the fraction of cells with 
condensed or fragmented nuclei (18.60±1.67 vs. 2.00±1.00%; 
P&lt;0.01) (Fig. 3B and F). These defects were rescued 
by pretreatment with morroniside (1, 10 and 100 µM), 
which reduced the fraction of apoptotic cells (14.80±0.84, </p>

<p>10.40±1.14 and 13.20±1.48%, respectively vs. 18.60±1.67%; 
P&lt;0.01) (Fig. 3C-F). Consistent with these findings, there were 
few cells positive for Annexin V/PI staining detected in the 
control group (Fig. 3G). H 2 O 2 (200 µM) treatment increased the 
percentage of Annexin V 
+ /PI 
+ cells (34.58±4.59 vs. 4.96±2.44%; 
P&lt;0.001) (Fig. 3H and L), which was reduced by morroni-
side (1, 10 and 100 µM) treatment (26.86±4.05, 22.42±2.81 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Morroniside blocks H 2 O 2 -induced apoptosis of SK-N-SH cells. Apoptotic nuclei were visualized by Hoechst 33342 staining. (A) Untreated cells with 
normal nuclei. (B) Cells exposed to 200 µM H 2 O 2 with condensed nuclei. (C-E) Cells pretreated with morroniside at concentrations of (C) 1 µM, (D) 10 µM and 
(E) 100 µM for 24 h showed reduced sensitivity to the effects of H 2 O 2 , as evidenced by fewer cells with condensed nuclei. Scale bar, 20 µM. (G-K) Annexin V/ 
propidium iodide (PI) double-staining was used to confirm apoptosis in SK-N-SH cells. Few cells positive for Annexin V/PI staining were detected in the control 
group (G), while H 2 O 2 (200 µM) treatment increased the percentage of Annexin V </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>/PI 
+ cells (H). Preincubation with (I) 1 µM, (J) 10 µM and (K) 100 µM morroni-
side for 24 h inhibited H 2 O 2 -induced apoptosis. Quantitative analyses are shown in panels (F and L). Data represent mean ± SD of three independent experiments. 
### P&lt;0.001 vs. control group; </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01, </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 and </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 vs. injury group. </p>

<p>ZHANG et al: MORRONISIDE PROTECTS SK-N-SH CELLS AGAINST H 2 O 2 -INDUCED DAMAGE </p>



<p>and 22.62±2.48%, respectively vs. 34.58±4.59%; P&lt;0.05) 
(Fig. 3I-L). </p>

<p>Morroniside inhibits H 2 O 2 -induced elevation in intracel-
lular ROS level. Intracellular ROS levels were detected </p>

<p>with 2,7'-dichlorofluorescein (DCF) diacetate. SK-N-SH 
cells exposed to 200 and 400 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h showed 
dose-dependent increases in intracellular DCF fluorescence 
(P&lt;0.01) (Fig. 4A-C and G), indicating that ROS levels were 
elevated. However, 10 µM morroniside pretreatment abro-
gated these increases in fluorescence intensity compared to 
the H 2 O 2 -treated groups (P&lt;0.01) (Fig. 4E-G), suggesting a 
protective effect against H 2 O 2 -induced free radical formation. 
Superoxide anion is a type of ROS that is associated 
with oxidative stress. To determine whether it is involved 
in H 2 O 2 -induced cytotoxicity, we measured intracel-
lular superoxide anion levels with the dihydroethidium 
probe (Fig. 4H-M). The fluorescence intensity of SK-N-SH 
cells increased markedly after incubation for 24 h with H 2 O 2 
(P&lt;0.001) (Fig. 4I and M). However, pretreatment with 1, 10 
and 100 µM morroniside significantly reduced intracellular 
superoxide anion levels. </p>

<p>Morroniside suppresses H 2 O 2 -induced lipid peroxidation. 
Lipid peroxidation levels were monitored by detecting the </p>

<p>Figure 4. Morroniside attenuates H 2 O 2 -induced accumulation of intracel-
lular reactive oxygen species (ROS) in SK-N-SH cells. Cells were pretreated 
with (D-F) 10 µM morroniside for 24 h followed by (B and E) 200 µM 
or (C and F) 400 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h. Untreated control cells are shown 
in (A). ROS levels were increased in a dose-dependent manner by treatment 
with (B) 200 µM and (C) 400 µM H 2 O 2 . The increase was abolished by 
pretreatment with 10 µM morroniside (E and F). Intracellular superoxide 
anion levels were measured by dihydroethidium staining. Compared to the 
control (H), H 2 O 2 (200 µM) increased superoxide anion production (I), 
an effect that was reversed by pretreatment with (J) 1 µM, (K) 10 µM and 
(L) 100 µM morroniside. Quantitative analyses are shown (G and M). 
Data represent mean ± SD of three independent experiments. 
## P&lt;0.01 and 
### P&lt;0.001 vs. control group; 
* P&lt;0.01, 
** P&lt;0.01 and 
*** P&lt;0.001 vs. injury 
group. Scale bars: (F) 50 µM and (L) 20 µM. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Effect of morroniside on H 2 O 2 -induced lipid oxidation. Cells were 
pretreated with indicated concentrations of morroniside for 24 h followed by 
200 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h. Data represent mean ± SD of three independent experi-
ments. 
### P&lt;0.001 vs. control group; </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 and </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 vs. injury group. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Morroniside blocks the H 2 O 2 -induced decrease in superoxide dis-
mutase (SOD) level in SK-N-SH cells. Cells were pre-incubated with 1, 10 
or 100 µM morroniside for 24 h followed by H 2 O 2 for 24 h. Data represent 
mean ± SD of three independent experiments. 
### P&lt;0.001 vs. control group; </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 and </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 vs. injury group. </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 39: 603-612, 2017 </p>



<p>stable end products of lipid peroxidation using an MDA 
assay kit. Under normal conditions, cellular MDA content 
was ~119.47±14.14 nmol/g protein (Fig. 5). In cells treated 
with 200 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h, the level was increased to 
296.28±24.25 nmol/g protein (P&lt;0.001). However, pretreat-
ment with 1, 10 and 100 µM morroniside reduced MDA 
levels to 256.26±6.70, 223.63±12.47 and 224.35±10.18 nmol/g 
protein, respectively (P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Morroniside inhibits H 2 O 2 -induced SOD depletion. To inves-
tigate the antioxidant properties of morroniside, we measured 
intracellular levels of SOD. Treatment with 200 µM H 2 O 2 
for 24 h reduced intracellular SOD levels from 6.77±0.45 to 
3.74±0.41 U/mg (P&lt;0.001). This was reversed by morroniside 
pretreatment at concentrations ranging from 1 to 100 µM; for </p>

<p>example, a concentration of 10 µM enhanced SOD level by 
over 45% relative to the H 2 O 2 -treated group (Fig. 6). </p>

<p>Morroniside suppresses H 2 O 2 -induced decreases in MMP. 
We investigated whether morroniside could suppress the 
H 2 O 2 -induced decrease in MMP using JC-1 dye. SK-N-SH 
cells treated with 200 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h showed an obvious 
decrease in MMP, as evidenced by a decrease in the ratio of 
red to green fluorescence (Fig. 7). This effect was mitigated 
by treatment with morroniside, most obviously at a concentra-
tion of 10 µM. </p>

<p>Morroniside inhibits H 2 O 2 -induced caspase-3 level. 
Caspase-3 is a key protein in the regulation of apoptosis. 
SK-N-SH cells treated with 200 µM H 2 O 2 for 24 h showed 
a nearly 2-fold increase in the caspase-3 level relative to the 
control cells (P&lt;0.01) (Fig. 8). Pretreatment with morroniside 
(1, 10 and 100 µM) suppressed the H 2 O 2 -induced upregulation 
of caspase-3 (3.77±0.31, 3.05±0.16 and 3.31±0.12 µM pNA/g, 
respectively vs. 4.91±0.36 µM pNA/g; P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Morroniside modulates expression of apoptosis-related 
proteins. The expression levels of the apoptosis-related genes 
Bcl-2 and Bax were altered in the SK-N-SH cells by H 2 O 2 
administration; the Bcl-2 mRNA level was downregulated 
while that of Bax was upregulated (Fig. 9A-C). These changes 
were abolished by pretreatment with 1-100 µM morroniside. 
Similarly, western blot analysis revealed that H 2 O 2 (200 µM) 
decreased the Bcl-2 level (P&lt;0.001) and increased that of Bax 
(P&lt;0.01) after 24 h (Fig. 9D-F). However, pretreatment with 1, 
10 and 100 µM morroniside restored Bcl-2 and Bax expression 
levels compared to these levels in the H 2 O 2 -induced group. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Oxidative stress caused by ROS is implicated in the patho-
genesis of most chronic diseases (23,24). ROS accumulation </p>

<p>Figure 7. Inhibition of H 2 O 2 -induced reduction in mitochondrial membrane potential (MMP) by morroniside. (A and B) Cells were pretreated with the 
indicated concentrations of morroniside followed by 200 µM H 2 O 2 . The decrease in MMP was quantified with JC-1 staining and fluorescence microscopy. 
Scale bar, 20 µM. </p>

<p>Figure 8. Effect of morroniside on caspase-3 activity. Cells were pretreated 
with indicated concentrations of morroniside for 24 h followed by H 2 O 2 
for 24 h. Data represent mean ± SD of four independent experiments. 
## P&lt;0.01 vs. control group; </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 and </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 vs. injury group. </p>

<p>ZHANG et al: MORRONISIDE PROTECTS SK-N-SH CELLS AGAINST H 2 O 2 -INDUCED DAMAGE </p>



<p>results in cellular damage (5). Loss of neurons due to oxidative 
stress plays a key role in the development of cerebrovascular 
and/or neurodegenerative diseases (1,8,25). Neurons are 
thought to be more susceptible to oxidative damage than other 
cell types due to their high oxygen consumption and low anti-
oxidant capabilities (26). In the present study, we found that 
H 2 O 2 , a freely diffusible ROS, induced apoptosis in the human 
neuroblastoma SK-N-SH cells. 
Usually, antioxidants, especially those derived from 
natural sources, have many therapeutic applications (27,28). 
Morroniside is a constituent of C. officinalis, a traditional 
Chinese medicine (29), and has demonstrated protective effects 
against cerebral ischemic damage (15), indicating a potential 
role of morroniside on restoring injured neurons. However, 
little is known concerning the underlying mechanisms. In this 
study, we investigated the neuroprotective role of morroniside 
in SK-N-SH cells treated with H 2 O 2 . 
Exposure of cells to exogenous H 2 O 2 can induce ROS over-
production (30), leading to peroxidation of membrane lipids 
and disruption of cellular integrity (31). The present study 
showed that pretreatment with morroniside reversed H 2 O 2 -
induced apoptosis by blocking ROS production. 
SOD is a component of the antioxidant machinery in 
neurons (32). In most situations, ROS produced through </p>

<p>metabolic processes are quenched by intracellular defense 
systems, including SOD (33). Previous studies have shown 
that depletion of cellular glutathione leads to accumulation of 
ROS and mitochondrial dysfunction (34). We found here that 
morroniside treatment increased SOD activity in the SK-N-SH 
cells, which prevented ROS accumulation. Thus, we propose 
that the cytoprotective effects of morroniside are associated 
with its antioxidant capacity, for which, antioxidants such as 
glutathione or SOD are indispensable. 
Overproduction of ROS disrupts the intracellular redox 
equilibrium, resulting in apoptosis (35). ROS target mito-
chondrial membrane proteins, leading to activation of the 
mitochondrial permeability transition pore, which decreases 
the MMP (36) and releases cytochrome c into the cytosol, 
where it binds to apoptotic protease activating factor 1 
and forms the apoptosome, which activates pro-apoptotic 
caspases (37). Indeed, we observed that H 2 O 2 treatment 
reduced the MMP and activated the pro-apoptotic protein 
caspase-3. These effects were blocked by pretreatment with 
morroniside, suggesting that morroniside exerts protective 
effects by blocking the mitochondrial apoptotic pathway. 
H 2 O 2 has been reported to modulate the levels of Bcl-2 and 
Bax, two genes associated with mitochondrial apoptosis, in 
various cell types including cortical neurons (30), endothelial </p>

<p>Figure 9. Effect of morroniside on the expression of apoptosis-related proteins. Cells were pretreated with the indicated concentrations of morroniside for 
24 h followed by H 2 O 2 for 24 h. Bcl-2 and Bax expression was evaluated by (A-C) RT-PCR and (D-F) western blotting. Values represent mean ± SD of three 
independent experiments. 
## P&lt;0.01 and 
### P&lt;0.001 vs. the control group; </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01and </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 vs. the injury group. </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 39: 603-612, 2017 </p>



<p>cells (38), and HT22 cells (39), specifically by suppressing 
Bcl-2 and stimulating Bax expression (30). This was observed 
in our study at both the mRNA and protein levels following 
administration of H 2 O 2 for 24 h. Moreover, morroniside 
treatment reversed the changes in Bcl-2 and Bax expression 
induced by H 2 O 2 . The pro-apoptotic protein Bax is activated 
during apoptosis, and its relocation from the cytoplasm to the 
mitochondrial outer membrane leads to formation of the mito-
chondrial permeability transition pore and downstream events. 
Bax accumulated in the mitochondrial outer membrane binds 
to the anti-apoptotic protein Bcl-2 and maintains it in an inac-
tive state (37). Bcl-2 also acts as an antioxidant by suppressing 
ROS levels and the mitochondrial apoptosis pathway (40). 
Taken together, these findings suggest that morroniside blocks 
mitochondrial apoptosis via modulation of Bcl-2 and Bax 
expression. 
In conclusion, in the present study, morroniside was 
found to protect against H 2 O 2 -induced oxidative damage in 
SK-N-SH neuronal cells. This effect was mediated by inhibi-
tion of ROS-induced oxidative stress as well as suppressing 
and stimulating Bax and Bcl-2 expression, respectively, 
leading to inhibition of the mitochondrial apoptotic pathway. 
Thus, morroniside can potentially be used for the prevention 
and treatment of neurodegenerative diseases. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The present study was supported by the National Natural 
Science Foundation of China (no. 81471277) and the Program 
of Anhui Province for Academic and Technical Leader in 
University. </p>



<p>ZHANG et al: MORRONISIDE PROTECTS SK-N-SH CELLS AGAINST H 2 O 2 -INDUCED DAMAGE </p>





</text></tei>