<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5132146" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Stroke is a common cause of disability and death world-
wide. Ischemic stroke, a major cause of brain damage, </p>

<p>results from cerebral artery occlusion and induces a series 
of alterations in the penumbra with neurochemical events 
including release of glutamate, calcium channel dysfunc-
tion, membrane disruption, inflammatory changes and 
necrotic/apoptotic cell death triggering [1, 2]. 
Over the past few decades, several in vivo preclinical 
trials used various animal models of stroke. Rodent mod-
els of stroke mimic the ischemic conditions in humans in 
terms of cerebral vasculature and physiology, and have 
advantages of lower cost and moderate body size, which 
facilitates monitoring [3]. 
Middle cerebral occlusion (MCAO) surgery is widely 
used to induce ischemic stroke in animal models. How-
ever, permanent MCAO produces significant edema and 
hemorrhage within the forebrain cortex and the lesions 
are variable in size, which can result in unexpected 
behaviors [4]. In addition, differences among mouse </p>

<p>Research Article </p>

<p>Effect of human mesenchymal stem cell transplantation 
on cerebral ischemic volume-controlled photothrombotic 
mouse model </p>

<p>Yun-Kyong Choi, Enerelt Urnukhsaikhan, Hee-Hoon Yoon, Young-Kwon Seo and Jung-Keug Park </p>

<p>Department of Medical Biotechnology, Dongguk University, Gyeonggi-do, Republic of Korea </p>

<p>Various animal models of stroke have been developed to simulate the human stroke with the devel-
opment of the ischemic method facilitates preclinical stroke research. The photothrombotic 
ischemia model, based on the intravascular photochemical reaction, is widely used for in vivo stud-
ies. However, this study has limitations, which generated a relatively small-sized infarction model 
on superficial cortex compared to that of the MCAO stroke model. In this study, the photothorom-
bosis mouse model is adapted and the optimum conditions for generation of cell death and deficits 
with high reproducibility is determined. The extent of damage within the cortex was assessed by 
infarct volume and cellular/behavioral analyses. In this model, the neural cell death and inflamma-
tory responses is detected; moreover, the degree of behavioral impairment is correlated with the 
brain infarct volume. Further, to enhance the understanding of neural repair, the effect of neural 
differentiation by transplantation of human bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells 
(BM-MSCs) is analyzed. The authors demonstrated that transplantation of BM-MSCs promoted the 
neural differentiation and behavioral performance in their photothrombosis model. Therefore, this 
research was meaningful to provide a stable animal model of stroke with low variability. Moreover, 
this model will facilitate development of novel MSC-based therapeutics for stroke. </p>

<p>Keywords: Cerebral ischemic stroke · Human bonemarrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells (hBM-MSCs) · Infarct volume · 
Neural differentiation · Photothrombotic mouse model </p>

<p>See accompanying commentary by I-Ming Chu DOI 10.1002/biot.201600414 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Prof. Jung-Keug Park. Department of Medical Biotech-
nology, Dongguk University, 32 Dongguk-ro, Ilsandong-gu, Goyang-si, 
Gyeonggi-do 10326, Republic of Korea 
E-mail: jkpark@dongguk.edu </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BM-MSC, bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells; 
EDTA, ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid; hBM-MSC, human bone marrow-
derived mesenchymal stem cells; H&amp;E, hematoxylin and eosin; MAPK, MAP 
kinase; MCAO, middle cerebral occlusion; MSC, mesenchymal stem cells; 
NF-kB, nuclear factor kappa B; NF, neurofilament; NH, non-hematopoietic; 
PAGE, polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis; PARP, poly(ADP-ribose) poly-
merase; PBS, phosphate-buffered saline; ROS, reactive oxidative stress; 
SDS, sodium dodecylsulfate </p>

<p>Received 
07 APR 2016 
Revised 
12 JUL 2016 
Accepted 
14 JUL 2016 
Accepted 
article online 21 JUL 2016 </p>

<p>www.biotechnology-journal.com </p>

<p>www.biotecvisions.com </p>

<p>Biotechnology 
Journal </p>

<p>Biotechnol. J. 2016, 11, 1397-1404 </p>

<p>1398 
© 2016 The Authors. Biotechnology Journal published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim </p>

<p>strains in susceptibility to the effects of focal ischemia 
were identified, for example, the C57BL/6 strain is unsuit-
able for MCAO model [5]. In this study, we used a photo-
thrombotic ischemia model that has been widely used as 
an experimental model. Photothrombosis models have the 
advantages of reproducibility, low mortality and low inva-
siveness with no mechanical damage to the endothelium. 
This model also can produce easily the well-defined 
infarcts in specific regions of the cortex based on photo-
chemical reaction, and can be readily controlled by 
adjusting the intensity and field of light/laser [6, 7]. 
However, the photothrombosis-induced method has the 
limitation that it generally produces small-sized ischemic 
penumbra. The size and location of ischemia can be altered 
by modifying the duration and intensity of the light source. 
The biochemical responses are altered and degree of tissue 
injury differed according to volume of ischemic injury, 
accompanied by histological and behavioral deficits [8]. 
This allows the location and size of the infarct region to be 
precisely controlled in the photothrombosis animal model. 
According to many clinical researches, bone marrow-
derived mesenchymal stem cells (BM-MSCs) have been 
suggested to have potential for treatment of ischemic 
stroke. Early studies have reported the efficacy of MSCs 
for the treatment of stroke both in vitro and in vivo [9-12]. 
Transplanted BM-MSCs secreted bioactive factors and 
mediated diverse endogenous processes, including angi-
ogenesis, apoptosis, and inflammation, within the delete-
rious post-ischemia environment [13-15]. 
In the present study, we adapted the mouse photo-
thrombosis model and performed a histological, cellular and 
behavioral assessment to determine the optimal ischemic 
condition for generation of severe ischemic penumbra. In 
addition, we analyzed the neurogenic effect of transplanted 
human BM-MSCs in our photothrombosis model. </p>

<p>2 Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1 Animals and cerebral ischemic surgery </p>

<p>Male C57BL/6 mice at eight weeks of age were used 
(Samtako Bio Korea, Osan, Korea). The Institutional Ani-
mal Ethics Committee of Dongguk University approved all 
animal experiments. Mice were anesthetized by intra-
peritoneal (i.p.) injection of tiletamine/zolazepam (Zoletile; 
Virbac Lab., Carros, France) and xylazine (Rompun; Bayer, 
Seoul, South Korea). The ischemic surgery procedure was 
described by [16, 17]. Before surgery, animals were main-
tained at a body temperature of 37°C on a heating pad. 
After mice were placed on a stereotaxic apparatus, the 
skin of mice was incised and craniotomy made on the 
midline scalp. The photosensitive dye Rose Bengal (Sig-
ma-Aldrich; 0.1 mL of a 10 mg/mL solution in sterile 
saline) was injected into the penile vein for 5 min before 
illumination. To induce photothrombosis, the brain was </p>

<p>exposed to illumination with distance of 1-mm from a 
fiber-optic bundle connected to a cold light source (wave 
length 560 nm, KL 1500 LCD, Schott, Germany) on mouse 
left frontal cortex, focused at 0.5 mm anterior to the 
bregma and 2.5 mm lateral from the midline for 15 min. 
To generate ischemia of various sizes, injured mice 
were randomly divided into three groups according to 
output level. The aperture size of irradiated area was fixed 
at position C (5 mm diameter). The intensity of light 
source emitted by halogen lamp was set to three types of 
output level which can be controlled by turning knob. The 
light intensity is following; C-4 (3200 K), C-5 (3250 K) and 
C-6 (3300 K) (step width 50 K). 
After surgery, the scalp was sutured and injured mice 
were returned to their cages to recover. </p>

<p>2.2 Transplantation of human BM-MSCs </p>

<p>Human BM-MSCs were cultured and expanded in non-
hematopoietic (NH) stem cell medium (Miltenyi Biotech, 
Bergisch-Gladbach, Germany) supplemented with 100 U/mL 
penicillin and 100 μg/mL streptomycin (Invitrogen, Carls-
bad, CA, USA). At 24 h after surgery, mice were anesthe-
tized and the human BM-MSCs (1 × 10 5 cells) suspended 
in 1 mL Phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) were transplanted 
intravenously. The control groups were performed as same 
procedures with an equal volume of saline. For immuno-
suppression, all animals were injected with cyclosporine A 
daily (10 µg/g body weight, intraperitoneally). </p>

<p>2.3 Hematoxylin and eosin staining 
and measurement of infarct volume </p>

<p>The brains were removed from the skull and embedded in 
paraffin after ischemia. Brain tissue was dissected later-
ally into 2 mm slices on the mouse brain matrix using a 
surgical blade. For staining, slices including the perile-
sional ischemic core on the cortex were picked up and 
stained with 10% formalin for 30 min and then washed 
three times with 10 mM Tris-HCL (pH 7.2). The sections 
were stained with Mayer's hematoxylin, and washed in 
tap water to mature the hematoxylin staining. Then the 
sections were stained with eosin followed by immersion 
in maturation baths containing 95% ethanol and 100% 
ethanol, followed by xylene. Cover slides were directly 
mounted using permanent mounting medium (Richard-
Allan Scientific, Kalamazoo, USA). 
Infarct volume was measured by result of hemotoxylin 
and eosin (H&amp;E) staining of brain sections. The loss areas of 
cerebral infarction were analyzed by multiplying each area 
in the consecutive sections by the thickness of the sections. </p>

<p>2.4 Protein extraction and Western blotting </p>

<p>On day 30 after ischemia, cells were washed with PBS, 
lysed in sample buffer (2% SDS, 5% 2-mercaptoethanol, </p>

<p>www.biotecvisions.com </p>

<p>www.biotechnology-journal.com </p>

<p>Biotechnology 
Journal </p>

<p>Biotechnol. J. 2016, 11, 1397-1404 </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Biotechnology Journal published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim 
1399 </p>

<p>10% glycerol, and 0.1 mg/mL bromphenol blue in Tris-
HCl, pH 6.8), and heated at 100°C for 10 min. Brain tissue 
was washed twice with cold PBS, and homogenized in ice 
cold RIPA buffer containing a protease inhibitor cocktail 
comprising aprotinin (serine protease inhibitor), leupep-
tin (serine and cysteine proteases inhibitor), bestatin 
(aminopeptidase inhibitor), and ethylenediaminetet-
raacetic acid (EDTA) (metalloprotease inhibitor). Protein 
concentrations of total lysates were determined by BCA 
Protein Assay (Thermo Scientific, Rockford, IL, USA). For 
Western blot analysis, 20 µg of lysates were electro-
phoresed by in a 10% SDS-PAGE gel and transferred onto 
nitrocellulose membranes. Membranes were blocked 
with 5% skim milk in TBS-T (pH 7.4) for 30 min at room 
temperature, followed by incubation with neural and 
synaptic-related antibodies as well as anti-β-actin anti-
body at the appropriate dilutions overnight at 4°C. After 
washing, membranes were incubated with anti-mouse 
and anti-rabbit secondary antibodies for 1 h at room tem-
perature, and visualized using the ECL system (Thermo 
Fisher Scienctific, USA). Images were obtained using the 
ChemiDoc XRS+ Imaging System (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, 
USA). </p>

<p>2.5 Behavioral tests </p>

<p>All animals were subjected to the rotarod test by a blinded 
investigator. Pre-training conducted daily for three days 
before ischemia. Rotarod tests were performed at 1, 7, 14, 
21 and 28 days after surgery as described previously [18] 
with some modifications. Mice were placed on the rotarod 
cylinder and the speed was slowly increased to 20 rpm, at 
which the mice walked stable. All animals were subjected 
to three trials of a maximum duration of 3 min. The maxi-
mum speed and time were selected so that uninjured 
mice would not fall off from the cylinder. The results were 
recorded as the time in seconds at which the mice fell off 
from the rung of the cylinder. </p>

<p>2.6 Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were reported as mean ± standard deviation (SD) 
and analyzed using the <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">10.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS, Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL). Differences between groups were assessed 
by Student's t-test. A value of p &lt; 0.05 was considered to 
indicate statistical significance. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Infarct size of irradiated area 
on mouse cortex on day 1 (A) and 
day 30 (B). Brain sections were stained 
with H&amp;E and the infarcted area was 
revealed with pale-staining, surrounded 
by curvilinear border (left). Different siz-
es of infarct areas were generated by dif-
ferent irradiation level, C-4, C-5 and C-6 
(right). On day 30 after ischemia, the 
volume of infarction in C-6 was signifi-
cantly greater than other groups. Each 
bar represents the mean ± SD of inde-
pendent experiments performed (n = 5; 
*P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>www.biotechnology-journal.com </p>

<p>www.biotecvisions.com </p>

<p>Biotechnology 
Journal </p>

<p>Biotechnol. J. 2016, 11, 1397-1404 </p>

<p>1400 
© 2016 The Authors. Biotechnology Journal published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>3.1 Changes in the size of infarcts on mouse cortex </p>

<p>Photothrombotic ischemia in the mouse cortex was 
induced using a cold-light source after injection of the 
photo-sensitive dye, Rose Bengal. We used about 5 mm 
diameter of aperture size with three types of output level 
from halogen lamp (Phillips, USA) to generate infarcts. 
Infarct lesions were made on the left frontal cortex by 
forming a 5 mm diameter infarct core. After one day and 
30 days after ischemia, each mouse was sacrificed and all 
brain slices were stained with H&amp;E to evaluate infarct 
volume. One day after ischemia, the average infarct vol-
ume was 2.11 mm 3 in the C-4 group, 2.225 mm 3 in the C-5 
group, and 3.128 mm 3 in the C-6 group; the differences 
were not significant. Infarct lesions had similar patterns 
that were located in the parietal and occipital cortex and 
showed pale-staining, surrounded by curvilinear border. 
On day 30, the average of infarct volume in the C-6 group 
(0.835 mm 3 ) was significantly greater than that in the 
other groups. In contrast, infarct lesions in brains in the 
C-4 group recovered gradually (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>3.2 Changes in the levels of apoptosis-
and inflammation-related proteins </p>

<p>We performed Western blot analysis of ischemic lesion to 
assess the cellular response. On day 30 after ischemia, 
apoptosis-related proteins in infarct lesions were ana-
lyzed by Western blotting because apoptosis is a funda-
mental and important process accompanied by ischemic 
events. Caspase-3 and poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase 
(PARP) are crucial mediators of apoptosis in response to 
cellular stress [19, 20]. As shown in Fig. 2, the cleaved 
caspase-3 and PARP protein levels were higher after 
ischemia. In particular, mice treated with C-6 irradiation 
exhibited the greatest increases in the levels of these 
proteins. Interestingly, the C-6 irradiation treated-mice 
also showed significant phosphorylation of p38 and 
MAPKAPK-2, which regulate cellular responses to extra-
cellular stress stimuli. The p38 MAP kinase (MAPK) fam-
ily and its downstream signaling molecule MAPKAPK-2 
are known as signaling cascades which can control the 
cellular responses to cytokines and stresses [21]. 
In addition, we analyzed the protein level of the tran-
scription nuclear factor kappa B (NF-kB) to evaluate the </p>

<p>Figure 2. (A) The result of Western blot analysis on infarct lesion induced by C-4, C-5 and C-6 irradiation. On 30 days, each mouse brain was lysed and 
detected using apoptosis and inflammatory response-related proteins. The proteins were significantly phosphorylated in C-6 irradiation group. (B) Quanti-
tative analysis of expression level in comparison to β-actin, an internal control. Each bar represents the mean ± SD of independent experiment performed 
in triplicate (n = 3; *P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>www.biotecvisions.com </p>

<p>www.biotechnology-journal.com </p>

<p>Biotechnology 
Journal </p>

<p>Biotechnol. J. 2016, 11, 1397-1404 </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Biotechnology Journal published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim 
1401 </p>

<p>inflammatory response. NF-kB plays a major role in sev-
eral inflammatory mechanisms in response to ischemic 
injury [22, 23]. Phosphorylated NF-kB expression was 
significantly higher in the C-6 group. 
These results showed that the levels of proteins asso-
ciated with endogenous cellular responses were increased 
following ischemic injury, particularly C-6 irradiation. </p>

<p>3.3 Changes in behavioral ability </p>

<p>The behavior ability was investigated using a rotarod test 
in detecting motor deficits and recovery. Before surgery, 
all animals showed similar behavior function, actively </p>

<p>walking on the rod for 3 min. At 24 h after surgery, all mice 
could not use their paws (both right fore-and hind-limbs) 
so that they immediately fell off from the device. On day 7, 
all mice showed increase in spontaneous limbs rather 
than day 1. However, by 28 days, the functional ability of 
mice in the C-4 and C-5 groups had improved (time of 
walking on the rotarod) to a great extent than mice in the 
C-6 group. The group of C-6 showed slightly recovery on 
behavioral performance. On day 21 and 28, there were 
significant (p &lt; 0.5) deficits in performance in the C-6 
group (Fig. 3). 
These data suggested that mice in the C-6 group were 
significantly impaired, and their behavioral performance 
improved slowly after ischemia. </p>

<p>3.4 The effect of neural differentiation on ischemic 
lesion treatment with human BM-MSCs </p>

<p>We obtained results that the C-6 irradiation induced 
severe ischemia by generating large infarct lesions in the 
mouse cortex and deficits in behavioral performance. To 
confirm neurogenesis by human BM-MSCs in the C-6 
group, we performed a further in vivo experiment using 
the same photothrombosis-induced method. 
As shown in Fig. 4 and Fig. 5, we performed Western 
blotting, H&amp;E staining and rotarod test in mice treated or 
not with human BM-MSCs. On day 30 after surgery, we 
observed that neural and synaptic-related proteins were 
more expressed after transplantation of BM-MSCs com-
pared with non-transplanted. The human-specific pro-
teins, NF (neurofilament) and NeuroD1 protein levels were 
also up-regulated in the hBM-MSCs transplanted mice. 
Further, the relative infarct volume was significantly 
lower in the MSC-treated groups (0.52 mm 3 ) than the 
control group (0.885 mm 3 ). 
No significant difference was observed in behavioral 
ability between the control and BM-MSCs treated group </p>

<p>Figure 3. Behavioral performance after photothrombotic ischemia by 
28 days. After one day of ischemia, the mice have a significant deficit that 
could not well use their forepaws. Mice in C-4 and C-5 groups was gradu-
ally improved the functional ability (time of walking on the rotarod), how-
ever, C-6 mice showed slightly recovery on behavioral performance. Data 
are expressed as mean ± SD (n = 10; BL, internal baseline average before 
surgery). *p &lt; 0.05, between C-4 group and C-6 group. #p &lt; 0.05, between 
C-5 group and C-6 group. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Western blot analysis after transplantation of human BM-MSCs in photothrombosis model on day 30. (A) The hBM-MSCs treated groups were 
more expressed neural and synaptic-related proteins than control group (non-transplanted hBM-MSCs). (B) The human specific proteins, NF and Neu-
roD1, were expressed after transplantation of MSCs. </p>

<p>www.biotechnology-journal.com </p>

<p>www.biotecvisions.com </p>

<p>Biotechnology 
Journal </p>

<p>Biotechnol. J. 2016, 11, 1397-1404 </p>

<p>1402 
© 2016 The Authors. Biotechnology Journal published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim </p>

<p>at one week. However, the significant behavioral improve-
ment (p &lt; 0.5) appeared in the BM-MSCs-treated group 
after the day 7. </p>

<p>4 Discussion </p>

<p>Ischemic stroke is a leading cause of morbidity and dis-
ability, and results in damage to neural cells, massive 
tissue infarction and loss of brain function [1, 2, 24]. The 
ischemic stroke induced by photothrombosis has 
emerged recently as an alternative MCAO surgery, 
which has poor reproducibility and small infarct size. 
Photothrombosis is based on photochemical reaction 
between light and a photo-sensitive dye such as Rose 
Bengal. It was injected intravenously and activated by 
light, generating thrombotic events including peroxida-
tive damage, platelet aggregation and coagulation cas-
cades, which lead to microvascular occlusion [8]. This 
model can be easily changed by different infarct sizes 
and regions on focal brain. Several studies have focused 
on design and development of the photothrombotic 
ischemic model by regulating the various light sources 
and intensities. 
Here, we made three experimental ischemic groups 
on mouse focal cortex. The infarct volume was controlled 
by varying the light intensity and aperture size. As shown 
in Fig. 1, infarct size in the C-6 irradiation group was 
greater on day 30. In contrast, the C-4 and C-5 groups 
showed small-sized infarct lesions that recovered sponta-
neously from injury. </p>

<p>These results were verified by Western blotting and a 
behavioral test shown in Fig. 2 and Fig. 3. We performed 
a Western blot analysis of proteins related to apoptosis 
and the inflammatory-response. Many reports have been 
already shown that inflammatory cascades are activated 
after ischemic events or brain injury because the ischemia 
closely mediates with various pathophysiological mecha-
nisms such as disruption of glucose metabolism, reactive 
oxidative stress (ROS) production, necrosis and apoptosis 
[21-23, 25, 26]. In infarcted lesions, we detected signifi-
cantly increased inflammatory responses, particularly in 
the C-6 irradiation group. 
Ischemic mice had behavioral deficits and their motor 
performance had not fully recovered by day 28, especially 
in the C-6 group. We detected that the C-6 irradiation 
level was optimal for making the photothrombotic mouse 
model, which can maintain an ischemic state for a pro-
longed period. Further, our results also indicated that 
behavioral ability was closely correlated with the appear-
ance and volume of infarct lesions on the focal cortex. 
Regarding behavioral results, some mice showed min-
imal recovery and stabilized after 14 days of ischemia. 
These observations are consistent with previous reports 
that the behavioral performance of ischemic animals 
tended to recover spontaneously after surgery, in particu-
lar after photothrombosis [3, 6, 27, 28]. The photothrom-
botic model showed a smaller ischemia penumbra on the 
superficial cortex compared to the MCAO model, so that 
infarct lesions by photothrombosis tend to readily medi-
ate axonal reorganization and functional recovery within 
the brain. The exact mechanism underlying spontaneous </p>

<p>Figure 5. (A) Histological analysis of infarct lesion on mice cortex after photothrombotic ischemia (H&amp;E) on day 30 after surgery. Infarct size was signifi-
cantly reduced after transplantation of hBM-MSCs. Each bar represents the mean ± SD (n = 10). (B) Behavioral performance (rotarod test) by 28 days after 
transplantation of hBM-MSCs. Behavioral performance was significantly recovered 14 days after ischemia. Control mice have a severe deficit, so they 
couldn't recover by four weeks. Data are expressed as mean ± SD (n = 10; BL, internal baseline average before surgery). *p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>www.biotecvisions.com </p>

<p>www.biotechnology-journal.com </p>

<p>Biotechnology 
Journal </p>

<p>Biotechnol. J. 2016, 11, 1397-1404 </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Biotechnology Journal published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim 
1403 </p>

<p>recovery is unclear. This phenomenon is generally known 
due to brain plasticity with cortical reconnection and 
axonal sprouting in adjacent cortical areas [29, 30]. After 
ischemia, few damaged neurons are replaced by neuro-
genesis, and these express markers of developing and 
mature of new neurons [31, 32]. Therefore, to make severe 
ischemia penumbra with large and deep infarction like 
MCAO model is an important point in terms of design of 
animal stroke model. Recently, many studies have been 
focused on modifying the photothrombotic method to 
induce internal damage and produce severe motor deficit 
[33-35]. Therefore, our photothrombotic mouse model has 
possibility to replace the MCAO model as it shows long-
lasting neurological severity and behavioral deficit. 
To confirm that C-6 is optimal for neural differentia-
tion, we performed an additional in vivo experiment using 
human BM-MSCs. After transplantation of BM-MSCs, the 
expression of neural and synaptic-related protein levels 
was increased. In particular, the human specific-proteins 
were detected and their expression levels increased in 
MSCs-treated mice. As shown in Fig. 4, we observed that 
the cells not only were well incorporated into the injured 
site but also enhanced endogenous neurogenesis. These 
results were confirmed in an additional experiment, Prus-
sian blue staining. After transplantation of hBM-MSCs 
incorporated with nanoparticle, the cells were well detect-
ed in infarct lesion with blue dots (data not shown). Fur-
ther, infarct volume and behavioral performance also 
recovered significantly (Fig. 5). Therefore, human BM-
MSCs were successfully transplanted at the lesion site 
and promoted endogenous neural differentiation in our 
ischemia-induced mouse model. 
This tendency for behavioral recovery and neurogen-
esis is in agreement with many previous in vivo studies. 
The method of BM-MSCs transplantation was well known 
as excellent and used for neural cell therapy and for treat-
ment of experimental ischemic stroke [9-12]. However, 
most studies used the MCAO model. To date, few studies 
using the photochemically-induced mouse model have 
been reported. Wang et al. demonstrated that in the pho-
tothrombosis model, the size of the irradiated area affect-
ed infarct volume and neuronal death within the cortex 
[34]. Li et al. reported microglia proliferation and behavio-
ral deficits after photothrombosis-induced brain ischemia 
in adult mice [36]. Ma et al. and Hou et al. reported that 
transplantation of neural stem cells enhanced neurologi-
cal function in a photothrombosis stroke model, showing 
decreased infarct areas [37, 38]. However, there were no 
reports on the effects of transplantation of MSCs on neu-
rogenesis in the photothrombosis stroke model. Our study 
is meaningful as it is the first report of the neurogenic 
effect of BM-MSCs in a photothrombosis mouse model, 
which has not been demonstrated before. 
Our model, which involved transplantation of BM-
MSCs, significantly enhanced the effect of neurogenesis 
with low mortality and low variability. This model will </p>

<p>contribute to provide novel methods for developing a sta-
ble animal model of stroke. Therefore, it is reasonable to 
expect that our study has the potential to improve under-
standing of the photothrombotic stroke model. Moreover, 
we proposed a new parameter for MSC-based stroke 
therapy. To establish the clinical trials, further studies will 
be required to understand the underlying mechanisms 
and pathophysiological processes after ischemic stroke. </p>

<p>This research was supported by the Pioneer Research 
Center Program through the National Research Founda-
tion of Korea funded by the Ministry of Science, ICT &amp; 
Future Planning (Grant number: 2009-0082941). </p>

<p>The authors declare no financial or commercial conflictof 
interest. </p>



<p>www.biotechnology-journal.com </p>

<p>www.biotecvisions.com </p>

<p>Biotechnology 
Journal </p>

<p>Biotechnol. J. 2016, 11, 1397-1404 </p>

<p>1404 
© 2016 The Authors. Biotechnology Journal published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim </p>



<p>© 2016 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim </p>

<p>www.biotechnology-journal.com </p>

<p>Editorial 
Asian Congress on Biotechnology 2015 </p>

<p>Hyung Joon Cha, Noriho Kamiya and 
S. Vikineswary Sabaratnam </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600650 </p>

<p>Commentary 
Therapeutic effects of stem cells on ischemic stroke were 
confirmed in an improved photothrombotic mouse model </p>

<p>I-Ming Chu </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600414 </p>

<p>Review 
Solid-in-oil nanodispersions for transdermal drug delivery 
systems </p>

<p>Momoko Kitaoka, Rie Wakabayashi, Noriho Kamiya 
and Masahiro Goto </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600081 </p>

<p>Review 
Design of nanoscale enzyme complexes based on various 
scaffolding materials for biomass conversion 
and immobilization </p>

<p>Jeong Eun Hyeon, Sang Kyu Shin and Sung Ok Han </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600039 </p>

<p>Research Article 
Effect of human mesenchymal stem cell transplantation 
on cerebral ischemic volume-controlled photothrombotic 
mouse model </p>

<p>Yun-Kyong Choi, Enerelt Urnukhsaikhan, Hee-Hoon Yoon, 
Young-Kwon Seo and Jung-Keug Park </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600057 </p>

<p>Research Article 
Multiplex 16S rRNA-derived geno-biochip for detection 
of 16 bacterial pathogens from contaminated foods </p>

<p>Hwa Hui Shin, Byeong Hee Hwang and Hyung Joon Cha </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600043 </p>

<p>Research Article 
Fabrication of multilayered vascular tissues using microfluidic 
agarose hydrogel platforms </p>

<p>Keita Kinoshita, Masaki Iwase, Masumi Yamada, 
Yuya Yajima and Minoru Seki </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600083 </p>

<p>Research Article 
Enhanced production of 2,3-butanediol in pyruvate 
decarboxylase-deficient Saccharomyces cerevisiae through 
optimizing ratio of glucose/galactose </p>

<p>Eun-Ji Choi, Jin-Woo Kim, Soo-Jung Kim, Seung-Oh Seo, 
Stephan Lane, Yong-Cheol Park, Yong-Su Jin and Jin-Ho Seo </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600042 </p>

<p>Research Article 
Ex vivo culture of circulating tumor cells using magnetic 
force-based coculture on a fibroblast feeder layer </p>

<p>Shuhei Yamamoto, Kazunori Shimizu, Jiahui Fei, Hiroji 
Iwata, Mina Okochi, Hayao Nakanishi and Hiroyuki Honda </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600084 </p>

<p>Research Article 
Protein-stabilizing and cell-penetrating properties 
of α-helix domain of 30Kc19 protein </p>

<p>Jina Ryu, Hyoju Kim, Hee Ho Park, Hong Jai Lee, 
Ju Hyun Park, Won Jong Rhee and Tai Hyun Park </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600040 </p>

<p>Biotechnology Journal -list of articles published in the November 2016 issue. </p>

<p>Cover illustration </p>

<p>This special issue, in collaboration with the Asian Federation of Biotechnology and edited by Professors Hyung 
Joon Cha, Noriho Kamiya and S. Vikineswary Sabaratnam, covers the most advanced biotech research from 
Asian Congress of Biotechnology 2015. This issue includes articles on drug delivery, enzyme engineering, cellular 
therapy, biosensors, etc. The 30Kc19 protein derived from the silkworm hemolymph consists of two domains, 
which are 30Kc19α (blue) and 30Kc19β (red). The cover image shows that 30Kc19α has multifunctional proper-
ties, which are cell penetration, protein stabilization, and cargo delivery. The Image is provided by Jina Ryu, Hyoju 
Kim, Hee Ho Park, Hong Jai Lee, Ju Hyun Park, Won Jong Rhee and Tai Hyun Park authors of "Protein-stabilizing 
and cell-penetrating properties of α-helix domain of 30Kc19 protein" (http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600040). </p>

<p>Research Article 
Enzymatically prepared redox-responsive hydrogels as potent 
matrices for hepatocellular carcinoma cell spheroid formation </p>

<p>Kousuke Moriyama, Shono Naito, Rie Wakabayashi, 
Masahiro Goto and Noriho Kamiya </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600087 </p>

<p>Research Article 
Theoretical calculations on the feasibility of microalgal biofuels: 
Utilization of marine resources could help realizing the 
potential of microalgae </p>

<p>Hanwool Park, Choul-Gyun Lee </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201600041 </p>

<p>© 2016 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim 
www.biotechnology-journal.com </p>

</text></tei>