<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5223687" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: Many studies have investigated </p>

<p>multimorbidity, whose prevalence varies according to 
settings and data sources. However, few studies on 
this topic have been conducted in Italy, a country with 
universal healthcare and one of the most aged 
populations in the world. The aim of this study was to 
estimate the prevalence of multimorbidity in a Northern 
Italian region, to investigate its distribution by age, 
gender and citizenship and to analyse the correlations 
of diseases. </p>

<p>Design: Cross-sectional study based on administrative </p>

<p>data. </p>

<p>Setting: Emilia-Romagna, an Italian region with ∼4.4 </p>

<p>million inhabitants, of which almost one-fourth are 
aged ≥65 years. </p>

<p>Participants: All adults residing in Emilia-Romagna </p>

<p>on 31 December 2012. Hospitalisations, drug 
prescriptions and contacts with community mental 
health services from 2003 to 2012 were traced to 
identify the presence of 17 physical and 9 mental 
health disorders. </p>

<p>Primary and secondary outcome measures: </p>

<p>Descriptive analysis of differences in the prevalence of 
multimorbidity in relation to age, gender and 
citizenship. The correlations of diseases were analysed 
using exploratory factor analysis. </p>

<p>Results: The study population included 622 026 men </p>

<p>and 751 011women, with a mean age of 66.4 years. 
Patients with multimorbidity were 33.5% in 75 years 
and &gt;60% among patients aged ≥90 years; among 
patients aged ≥65 years, the proportion of 
multimorbidity was 39.9%. After standardisation by 
age and gender, multimorbidity was significantly more 
frequent among Italian citizens than among 
immigrants. Factor analysis identified 5 multimorbidity 
patterns: (1) psychiatric disorders, (2) cardiovascular, 
renal, pulmonary and cerebrovascular diseases, (3) 
neurological diseases, (4) liver diseases, AIDS/HIV and 
substance abuse and (5) tumours. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Multimorbidity was highly prevalent in </p>

<p>Emilia-Romagna and strongly associated with age. This 
finding highlights the need for healthcare providers to 
adopt individualised care plans and ensure continuity 
of care. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Barnett et al 
2 estimated that, in Scotland, 
almost one-fourth of all individuals, and 
more than half of those with a chronic dis-
order, have multimorbidity. Multimorbidity is 
more common among women and older 
people, 
3 and is now considered the most 
prevalent chronic health condition in the 
overall population. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>It has been reported that people with mul-
timorbidity have poorer quality of life and 
worse outcomes, 
5 and are frequent users of 
healthcare services. 
6 In fact, the treatment of 
multimorbidity results in high healthcare 
costs and involves multiple professionals. 
However, although many clinical guidelines 
are available for the management of specific 
chronic conditions, such as hypertension, 
diabetes and heart failure, there is a lack of 
evidence-based integrated treatments for 
patients with multiple diseases. 
7 So, the treat-
ment of multimorbidity would require a hol-
istic approach to cope with patients' complex 
healthcare needs, 
8 9 and continuity of care </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This is the first study conducted in Italy to 
assess the prevalence and pattern of multimor-
bidity and its distribution by age, gender and 
citizenship. 
▪ This is a population-based study comprising all 
adults residing in the region of Emilia-Romagna, 
a large Italian region with ∼4.4 million inhabi-
tants, of which almost one-fourth are aged 
≥65 years and &gt;10% are foreign citizens. 
▪ The use of administrative data may have under-
estimated multimorbidity, as they do not include 
primary care data. </p>

<p>Lenzi J, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e012812. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012812 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>should be ensured to multimorbid patients. 
10 11 Primary 
care has thus a key role in managing multimorbidity, as 
it is person-focused rather than disease-focused, it is con-
tinuous over time and co-ordinates specialist care when 
necessary. </p>

<p>12 13 </p>

<p>Many studies were conducted to investigate the preva-
lence of multimorbidity in different countries, but 
results may differ according to the diseases considered, 
the age of the population, settings and data sources. 
3 Of 
note, few studies on this topic have been conducted in 
Italy, a country with universal healthcare and one of the 
most aged populations in the world. 
The aim of the present study was to estimate the 
prevalence of multimorbidity in Emilia-Romagna (Italy), 
to investigate its distribution by age, gender and citizen-
ship and to analyse the correlations of diseases. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study design and participants 
This cross-sectional study is based on demographic and 
clinical data retrieved from five data sources linked 
using the patient's identification code: 
1. The hospital discharge record (HDR) database, 
which includes demographic characteristics, admis-
sion referral source, admission and discharge dates, 
main diagnosis, up to five secondary diagnoses, up to 
six interventions (identified using the ICD-9-CM 
coding system) and discharge status. HDRs are sent 
by all public and private hospitals to the Regional 
Authority and on a regular basis from the Regional 
Authority to the Ministry of Health after data quality 
control. Since 1995, the diagnosis-related group 
system has been systematically used to allocate funds 
to hospitals and to monitor quality of care and 
outcomes. 
2. The mental health information system. This register 
was implemented in 2005 for administrative and clin-
ical epidemiological purposes. All adult patients who 
have at least one contact with the community mental 
health centres (CMHCs) are recorded in the data-
base, which includes demographic characteristics, the 
ICD-9-CM diagnosis and information of each type of 
intervention administered. 
3. Residential mental healthcare discharge records, a 
database active since 2008 that includes mandatory 
information on patients discharged from non-profit 
or accredited private facilities, that is, admission and 
discharge dates, main diagnosis and discharge status. 
Accredited facilities are private hospitals where fees 
are reimbursed by the Italian National Health Service 
if the patient is an official resident in Italy. 
4. The outpatient pharmaceutical database, which 
contains information on patients' gender and age, 
prescriptions (substance name, ATC System code-
V.2013, trade name, date of prescription filling and 
number of packages) and prescribers. This register 
includes drugs reimbursed by the healthcare system </p>

<p>that are prescribed by the general practitioner or a 
specialist, or directly delivered by the hospital 
pharmacies. 
5. The regional mortality register database, which con-
tains information on patients' demographic character-
istics as well as date, place and cause of death. This 
database was used to identify patients who alive on the 
prevalence date. 
The study population comprised of all adults (aged 
≥18 years) who were residing in the region of Emilia-
Romagna on 31 December 2012. Emilia-Romagna is a 
Northern Italian region with ∼4.4 million inhabitants, of 
which almost one-fourth are aged ≥65 years and &gt;10% 
are foreign citizens-one of the highest proportion 
among all Italian regions. 
In Italy, all residents are registered with the National 
Health Service that provides uniform and comprehen-
sive care. Under the Italian Constitution and its recent 
modification (2001), the State has exclusive power to set 
the 'essential levels of care' for all residents throughout 
the country, whereas the regions have responsibility 
for the organisation and administration of publicly 
financed healthcare. Primary healthcare is provided by 
general practitioners remunerated on a capitation base/ 
formula; they are in charge of providing care and assess 
patients' needs, order diagnostic procedures, prescribe 
drugs and refer patients to specialists and hospitals. 
They thus act as 'gatekeepers' for the system and ensure 
continuity of care to patients with chronic diseases. 
Foreign citizens with regular stay permit are entitled 
to registration with the Italian National Health Service 
and to the same treatment as Italian citizens with refer-
ence to contributory burden and healthcare provided. 
Irregular immigrants, that is, without stay permit, can be 
assisted as 'temporarily present foreigners': they are pro-
vided a special card that ensures basic and specialised 
health services. Doctors in emergency services are not 
asked to report migrants who have no residence permit 
(law 94/2009 'Norms on public security'). In 
Emilia-Romagna, hospitalisation is lower among immi-
grants than among Italians, for men and women, when 
excluding obstetric causes. Even if hospital admissions of 
immigrants increased from 3.1% of total in 2002 to 
7.4% in 2009, the number continues to be lower com-
pared with hospital admissions of residents. However, 
immigrants tend to have more frequently urgent hospita-
lisations, probably due to limited knowledge of commu-
nity health services and general practitioners. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Definition of multimorbidity 
No standard approach for the measurements of multi-
morbidity exists, and selection and definition of the dis-
eases to be considered is inevitably subjective and 
dependent on the data available. 
2 In the present study, 
we sought to identify all diseases recommended as core 
for any multimorbidity measure in a systematic review, </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>and which are likely to have a significant impact on 
patients in terms of need for chronic treatment, </p>



<p>Lenzi J, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e012812. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012812 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>reduced function, reduced quality of life and risk of 
future morbidity and mortality. However, in Italy, elec-
tronic clinical records for primary care are not available 
because general practitioners are not requested to 
collect information about diseases. Thus, we tracked the 
presence of a number of diseases using information on 
hospital discharges, contacts with community mental 
health services and accredited residential facilities, and 
drug prescriptions. 
Specifically, 16 physical illnesses were defined using 
the comorbidity ICD-9-CM coding algorithms developed 
by Charlson et al 
16 and Elixhauser et al, 
17 and enhanced 
by Quan et al, 
18 whereas 10 mental health disorders were 
tracked using an ad hoc ICD-9-CM coding algorithm. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>We also used drug prescriptions for tracking hyperten-
sion, diabetes, bipolar disorder, depression and anxiety 
-all diseases that, in Italy, are managed to a large 
extent by general practitioners. Table 1 provides further 
details of definitions and the 26 diseases included in the 
study. Complete lists of ICD-9-CM codes and ATC codes 
used for defining the 26 diseases are provided in online 
supplementary files 1 and 2, respectively. In online 
supplementary file 3, we have displayed the percentage 
contribution of hospitalisations and drug prescriptions 
in defining hypertension, diabetes, bipolar disorder, 
depression and anxiety. 
As in most other studies, 
15 we defined multimorbidity 
as the co-occurrence of two or more diseases in one 
patient. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
We used graphical displays for descriptive analysis of dif-
ferences in the prevalence of morbidity and multimor-
bidity across age groups and between women and men. 
Age-and gender-standardised prevalence of multimor-
bidity among foreign citizens was calculated using the 
Italian population resident in the region of 
Emilia-Romagna on 31 December 2012 as the standard 
population. Differences across age-groups, between 
women and men and between Italians and foreigners 
were assessed using the χ² test. 
The correlations of the 26 conditions were analysed 
using exploratory factor analysis, as suggested by Schäfer 
et al, 
20 and using the iterated principal factor method. 
We used a tetrachoric correlation matrix for factor ana-
lysis: in doing so, we made the assumption that all the 
dichotomous diagnoses ( presence or absence of the 
disease) reflected an underlying continuous latent trait, 
that is, that the chronic conditions included in the mul-
timorbidity count had a progressive course and got diag-
nosed if a certain threshold was reached during this 
course. The factors resulting from this analysis can be 
interpreted as multimorbidity patterns (ie, clusters of 
diagnoses frequently associated with each other), and 
each factor loading represents the association of the spe-
cific disease with a pattern. As a measure of model fit, 
we reported the proportion of variance of the data 
accounted for by the multimorbidity patterns. The </p>

<p>extraction criterion for factors was a minimum eigen-
value of 1. Factor loadings of 0.30 or more were consid-
ered relevant and reported in the results. Since we 
assumed that multimorbidity factors were associated with 
each other, we used an oblique (oblimin) rotation of 
factor loading matrices. Spearman's ρ was used to 
analyse the relationship of factor scores with age, gender 
and citizenship. 
All analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Stata</rs> software, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">V.13</rs> 
(StataCorp, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-date">2013</rs>, Stata Statistical Software: Release 13, 
College Station, Texas, USA: StataCorp LP). </p>

<p>Ethics statement 
The study was exempt from approval from the Ethics 
Committee of Emilia-Romagna. It was conducted in con-
formity with the regulations for data management from 
the Regional Health Authority of Emilia-Romagna, and 
with the Italian Code of conduct and professional practice 
applying to processing of personal data for statistical and scien-
tific purposes (art. 20-21, legislative decree 196/2003; 
http://www.garanteprivacy.it/web/guest/home/docweb/-/ 
docweb-display/docweb/1115480) published in the 
Official Journal no. 190 of August 14, 2004, which expli-
citly exempts the need for approval from the Ethics 
Committee when using anonymous data (Preamble 
number 8). 
In Italy, anonymous administrative data-gathering is 
subject to the law Protection of individuals and other subjects 
with regard to the processing of personal data, ACT no. 675 of 
31.12.1996 (amended by Legislative Decree no. 123 of 
09.05.1997, no. 255 of 28.07.1997, no. 135 of 08.05.1998, 
no. 171 of 13.05.1998, no. 389 of 6.11.1998, no. 51 of 
26.02.1999, no. 135 of 11.05.1999, no. 281 of 30.07.1999, 
no. 282 of 30.07.1999 and no. 467 of 28.12.2001) 
(http://www.privacy.it/legge675encoord.html). 
Data were anonymised prior to the analysis at the 
regional statistical office, and each patient was assigned 
a unique identifier that eliminates the ability to trace 
the patient's identity or other sensitive data. As anon-
ymised administrative data are used routinely for health-
care management, no specific written informed consent 
was needed to use the patient information. 
All procedures performed in this study were in accord-
ance with the 1964 Helsinki Declaration and its later 
amendments. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
We analysed data from 3 759 836 adults residing in the 
region of Emilia-Romagna on 31 December 2012 
(women: 1 956 857, 52.0%; aged ≥65 years: 1 018 053, 
27.1%; immigrants: 422 834, 11.2%). A total of 2 386 
799 participants (63.5%) had no disease, whereas 
798 829 (21.2%) had one disease and 574 208 (15.3%) 
two or more diseases. The demographic characteristics 
of the study population (ie, patients with one or more 
diseases) are provided in table 2. The mean number of 
diseases by age, gender and citizenship is also reported. </p>

<p>Lenzi J, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e012812. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012812 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Figure 1 shows the prevalence of each disease by gender. 
The prevalence of hypertension (men: 27.8%, women: 
31.1%; χ²=4700, p&lt;0.001), depression (2.6%, 5.9%; 
χ²=25 000, p&lt;0.001), anxiety (0.8, 1.5%; χ²=3800, p&lt;0.001), 
dementia (0.8%, 1.4%; χ²=3500, p&lt;0.001) and dysthymia </p>

<p>(0.5%, 1.2%; χ²=5900, p&lt;0.001) was higher among women, 
whereas diabetes (6.6%, 5.4%; χ²=2200, p&lt;0.001), chronic 
pulmonary disease (2.8%, 2.1%; χ²=1800, p&lt;0.001), myo-
cardial infarction (2.4%, 1.0%; χ²=12 000, p&lt;0.001), per-
ipheral vascular disease (1.9%, 0.9%; χ²=7700, p&lt;0.001) </p>

<p>Table 1 List of the 26 diseases included in multimorbidity count </p>

<p>Condition 
Variable definition </p>

<p>Mental/physical 
health 
condition </p>

<p>Observation 
period 
Data source </p>

<p>Myocardial infarction 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Congestive heart failure 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Peripheral vascular disease 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Cerebrovascular disease 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Hypertension 
Diagnosis code ever recorded or 
≥2 antihypertensive prescriptions 
over 12 months </p>

<p>Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR, OPD </p>

<p>Dementia, including Alzheimer's 
disease </p>

<p>Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical and/or 
mental </p>

<p>2003-2012 
HDR, MHIS, 
RMHDR 
Chronic pulmonary disease 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Rheumatic disease 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Peptic ulcer disease 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Liver disease 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Diabetes 
Diagnosis code ever recorded or 
≥2 antidiabetic prescriptions over 
12 months </p>

<p>Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR, OPD </p>

<p>Paralysis 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Other neurological disorders 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Renal disease 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Any malignancy, including lymphoma 
and leukaemia, except malignant 
neoplasm of skin </p>

<p>Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2008-2012 
HDR </p>

<p>Metastatic solid tumour 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2008-2012 
HDR 
AIDS/HIV 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Physical 
2003-2012 
HDR 
Schizophrenia and psychosis 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Mental 
2003-2012 
HDR, MHIS, 
RMHDR 
Bipolar disorder 
Diagnosis code ever recorded or 
≥4 lithium prescriptions over 12 
months </p>

<p>Mental 
2003-2012 
HDR, MHIS, 
RMHDR, OPD </p>

<p>Depression 
Diagnosis code ever recorded or 
≥4 antidepressant prescriptions 
over 12 months </p>

<p>Mental 
2012 
HDR, MHIS, 
RMHDR, OPD </p>

<p>Dysthymia 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Mental 
2003-2012 
HDR, MHIS, 
RMHDR 
Anxiety, dissociative and somatoform 
disorders </p>

<p>Diagnosis code ever recorded or 
≥4 anxiolytic/hypnotic prescriptions 
over 12 months </p>

<p>Mental 
2012 
HDR, MHIS, 
RMHDR, OPD </p>

<p>Personality disorders 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Mental 
2003-2012 
HDR, MHIS, 
RMHDR 
Substance use disorders 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Mental 
2003-2012 
HDR, MHIS, 
RMHDR 
Intellectual disabilities 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Mental 
2003-2012 
HDR, MHIS, 
RMHDR 
Other mental disorders 
Diagnosis code ever recorded 
Mental 
2003-2012 
HDR, MHIS, 
RMHDR </p>

<p>For conditions which have lifelong implications such as diabetes, we defined the presence of the condition on the basis of a diagnosis code 
ever being recorded between 2003 and 2012. For malignancies, depression and anxiety, we defined the presence of the morbidity in a 
shorter observation period. For MHIS and RMHDR databases, the observation period starts 2005 and 2008, respectively. 
HDR, hospital discharge record; MHIS, mental health information system; OPD, outpatient pharmaceutical database; RMHDR, residential 
mental healthcare discharge record. </p>



<p>Lenzi J, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e012812. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012812 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>and renal disease (1.1%, 0.7%; χ²=1800, p&lt;0.001) were 
more common among men. Figure 2 shows the preva-
lence of the 26 diseases by age group-dark blocks repre-
sent high prevalence values, whereas light blocks 
represent low prevalence values. The prevalence of all 
diseases increased with age, with the exception of AIDS/ 
HIV and some psychiatric disorders (schizophrenia and 
psychosis, bipolar disorder, personality disorders, sub-
stance use disorders and intellectual disabilities and 
other mental disorders). 
On 31 December 2012, in Emilia-Romagna, patients 
with a single disease were 798 829 (21.2%), whereas </p>

<p>patients with multimorbidity were 574 208 (15.3%). The 
prevalence of morbidity differed significantly by gender 
(men: 19.4%, women: 22.9%; χ²=25 000, p&lt;0.001), as 
well as the prevalence of multimorbidity (men: 15.1%, 
women: 15.4%; χ²=85.38, p&lt;0.001). However, in this 
latter case, the significance of the test seemed to be 
caused by the large size of the study population, rather 
than by the actual difference between the two preva-
lence values. 
The proportion of people with multimorbidity 
increased significantly with age (figure 3), from 19.1% 
in those aged 60-64 years up to 60.8% in the ≥90-year 
group (χ² for trend=700 000, p&lt;0.001); among old 
patients (aged ≥65 years), the proportion of multimor-
bidity was 39.9%. Italian citizens with a single disease 
were 19.9% and those with multimorbidity were 14.4%, 
whereas among immigrants these prevalence values, 
standardised by gender and age, were significantly lower 
(15.0% and 9.3%, respectively, χ²=8200, p&lt;0.001). 
Exploratory factor analysis of diseases identified five 
patterns (table 3). The first factor includes psychiatric 
disorders; the second factor includes cardiovascular, 
renal, pulmonary and cerebrovascular diseases; the third 
factor comprises neurological diseases; the fourth factor 
includes liver diseases, AIDS/HIV and substance abuse; 
the fifth factor includes tumours. As for the association 
between factor scores and demographic characteristics, 
we found that the only correlation coefficient close to 
0.30 was that between multimorbidity pattern 2 and age 
(Spearman's ρ=0.27, p&lt;0.001), indicating that the pres-
ence of cardiovascular, renal, pulmonary and/or cere-
brovascular diseases was more common among older 
than younger age groups. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In this population-based cross-sectional study, one of the 
six adults were multimorbid, whereas among older 
people (aged ≥65 years) this proportion was more than 
one of three. This result is consistent with the range of 
prevalence values found in other studies on multimor-
bidity, 
21-23 although very close to the lower boundary of 
this range (12.9% for participants aged ≥18 years). A 
possible explanation is that administrative databases 
contain only information about people seeking treat-
ment in public services and accredited facilities. 
Therefore, a prevalence of 15.3% only reflects attended 
morbidity. Another reason for this results is the lack of a 
more comprehensive selection of diagnoses, including 
other relevant conditions mentioned in systematic 
reviews. It is also worth noting that, in line with other 
studies, 
24-26 the proportions of men and women pre-
senting more than one chronic disease were very similar. 
The Italian National Institute of Statistics (Istat) 
reported that, in 2012, multimorbidity affected 20.4% of 
the Italian population (49.4% in participants aged 
54-74 years and 69.4% in participants aged ≥90 years) 
(http://www.istat.it/it/archivio/5471). These figures </p>

<p>Table 2 Demographic characteristics of the study 
population </p>

<p>Demographic 
characteristic 
N=1 373 037 </p>

<p>Average 
number 
of chronic 
diseases 
per patient </p>

<p>Gender, n (%) 
Male 
622 026 (45.3) 1.82 
Female 
751 011 (54.7) 1.73 
Age, mean±SD 
66.4±15.3 
Age group, n (%) 
18-24 
11 290 (0.8) 1.33 
25-29 
11 427 (0.8) 1.35 
30-34 
18 408 (1.3) 1.36 
35-39 
32 945 (2.4) 1.37 
40-44 
52 746 (3.8) 1.38 
45-49 
78 260 (5.7) 1.41 
50-54 
100 065 (7.3) 1.44 
55-59 
119 252 (8.7) 1.48 
60-64 
146 964 (10.7) 1.56 
65-69 
162 103 (11.8) 1.66 
70-74 
179 168 (13.0) 1.79 
75-79 
169 422 (12.3) 1.98 
80-84 
141 493 (10.3) 2.19 
85-89 
97 494 (7.1) 2.39 
≥90 
52 000 (3.8) 2.47 
Citizenship, n (%) 
Italian 
1 321 716 (96.3) 1.78 
Non-Italian 
51 321 (3.7) 1.40 
European Union 
9834 (19.2) 1.40 
Central and Eastern 
Europe </p>

<p>16 982 (33.1) 1.38 </p>

<p>Other European countries 
481 (0.9) 1.80 
North Africa 
8433 (16.4) 1.46 
West Africa 
4533 (8.8) 1.34 
East Africa 
457 (0.9) 1.55 
Central and Southern 
Africa </p>

<p>284 (0.6) 1.28 </p>

<p>Western Asia 
428 (0.8) 1.44 
Central and Southern Asia 
4251 (8.3) 1.45 
East Asia 
3123 (6.1) 1.33 
Northern America 
120 (0.2) 1.67 
Latin America 
2066 (4.0) 1.45 
Oceania 
13 (0.03) 1.62 
Unknown 
316 (0.6) 1.51 </p>

<p>Lenzi J, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e012812. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012812 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>differ from those presented in this study for two possible 
reasons: first, Istat included in multimorbidity count 
some chronic diseases that we did not detect (ie, celiac 
disease, allergies, migraine and osteoporosis); second, 
the Istat survey is based on self-reported information, 
thus possibly overestimating the prevalence of some 
chronic health diseases. 
When we examined each disease separately we found, 
consistently with other studies, that hypertension, dia-
betes and depression were highly prevalent, 
27 28 with 
some variation between genders (ie, hypertension and 
depression more common among women, and diabetes 
more common among men). In general, we found a 
high prevalence of hypertension, diabetes, depression, 
cerebrovascular disease, non-metastatic tumours, chronic 
pulmonary disease, congestive heart failure and myocar-
dial infarction-all diseases that, according to the litera-
ture, should be included in every multimorbidity 
index. </p>

<p>15 29 </p>

<p>As expected, we found that multimorbidity was 
strongly associated with increasing age. This finding cor-
roborates many other studies 
2 3 30 31 and may be 
explained by the longer exposure and increased vulner-
ability in older persons to risk factors for chronic health 
problems. 
3 Age-related multimorbidity has major finan-
cial and social implications, as populations are rapidly 
ageing in most countries, including developing coun-
tries and those in transition. Indeed, the burden of </p>

<p>chronic disease is the biggest financial challenge to 
countries and healthcare systems worldwide. </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>Of interest, immigrants had fewer diseases than Italian 
citizens. A possible explanation is that immigrants, pre-
sumably of first generation and looking for manual jobs 
that require intense physical work, are on average 
healthier than native-born. This phenomenon has been 
defined as the 'healthy immigrant effect'. 
33 34 However, 
it is more plausible that these figures reflect the well-
known lower access of immigrants to healthcare and par-
ticularly specialist healthcare. </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>Using factor analysis, we identified some relevant 
disease patterns. Comparing our results with those of 
other studies is difficult because of different diseases, 
data sources, populations and setting considered. Still, 
like Islam et al, 
28 we found the tumours constitute a dis-
tinct pattern, probably because risk factors for cancer 
may be specific. Moreover, similarly to many other 
studies, 
21 26 27 36 37 we found a strong association 
between cardiovascular, renal, pulmonary and cerebro-
vascular diseases, suggesting that this pattern is part of 
the natural biological and pathological course of these 
illnesses, such as inflammation, hypoxia, oxidative stress 
or ageing, and is related to general risk factors such as 
smoking or pollution. 
38 In line with Barnett et al, 
2 we 
also found that psychiatric disorders tended to correlate 
with each other and were not associated with age. 
Finally, we found a multimorbidity pattern composed of </p>

<p>Figure 1 Prevalence values (%) of single diseases by gender. </p>



<p>Lenzi J, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e012812. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012812 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Figure 2 Prevalence values (%) of single diseases by age group. Notes: Dark blocks represent high prevalence values, 
whereas light blocks represent low prevalence values. Cut-points of percentiles are displayed in the legend. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Number of chronic diseases by age group. Notes: Red dots indicate the prevalence of multimorbidity by age group. </p>

<p>Lenzi J, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e012812. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012812 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>liver diseases (ie, chronic hepatitis and cirrhosis), AIDS/ 
HIV and substance use, which is consistent with evidence 
that liver and infective diseases are common in patients 
with substance use disorder. 
Our results provide useful insights as regards the 
implementation of healthcare policies and the organisa-
tion of healthcare services. Although the evidence base 
for the management of multimorbidity appears to be 
thin and much more research is still needed, 
8 it is now 
well recognised that best practice should focus on the 
prevention of common risk factors and an orientation of </p>

<p>treatment towards the improvement of functional limita-
tions. 
21 These are core functions of primary care profes-
sionals, and particularly of generals practitioners, who 
are asked to have a broad knowledge base, be able to 
coordinate care across a range of different specialist ser-
vices, have good judgement to balance competing prior-
ities, inquire about patient preferences during a 
consultation and, as a whole, refine the treatment to 
multimorbid patients to promote better and more con-
sistent management and self-management of the ill-
nesses. 
6 9 39 Therefore, the high prevalence of </p>

<p>Table 3 Multimorbidity patterns derived from factor analysis </p>

<p>Multimorbidity pattern 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>Psychiatric 
disorders </p>

<p>Cardiovascular, renal, 
pulmonary and 
cerebrovascular diseases </p>

<p>Neurological 
diseases </p>

<p>Liver diseases, 
AIDS/HIV and 
substance use </p>

<p>5 
Tumours </p>

<p>Eigenvalue 
4.42 
3.37 
1.89 
1.34 
1.04 
Proportion of variance 
0.37 
0.28 
0.15 
0.11 
0.09 
Cumulative proportion 
0.37 
0.65 
0.80 
0.91 
1.00 
Condition 
Personality disorders 
0.77 
0.34 
Bipolar disorder 
0.74 
Schizophrenia and psychosis 0.60 
Dysthymia 
0.55 
Anxiety, dissociative and 
somatoform disorders </p>

<p>0.54 </p>

<p>Depression 
0.44 
Other mental disorders 
0.43 
Congestive heart failure 
0.80 
Renal disease 
0.67 
Peripheral vascular disease 
0.61 
Myocardial infarction 
0.56 
Chronic pulmonary disease 
0.54 
Cerebrovascular disease 
0.505 
0.504 
Hypertension 
0.42 
−0.30 
−0.39 
−0.38 
Dementia, including 
Alzheimer's disease </p>

<p>0.32 
0.38 
0.37 </p>

<p>Neurological disorders other 
than paralysis </p>

<p>0.74 </p>

<p>Paralysis 
0.72 
Intellectual disabilities 
0.47 
Liver disease 
0.74 
AIDS/HIV 
0.63 
Substance use disorders 
0.46 
0.55 
Any malignancy, including 
lymphoma and leukaemia, 
except malignant neoplasm 
of skin </p>

<p>0.95 </p>

<p>Metastatic solid tumour 
0.87 
Rheumatic disease 
Peptic ulcer disease 
Diabetes 
Correlation (Spearman's ρ) with: 
Age 
0.08 
0.27 
0.04 
−0.15 
0.02 
Female 
0.10 
−0.12 
0.04 
−0.09 
0.03 
Non-Italian citizenship 
−0.02 
−0.01 
−0.01 
0.05 
−0.004 </p>

<p>Factor loadings&lt;0.30 are not reported. </p>



<p>Lenzi J, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e012812. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012812 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>multimorbidity in older patients underscores the urgent 
need for providing these care interventions on a routine 
delivery system. 
The identification of clustering of conditions in 
patients with multimorbidity is no less important for 
three main reasons: 
21 from an aetiological perspective, 
to understand what makes conditions tend to co-occur 
with the aim to prevent their development in the first 
place; from a clinical perspective, to identify therapeutic 
approaches that allow the tailoring of care for significant 
strata of people with a given condition or combination 
of conditions and from a policy perspective, to target 
more common disease combinations and orient the 
delivery of care with the aim to ensure that the resources 
match the needs of patients of the same cluster. 
The implications of our study need to be interpreted in 
light of the study's limitations. First, the use of administra-
tive data may have underestimated multimorbidity. In 
fact, during the observation period, a number of partici-
pants suffering from chronic diseases (in particular psy-
chiatric disorders) may have never sought care, been 
hospitalised or been prescribed long-term drug therap-
ies. Moreover, the underestimation of multimorbidity 
may have been differential, that is, more pronounced for 
some patients rather than others ( presumably older 
people and immigrants). However, in order to improve 
the accuracy of our estimates, we extended the observa-
tion period to several years and integrated different data 
sources, including hospital records and prescriptions, as 
suggested by other authors. 
40 41 Second, we did not use 
antipsychotic prescriptions to identify patients with 
dementia because these drugs are quite non-specific in 
their effect and are commonly prescribed also for a large 
number of severe psychiatric disorders, including schizo-
phrenia, mania, agitated psychotic depression and para-
noid disorders. Third, hypertension and depression were 
traced using some drugs that are prescribed also for heart 
failure, ischaemic heart disease and neuropathic pain, 
thus increasing the sensitivity of the disease count but 
lowering the specificity. Fourth, it is possible that a study 
period of 10 years, from 2003 to 2012, was not long 
enough to detect thoroughly all chronic diseases, espe-
cially for the elderly, once again possibly underestimating 
the number of morbid and multimorbid patients; an 
excessively long observation period, however, may lead to 
the inclusion of conditions with a prolonged course but 
which are not active at the time of the study. 
23 It is also 
worth noting that our study included the periods preced-
ing and following the global financial crisis, and this may 
have overestimated the prevalence of some diseases 
which we investigated only in the post-crisis period such 
as depression and anxiety; for the same reason, estimates 
may have been inflated to some degree for younger 
people. Fifth, we did not include in the multimorbidity 
count a number of relevant conditions mentioned in sys-
tematic reviews, such as osteoporosis, angina, arthritis, 
cardiac arrhythmia, thyroid disease, anaemia, dyslipidae-
mia and obesity. We are well aware that this issue leads to </p>

<p>an underestimation of multimorbidity and makes com-
parison with other studies difficult; still, our choice was 
conditioned by the fact that these diseases are not 
present in the algorithms developed by Charlson and 
Elixhauser, are managed to a large extent by general 
practitioners and are characterised by differences and 
variety in the case definition. For all these reasons, the 
multimorbidity prevalence estimates calculated in this 
study should be interpreted as the 'lower boundary' for 
the proportion of participants suffering from two or 
more chronic health disorders; to summarise, in 
Emilia-Romagna, the prevalence of multimorbid adults is 
not lower than 15% (40% among the elderly). </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS 
We found that multimorbidity was highly prevalent in 
Emilia-Romagna and strongly associated with age. We 
also found five predominant combinations of chronic 
conditions, suggesting that single disease-oriented clin-
ical guidelines and pathways of care may be less effective 
than patient-centred care. These findings highlight the 
importance of planning studies that evaluate the impact 
of multimorbidity on health outcomes, costs and quality 
of care, and confirm the need for healthcare providers 
to promote access to healthcare, adopt individualised 
care plans and ensure continuity of care for patients 
who suffer from multiple chronic conditions. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank Eleonora Verdini, Luca Cisbani, 
Stefano Sforza and Mila Ferri, from the Emilia-Romagna region, for providing 
data. The authors thank Elisabetta Poluzzi from the University of Bologna for 
her assistance in the development of the algorithm for the identification of 
mental health disorders and Stewart Mercer from the University of Glasgow 
for his assistance in writing the paper. </p>

<p>Contributors JL and MPF made substantial contributions to the conception 
and design, analysis and interpretation of data, drafted the article and revised 
it critically for important intellectual content, and approved final version to be 
published. VMA, PR and MPF were responsible for interpretation of data, 
drafted the article and revised it critically for important intellectual content, 
and approved the final version to be published. GP was involved in 
conception and design, revised the article critically for important intellectual 
content, and approved the final version to be published. MPF is a guarantor 
for the study. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement Statistical code and raw data are available by 
emailing mariapia.fantini@unibo.it. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Lenzi J, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e012812. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012812 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>





<p>Lenzi J, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e012812. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012812 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>