<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5147514" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T16:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. It is well-established that inflammation plays an important role in Alzheimer's disease (AD) and frontotemporal 
lobar dementia (FTLD). Inflammation and synapse loss occur in disease prior to the formation of larger aggregates, but 
the contribution of tau to inflammation has not yet been thoroughly investigated. Tau pathologically aggregates to form 
large fibrillar structures known as tangles. However, evidence suggests that smaller soluble aggregates, called oligomers, are 
the most toxic species and form prior to tangles. Furthermore, tau oligomers can spread to neighboring cells and between 
anatomically connected brain regions. In addition, recent evidence suggests that inspecting the retina may be a window to 
brain pathology. We hypothesized that there is a relationship between tau oligomers and inflammation, which are hallmarks 
of early disease. We conducted immunofluorescence and biochemical analyses on tauopathy mice, FTLD, and AD subjects. 
We showed that oligomers co-localize with astrocytes, microglia, and HMGB1, a pro-inflammatory cytokine. Additionally, 
we show that tau oligomers are present in the retina and are associated with inflammatory cells suggesting that the retina may 
be a valid non-invasive biomarker for brain pathology. These results suggest that there may be a toxic relationship between 
tau oligomers and inflammation. Therefore, the ability of tau oligomers to spread may initiate a feed-forward cycle in which 
tau oligomers induce inflammation, leading to neuronal damage, and thus more inflammation. Further mechanistic studies 
are warranted in order to understand this relationship, which may have critical implications for improving the treatment of 
tauopathies. </p>

<p>In Alzheimer's disease (AD), the increased 
production of amyloid-␤ (A␤), and the altered </p>

<p>1 These authors contributed equally to this work. 
 *  Correspondence to: Rakez Kayed, PhD, Department of Neu-</p>

<p>rology, University of Texas Medical Branch, 301 University 
Blvd, Medical Research Building, Room 10.138C, Galveston, TX 
77555-1045, USA. Tel.: +1 409 772 0138; Fax: +1 409 747 0015; 
E-mail: rakayed@utmb.edu. </p>

<p>processing of the protein tau, are associated with 
synaptic dysfunction and neuronal death that leads 
to cognitive and behavioral deficits. It is becoming 
increasingly apparent that another prominent feature 
of AD brains is inflammation, which has a significant 
influence on disease progression [1]. The majority of 
transgenic mouse models of AD exhibit substantial 
reactive gliosis with the accumulation of activated 
astrocytes and microglia in affected brain regions, 
often prior to the appearance of plaque and tangle </p>

<p>ISSN 1387-2877/17/$35.00 © 2017 -IOS Press and the authors. All rights reserved </p>

<p>This article is published online with Open Access and distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (CC BY-NC 4.0). </p>



<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>pathology [2]. The severity of inflammation in many 
of these animals correlates with neuronal death [2], 
and moreover, the local inflammatory environment 
directly influences the rate of disease progression and 
the extent of neuronal loss [3]. Recent data shows 
that astrocyte-mediated inflammatory responses play 
a significant role in mediating neurotoxic responses 
to A␤ [4]. Importantly, these results suggest that dis-
rupting inflammatory signaling, in combination with 
other therapies such as anti-oligomer therapies, could 
provide a novel neuroprotective intervention for AD 
and related diseases. 
The pathological aggregation of the microtubule-
associated protein, tau, culminates in large insoluble 
aggregates known as neurofibrillary tangles (NFTs) 
and other inclusions containing hyperphosphorylated 
tau. These aggregates are the defining histopatholog-
ical features of AD and other tauopathies, including 
frontotemporal lobar dementia with tau (FTLD-tau), 
Pick's disease, and corticobasal degeneration [5]. 
FTLD encompasses a broad spectrum of distinct 
pathologies and protein aggregations that mani-
fest with similar symptoms, ranging from primary 
tauopathy to transactive response DNA/RNA bind-
ing protein-43 (TDP-43) or Fus positive inclusions 
[6, 7]. In FTLD-TDP there are TDP-43 positive, 
␣-synuclein negative, and tau negative inclusions. 
They typically do not have extensive tangle pathol-
ogy [8], but little to no research has been conducted 
on smaller tau oligomers in FTLD-TDP which we 
have investigated here. Recent research has shown 
that the NFTs themselves are not the most toxic 
form of tau, but rather the smaller aggregates called 
tau oligomers likely initiate neurodegeneration in 
tauopathies [9-23]. 
Inspection of the retina has been suggested as a 
potential biomarker for the diagnosis of neurode-
generation [24-26]. There is a higher incidence of 
age-related macular degeneration in patients with 
AD [27]. While the link remains unclear between 
retinal degeneration and neurodegeneration, there is 
increasing evidence that they may be linked. Tau 
oligomers were recently found in the retina of a rat 
model for glaucoma and suppression of tau reduced 
the occurrence of retinal degeneration [28]. Also, 
there is evidence of large protein deposits, such 
as A␤ and tau, being present in the retina of AD 
patients and in tauopathy mice as well as the pres-
ence of inflammation [24-26, 29, 30]. Early detection 
of AD, possibly even prodromal detection, would 
allow for the early intervention and prevention of 
neurodegeneration prior to major synapse loss and </p>

<p>cognitive decline. Using the retina for the detection 
of both retinal damage and AD would also be non-
invasive, inexpensive, and could be translated into the 
clinic as part of a normal screening done at patient 
checkups. 
Inflammation is a critical marker of neurodegen-
erative diseases, in addition to protein aggregates. 
Inflammation and cell death occur prior to, or inde-
pendently, from the formation of NFTs in AD and 
in transgenic mouse models [9, 12, 13, 15, 31]. 
Therefore, it is likely that tau oligomers, which form 
prior to NFTs, may be causing the inflammation 
[23]. This inflammatory response may induce a self-
perpetuating cycle, whereby tau oligomers increase 
inflammation, causing more damage to the neurons, 
which in turn may increase the rate of oligomer for-
mation. Furthermore, a majority of transgenic mouse 
models of AD exhibit astrogliosis and microgliosis 
in affected brain regions, often prior to the appear-
ance of plaque and tangle pathology [2]. The severity 
of inflammation in many of these animals correlates 
with neuronal death [2]. Moreover, the local inflam-
matory environment directly influences the rate of 
disease progression and the extent of neuronal loss 
[3, 32], suggesting that disrupting inflammatory sig-
naling, in addition to removing tau oligomers, could 
provide a novel neuroprotective intervention for neu-
rodegenerative diseases. 
Neuroinflammation is often thought to be a 
response induced by A␤ in AD [3, 32], given this, 
there are few reports investigating the role of tau 
oligomers in neuroinflammation. The studies that 
have investigated tau indicate tau may play a role in 
neuroinflammation and may be an early contributor 
to neurodegeneration [33, 34]. These results warrant 
further investigation. Thus, we used tauopathy mice 
and postmortem FTLD-TDP, and AD brain samples 
to study tau oligomers and inflammation. The tauopa-
thy mice that we used contained the P301L mutation, 
which is implicated in some genetic tauopathies. 
In addition, this mutation, along with the related 
P301S mutation, has been associated with increased 
inflammation in the brain as well as retinal deficits 
[24, 33]. However, these events were investigated 
in isolation and were not investigated thoroughly 
to determine if they are linked. Also, FTLD-TDP 
samples were used because they do not have A␤ 
plaques or tau tangles, thus removing these conditions 
as potential confounding factors for inflammation. 
Additionally, tau oligomers have never been exam-
ined in FTLD-TDP and may play a role in the late 
stages of the disease. Thus, we used this model to </p>

<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>



<p>determine the role tau oligomers play in inflamma-
tion in the absence of A␤ and NFTs. We hypothesized 
that tau oligomers play a role in the feed forward 
cycle of neuroinflammation in neurodegenerative 
tauopathies. We performed systematic immunohis-
tochemical and biochemical analyses of brain tissue 
from transgenic tau mice and FTLD patients. Anal-
yses were performed using a tau oligomer-specific 
antibody in combination with antibodies for inflam-
matory markers, including astrocytes and microglia. 
Our data shows that tau oligomers are associated with 
markers for neuroinflammation suggesting that tau 
oligomers may play a role in a feed forward mecha-
nisms resulting in chronic neuroinflammation. These 
descriptive results call attention to the important and 
novel role tau oligomers may play in inflammation 
and in accelerating neurodegeneration. Furthermore, 
these results validate the potential of the retina to be 
used as biomarker of neurodegeneration. This study 
demonstrates a need to identify and characterize the 
relationship and mechanism behind the association 
of tau oligomers and inflammation. Perhaps, dis-
rupting this association through anti-oligomer and 
anti-inflammatory combination therapies can slow 
the progression, or even halt, neurodegenerative 
tauopathies. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Tissue harvesting and preparation </p>

<p>Animals were handled in accordance with proto-
cols approved by the Institutional Animal Care and 
Use Committee at the University of Texas Medical 
Branch. Animals were euthanized with CO 2 and per-
fused transcardially with ice-cold phosphate buffered 
saline (PBS). Brains and eyes were collected and snap 
frozen. They were stored at -80 • C. The right eye 
and hemisphere were homogenized, while the left 
hemisphere and eye were sectioned. Briefly, frozen 
tissues were diced and homogenized in PBS with a 
protease inhibitor mixture (Roche, Indianapolis, IN) 
and 0.02% NaN3 using a 1:3 mass: volume dilution 
ratio. Samples were then centrifuged at 10,000 rpm 
for 10 min at 4 • C. The supernatants were divided into 
aliquots, snap-frozen, and stored at -80 • C until use. 
Postmortem human brain tissues were homogenized 
by the same protocol. Human samples were obtained 
from the Oregon Brain Bank and were collected 
by that institution following approved protocols and 
laws regarding human tissue. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence </p>

<p>Immunofluorescent labeling was conducted on 
frozen cortical brain sections of Htau (Jackson 
Laboratory, stock #004808, n = 3), and wildtype 
(WT) (Taconic, BALB/c, n = 2) mice as well as 
brain samples from FTLD (n = 4), AD (n = 4), and 
age-matched controls (n = 4) (Oregon Brain Bank). 
P301L (Taconic, stock #2508, n = 3) mouse eye 
sections were also used. Immunofluorescence was 
conducted as previously published [35]. Briefly, the 
sections were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde, per-
meabilized in 0.5% Triton-X 100 (Sigma-Aldrich, 
St. Louis, MO), and the human sections were treated 
with an autofluorescence eliminator as per manufac-
turer instructions (Millipore, Darmstadt, Germany). 
Mouse and human sections were blocked in 3% 
bovine serum albumin (Fisher Scientific, Pittsburgh, 
PA), and were then incubated with tau oligomer-
specific polycolonal antibody T22 (mouse-1:250, 
human-1:200, [22]) in 4 • C overnight. The following 
day, the sections were incubated with goat anti-rabbit 
IgG Alexa-488 or Alexa-568 (1:500, Invitrogen, 
Waltham, MA) for 1 h. Sections were then incubated 
overnight with glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) 
(mouse and human-1:150, BioLegend, San Diego, 
CA), Iba1 (mouse and human-1:100, Abcam, 
Cambridge, MA), or high motility group box 1 
(HMGB1) (Mouse-1:50, Abcam, human-1:500, 
Sigma-Aldrich) at 4 • C. The sections were incubated 
with goat anti-mouse IgG Alexa-568 (1:500, Invitro-
gen) or goat anti-rabbit 568 for 1 h. The sections were 
stained with 4 ,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) 
(Invitrogen) and mounted in Fluoromount-G (South-
ernBiotech, Birmingham, AL). The retinal slides 
were imaged with a confocal LSM510 Zeiss laser 
scanning microscope (Carl Zeiss, Thornwood, NY, 
USA) as a single digital image. The brain sections 
were imaged on a Nikon A1R MP laser scanning 
microscope (Nikon, Melville, NY) at 60X magnifi-
cation under oil submersion. The objective numerical 
aperture was 1.4. Using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs>, the corrected cell 
fluorescence method was used to quantify the images 
as previously described [35, 36]. Briefly, there were 
four separate images from each section analyzed 
using this method where five cells were measured as 
well as five background regions. In order to account 
for cell size and background, the background was 
multiplied by the area of the cell and subtracted from 
the total fluorescence. One-way ANOVA, student's 
t-tests, or Pearson's correlation were used to analyze 
the corrected cell fluorescence on Graphpad Prism </p>



<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>6 (Graphpad Software, La Jolla, CA). In addition, 
Pearson's correlation coefficient was measured to 
quantify the strength of co-localization between T22 
and GFAP using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software. </p>

<p>ELISA </p>

<p>An enzyme linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) 
was conducted to detect the astrocyte marker, GFAP, 
and total tau. All measurements were performed in 
triplicate. Plates were coated with 30 g/well using 
0.05 M sodium bicarbonate, pH 9.6, as coating 
buffer, followed by overnight incubation at 4 • C. Age-
matched control (n = 4), FTLD (n = 4), and AD (n = 4) 
brains obtained from the Oregon Brain bank, were 
used in the ELISA. Negative and positive controls 
were conducted. The positive control was Tg2576 
insoluble brain homogenate with 0.05% Triton-X in 
PBS. Plates were washed 1 time with Tris-buffered 
saline with low Tween (0.01%) (TBST), then blocked 
for 2 h at room temperature with 10% nonfat dry 
milk in TBST. The plates were then washed with 
TBST 1 time. Anti-GFAP (1:2000, Covance, Prince-
ton, NJ) was diluted in 5% nonfat milk in TBST 
and added to one plate. Anti-Tau5 (1:1000, Mil-
lipore), diluted in 5% nonfat milk in TBST, was 
added to another plate and all were allowed to react 
for 1 h at room temperature. The plates were then 
washed 3 times with TBST and 100 l of horseradish 
peroxidase-conjugated anti-mouse IgG (1:3000, Bio-
Rad, Hercules, CA) was added. The plates were 
incubated for 1 h at room temperature. Finally, plates 
were washed 3 times with TBST and developed 
with 3,3',5,5',-tetramethylbenzidine substrate from 
DAKO (Carpentaria, CA). The reaction was stopped 
with 100 l 1 M HCl, and samples were read at 
450 nm using a POLARstar OMEGA plate reader 
(BMG Labtechnologies, Ortenberg, Germany). One-
way ANOVA with a multiple comparisons test was 
used to analyze results on <rs id="software-4" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">6</rs> (Graph-
Pad Software). </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Images were quantified using corrected cell flu-
orescence, as described previously [35, 36]. Four 
images per subject were obtained and five cells were 
outlined and measured in each image. To account 
for both background and the size of the cell, five 
background measurements were also taken and the 
background fluorescence was multiplied by the area. 
This was subtracted from the total intensity for the </p>

<p>cell in order to obtain a corrected cell fluorescence. 
The corrected cell fluorescence for five cells per 
image were averaged and a One-Way ANOVA with a 
multiple comparisons test was conducted to compare 
control (n = 4, 20 cells quantified), FTLD (n = 4, 20 
cells quantified), and AD (n = 4, 20 cells quantified). 
A student's unpaired t-test was used for the mouse 
quantifications with two groups while a One-Way 
ANOVA was used for the mouse samples with more 
than two groups. For the ELISA, One-Way ANOVA 
was used with multiple comparisons test. All statis-
tics were performed on <rs type="software">GraphPad Prism6</rs> (GraphPad 
Software) and p &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>P301L mouse retina exhibits inflammation in 
association with tau oligomers </p>

<p>Tau abnormalities in the retina of transgenic 
animals have been investigated extensively, but 
the association of tau oligomers with inflam-
mation remains unknown. We investigated the 
co-localization of tau oligomers with inflammatory 
markers in the retina of an aggressive tauopathy 
mouse model, P301L. T22 is a novel conformational 
polyclonal antibody developed by our laboratory. 
It recognizes tau oligomers but does not recognize 
tau monomers or fibrils [22, 37]. We discovered the 
presence of activated astrocytes in the retina, associ-
ated with oligomeric tau aggregates. We also found 
that tau oligomers are present in the outer nuclear 
layer of the eye, localized in close proximity to acti-
vated astrocyte processes in the outer plexiform layer 
(Fig. 1). 
In order to further characterize the pattern of 
inflammation and tau oligomer pathology in the eye 
of transgenic tau mice, we investigated the presence 
of activated microglia and tau oligomers in the rod 
outer segment (ROS) of the eye. Labeling the P301L 
mouse retina with T22, Iba1, and DAPI revealed 
microglial cells co-localizing with tau oligomers in 
the ROS (Fig. 1). There was also evidence of hyper-
activation and proliferation of microglial cells at the 
ROS and retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) cell lay-
ers. Activation of microglia was seen throughout 
the retina of P301L transgenic mice. Of note, are 
small cell bodies with irregular, short, cell processes 
that are present near the deposits of T22 positive 
tau oligomers. Co-localization of the microglia with 
tau oligomers may indicate the engulfment of the </p>

<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>



<p>Fig. 1. Analysis of the P301L tau transgenic mouse model retina demonstrates the presence of tau oligomers and an association with 
inflammatory cells. A, B) The retina was stained for tau oligomers (T22, red), astrocytes (GFAP, green), and the nucleus (DAPI). A) The glial 
cell processes of Muller cells are shown extending to the outer nuclear cells. The co-localizing of mutant tau oligomers with the Muller cell 
processes concurs with the phagocytic nature of the Muller cells in a pathologic event. Both thick and thin ramifications of the Muller cell 
processes are noted throughout the outer nuclear layer (ONL) and as well as in close apposition to the outer limiting membrane. Also noted, 
were multiple small cell bodies of the Muller cells in the inner nuclear layer (INL), with some dendritic spurs towards the ganglion cell layers. 
The arrowhead in (A) indicates where tau oligomers were co-localizing with GFAP positive Muller cell processes near the rod outer segment 
(ROS). B) Mutant tau oligomers were observed in the ONL near glial cell processes in the outer plexiform layer (OPL). Arrows indicate the 
position of the tau oligomers in the ONL. C, D) P301L mouse model retina stained for tau oligomers (T22, red), microglia (Iba1, green), and 
DAPI. C) Staining revealed microglia cells co-localizing with mutant tau oligomers in the ROS. It is clear that there is hyper-activation and 
proliferation of microglia cells at the ROS and retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) cell layer. Activation of microglial cells were seen throughout 
the retina of the P301L transgenic mouse model. Of note, were the small cell bodies with irregular short cell processes that were present in 
increased numbers near the deposits of tau oligomers. Also, co-localization of the microglia with tau oligomers were observed, suggesting 
the engulfment of the oligomers by the activated microglial cells. D) Microglia cells co-localized with mutant tau oligomers in the ONL of 
the retina. GCL-ganglion cell layer. </p>



<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>oligomers by the activated microglia. Additionally, 
we detected glial cell processes of Muller cells 
extending to the outer nuclear cells, co-localizing 
with mutant tau oligomers, and concurring with the 
phagocytic nature of the Muller cells in a patholog-
ical event (Fig. 1). Both thick and thin ramifications 
of the Muller cell processes were noted throughout 
the outer nuclear layer, as well as in close apposi-
tion to the outer limiting membrane. Also noted were 
multiple small cell bodies of Muller cells in the inner 
nuclear layer, with some dendritic spurs towards the 
ganglion cell layers. These findings help support the 
idea that eyes can be used as a means to study some 
of the pathological changes in the central nervous 
system. </p>

<p>FTLD, AD subjects, and Htau mice exhibit 
an association between inflammation and tau 
oligomers </p>

<p>Frozen frontal cortical brain sections from FTLD, 
AD, and age-matched controls were analyzed with 
immunofluorescent staining. We found that tau 
oligomers were surrounded by the astrocyte marker, 
GFAP. Additionally, there was a significant increase 
in GFAP protein levels as compared to the control 
(Fig. 2). It is important to note that GFAP did not 
appear to co-localize with tau oligomers directly, 
yet GFAP was in close proximity suggesting that 
tau oligomers are interacting with astrocytes but not 
engulfing the tau oligomers. The astrocytes appear to 
be surrounding the tau oligomer containing cells but 
not fully internalizing the tau oligomers (Fig. 2F, I). 
To more accurately quantify GFAP protein levels and 
total tau protein, we conducted a direct ELISA. We 
found that in FTLD and AD, astrocyte levels were 
significantly higher than in the age-matched controls 
(Fig. 2J). However, total tau was not significantly 
different between age-matched controls, FTLD, and 
AD suggesting a gain of function toxicity for the tau 
oligomers rather than increased toxicity due to the 
upregulation of tau protein. 
In order to confirm and further validate the asso-
ciation between astrocytes and tau oligomers we 
used the Htau mouse model. The Htau mouse model 
was used here because it expresses all six human 
tau isoforms without expressing mouse tau mak-
ing it a better model for sporadic tauopathy. In 
addition, Htau mice have been shown to have neu-
roinflammation previously allowing us to investigate 
if this inflammation can be linked to tau oligomers 
[34]. Using immunofluorescence of cortical regions </p>

<p>with GFAP and T22 tau oligomer-specific antibod-
ies, we found that the number of astrocytes in Htau 
mice changes with age and in comparison to WT 
mice (Fig. 3). Seven-month-old WT mice exhibited 
low levels of reactive astrocytes and negligible tau 
oligomer staining. We showed that at 3 months of 
age, Htau mice have only limited astrocyte activa-
tion, but by 11 months, Htau mice begin to show 
evidence of fragmented astrocytes, as well as some 
reactive morphology. Astrocyte activation is dramat-
ically increased when tau oligomers are present at 
higher levels in the brains of 24-month-old Htau 
mice. GFAP corrected cell fluorescence was signifi-
cantly increased in the brains of Htau mice, increasing 
with the age of the mice as well as in comparison 
to the WT mice. Additionally, there was a positive 
correlation between GFAP and T22 corrected cell flu-
orescence regardless of age or genotype (r = 0.662, 
r 2 = 0.439, p &lt; 0.01). These data suggest a possible 
interaction between tau oligomers and reactive astro-
cytes in inflammation. 
The FTLD, AD, and control subject frontal cortical 
sections were stained for tau oligomers and microglia. 
Tau oligomers co-localized with microglia in FTLD 
and AD subjects, suggesting that tau oligomers may 
play a role in stimulating inflammation (Fig. 4). In 
contrast to the astrocytes, co-localization suggests 
internalization of the tau oligomers. Microglial quan-
tification by corrected cell fluorescence also showed 
a significant increase in Iba1 in FTLD and AD, 
which is common in inflammation and neurodegen-
erative diseases. Next, we examined the relationship 
of microglia and tau oligomers in Htau cortices. 
We used Iba1 and T22 to immunolabel brains from 
WT and Htau mice. We found little evidence of 
microglial activation in WT mice and negligible 
labeling for tau oligomers, as expected for a WT 
animal. However, in Htau mice at 24 months of 
age, a significant increase in activated microglia was 
detected, largely co-localizing with tau oligomers 
(Fig. 5). This was consistent with the results seen 
in the human cases and indicates a potential inter-
play between toxic oligomeric tau and microglia. In 
addition, this co-localization could indicate that tau 
oligomers are being internalized by the microglia, 
which may increase the spread of pathology [38]. 
To further characterize inflammation, we investi-
gated the association of tau oligomers with the chro-
matin protein, high motility group box 1 (HMGB1). 
HMGB1 is a protein normally found within the 
nucleus of cells that are not undergoing inflammatory 
processes. During inflammation, however, HMGB1 </p>

<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>



<p>Fig. 2. Astrocytes are associated with tau oligomers in the frontal cortex of FTLD and AD. A-I) There was increased staining of the astrocyte 
marker GFAP (red) in FTLD and AD sections as compared to control. F, I) Inset images are enlarged to show how astrocytes surround the 
T22 positive tau oligomer (green) containing cell. J) Control, FTLD, and AD homogenates were analyzed by direct ELISA with GFAP. 
GFAP levels increased significantly in FTLD and AD brains compared to control. K) The co-localization of T22 positive tau oligomers and 
GFAP was measured using Pearson's correlation coefficient. Pearson's correlation coefficient was significantly greater in FTLD and AD 
images when compared to controls.  *  p &lt; 0.05,  *  *  p &lt; 0.01,  *  *  *  p &lt; 0.001. Scale bar 20 m. </p>



<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>30000 
10000 </p>

<p>5000 </p>

<p>-5000 </p>

<p>10000 
20000 
30000 </p>

<p>20000 </p>

<p>10000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-10000 </p>

<p>Fluorescent Intensity (AU) </p>

<p>W 
il d t y p e 
3 </p>

<p>m 
o n t h s </p>

<p>1 1 </p>

<p>m 
o n t h s </p>

<p>2 4 </p>

<p>m 
o n t h s </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Immunofluorescence analysis of the human tau transgenic mouse model demonstrates an age-dependent increase in tau oligomers 
and astrocytes in cortical tissues. A-C) WT mice exhibit low astrocyte levels, low levels of reactive astrocytes, and negligible T22 positive 
tau oligomer (green) staining. D-L) There was an age dependent increase in astrocyte marker GFAP (red) and T22 positive tau oligomers 
at 11 and 24 months of age. D-F) At 3 months, Htau mice have limited astrocyte activation. G-I) At 11 months of age, Htau mice begin to 
show evidence of fragmented astrocytes, as well as an increased abundance of both astrocytes and tau oligomers in comparison to WT and 
3-month-old Htau mice. J-L) Astrocyte activation is dramatically increased with T22 positive tau oligomers in the brain tissue of 24-month-
old Htau mice. M) Quantified GFAP intensity using corrected cell fluorescence. ANOVA with multiple comparisons showed a significant 
difference between WT and 24-month-old Htau mice. 24-month-old Htau mice were also significantly higher than 3-month-old Htau mice. 
There was a steady increase in GFAP as the Htau mice aged, consistent with astrogliosis and disease progression. N) As GFAP increased, T22 
positive tau oligomer staining also increased with WT and 3-month-old Htau mice in the lower left portion of the correlation and increasing 
with the 24-month-old mice as shown in the upper right. There was a moderate correlation between GFAP and T22 positive tau oligomer 
staining (r = 0.662, r 2 = 0.439, p &lt; 0.01).  *  *  *  *  p &lt; 0.0001,  *  *  *  p &lt; 0.001. Scale bar 20 m. </p>

<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>



<p>Fig. 4. Microglia co-localized with tau oligomers in the frontal cortex of FTLD and AD. A-I) Microglia Iba1 (red) staining increased in FTLD 
and AD compared to control and co-localized with T22 positive tau oligomers (green). D-F) Representative FTLD sections. Enlargement in 
(F) shows microglia co-localizing with T22 positive tau oligomers suggesting engulfment of oligomers by microglia. G-I) Representative 
AD images also showed co-localization between T22 positive tau oligomers and microglia. J) Iba1 corrected cell fluorescence showed 
significantly elevated levels of Iba1 in FTLD and AD compared to controls, indicating microgliosis.  *  *  p &lt; 0.01. Scale bar 20 m. </p>



<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Microglia co-localized with tau oligomers in an aged human tau transgenic mouse model but not in wildtype mouse cortical brain 
regions. A-C) Minimal microglia Iba1 (red) activation was observed in WT mice. D-F) An increase in activated microglia detected by Iba1 
was seen co-localizing with T22 positive tau oligomers (green) in 24-month-old Htau mice. A few examples of microglia co-localizing with 
T22 positive tau oligomers are indicated by the arrows. G) 24-month-old Htau mice had significantly higher Iba1 compared to WT according 
to corrected cell fluorescence.  *  *  p &lt; 0.01. Scale bar 20 m. </p>

<p>can translocate from the nucleus to the cytosol and can 
then be secreted as a pro-inflammatory cytokine. We 
conducted T22 and HMGB1 immunofluorescence on 
tissues from the frontal cortex of FTLD, AD, and age-
matched controls. HMGB1 localized to the cytoplasm 
rather than the nucleus, as was seen in the control sub-
jects indicating inflammatory signaling in the FTLD 
and AD subjects (Fig. 6). HMGB1 showed signifi-</p>

<p>cantly increased corrected cell fluorescence in FTLD 
and AD samples compared to controls. The increase 
in HMGB1 and its translocation to the cytoplasm 
indicate it has been activated as a pro-inflammatory 
signal in FTLD and AD brains. The co-localization 
of tau oligomers with HMGB1 suggests there may be 
an interaction between tau oligomers and inflamma-
tory signaling. To further characterize the relationship </p>

<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>



<p>Fig. 6. Tau oligomers co-localized with HMGB1 in the frontal cortex of FTLD and AD subjects. A-C) Control subjects showed HMGB1 
(red) in proximity to the nucleus (enlargement in C). D-F) FTLD samples displayed HMGB1 translocated out of the nucleus (enlargement in 
F). T22 positive tau oligomers (green) were co-localized with HMGB1 in FTLD. G-I) AD frontal cortex showed a consistent co-localization 
between HMGB1 and T22 positive tau oligomers as seen in FTLD. J) There were significantly elevated levels of HMGB1 in FTLD and AD 
brains compared to controls that were quantified using corrected cell fluorescence.  *  p &lt; 0.05,  *  *  *  *  p &lt; 0.0001. Scale bar 20 m. </p>



<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Altered localization of HMGB1in aged human tau transgenic mouse cortical tissue compared to wildtype. HMGB1 co-localized 
with tau oligomers. A-C) HMGB1 (red) was detected primarily co-localizing with the nucleus (arrow) in WT mice with negligible T22 
positive tau oligomers (green). D-F) HMGB1 translocated out of the nuclei (arrowhead) in 24-month-old Htau mice, representative of the 
activation of HMGB1 as a pro-inflammatory cytokine. Enlargement in (D-F) illustrates the translocation of HMGB1 out of the nucleus and 
co-localization with T22 positive tau oligomers. G) The HMGB1 corrected cell fluorescence showed a significant increase in aged Htau 
compared to WT. This is consistent with HMGB1 translocating to the cytoplasm during inflammatory signaling.  *  p &lt; 0.05. Scale bar 20 m. </p>

<p>of HMGB1 and tau oligomers in the cortex we con-
ducted immunofluorescence in WT and Htau mice. 
We found that HMGB1 was detected at low levels 
that were, primarily, associated with the nucleus in 
WT mice (Fig. 7). HMGB1 was transported out of 
the nuclei in 24-month-old Htau mice, a condition 
that was representative of the activation of HMGB1 as </p>

<p>an inflammatory cytokine. These results were consis-
tent with those seen in the brains of human subjects. 
However, tau oligomers co-localized with HMGB1 
to a much lesser extent in mice as compared to the 
human samples, suggesting the relationship between 
tau oligomers and the pro-inflammatory cytokine 
HMGB1 may be different between species or that </p>

<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>



<p>the relationship is more complex. These results war-
rant further research to determine more specifically 
the mechanisms in human subjects. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>A growing body of evidence suggests that large 
meta-stable tau aggregates, including NFTs, are not 
causally linked to tauopathy phenotypes and appear 
after neuronal toxicity [9-23], suggesting that solu-
ble tau oligomers may underlie early disease stages. 
We recently demonstrated that tau oligomers form 
prior to NFTs, are present intra-and extracellularly, 
are highly toxic, induce cognitive deficits in vivo, 
and play a crucial role in neuronal cytopathology 
[11, 22, 39, 40]. We also established the specificity 
and efficacy of one tau oligomer-specific monoclonal 
antibody that recognizes a conformationally distinct 
subset of tau oligomers in the same tauopathy ani-
mal models used in the present study: aged P301L 
mice [41, 42] and Htau mice [43, 44]. Furthermore, 
we published evidence that tau oligomer transfor-
mation into pore-like structures is cell-specific and 
disease-specific [45]. In addition we were able to 
isolate, characterize, and propagate tau oligomers 
from postmortem brain tissue of patients with var-
ious neurodegenerative diseases, as well as, patients 
with traumatic brain injury [35, 36, 44]. 
Our results demonstrate that tau oligomers may 
induce inflammation in FTLD, AD, and potentially, 
other neurodegenerative diseases, thus linking tau 
oligomer deposition to inflammatory signaling in 
the brain. It is interesting that our results suggest 
that astrocytes interact with tau oligomers but do 
not appear to engulf them, while microglia showed 
extensive co-localization. This is consistent with data 
in current literature that indicates that microglia can 
engulf tau oligomers and secrete them in exosomes, 
facilitating their propagation to surrounding cells 
[38]. Tau oligomers and inflammation may be self-
reinforcing stimuli leading to chronic inflammation, 
physiological impairments, cellular dysfunction, 
and ultimately, neurodegeneration. Additionally, the 
spread of tau oligomers from one brain region to 
another [37, 46, 47] may initiate inflammation, induc-
ing a toxic cycle of tau oligomers, inflammation, and 
cell death in larger anatomical areas (Fig. 8). This 
suggests that the propagation of tau oligomers may 
also propagate inflammation and increase the rate 
of degeneration. Future studies characterizing the 
inflammation phenotypes specific to tau oligomers </p>

<p>in FTLD, AD, and other neurodegenerative diseases 
should elucidate the mechanism and confirm that 
tau oligomers are inducing the inflammation. Our 
results are novel in that they associate tau oligomers 
specifically with inflammation, a process that occurs 
early in disease pathogenesis, and they lay the foun-
dation for future studies to explore this relationship. 
Further studies should be done to investigate whether 
inflammation can induce oligomer production, 
which would contribute to this vicious cycle. Our 
results confirm inflammation as a contributing factor 
to the neurodegenerative disease cascade, and they 
have implications for therapeutic approaches [32]. 
Moreover, the findings reported here, and by other 
investigators, regarding retinal damage in tau trans-
genic mice provide a basis for the under-reported 
visual deficits in these animals [30]. These data also 
provide evidence that detecting neurodegeneration 
may be possible by detecting retinal damage. Devel-
opment of non-invasive techniques to detect early 
neurodegeneration is essential for the advancement 
of therapies. Our descriptive data shown here call for 
the characterization of eye pathology in neurodegen-
erative diseases such as FTLD and AD in order to 
determine how the retina changes throughout disease 
progression. Perhaps, non-invasive eye examinations 
could be used as a diagnostic for the detection of these 
diseases. 
Another exciting result from our research is the dis-
covery of the association between tau oligomers and 
HMGB1, which is an important mediator for inflam-
mation in the brain, as well as peripherally. HMGB1 
has been well-established as a pro-inflammatory 
cytokine when it is released into the extracellu-
lar space and is produced by neurons, astrocytes, 
and microglia [48-50]. In addition, astrocytes and 
microglia can respond to HMGB1 by producing pro-
inflammatory conditions, which is suggested to play 
an important role in neuroinflammation in neurode-
generative diseases [51-53]. HMGB1 is an important 
pro-inflammatory cytokine, but it has also been impli-
cated in a necrotic cell death response [54, 55]. 
Following acute injuries, such as ischemic brain 
insults, HMGB1 is translocated out of the nucleus 
and appears to play a role in necrosis or necropto-
sis (programed cell death in response to injury) [55]. 
However, it is unlikely that the HMGB1 response 
seen here is necrosis related due to that fact that 
neurodegeneration is a process lasting many years to 
many decades. Rather, it is much more likely that the 
HMGB1 translocation out of the nucleus is stimulat-
ing the pro-inflammatory signaling pathways leading </p>



<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>Fig. 8. A hypothetical model of the toxic relationship between tau oligomers and inflammation. A) Tau oligomers can spread from brain 
region to brain region, potentially triggering inflammation and the secretion of pro-inflammatory cytokines by interacting with astrocytes 
and microglia. The inflammation may become chronic, resulting in further damage to the neurons and in turn, increased inflammation and 
eventual cell death. B) RAGE, a potential receptor for tau oligomers, signals NFB through several pathways including through RAS and 
p38. This increases the production of both RAGE and its ligand, HMGB1, initiating a feed-forward mechanism producing a state of chronic 
inflammation. Additionally, p38 is known to phosphorylate tau and may increase the abundance of hyperphosphorylated tau, which is more 
prone to aggregate into oligomers. This may, in turn, induce more inflammation through the production of more oligomers. </p>

<p>to the chronic state of inflammation that is a known 
characteristic of most neurodegenerative diseases. 
One of several possible pathways by which 
HMGB1 may be acting as a pro-inflammatory 
cytokine is through the receptor for advanced glyca-
tion end products (RAGE). RAGE is a multi-ligand 
receptor that binds HMGB1, A␤, and advanced 
glycation end products [56]. It is possible that 
RAGE may also bind tau oligomers and initi-
ate pro-inflammatory signaling through the RAS, 
p38, and nuclear factor-B (NFB) pathway [56]. 
The NFB transcription factor increases the expres-
sion of HMGB1 and its receptor RAGE, increasing </p>

<p>pro-inflammatory RAGE signaling by a feed-forward 
mechanism [57, 58]. HMGB1 is well established as 
a pro-inflammatory cytokine, which can induce the 
production of other cytokines through the NFB path-
way [59]. Figure 8 illustrates a hypothetical model 
for these interactions. Tau oligomers may interact 
with astrocytes and microglia to induce inflammation, 
potentially through RAGE signaling. This inflam-
mation, in turn, damages neurons resulting in more 
inflammation. In addition, signaling via the RAGE 
receptor on the surface of neurons can activate p38, 
which is known to phosphorylate tau, and may 
increase the presence of hyperphosphorylated tau. </p>

<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>



<p>Hyperphosphorylated tau is more prone to aggregate, 
leading to the production of more oligomers that can 
produce their own toxicity and induce further inflam-
mation. Our results implicate HMGB1 as a possible 
key player in tau-induced inflammation and toxic-
ity, and therefore, further investigation of its role in 
tauopathies and brain injuries are warranted. Thus, 
the association of tau oligomers with cells producing 
and secreting HMGB1 could have important implica-
tions for inflammation associated with tauopathies. 
Finally, the existence of tau oligomers in FTLD-
TDP is a novel finding since FTLD-TDP is associated 
with TDP-43 inclusions rather than tau inclusions. 
These results may be relevant to disease progres-
sion, and it would be interesting to investigate the 
temporal appearance of tau oligomers and disease 
progression. It is likely that the appearance of tau 
oligomers is a late occurrence in FTLD-TDP due to 
the lack of larger insoluble aggregates of tau in this 
disease. However, it is also possible that the oligomers 
are more stable in FTLD-TDP, thus prolonging their 
toxic longevity and inhibiting the formation of the 
less-toxic fibrils. The specificity of the T22 antibody 
has been established in previous studies. We found 
that it reliably and specifically detects tau oligomers 
[22, 35-37, 39]. 
In summary, our results demonstrate increased 
deposition of tau oligomers and neuroinflammation 
in the retina and brain tissue from tauopathy mice 
and from patients with FTLD-TDP and AD. The 
tau oligomer pathology and inflammation in the ani-
mal models showed a clear association. Furthermore, 
there is promise in the development of non-invasive 
eye examinations for the early detection of neurode-
generative diseases. Additionally, these results can 
be translated into FTLD and AD, and they indicate 
that tau oligomers are associated with inflammation. 
The descriptive results shown here demonstrate a 
novel association between tau oligomers and inflam-
mation. However, the mechanism and pathways that 
associate tau oligomers and inflammation need to 
be elucidated, and this should be a priority for neu-
roinflammation and neurodegeneration researchers. 
Moreover, these results suggests that the degenera-
tion of neurons due to chronic inflammation induced 
by tau oligomers may be inhibited through the com-
bination of anti-tau oligomer and anti-inflammatory 
therapeutics for the treatment of AD and other 
tauopathies. This combination would inhibit the pro-
posed feed forward cycle shown in Fig. 8 from two 
different angles, tau oligomers and inflammatory 
signaling. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by the Mitchell 
Center for Neurodegenerative Disease, the University 
of Texas System Neuroscience and Neurotechnology 
Research Institute and Retina Research Foundation 
(R.K. and W.Z.), NIH grants AG054025 (R.K.) and 
EY022694 (W.Z). We thank the Kayed lab members 
for their support and suggestions in preparing the 
manuscript. 
Authors' disclosures available online (http://j-alz. 
com/manuscript-disclosures/16-0912). </p>





<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>



<p>A.N. Nilson et al. / Tau and Inflammation in Neurodegeneration </p>





</text></tei>