<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5076548" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Environmental factors impact the skin aging resulting in decrease of skin radi-
ance. Nutrition and particularly antioxidants could help to fight against skin degradation. 
Objective: The aim of this study was to evaluate the effects of an oral supplement rich in specific 
antioxidants, SkinAx </p>

<p>2TM </p>

<p>, on the improvement of the skin radiance in women. 
Methods: The open-label clinical study enrolled 35 women, aged 40-70, with facial dull com-
plexion. Subjects were supplemented orally with a daily dosage of 150 mg of an antioxidant-rich 
formulation containing superoxide dismutase-rich melon concentrate, grape seed extract rich 
in monomers of flavanols, vitamin C, and zinc for 8 weeks. Each subject served as her own 
control. The C.L.B.T. 
™ test has been used to evaluate facial skin coloring (C), luminosity (L), </p>

<p>brightness (B), and transparency (T) involved in skin radiance. Facial skin imperfections have 
been assessed by clinical assessment. Firmness has been evaluated by clinical assessment and 
cutometer measurement. Finally, an auto-questionnaire has been carried out in order to evaluate 
the satisfaction of the subjects concerning different parameters involved in skin radiance and 
the global efficacy of the supplement. 
Results: Skin "red pink" and "olive" colors were significantly improved after supplementation 
(P&lt;0.0001). Luminosity was increased by 25.9% (P&lt;0.0001) whereas brightness and transpar-
ency were not affected by the supplementation. Facial skin imperfections were significantly 
reduced after the antioxidant-rich formulation intake (global reduction: -18.0%; P&lt;0.0001). 
Indeed, dark circles, redness, and spots significantly diminished after oral treatment. Firmness 
and elasticity have been shown to be improved. Subjects were globally satisfied by the product 
(82.4%) and have found improvements on their facial skin. Furthermore, 64.7% reported to 
look better at the end of the supplementation. 
Conclusion: The oral supplement containing the antioxidant-rich formulation was found to 
improve skin radiance by reducing skin coloring, increasing face luminosity, reducing imperfec-
tions, and improving skin firmness in women with dull complexion. 
Skin is the largest organ of the body and represents 16% of total body weight. It is a 
complex and multifunctional organ. Indeed, skin protects the body from the outside 
which means from physical, chemical, and infectious attacks and plays a role in several 
biological and biochemical processes. </p>

<p>1   Visible skin appearance is an important moderator in human social interaction. It 
facilitates nonverbal communication. Humans attach great importance to a beautiful, </p>

<p>Correspondence: Marion Dumoulin 
Activ'Inside, Espace Legendre, 33 rue 
Max Linder, 33500 Libourne, France 
Tel +33 535 541 560 
Email m.dumoulin@activinside.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 
18 October 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>316 </p>

<p>Dumoulin et al </p>

<p>healthy, and youthful-looking skin. Partly conveyed by the 
cosmetic industry, skin beauty includes a radiant complexion 
without imperfections. </p>

<p>2   There is no universal definition of skin radiance. The 
radiance of the complexion is multifactorial and it is difficult 
to list all the parameters that constitute it with their relative 
proportions. 
3-5 The main characteristics are the skin contrast 
defined by the luminosity, brightness, and transparency; the 
skin color, mainly affected by the skin microcirculation; 
and the skin imperfections such as the homogeneity, dark 
circles, or spots. </p>

<p>3,4,6   The skin radiance is influenced by intrinsic and extrinsic 
factors which can modulate skin aging. 
7-10 While the intrinsic 
aging is inevitable, extrinsic aging is the result of the interplay 
of external factors and human behaviors, such as tobacco, 
nutritional deficiencies, alcohol, stress, and ultraviolet (UV) 
exposure. Both of these factors impact the oxidative stress 
by an overproduction of reactive oxygen species. 
7,9,10 Thus, 
with aging, the skin is potentially more exposed to oxida-
tive stress, leading to exacerbated reactive oxygen species 
production. 
11-13 This overproduction of free radicals, which 
plays an important role in skin aging, damages skin cells 
and in addition leads to a degradation of collagen and elas-
tin. These fibers are responsible for the skin firmness and 
elasticity and the vessels integrity, and hence for the good 
skin vascularization. 
9,10,14 Moreover, cell degradation and 
UV exposure will lead to a heterogeneous overproduction 
of melanin by melanocytes, which leads to facial spots and 
a heterogeneous complexion. </p>

<p>15   As the first line of cell defense against oxidative stress, 
primary antioxidants correspond to the endogenous system 
comprised of the only three antioxidant enzymes of the 
body: superoxide dismutase (SOD), catalase, and glutathione 
peroxidase. These enzymes contain trace elements in their 
active sites, such as copper, zinc, and selenium, supplied by 
food and essential for their enzymatic activity. </p>

<p>16   To avoid such cellular damages, a reduction of the amount 
of secondary oxidants is the complementary step to lower 
the oxidative stress. This occurs firstly by enhancing the 
synthesis of primary antioxidants and secondly by lowering 
their spreading thanks to secondary antioxidants. Secondary 
antioxidants, as the second level of antioxidant protection, 
also called scavengers, correspond to exogenous substances, 
including hydrosoluble antioxidants (vitamin C, glutathione, 
and polyphenols) and liposoluble antioxidants (vitamin E, 
carotenoids, and bilirubin), which allow the diminution of 
the amplification loop of skin cell damage. </p>

<p>11   Thus, nutrition and particularly dietary antioxidant active 
ingredients could help to protect skin from aging. First, they 
can act against the oxidative stress and secondly some of them 
are able to impact specific biological mechanisms enhancing 
the skin protection and repair. 
The main objective of this study was to evaluate the effect 
of an 8-week oral supplementation with a formulation rich 
in specific antioxidants on skin radiance in healthy women 
with dull complexion. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Subjects and product </p>

<p>The clinical trial was conducted as an open-label, single-center 
study, approved by the Ethics Committee (Comité de Protec-
tion des Personnes Est-II, Besançon, France), complying with 
Good Clinical Practices in Human Beings, involving 35 female 
subjects aged between 40 and 70 years old, with a dull com-
plexion evaluated by clinical scoring, phototypes II to IV on the 
Fitzpatrick scale, without a history of allergy or hypersensitivity 
to the products or one of their components. After having signed 
a written informed consent, the subjects were first checked for 
inclusion and exclusion criteria: eating habits (stable before 
and during the study); no concomitant treatment; no history of 
skin disease or treatment; no facial skin care (peeling, mask, 
and so on) during the study and 15 days before the beginning 
of the study; smoking habits (nonsmoking or &lt;5 cigarettes per 
day); no UV exposure during the study; not pregnant, nursing, 
or intending to be pregnant in the course of the study; and use 
of oral nutritional supplements and/or vitamin supplementa-
tion (not &lt;1 month before inclusion and not during the study). 
A first assessment was performed in order to determine a 
baseline for each parameter (T0). Subjects then started daily 
oral use of SkinAx 
2TM (Activ'Inside, Libourne, France), a patent 
pending formulation containing grape seed extract, especially 
rich in flavanol monomers, a melon concentrate providing an 
SOD activity, zinc, and vitamin C, in a single intake of 150 mg 
capsule for 8 weeks (from October to December 2014). A last 
assessment was performed at the end of the supplementation 
(T8) in order to compare the parameter values with the baseline. </p>

<p>Clinical assessment </p>

<p>Measurements were carried out on face skin which had 
received no application of product or makeup since the eve-
ning before the date of the visit as well as on the day of the 
visit. Before each assessment, volunteers were asked to remain 
in the examination room (airconditioned room, temperature-
and hygrometry-controlled: 22°C±2°C; 50%±10% RH) for </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>317 </p>

<p>Effects of an antioxidant-rich oral supplement on skin radiance </p>

<p>15 minutes in order to be in stable conditions of blood flow 
and skin temperature. All the descriptors have been evaluated 
by a unique trained assessor. </p>

<p>Skin radiance assessment </p>

<p>The main criterion was skin radiance evaluated by clinical 
scoring using the coloring, luminosity, brightness, and trans-
parency (C.L.B.T. </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>) 
17 scale and imperfections scale (dark 
circles, redness/rosacea, spots, and heterogeneity). 
The C.L.B.T. 
TM methodology allows assessing different 
descriptors of the complexion: coloring, luminosity, bright-
ness, and transparency of facial skin. The descriptors have </p>

<p>been defined precisely to ensure the homogeneity of the 
measurements. To determine the coloring, the following 
descriptors have been used: "red pink," "olive," and "beige." 
These descriptors have been evaluated visually based on 
structured visual color scales for the three hues (from 0% 
to 100% color saturation). Optimal values for each color 
have been interpreted as follows: red pink should decrease 
to diminish the red skin aspect, olive should decrease to 
diminish the sallow complexion, and beige should tend to 
medium as a clear complexion (Table 1). 
Skin luminosity is defined as the intensity of the light 
areas reflected on the prominent areas of the face. Skin </p>

<p>Descriptors 
(C.L.B.T. 
TM and imperfections) 
Scales and optimal values 
Definition </p>

<p>± red skin aspect </p>

<p>± sallow complexion </p>

<p>± clear complexion </p>

<p>± luminous skin </p>

<p>± uniform and regular skin </p>

<p>± transparent skin, vascularized </p>

<p>± dark intensity </p>

<p>± deep </p>

<p>± colored and pronounced </p>

<p>± colored and present </p>

<p>± heterogeneous, defects </p>

<p>± imperfections </p>

<p>Absence of red 
0% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>0% 
100% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>Min 0 </p>

<p>Min 0 </p>

<p>Min 0 </p>

<p>Min 0 </p>

<p>Min 0 </p>

<p>Min 0 </p>

<p>Min 0 </p>

<p>Min 0 </p>

<p>Min 0 
Max 45 </p>

<p>Max 9 </p>

<p>Max 9 </p>

<p>Max 9 </p>

<p>Max 9 </p>

<p>Max 9 </p>

<p>Max 10 </p>

<p>Max 10 </p>

<p>Max 10 </p>

<p>Absence of olive </p>

<p>Medium beige 
(tends to 50%) </p>

<p>Optimal luminosity </p>

<p>Optimal brightness 
(increase when low, decrease if close to 10) </p>

<p>Optimal transparency 
(increase when low, decrease if close to 10) </p>

<p>Clear </p>

<p>Smooth </p>

<p>Light and small </p>

<p>Clear and few </p>

<p>Homogeneous complexion </p>

<p>Optimal imperfection score </p>

<p>Red pink </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>Imperfections </p>

<p>Olive </p>

<p>Beige </p>

<p>Luminosity </p>

<p>Brightness </p>

<p>Transparency </p>

<p>Dark circles (color) </p>

<p>Dark circles (relief) </p>

<p>Redness/rosacea 
(color-surface) </p>

<p>Spots (color-quality) </p>

<p>Heterogeneity </p>

<p>Global imperfection 
score </p>

<p>Abbreviations: C.L.B.T., coloring, luminosity, brightness, and transparency; Min, minimum; Max, maximum. </p>

<p>Table 1 Clinical descriptors evaluated by C.L.B.T. 
™ and imperfections scale </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>318 </p>

<p>Dumoulin et al </p>

<p>brightness corresponds to the uniformity of the skin in terms 
of coloring and texture. Skin transparency is the possibility 
of seeing the vessels beneath the skin reflecting the level of 
vascularization and the skin thickness. The evaluation of 
luminosity, brightness, and transparency has been performed 
visually using a scale ranging the parameters from "no inten-
sity" (limit 0) to "maximum" (limit 10). In this way, L.B.T. 
parameters have been interpreted as follows: luminosity 
should increase (from dark skin to luminous skin); brightness 
should increase, when low, to have a more uniform and regu-
lar skin, or should decrease, when high, to have a balanced 
shiny skin; and transparency should increase if low to have 
a more transparent skin, thinner, and well vascularized or 
should decrease when high to avoid seeing too many vessels 
under the skin (Table 1). 
Facial skin imperfections have been evaluated through a 
clinical scoring reporting the color and relief of dark circles, 
redness/rosacea (color and surface), presence of spots (color 
and quantity), and heterogeneity of the skin imperfections. 
These criteria have been classed from 0 (absence or low) to 9 
(very). Then, a global imperfection score has been calculated 
summing these five parameters (0 to 45) (Table 1). </p>

<p>Skin firmness and elasticity assessment </p>

<p>Skin firmness and elasticity have been evaluated respec-
tively with a clinical evaluation and a Cutometer SM575 </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>(Courage-Khazaka Electronic, Köln, Germany). The firmness 
evaluation was scored from "Absent/Light" to "Moderate/ 
Important" by an examiner. The cutometer measures the 
elasticity of the skin in vivo by a suction test. A probe of 6 
mm diameter is applied to the skin and a temporary vacuum 
is created (400 mbars), thus deforming the skin (on time: 3 
seconds; off time: 2 seconds; repetition: 5). Adhesive tape 
is attached to the probe and prevents the adjacent skin from 
being sucked into the chamber. The device holds a spring 
ensuring a constant application pressure (50 g/cm²). An opti-
cal system made of a light source and a receptor determines 
the skin deformation and its slackness. Different parameters 
are measured: immediate deformation Ue (U extensibility), 
delayed deformation Uv (U viscous), final deformation Uf 
(Uf = Ue + Uv), and deformation of immediate retraction Ur, 
when the vacuum is removed. The ratio Ur/Ue characterizes 
the elasticity of the skin and is independent of the thickness 
of the skin. </p>

<p>18   Self-assessment of skin parameters </p>

<p>As the perception of the skin radiance is subjective, a self-
assessment has been performed through a questionnaire. Ten 
different questions were asked. </p>

<p>Eight were answered at T0 and T8: "For you, the radi-
ance of your complexion is?" from 0= dull to 10= glowing; 
"Is your complexion fresh?" from 0= not to 10= very; "Is 
your complexion luminous?" from 0= not to 10= very; "Is 
your complexion homogeneous?" from 0= not to 10= very; 
"Is your skin smooth?" from 0= not to 10= very; "Is your 
skin texture refined?" from 0= not to 10= very; "Is your skin 
firm?" from 0= soft to 10= firm; and "Is your skin hydrated?" 
from 0= not to 10= very. 
Two satisfaction questions were asked at T8 only: "Do you 
think you look better?" yes or no; and "How do you estimate 
the global efficacy of the dietary supplement?" 0= none, 1= 
moderate, 2= good, and 3= very good. 
The tolerance of the product has been evaluated by spon-
taneous comments and/or clinical observations. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Statistical analyses have been realized using <rs id="software-0" type="software">StatView</rs> </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc</rs>., Cary, NC USA). Graphical 
representations were performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software, Inc</rs>., La Jolla, CA, USA). The difference 
between T0 and T8 has been tested using Student's paired t-test 
or Wilcoxon Signed-Rank Test according to the normality 
assumption of data distribution (Kolmogorov-Smirnov test). 
The firmness score has been analyzed using chi-square test. </p>

<p>Results 
Effects of the supplementation on the 
C.L.B.T. 
TM parameters </p>

<p>C.L.B.T. 
TM parameters have been scored by an examiner at T0 
and T8. Concerning the color parameters, statistical analyses 
revealed a significant decrease of the saturation for the red 
pink color (−34.8% vs T0; P&lt;0.0001) and the olive color 
(−21.6% vs T0; P&lt;0.0001) between T0 and T8. However, no 
significant effect has been observed for the beige color which 
only changed from 6.5% to 9.1% (absolute values) in devia-
tion from the optimal value of 50% (P=0.1069) (Figure 1A). 
Analyses have also shown that the luminosity was significantly 
increased after 8 weeks of supplementation (+25.9% vs T0; 
P&lt;0.0001) (Figure 1B). On the contrary, brightness has been 
observed to decrease from T0 to T8 by 12.3% (P&lt;0.05) 
( Figure 1C). Finally, no significant change has been observed 
for the transparency (+7.9%; P=0.238) (Figure 1D). </p>

<p>Effects of the supplementation on skin 
imperfections </p>

<p>Significant improvements have been observed at study end 
on the imperfection parameters measured. Dark circles have </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>319 </p>

<p>Effects of an antioxidant-rich oral supplement on skin radiance </p>

<p>Red pink 
Olive 
Beige </p>

<p>Transparency 
Brightness 
Luminosity </p>

<p>T0 </p>

<p>T8 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C 
D </p>

<p>50 
12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.0 
0.0 
0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 
 *  *  *  </p>

<p> *  *  *  </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p> *  *  *  </p>

<p>15 
Saturation (%) </p>

<p>Score 
Score 
Score </p>

<p>Saturation (%) </p>

<p>Change from 50% saturation (%) 
10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Evaluation of the C.L.B.T. 
TM parameters before and after supplementation. 
Notes: (A) Red pink and olive color decrease significantly (***P&lt;0.0001). Beige color is not significantly altered as the change of deviation from the optimal value 50 is 
not modified after the supplementation. (B) Luminosity is significantly increased at the end of the supplementation compared to the baseline (***P&lt;0.0001). (C) Brightness 
decreases at T8 compared to the baseline (*P&lt;0.05). (D) Transparency increases slightly but not significantly at T8. 
Abbreviations: C.L.B.T., coloring, luminosity, brightness, and transparency; T0, Time 0, baseline; T8, Time 8, eight weeks. </p>

<p>been shown to be reduced in both relief (-11.7% vs T0; 
P&lt;0.01) and color (-19.2% vs T0; P&lt;0.0001) (Figure 2A). 
Redness/rosacea (color and surface) has also been reduced 
after supplementation (-19.3% vs T0; P&lt;0.0001) as well as 
the spots (color and quantity) (-20.7% vs T0; P&lt;0.0001) 
(Figure 2B and C). However, heterogeneity of the skin has 
not been significantly modified (-1.7% vs T0; P=0.2850) 
(Figure 2D). The global score of imperfection (dark circles 
relief and color, redness/rosacea, spots, and heterogeneity) 
has thus been significantly reduced after the supplementa-
tion as revealed by the decrease of 18.0% compared to 
the baseline (T0) value for this global score (P&lt;0.0001) 
(Figure 2E). </p>

<p>Effects of the supplementation on the 
firmness and the elasticity of the skin </p>

<p>First, an evaluation of the skin firmness has been realized by 
an examiner. Skin firmness was classified as Absent-Light </p>

<p>firmness or Moderate-Important firmness. A chi-square 
analysis revealed a significant change from the Absent-Light 
category to the Moderate-Important category of firmness 
after the supplementation (chi-square =4.121; P&lt;0.05) 
(Table 2). 
Elasticity has been evaluated with a cutometer. A sig-
nificant increase of elasticity (Ur/Ue) has been measured 
(+8.53% vs T0; P&lt;0.05) (Figure 3). </p>

<p>Auto-evaluation and satisfaction of women </p>

<p>Women subjects were asked to answer an auto-questionnaire. 
As observed in Table 3, from baseline to the end of the 
supplementation, they found their skin more radiant (+28.9%; 
P&lt;0.01), fresher (+35.9%; P&lt;0.0001), more luminous 
(+30.6%; P&lt;0.01), more homogeneous (+37.2%; P&lt;0.01), 
smoother (+18.7%; P&lt;0.05), and firmer (+19.5%; P&lt;0.05). 
However, they did not see a significant improvement of the 
skin texture or of its hydration. The proportion of the total </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>320 </p>

<p>Dumoulin et al </p>

<p>numbers of women seeing an improvement has also been 
calculated revealing that the majority of the population 
observed a positive evolution of these parameters. Moreover, </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C 
D 
E </p>

<p>B 
6 </p>

<p>5 
 *  *  
 *  *  *  </p>

<p> *  *  *  
 *  *  *  </p>

<p> *  *  *  </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 
Score 
Score </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>T0 
T8 </p>

<p>T0 
T8 
T0 
T8 </p>

<p>T0 
T8 </p>

<p>T0 
T8 
T0 
T8 </p>

<p>T0 
T8 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Score </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Score </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Score </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Score (%) </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Dark circles (relief) </p>

<p>Spots 
Heterogeneity 
Imperfection score % </p>

<p>Dark circles (color) 
Redness/rosacea </p>

<p>Figure 2 Evaluation of the facial skin imperfections before and after supplementation. 
Notes: (A) Dark circles relief and color are reduced after supplementation compared to baseline (**P&lt;0.01; ***P&lt;0.0001), (B) redness is also reduced at T8 compared to 
baseline T0 (***P&lt;0.0001), and (C) spots are decreased after supplementation (***P&lt;0.0001). (D) Complexion heterogeneity is not modified by the supplementation. (E) The 
global imperfection score (dark circles relief and color + redness/rosacea + spots + heterogeneity scores) decreased by 18% (***P&lt;0.0001). 
Abbreviations: T0, Time 0, baseline; T8, Time 8, eight weeks. </p>

<p>Table 2 Firmness evaluation by clinical examination </p>

<p>Firmness 
T0 
T8* </p>

<p>n 
% 
n 
% </p>

<p>Absent-Light 
16 
47.1 
8 
23.5 
Moderate-Important 
18 
52.9 
26 
76.5 </p>

<p>Note: Population repartition was significantly different between T0 and T8 switching 
from the "Absent-Light" to the "Moderate-Important" category of firmness (*P&lt;0.05). 
Abbreviations: T0, Time 0, baseline; T8, Time 8, eight weeks. </p>

<p>this positive evolution is globally important, ranging from 
+37.7% for the skin grain to 101.1% for the homogeneous 
complexion (Table 3). 
When women were asked if they looked better after 
the supplementation, 64.7% answered yes. In parallel, 
82.4% of the subjects answered that they were satisfied 
by the efficacy of the supplement (from moderate to very 
good) (Table 4). 
The tolerance of the product was considered as safe 
because no serious adverse events occurred during the 
study. </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>321 </p>

<p>Effects of an antioxidant-rich oral supplement on skin radiance </p>

<p>stress. The production of free radicals leads to the deteriora-
tion of cellular structures, lipids, DNA, and proteins. At the 
skin level, one of the main consequences is the degradation 
of collagen and elastin. 
7-10 These fibers are responsible for the 
skin firmness and elasticity. Moreover, they play an important 
role in the vessels integrity and thus in the skin vasculariza-
tion. 
9,10,14 Furthermore, cell degradation and UV exposure 
results in a heterogeneous overproduction of melanin by 
melanocytes, which can cause the appearance of facial spots 
and a heterogeneous complexion. </p>

<p>15   Our results suggest a positive effect of oral supplemen-
tation rich in primary and secondary antioxidants on skin 
radiance. Skin color, facial luminosity, and firmness have 
been improved and imperfections reduced. As oxidative 
stress actively impacts skin aging, the scavenger effect of 
antioxidant-rich formulation components seems to be rel-
evant to protect skin. 
Above all, the dietary formulation has been specially 
developed to protect skin against the oxidative stress by 
using different antioxidants, primarily with the SOD, and </p>

<p>Table 3 Auto-evaluation of skin parameters at T0 and T8 </p>

<p>Questions 
T0 
T8 
P-value 
(T8 vs T0) </p>

<p>Evolution 
(%) </p>

<p>Women 
with positive 
evolution (%) </p>

<p>Evolution in 
women with 
positive score (%) </p>

<p>For you, the radiance of your complexion is? 
(0= dull -&gt;10= glowing) </p>

<p>4.0±0.3 
5.1±0.3 
** &lt;0.01 
28.9 
76.5 
62.3 </p>

<p>Is your complexion fresh? 
(0= not -&gt;10= very) </p>

<p>3.9±0.2 
5.3±0.3 
*** &lt;0.0001 
35.9 
79.4 
52.6 </p>

<p>Is your complexion luminous? 
(0= not -&gt;10= very) </p>

<p>3.8±0.3 
5.0±0.3 
** &lt;0.01 
30.6 
70.6 
69.4 </p>

<p>Is your complexion homogeneous? 
(0= not -&gt;10= very) </p>

<p>3.2±0.4 
4.3±0.4 
** &lt;0.01 
37.2 
67.6 
101.0 </p>

<p>Is your skin smooth? 
(0= not -&gt;10= very) </p>

<p>4.4±0.4 
5.2±0.3 
* &lt;0.05 
18.7 
61.8 
52.3 </p>

<p>Is your skin texture refined? 
(0= not refined -&gt;10= very refined) </p>

<p>4.7±0.4 
5.2±0.3 
NS 0.1598 
8.7 
66.7 
37.7 </p>

<p>Is your skin firm? 
(0= soft -&gt;10= firm) </p>

<p>3.7±0.3 
4.4±0.3 
* &lt;0.05 
19.5 
67.6 
55.8 </p>

<p>Is your skin hydrated? 
(0= not -&gt;10= very) </p>

<p>4.4±0.3 
4.8±0.3 
NS 0.2365 
9.6 
58.8 
45.9 </p>

<p>Notes: *P&lt;0.05; **P&lt;0.01; ***P&lt;0.001. 
Abbreviations: NS, not significant; T0, Time 0, baseline; T8, Time 8, eight weeks. </p>

<p>Table 4 Auto-evaluation after the supplementation: satisfaction 
questions </p>

<p>Satisfaction questions </p>

<p>Do you think you look better? 
No 
Yes 
35.3% (n=12) 
64.7% (n=22) 
How do you estimate the 
global efficacy of the dietary 
supplement? </p>

<p>None 
Moderate to 
very good </p>

<p>17.6% (n=6) 
82.4% (n=28) </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>Elasticity </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>T0 
T8 </p>

<p>Ur/Ue 
0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Evaluation of the skin elasticity by cutometer. 
Note: Elasticity, represented by the ratio Ur/Ue, increases reflecting a better skin 
elasticity (*P&lt;0.05). 
Abbreviations: Ue, U extensibility; Ur, immediate retraction; T0, Time 0, baseline; 
T8, Time 8, eight weeks. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>According to several authors, the skin radiance appears to 
be the combination of the light reflection within the skin 
(luminosity and brightness), level of skin imperfections, 
and skin color. 
3,4,6 Complemented by appropriate techniques, 
sensory evaluation seems to be a good method to appreciate 
skin radiance as a whole. 
The skin aging process is influenced by genetic and envi-
ronmental factors with consequent impact on the oxidative </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>322 </p>

<p>Dumoulin et al </p>

<p>secondarily with the flavanol monomers from grape, vitamin 
C, and zinc. 
16,19,20 Monomers of flavanols have been chosen 
instead of polymers because they are more bioavailable. 
Indeed, studies have shown that flavanol polymerization limits 
absorption in the gut. 
21,22 Furthermore, a potential synergis-
tic effect between vitamin C (ascorbic acid) and flavanol 
monomers has been demonstrated in vitro and in vivo. This 
synergistic effect has been observed on antioxidant capaci-
ties with catechin alone or in the presence of ascorbic acid. </p>

<p>23   The authors suggested that the higher radical-scavenging 
ability can be due to a regeneration process of catechin radi-
cal by ascorbic acid. Another synergistic potential has been 
confirmed in vivo where it has been shown that flavanols 
improved the vitamin C bioavailability. </p>

<p>24   The improvement of the firmness and the elasticity sug-
gests that elastic fibers have been protected by the supple-
mentation. Indeed, the firmness of the skin is mainly linked to 
collagen and elastin, which confer stability to the dermis and 
its elastic properties. 
9 Furthermore, improvement of skin firm-
ness also allows reduction of dark circles. The generation of 
reactive oxygen species, in particular by UV radiation, induces 
the production of collagenase and elastase, responsible for 
collagen and elastin degradation. Vitamin C stimulates col-
lagen synthesis, acting as a cofactor in the hydroxylation of 
proline and lysine, essential amino acids in the formation of 
collagen fibers. 
25,26 Flavanols, and in particular monomers, 
inhibit the degradation of collagen and elastin by fixation on 
fibers, which reduce the action of collagenase and elastase. 
Moreover, flavanols are known to stimulate the synthesis of 
amino acids precursors of collagen and elastin. </p>

<p>27-38   This action on skin elastic fibers has a direct impact on 
the vascularization system acting on the capillary resistance. 
This effect on skin circulation has been observed through 
the skin color improvement after supplementation as the 
main pigments responsible for the different hues are mela-
nin, bilirubin, and hemoglobin. 
17 The reductions of redness/ 
rosacea and dark circles color are linked with these impacts 
on vascularization. Moreover, the vascularization improve-
ment is also possible through the vasodilation and blood 
flow. First, it allows improving the nutrient circulation, and 
it is important for the bioavailability of the product. Blood 
flow also participates in the skin hydration. Thus, flavanol 
monomers from grape and SOD are known to improve the 
vasodilation increasing the nitroso species production. </p>

<p>39-44   A regulation of the age-related heterogeneous overpro-
duction of melanin has been observed in particular with the 
reduction of facial spots. The improvement of skin color also 
reflects this impact as one of the main pigments responsible 
for skin hue is the melanin. 
17 Flavanol monomers and vitamin </p>

<p>C are known to reduce the tyrosinase activity necessary for 
the melanogenesis and, thus, they are able to regulate the 
melanin synthesis. </p>

<p>15,45-47   The term "radiance" often refers to the shining and 
lightening aspect. Interestingly, in our study, luminosity, 
linking with the global skin color and skin homogeneity, was 
improved. However, a radiant complexion seems to be asso-
ciated with several skin characteristics reflecting the physi-
cal and psychological health. 
4,48 Thus, radiance evaluation 
remains at least in part subjective. The final auto-assessment 
of several parameters involved in skin radiance contributes 
to bringing more information concerning the effects of the 
oral supplementation. Tested women were satisfied concern-
ing different specific points, such as their skin radiance, skin 
luminosity, or its hydration. They were also globally satisfied 
by the product, up to 82.4%. Finally, they felt they looked 
better after the supplementation. 
This study brings positive arguments in favor of an oral 
supplementation with a formulation rich in specific antioxi-
dants to protect skin from the environmental daily damage and 
intrinsic aging. However, further investigation with comple-
mentary methods could bring more information concerning 
the potential of the product. In particular, the lack of a control 
group and relatively small population size limit the conclu-
sions that can be drawn about the efficacy of this product. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The clinical study results suggest that daily oral supplemen-
tation with an antioxidant-rich formulation, which contains 
a melon concentrate providing an SOD activity, grape seed 
extract rich in monomers of flavanols, vitamin C, and zinc, 
has a beneficial effect on skin radiance (improvement of 
luminosity, reduction of imperfections, and improvement of 
skin firmness) in women. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>This study was sponsored by Activ'Inside. Activ'Inside is the 
supplier of SkinAx </p>

<p>2TM </p>

<p>. The authors report no other conflicts 
of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Effects of an antioxidant-rich oral supplement on skin radiance </p>



<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: https://www.dovepress.com/clinical-cosmetic-and-investigational-dermatology-journal </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology is an interna-
tional, peer-reviewed, open access, online journal that focuses on 
the latest clinical and experimental research in all aspects of skin 
disease and cosmetic interventions. This journal is included 
on PubMed. The manuscript management system is completely online </p>

<p>and includes a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy 
to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real 
quotes from published authors </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Dumoulin et al </p>

</text></tei>