<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5463043" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Long interspersed nuclear element-1 (LINE-1) is a retrotrans-
poson that contains a CpG island in its 5-untranslated re-
gion. The CpG island of LINE-1 is often heavily methylated in 
normal somatic cells, which is associated with poor progno-
sis in various cancers. DNA methylation can differ between 
formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) and frozen tissues. 
Therefore, this study aimed to compare the LINE-1 methyla-
tion status between the two tissue-storage conditions in 
gastric cancer (GC) clinical samples and to evaluate whether 
LINE-1 can be used as an independent prognostic marker 
for each tissue-storage type. We analyzed four CpG sites of 
LINE-1 and examined the methylation levels at these sites in 
25 FFPE and 41 frozen GC tissues by quantitative bisulfite 
pyrosequencing. The LINE-1 methylation status was signifi-
cantly different between the FFPE and frozen GC tissues (p 
&lt; 0.001). We further analyzed the clinicopathological features 
in the two groups separately. In the frozen GC tissues, LINE-1 
was significantly hypomethylated in GC tissues compared to 
their corresponding normal gastric mucosa tissues (p &lt; 0.001), 
and its methylation status was associated with gender, dif-
ferentiation state, and lymphatic and venous invasion of </p>

<p>GC. In the FFPE GC tissues, the methylation levels of LINE-1 
differed according to tumor location and venous invasion of 
GC. In conclusion, LINE-1 can be used as a useful methylation 
marker for venous invasion in both FFPE and frozen tumor 
tissues of GC. </p>

<p>Long interspersed nuclear element-1 (LINE-1) constitutes 
~17% of the human genome (Lander et al., 2001). LINE-1 
functions as a retrotransposon across its two open reading 
frames-ORF1p and ORF2p-and causes somatic retrotrans-
position, transcriptome effects, and DNA damage (Rodic  and Burns, 2013). Thus far, many studies have proposed 
that the LINE-1 methylation status is associated with variant 
features in several cancer types. The hypomethylation of 
LINE-1, specifically, is associated with tumor progression, </p>

<p>Molecules and Cells </p>

<p>Received 31 January, 2017; revised 13 April, 2017; accepted 24 April, 2017; published online 22 May, 2017 </p>

<p>eISSN: 0219-1032 
The Korean Society for Molecular and Cellular Biology. All rights reserved. 
This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported 
License. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/. </p>

<p>LINE-1 As a Marker for Venous Invasion in Gastric Cancer 
Jimin Min et al. </p>

<p>Mol. Cells 2017; 40(5): 346-354 347 </p>

<p>cancer risk, and poor prognosis in colon cancer, bladder 
cancer, breast cancer, and gastric cancer (GC) (Cash et al.,  2012; Shigaki et al., 2013; Sunami et al., 2011; van Hoesel  et al., 2012). LINE-1 is known to be hypomethylated in can-
cer tissues compared to normal tissues (Chalitchagorn et al.,  2004). Previous studies reported that global LINE-1 hypo-
methylation was correlated with microsatellite instability and 
poor overall survival in colorectal cancer (Estecio et al., 2007;  Ogino et al., 2008a; 2008b). In addition, LINE-1 hypometh-
ylation promotes liver metastasis by inducing expression of </p>

<p>proto-oncogenes such as MET, RAB3IP, and CHRM 3 in col-</p>

<p>orectal cancer (Hur et al., 2014). 
GC is the fifth most-common cancer in the world (Ferlay  et al., 2015) and the second leading cause of cancer-
related death in Asian countries (Rahman et al., 2014). The 
methylation status of LINE-1 differs between low-grade 
gastric dysplasia, high-grade dysplasia, and intramucosal 
cancer, and LINE-1 hypomethylation may be a diagnostic 
marker for high-grade dysplasia and intramucosal cancer 
(Lee et al., 2011). A previous study reported an association 
between LINE-1 hypomethylation and prognosis in gastric 
carcinogenesis (Shigaki et al., 2013). Moreover, the 
methylation status of LINE-1 changes when intestinal 
metaplasia progresses to gastric adenoma and is associ-
ated with poor prognosis in patients with GC (Bae et al.,  2012). Thus, LINE-1 has been studied as an epigenetic 
marker associated with the risk for GC using blood or tis-
sue samples. A meta-analysis of the LINE-1 methylation 
status in human cancers showed that LINE-1 is significantly 
hypomethylated as compared to controls in tissue samples 
such as fresh/frozen or formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded 
(FFPE) samples, but not in blood samples (Barchitta et al.,  2014). 
LINE-1 is associated with various clinicopathological fea-
tures in cancer, particularly, tumor metastasis. In GC, the 
invading submucosa can cause lymph node (LN) metastasis. 
Although rarely observed, several patients have relatively 
high number of LN metastasis regardless of the depth of 
tumor invasion (T stage). While determining biomarkers for 
aggressive LN metastasis in GC, a previous study revealed 
that overexpressed plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 (PAI-
1) is a promising marker for aggressive LN metastasis with 
low T stage (Suh et al., 2015). Furthermore, GCRG213p, a 
variant of LINE-1 endonuclease, is overexpressed in both 
primary GC and LN metastasis (Wang et al., 2013). Previ-
ously, LINE-1 methylation was analyzed at specific com-
bined CpG sites using 434 FFPE tissues, to investigate asso-
ciations with clinicopathological features, including lym-
phatic and venous invasion, and considering the tissue-
storage conditions, LINE-1 was reportedly more hyper-
methylated in FFPE tissues than in paired fresh-frozen tis-
sues in GC (Song et al., 2016). 
Thus far, the relationship between the LINE-1 methylation 
level in different tissue types and several clinicopathological 
parameters such as differentiation, tumor location, lymphat-
ic and venous invasion, and aggressive LN metastasis has not 
been investigated. Therefore, in the present study, we aimed 
to determine whether the LINE-1 methylation status could 
be used as a marker for GC in two tissue types, FFPE and </p>

<p>frozen tissues. In addition, we assessed LINE-1 as an epige-
netic marker for each tissue type and investigated the clini-
copathological characteristics by LINE-1 methylation status in 
patients with GC. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Tissue specimens </p>

<p>Forty-one frozen and 25 FFPE GC tissues were analyzed in 
this study. Pathological examination was performed by a 
pathologist to identify tumor cellularity or tumor area in the 
tissues. Frozen GC tissues were paired with normal gastric 
mucosa (NM), and only tumor area was used from FFPE 
tissues. The clinical characteristics of all patients are shown in 
Supplementary Tables S1 and S2. 
All tissue samples were obtained from Seoul National Uni-
versity Hospital, Korea, and written informed consent was 
obtained from all patients. The present study was approved 
by the institutional review boards (IRB) of Seoul National 
University Hospital (IRB No. 1501-086-642). </p>

<p>LINE-1 methylation analysis </p>

<p>The analysis of LINE-1 methylation was performed in pa-
tients with GC who had data about gender, age, WHO clas-
sification, Lauren classification, tumor location, lymphatic 
invasion, venous invasion, perineural invasion, TNM stage 
and microsatellite instability. The methylation levels at four 
CpG sites of LINE-1 were measured in bisulfite-converted 
DNA from each tissue sample (Supplementary Fig. S1). To 
compare LINE-1 methylation levels, patients were grouped 
according to each clinicopathological parameter. In frozen 
tissues, different LINE-1 methylation levels in normal versus 
tumor tissue were also determined. In all the analysis, both 
the average methylation level of the four CpG sites and each 
CpG site were analyzed. </p>

<p>DNA extraction and sodium bisulfite modification </p>

<p>We collected tumor tissues from FFPE slides and placed 
them in microcentrifuge tubes with 1 ml xylene. After 
vortexing and centrifugation, the supernatant was re-
moved. The pellet was washed twice with 1 ml 100% 
ethanol. Subsequently, genomic DNA (gDNA) was ex-
tracted using the QIAamp DNA Mini Kit (Qiagen, Germa-
ny) according to the manufacturer's instructions. GC tis-
sues and the corresponding NM were immediately frozen 
in liquid nitrogen without fixation following gastrectomy. 
The gDNA was extracted from frozen tissues using the 
QuickGene DNA tissue kit S with QG-Mini80 (Kurabo, 
Japan) following the manufacturer's instructions. Bisul-
fite-modified gDNA was prepared using the EpiTect Bisul-
fite Kit (Qiagen, Germany) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. The bisulfite reaction was carried out with 600 
ng gDNA, and the reaction volume was adjusted to 40 l 
with elution buffer. The sample tubes were placed in a 
thermal cycler (Eppendorf, Germany) under the following 
conditions: 5 min at 95℃, 25 min at 60℃, 5 min at 95℃, 85 
min at 60℃, 5 min at 95℃, 175 min at 60℃, and overnight 
at 20℃. Converted DNA samples were finally stored at -20℃ 
until further use. </p>

<p>LINE-1 As a Marker for Venous Invasion in Gastric Cancer 
Jimin Min et al. </p>

<p>348 Mol. Cells 2017; 40(5): 346-354 </p>

<p>Quantitative bisulfite pyrosequencing for LINE-1 methylation </p>

<p>We used the bisulfite pyrosequencing method for methyla-
tion analyses of the LINE-1 gene, as described previously 
(Kile et al., 2010). Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was car-
ried out in a reaction volume of 20 l, with ≥20 ng convert-
ed gDNA, PCR premixture (Enzynomics, Korea), 1 l of 10 
pmol/l forward primer, and 1 l of 10 pmol/l biotinylated-
reverse primer. The amplification was carried out according 
to the general guidelines for pyrosequencing: denaturation 
at 95℃ for 10 min; followed by 45 cycles at 95℃ for 30 s, 
53℃ for 30 s, and 72℃ for 30 s; and a final extension at 
72℃ for 5 min. The PCR products (2 l) were separated by 
electrophoresis using a 2% agarose gel and visualized by 
ethidium bromide staining. 
A single-stranded DNA template was prepared from 16-18 
l of the biotinylated PCR product using streptavidin Se-
pharose HP beads (Amersham Biosciences, Sweden) fol-
lowing the PSQ 96 sample preparation guide using multi-
channel pipettes. Fifteen picomoles of the respective se-
quencing primer were added for analysis. Sequencing was 
performed on a PyroMark ID system with a Pyro Gold rea-
gents kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions without further optimization. The methylation percent-
age was calculated from the average of the degree of meth-
ylation at 4 CpG sites formulated in pyrosequencing. The 
primer sequences are described in Supplementary Table S3. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
A paired t-test was used to compare the methylation levels </p>

<p>in GC tissues paired with NM. For the analyses of clinical </p>

<p>implications, an unpaired t-test was used to analyze methyl-</p>

<p>ation levels among each classified groups according to clini-
copathological parameters. The significant difference be-
tween samples considering the tumor location and TNM 
stage was calculated using the ANOVA test. Statistical signif-</p>

<p>icance was considered at p-value &lt; 0.05. Statistical analyses </p>

<p>were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> V<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, USA) </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>LINE-1 methylation patterns according to sample types in GC </p>

<p>Comparison of the methylation levels at four CpG sites of 
the LINE-1 promoter showed that the average LINE-1 meth-
ylation was significantly different between the frozen and 
FFPE tumor tissues (Fig. 1A), and the differences were espe-
cially evident at CpG3 and CpG4 (Supplementary Fig. S2). 
Before we analyzed the clinical factors, we confirmed the 
LINE-1 methylation patterns at each CpG site according to 
the sample types. In frozen GC tissues, CpG3 of LINE-1 was 
significantly hypomethylated compared to other three CpG </p>

<p>sites (CpG1; p = 0.031, CpG2; p &lt; 0.001, CpG4; p &lt; 0.001, </p>

<p>Fig. 1B). In contrast, in FFPE GC tissues, CpG3 was signifi-
cantly hypermethylated compared to CpG1 or CpG2 (CpG1; </p>

<p>p = 0.022, CpG2; p &lt; 0.001, Fig. 1C). In addition, CpG4 </p>

<p>showed the maximum hypermethylation (Fig. 1C). Analysis 
of the LINE-1 methylation patterns according to the sample 
type and CpG sites showed that the LINE-1 methylation sta-
tus varied between sample types and CpG sites in GC. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Fig. 1. LINE-1 methylation status according to sample types. (A) 
The average LINE-1 methylation level (%) was significantly 
different between the frozen tumor tissues and FFPE GC tissues </p>

<p>(*p &lt; 0.001, unpaired t test). (B) In 41 frozen GC tissues, LINE-1 </p>

<p>methylation level (%) was significantly lower at CpG3 than at </p>

<p>CpG1, CpG2 and CpG4 (p = 0.031, p &lt; 0.001, p &lt; 0.001, </p>

<p>respectively). (C) In 25 FFPE GC tissues, CpG3 was significantly 
hypermethylated compared to CpG1 (p = 0.022) or CpG2 (p &lt; 
0.001). CpG4 showed the maximum hypermethylation compared </p>

<p>to other three sites (p &lt; 0.001, p &lt; 0.001, p &lt; 0.001, respectively). 
*p &lt; 0.05, paired t test. </p>

<p>Association between LINE-1 methylation status and 
clinical characteristics in frozen GC tissues </p>

<p>We analyzed LINE-1 methylation levels in each CpG site </p>

<p>LINE-1 As a Marker for Venous Invasion in Gastric Cancer 
Jimin Min et al. </p>

<p>Mol. Cells 2017; 40(5): 346-354 349 </p>

<p>Table 1. LINE-1 methylation status in frozen GC tissues </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Number 
LINE-1 methylation level (%) </p>

<p>CpG 1 </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>CpG 2 </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>CpG 3 </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>CpG 4 </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>T y p e </p>

<p>Normal mucosa 
41 
81.61 
&lt;0.001 
78.27 
&lt;0.001 
76.32 
&lt;0.001 
80.48 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Gastric cancer 
41 
70.73 
71.32 
68.74 
71.76 </p>

<p>A g e </p>

<p>≤61 
18 
70.82 
0.965 
73.48 
0.157 
71.12 
0.189 
74.13 
0.215 </p>

<p>&gt;61 
23 
70.66 
69.62 
66.88 
69.90 </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
30 
68.42 
0.021 
69.19 
0.007 
65.69 
&lt;0.001 
69.12 
0.008 </p>

<p>Female 
11 
77.02 
77.12 
77.07 
78.95 </p>

<p>WHO classification </p>

<p>Differentiated 
18 
66.32 
0.017 
67.38 
0.012 
64.53 
0.036 
67.10 
0.020 </p>

<p>Undifferentiated 
20 
74.77 
74.53 
71.53 
75.34 </p>

<p>Lauren classification </p>

<p>Intestinal 
20 
67.18 
0.199 
68.40 
0.252 
65.25 
0.211 
68.14 
0.214 </p>

<p>Diffuse 
12 
72.53 
71.97 
70.02 
73.12 </p>

<p>Tumor location </p>

<p>Upper 
11 
69.59 
0.887 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>68.70 
0.295 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>65.29 
0.296 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>68.12 
0.207 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Middle 
8 
69.85 
75.02 
72.80 
77.04 </p>

<p>Lower 
21 
71.40 
70.93 
68.88 
71.31 </p>

<p>Lymphatic invasion </p>

<p>Not identified 
11 
75.53 
0.041 
74.28 
0.020 
72.00 
0.020 
75.35 
0.029 </p>

<p>Present 
11 
65.28 
66.17 
61.65 
65.60 </p>

<p>Venous invasion </p>

<p>Not identified 
18 
72.86 
0.037 
72.20 
0.016 
69.34 
0.016 
73.06 
0.012 </p>

<p>Present 
4 
59.36 
61.36 
55.50 
58.82 </p>

<p>Perineural invasion </p>

<p>Not identified 
16 
70.90 
0.757 
70.87 
0.570 
67.35 
0.716 
71.11 
0.659 </p>

<p>Present 
6 
69.07 
68.51 
65.41 
68.77 </p>

<p>TNM stage </p>

<p>II 
26 
70.92 
0.922 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>70.59 
0.535 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>67.58 
0.487 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>71.01 
0.532 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>III 
13 
69.98 
71.79 
70.01 
72.00 </p>

<p>IV 
2 
73.10 
77.64 
75.73 
79.98 </p>

<p>Microsatellite instability </p>

<p>MSS 
16 
67.31 
0.431 
67.58 
0.141 
63.52 
0.093 
67.32 
0.189 </p>

<p>MSI 
6 
72.15 
73.71 
72.36 
74.37 
a ANOVA test </p>

<p>according to several clinicopathological characteristics by 
using frozen GC tissues, as shown in Table 1. LINE-1 at each 
CpG site showed hypomethylation in GC tissues compared 
to NM. Moreover, the LINE-1 methylation levels differed 
according to gender, WHO classification, lymphatic invasion, 
and venous invasion. Then, we also compared the average 
LINE-1 methylation level in each parameter. In the same 
manner, LINE-1 was significantly hypomethylated in tumor </p>

<p>tissue compared to NM (Fig. 2A, p &lt; 0.001), and the LINE-1 </p>

<p>methylation level significantly differed between genders (Fig. 
2B). Furthermore, we assessed LINE-1 methylation in GC 
tissue considering both differentiation and lymphatic inva-
sion compared to NM. Although LINE-1 was significantly </p>

<p>hypomethylated in GC irrespective of both the differentia-
tion and lymphatic invasion statuses, it was more hypometh-
ylated in differentiated gastric adenocarcinoma and in GC 
showing lymphatic invasion (Figs. 2C and 2D). Therefore, we 
believe that frozen GC tissues have a different LINE-1 meth-
ylation status in each differentiation and lymphatic invasion 
state and that LINE-1 hypomethylation is especially associat-
ed with the male gender, differentiated gastric adenocarci-
noma, and the presence of lymphatic invasion. </p>

<p>Clinicopathological association of LINE-1 methylation 
status in FFPE GC tissues </p>

<p>In the frozen GC tissues, LINE-1 methylation was associated </p>

<p>LINE-1 As a Marker for Venous Invasion in Gastric Cancer 
Jimin Min et al. </p>



<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>Fig. 2. LINE-1 methylation and clinical characteristics in frozen GC tissues. (A) LINE-1 was significantly hypomethylated in gastric tumor (T) </p>

<p>compared to NM (N) (*p &lt; 0.001, paired t test). (B) Significant difference of LINE-1 methylation level (%) between genders (p = 0.004). </p>

<p>(C) LINE-1 was significantly hypomethylated in both differentiated and undifferentiated gastric adenocarcinoma compared to Normal (p </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001, p = 0.002, respectively). Particularly, it was more hypomethylated in differentiated. than in undifferentiated gastric </p>

<p>adenocarcinoma. (p = 0.016). (D) Hypomethylated LINE-1 in tumor was observed irrespective of whether patients have lymphatic </p>

<p>invasion or not (p &lt; 0.001, p &lt; 0.001, respectively). LINE-1 was significantly hypomethylated in the presence of invasion (Present) compared 
to the absence of it (Not identified) (p = 0.023). *p &lt; 0.05 (unpaired t test). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Fig. 3. LINE-1 methylation and clinical characteristics in FFPE GC samples. (A) No significant difference between two groups, high T stage 
without LN metastasis (T3/4N0) or low T stage with more than 7 regional LN metastasis (T1N3) (p = 0.211). (B) LINE-1 was significantly 
hypomethylated in tumors located in the lower third of stomach compared to those in the middle third of stomach (p = 0.008). *p &lt; </p>

<p>0.05 (unpaired t test). </p>

<p>with lymphatic invasion. Several patients had LN metastasis, 
although they were diagnosed with early GC. To determine 
whether LINE-1 methylation is a marker for aggressive LN 
metastasis, we obtained 25 FFPE tissue samples from pa-
tients with high T stage without LN metastasis (T3/4N0) or </p>

<p>low T stage with &gt;7 regional LN metastases (T1N3). However, 
we found no significant differences in the LINE-1 methyla-
tion levels between T3/4N0 and T1N3 (Fig. 3A). Therefore, 
we examined whether LINE-1 methylation in the FFPE tissues 
was associated with clinicopathological characteristics. We </p>

<p>LINE-1 As a Marker for Venous Invasion in Gastric Cancer 
Jimin Min et al. </p>

<p>Mol. Cells 2017; 40(5): 346-354 351 </p>

<p>Table 2. LINE-1 methylation status in FFPE GC tissues </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Number 
LINE-1 methylation level (%) </p>

<p>CpG 1 </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>CpG 2 </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>CpG 3 </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>CpG 4 </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>T y p e </p>

<p>T3/4N0 
13 
73.78 
0.207 
73.64 
0.250 
76.84 
0.446 
83.98 
0.226 </p>

<p>T1N3 
12 
77.26 
75.57 
78.91 
87.31 </p>

<p>A g e </p>

<p>≤57 
14 
77.85 
0.043 
74.57 
0.997 
79.09 
0.293 
85.56 
0.991 </p>

<p>&gt;57 
11 
72.40 
74.56 
76.23 
85.60 </p>

<p>G e n d e r </p>

<p>Male 
12 
75.25 
0.889 
74.23 
0.707 
76.88 
0.500 
85.16 
0.774 </p>

<p>Female 
13 
75.64 
74.87 
78.72 
85.96 </p>

<p>W H O c l a s s i f i c a t i o n </p>

<p>Differentiated 
6 
71.51 
0.103 
74.04 
0.870 
75.71 
0.384 
87.09 
0.487 </p>

<p>Undifferentiated 
15 
76.97 
74.40 
78.70 
84.60 </p>

<p>L a u r e n c l a s s i f i c a t i o n </p>

<p>Intestinal 
8 
71.58 
0.090 
74.28 
0.955 
76.07 
0.518 
87.35 
0.300 </p>

<p>Diffuse 
15 
76.55 
74.18 
77.96 
84.14 </p>

<p>T u m o r l o c a t i o n </p>

<p>Upper 
5 
75.44 
0.014 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>73.59 
0.156 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>75.17 
0.252 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>82.11 
0.367 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Middle 
5 
82.75 
0.002 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>77.73 
0.008 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>81.95 
0.080 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>88.19 
0.319 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Lower 
15 
73.02 
73.83 
77.35 
85.87 </p>

<p>L y m p h a t i c i n v a s i o n </p>

<p>Not identified 
11 
75.68 
0.883 
74.01 
0.563 
78.12 
0.856 
85.54 
0.982 </p>

<p>Present 
14 
75.27 
75.00 
77.62 
85.61 </p>

<p>V e n o u s i n v a s i o n </p>

<p>Not identified 
22 
76.11 
0.189 
75.17 
0.042 
79.10 
0.007 
86.67 
0.025 </p>

<p>Present 
3 
70.56 
70.10 
68.56 
77.58 </p>

<p>P e r i n e u r a l i n v a s i o n </p>

<p>Not identified 
12 
77.65 
0.120 
75.24 
0.440 
78.52 
0.631 
85.69 
0.939 </p>

<p>Present 
13 
73.41 
73.94 
77.21 
85.47 </p>

<p>T N M s t a g e </p>

<p>II 
23 
75.49 
0.919 
74.82 
0.309 
77.99 
0.703 
86.02 
0.274 </p>

<p>IV 
2 
74.97 
71.67 
76.07 
80.47 </p>

<p>Microsatellite instability </p>

<p>MSS 
14 
75.15 
0.379 
73.66 
0.826 
77.21 
0.852 
83.57 
0.555 </p>

<p>MSI-high 
3 
71.06 
74.33 
76.34 
86.53 
a ANOVA test </p>

<p>b Unpaired t-test (middle vs. lower)   divided the patients into three groups according to tumor 
location (i.e., upper, middle, or lower third of the stomach), 
and on average, LINE-1 was significantly hypomethylated in 
tumors located in the lower third region compared to those 
in the middle third region (Fig. 3B). When we analyzed LINE-
1 methylation patterns in each CpG site, the differences of 
LINE-1 methylation levels were also shown in several other 
characteristics (Table 2). On classifying patients into two 
groups according to the average age, only CpG1 of LINE-1 
was significantly hypomethylated in patients older than 57 
years. When tumor location was considered, only CpG1 and 
CpG2 were significantly different between tumors located in </p>

<p>the middle and lower third regions (p = 0.002 and p = 0.008, </p>

<p>respectively). In particular, LINE-1 methylation at CpG1 
showed a significant difference according to the tumor loca-
tion. The above-mentioned results indicate that LINE-1 
hypomethylation occurs at CpG1 in aged patients with GC. 
In addition, LINE-1 is hypomethylated in tumors located in 
the lower third region considering FFPE GC tissues. </p>

<p>LINE-1 hypomethylation in the presence of venous 
invasion in frozen and FFPE tissues </p>

<p>When we analyzed the LINE-1 methylation according to 
lymphatic invasion, LINE-1 hypomethylation was associated 
with the presence of lymphatic invasion in frozen tissues but 
not in FFPE tissues. Further analysis using FFPE tissues did </p>

<p>LINE-1 As a Marker for Venous Invasion in Gastric Cancer 
Jimin Min et al. </p>



<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Fig. 4. LINE-1 methylation and venous invasion in frozen and FFPE tissues. (A) LINE-1 hypo-methylation in frozen GC was observed </p>

<p>irrespective of whether patients have venous invasion or not (p &lt; 0.001, p &lt; 0.001, res-pectively). LINE-1 was significantly hypomethy-</p>

<p>lated in the presence of invasion (Present) compared to the absence of it (Not identified) (p = 0.016). (B) LINE-1 methylation significant-
ly differed considering the presence (Present) and absence of venous invasion (Not identified) (p = 0.017). (C) LINE-1 was significantly </p>

<p>hypo-methylated in the presence of venous invasion in combined frozen and FFPE tissues (p = 0.001). *p &lt; 0.05 (unpaired t test). </p>

<p>not show any significant difference between the absence of 
LN metastasis and the presence of aggressive LN metastasis. 
Therefore, we investigated whether LINE-1 methylation 
changes are associated with venous invasion in both frozen 
and FFPE tissues. LINE-1 in frozen tissues became hypo-
methylated in the presence of venous invasion compared to 
the absence of venous invasion or NM (Fig. 4A and Table 1). 
Moreover, in FFPE tissues, LINE-1 methylation significantly 
differed considering the presence and absence of venous 
invasion (Fig. 4B). The difference was significant at the CpG2, 
CpG3, and CpG4 sites (Table 2). In addition, we analyzed 
the average LINE-1 methylation level at CpG1 and CpG4 
together according to all clinical characteristics, since a pre-
vious study showed that analysis of this combination was 
useful to predict prognosis for GC (Song et al., 2016). The 
results from this analysis were consistent with our findings 
from all CpG sites (data not shown), and combined two 
CpG sites was also a predictive factor of venous invasion 
(Supplementary Fig. S3). Therefore, LINE-1 hypomethylation 
was indicated in the presence of venous invasion in com-
bined frozen and FFPE tissues (Fig. 4C). These results sug-
gest that LINE-1 hypomethylation is strongly associated with 
venous invasion, irrespective of the tissue-storage type. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Considering the tissue-storage conditions in different cancer 
types, a previous study reported that colon tissues show 
clustered methylation patterns according to storage type 
(frozen vs. FFPE), and differentially methylated loci have 
been observed between the two sample types (Jasmine et al.,  2012). Another study postulated that the methylation status </p>

<p>of the MGMT promoter differs between paraffin-fixed and </p>

<p>fresh-frozen tissues of glioblastoma (Hamilton et al., 2011). 
On evaluating 38 patients with GC, LINE-1 was reportedly 
more hypermethylated in FFPE tissues than in paired fresh-
frozen tissues (Song et al., 2016). 
Since the patient tissues were dissected for different pur-
poses, they were preserved in various forms and given dif-
ferent pre-treatments. For pathological examination, GC </p>

<p>tissues were fixed with formalin and embedded in paraffin. 
In contrast, for genomic analysis, tissues were immediately 
frozen in liquid nitrogen without fixation following gastrec-
tomy. Bisulfite conversion can be affected by formalin fixa-
tion, as sequence artifacts such as cytosine deamination can 
be caused by formaldehyde (Do and Dobrovic, 2015). There-
fore, we screened the LINE-1 methylation patterns in each 
tissue type separately to determine whether LINE-1 can be 
used as a marker under all circumstances. In the current 
study, we used samples from different patient groups, and 
different methylation levels were also observed between the 
two tissue types (Fig. 1A). Moreover, when we compared 
the LINE-1 methylation level in frozen GC tissues and paired 
adjacent NM, LINE-1 was significantly hypomethylated in GC 
tissue compared to NM (Fig. 2A), consistent with the find-
ings of previous studies (Bae et al., 2012; Shigaki et al.,  2013). 
There are various methods to develop methylation bi-
omarkers by quantification of DNA methylation. Recently, all 
routinely used assays for DNA methylation analysis were 
compared in different laboratories and countries. The results 
suggested that bisulfite pyrosequencing is a powerful and 
promising assay for developing biomarkers to measure abso-
lute DNA methylation levels (Consortium, 2016). For LINE-1 
methylation analysis, diverse assays, such as pyrosequencing, 
combined bisulfite restriction analysis, or MethyLight, have 
been used to measure methylation changes in samples from 
patients with cancer. However, among them, pyrosequenc-
ing is the most useful technique to detect LINE-1 methyla-
tion because it provides accurate and reliable results (Apari- cio et al., 2009; Baba et al., 2014; Irahara et al., 2010). 
Therefore, this method is most commonly used in research 
on LINE-1 in human cancers. 
Recently, Kim et al. reported that LINE-1 was differentially 
methylated according to the Vienna classification, and they 
suggested LINE-1 as a marker for early GC (Kim et al., 2016). 
Moreover, LINE-1 methylation at specific CpG sites was a 
prognostic marker in FFPE tissues obtained from 434 pa-
tients with advanced GC (Song et al., 2016). Likewise, sev-
eral studies have evaluated LINE-1 methylation in GC, to the </p>

<p>LINE-1 As a Marker for Venous Invasion in Gastric Cancer 
Jimin Min et al. </p>

<p>Mol. Cells 2017; 40(5): 346-354 353 </p>

<p>best of our knowledge, this is the first study to determine 
the association between LINE-1 methylation level and clini-
copathological parameters in both frozen and FFPE sample 
types in GC. The current study had two main aims. The first 
was to determine the relationship between LINE-1 methyla-
tion and clinicopathological features using frozen tissues, 
and several features were associated with LINE-1 methyla-
tion change. The second aim was to analyze the relationship 
between LINE-1 methylation and aggressive LN metastasis 
using FFPE tissues, because we only obtained FFPE tissues 
from patients diagnosed with early GC (T1) with high LN 
metastasis (N3). However, we did not find any significant 
difference in LINE-1 methylation between T3/4N0 and T1N3 
(Fig. 3A). 
In other cancers, LINE-1 methylation was associated with 
venous invasion in various samples such as serum or frozen 
tissue (Ikeda et al., 2013; Tangkijvanich et al., 2007). In GC, 
vascular invasion can increase angiogenesis and distant me-
tastasis including lymph node metastasis (Maehara et al.,  2000). After curative resection, LINE-1 methylation is even 
associated with recurrence and poor survival in GC, even 
though patients do not have metastasis (Li et al., 2015). 
Accordingly, finding biomarkers for venous invasion can be a 
powerful tool to predict invasive potential and prognosis. 
Because LINE-1 methylation has been known to be associat-
ed with venous invasion in GC FFPE tissues, we additionally 
used frozen tissues to clarify whether LINE-1 could also be a 
biomarker for venous invasion in other sample types. LINE-1 
hypomethylation was detected in the presence of venous 
invasion in both FFPE and frozen tissues (Fig. 4). Further 
study using blood samples is needed to investigate whether 
LINE-1 methylation can be a non-invasive marker in GC. 
Despite our important findings, our present study has 
some limitations. First, we used FFPE GC tissues according to 
specific T and N stages without paired normal tissues to ana-
lyze the relationship between LINE-1 methylation and T1N3 
GC. Therefore, we could not compare the LINE-1 methyla-
tion levels in both normal and GC tissues. Second, the sam-
ple size was relatively small. Although a significant difference 
in the LINE-1 methylation level was correlated with venous 
invasion in FFPE and frozen tissues, only few cases of venous 
invasion were analyzed. In further studies, a larger sample 
size should be included to increase the reliability and acquire 
statistically significant data. In particular, validation studies 
using larger sample sizes irrespective of the T or N stages 
should be conducted. 
In conclusion, this study validated the LINE-1 methylation 
patterns in FFPE and frozen tissues in different GC patient 
groups and verified the relationships between clinicopatho-
logical parameters and LINE-1 methylation in each sample 
set. In frozen tissues, the LINE-1 methylation was associated 
with gender, differentiation state, and lymphatic and venous 
invasion. In FFPE tissues, the LINE-1 methylation levels signif-
icantly differed according to tumor location and venous in-
vasion. Therefore, LINE-1 can be a useful marker for several 
clinical factors in each tissue-storage type and could be a 
biomarker for venous invasion in both frozen and FFPE GC 
tissues. </p>

<p>Note: Supplementary information is available on the Mole-
cules and Cells website (www.molcells.org). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants from the Korean 
Healthcare Technology R&amp;D project through the Korean 
Health Industry Development Institute (KHIDI), funded by the 
Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare, Republic of Korea (grant No. 
HI14C3426). This study was supported by the National Re-
search Foundation of Korea (NRF) grant, funded by the Ko-
rean government (2014R1A5A2009242). </p>



</text></tei>