<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5348138" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The beat-to-beat blood pressure (BP) monitoring parameters, such as average beat-to-beat BP, BP variability (BPV), could have an 
influence on the vascular elasticity. This study hypothesized that the elevated beat-to-beat BPV could evoke the reduction of the vascular 
elasticity independent of BP levels. We measured the beat-to-beat BP recordings and total arterial compliance (TAC), which was used to 
assess the vascular elasticity, in 80 young healthy adults during the cold pressor test (CPT). The CPT included 3 phases: baseline phase, 
cold stimulus phase, recovery phase. Six parameters were used to estimate BPV. In bivariate correlation analysis, TAC showed a 
significant correlation with systolic BP (SBP) and diastolic BP (DBP) in the cold stimulus phase; and 4 indices of SBP variability (SBPV) 
were associated with TAC (r = 0.271∼0.331, P 0.015) in the recovery phase; similarly, 2 indices of DBP variability (DBPV) were also 
correlated with TAC (r = 0.221∼0.285, P 0.048) in the recovery phase. In multivariate regression analysis, DBPV (b = 0.229, P = 0.001) 
was a determinant of TAC independent of average DBP, sex, and weight. In addition, both beat-to-beat BP and BPV values increased in 
the cold stimulus phase (P &lt; 0.01); whereas, the TAC decreased in the cold stimulus phase (P &lt; 0.01). In conclusion, these data suggest 
that the beat-to-beat DBPV shows an independent association with the vascular elasticity in young normal adults during the CPT. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ARV = average real variability, BP = blood pressure, BPV = blood pressure variability, CPT = cold pressor test, CV 
= coefficient of variation, CVD = cardiovascular disease, DBP = diastolic blood pressure, DBPV = diastolic blood pressure variability, 
HF = high frequency, HR = heart rate, HRV = heart rate variability, IMT = intima-media thickness, LF = low frequency, LF/HF = the 
ratio between low frequency and high frequency, LV = left ventricle (LV), PNS = parasympathetic nerve system, PWV = pulse wave 
velocities, RSD = residual standard deviation, SBP = systolic blood pressure, SBPV = systolic blood pressure variability, SD = 
standard deviation, SNS = sympathetic nervous system, SV = successive variation, SV/PP = the ratio of stroke volume to pulse 
pressure, TAC = total arterial compliance, VIM = variation independent of mean. </p>

<p>According to the report from the World Health Organization, the 
cardiovascular disease (CVD) remained the number one cause of 
death globally. 
[1] Some studies had demonstrated that aging 
played an important role in the progress of CVD, 
[2-4] and the 
early vascular aging reflected the progress of aging on vascular 
tree and arterial function. 
[5] The early vascular aging could cause 
the structural and functional modifications in the vasculature, 
accompanied by the decreased arterial elasticity and elevated 
arterial stiffness. </p>

<p>[6,7] </p>

<p>Arterial elasticity could be assessed by total arterial compliance 
(TAC). TAC was an assessment of the stiffness of the arteries 
in the entire arterial tree, 
[8] and it reflected the elasticity of the 
vascular system. 
[9,10] Some studies had demonstrated that TAC 
played a critical role in predicting CVD. 
[9-12] Moreover, previous 
studies had also manifested that TAC was an important 
determinant of arterial load, left ventricle (LV) afterload, and 
pulse wave velocities (PWV). 
[13,14] TAC might be influenced by 
the blood pressure (BP) parameters, such as BP and BP variability 
(BPV). Recently, some studies investigated the relation between 
short-term BPV parameters, which included the 24-hour BPV and 
beat-to-beat BPV, and vascular properties. 
[7,15-19] And they 
found that the increased 24-hour BPV had adverse influences on 
the vascular properties, 
[7,15-18] while the relationship between 
vascular properties and beat-to-beat BPV was non-significant. </p>

<p>[19] </p>

<p>Beat-to-beat BP measurement was increasingly used both in the 
research field and clinical research, as it could reflect more </p>

<p>Editor: Leonardo Gilardi. </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by the Science Technology and Innovation 
Committee of Shenzhen for research projects (Grant CXZZ20140909004122087 
and JCYJ20150529164154046), Guangdong Image-guided Therapy Innovation 
Team (2011S013), the Guangzhou Science and Technology Planning Project 
(No. 2016A030310129), the STS project of Chinese Academy of Sciences (KFJ-
EW-STS-097), Shenzhen Innovation Funding (SGLH20150213143207911, 
JCYJ20140901003939025, JCYJ20151030151431727), and the National Key 
Research and Development Program of China (2016YFC1300300). </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>a Research Center for Biomedical Information Technology, Shenzhen Institute of 
Advance Technology, Chinese Academic of Science, 
b Shenzhen Children 
Hospital, 
c Department of Neurology, Shenzhen Second People's Hospital, Futian 
District, 
d Shenzhen College of Advanced Technology, University of Chinese 
Academy of Sciences,Shenzhen University Town, Shenzhen, China. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Correspondence: Wanqing Wu, Research Center for Biomedical Information 
Technology, Shenzhen Institute of Advance Technology, Chinese Academic of 
Science, 1068 Xueyuan Avenue, Shenzhen University Town, Shenzhen, 518055, 
China (e-mail: wq.wu@siat.ac.cn); Lijie Ren, Department of Neurology, Shenzhen 
Second People's Hospital, Sungang Road, Futian District, Shenzhen, 518035, 
China (e-mail: 13631605966@126.com). </p>

<p>Copyright © 2017 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-ShareAlike License 4.0, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build 
upon the work, even for commercial purposes, as long as the author is credited 
and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms. </p>

<p>Medicine (2017) 96:8(e6000) </p>

<p>Received: 8 December 2016 / Received in final form: 27 December 2016 / 
Accepted: 28 December 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000006000 </p>

<p>Observational Study </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>OPEN </p>



<p>information than 24-hour BP and office BP. 
[20] And beat-to-beat 
BP recordings were considered as the optimal method to obtain 
the short-term BPV. 
[19,20] Moreover, beat-to-beat BP parameters 
had also been proved to associate with CVD and target organ 
damage. 
[19,21] Accurate beat-to-beat BP used to obtain from 
invasive method 
[22] ; the non-invasive continuous BP monitoring 
in the finger arterial was an excellent innovation in continuous BP 
measurement. 
In this study, we hypothesized that the beat-to-beat BP 
monitoring parameters, such as systolic BP (SBP), diastolic BP 
(DBP), SBP variability (SBPV), and DBP variability (DBPV), 
could have influences on the vascular elasticity, assessed by TAC. 
We measured beat-to-beat BP values, TAC, electrocardiograph 
(ECG), and demographics in a normal young population. As the 
TAC could be changed in the cold pressor test (CPT), 
[23] which 
had been used as a stress to estimate the cardiac autonomic 
function, left ventricular function, cardiovascular reactivity, and 
sympathetic activity, 
[23,24] we used CPT in this study. Our aim 
was to investigate the relationship between vascular elasticity and 
beat-to-beat BPV in normal young adults during the CPT. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Study population </p>

<p>The study population consisted of 80 healthy, normal young adults 
(51 men, 63.75%, age range 21-33 years). All the subjects met the 
following criteria: (a) no history of hypertension; (b) no history of 
diabetes mellitus, cardiopathy, or other chronic diseases; (c) no 
pharmacological treatment; (d) no history of drug abuse. Body 
weight and height were measured with the subjects without shoes 
and in light clothing. Body mass index (BMI) was estimated by the 
ratio of weight (kg) to the height square (m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). All the subjects were 
asked to refrain from caffeine, cigarette, alcohol, or severe physical 
activities for 3 to 4 hours prior to the experiment. They were 
informed of the discomfort or pain elicited by the CPT before the 
experiment. All subjects volunteered to participate in this study, 
and the written informed consent forms were obtained from all of 
the subjects. The study was approved by the Institutional Review 
Board of Shenzhen Institutes of Advanced Technology. </p>

<p>2.2. Experimental design </p>

<p>The experiment took place in a quiet temperature-controlled 
laboratory, and the ambient temperature was kept 26°C. In the 
experiment, the subjects lay in the supine position on a single bed 
quietly throughout the experimental procedure. The procedure of 
the CPT experiment lasted 13 minutes and included 3 phases 
(showed in Fig. 1): the baseline phase (5 minutes), the cold stimulus 
phase (3 minutes), and the recovery phase (5 minutes). In the cold 
stimulus phase, the subject immersed his/her left hand to the wrist 
into a mixture of ice and water (4°C) for 3 minutes. During the 
entire experimental procedure, cardiovascular signals were 
collected by Finometer MIDI (Model II, Finapres Medical Systems 
B.V., Amsterdam, The Netherlands); and the cardiovascular 
signals mainly included SBP, DBP, stoke volume, and electrocar-
diograph (ECG). Then these cardiovascular signals were stored in a </p>

<p>personal computer by the <rs id="software-0" type="software">BeatScope Easy software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Finapres Medical Systems B.V., Amsterdam, The Netherlands</rs>). The BP was 
measured by the volume-clamp method in the Finometer MIDI </p>

<p>[25] </p>

<p>; 
in the volume-clamp method, a cuff wrapped around the finger to 
keep the arterial diameter constant, and the changes in the arterial 
diameter were detected by photo-plethysmography </p>

<p>[25] </p>

<p>; physiocal 
algorithm was used to maintain the correct arterial diameter. </p>

<p>[26] </p>

<p>The stroke volume was measured by Modelflow method </p>

<p>[25] </p>

<p>; 
the Modelflow method was utilized to calculate an aortic flow 
waveform from the finger pressure by simulating a non-linear 
three-element model of aortic input impedance. </p>

<p>[25] </p>

<p>2.3. TAC assessment </p>

<p>There was no "gold standard" to assess the TAC. Chemla et al </p>

<p>[13] </p>

<p>proposed the ratio of stroke volume to pulse pressure (SV/PP) to 
measure TAC. The pulse pressure represented the difference 
between SBP and DBP readings. The SV/PP had been proven 
reliable to assess the TAC. 
[11] Therefore, we used SV/PP to 
estimate TAC in this study. </p>

<p>2.4. BPV assessment </p>

<p>Usually, BPV was evaluated by the standard deviation (SD) and 
coefficient of variation (CV) of BP measurements. 
[27] However, 
the assessment by SD might be unreliable in multivariate 
module, 
[28,29] because SD only reflected the global fluctuation 
of BP measurements around the mean value and did not take the 
time sequence of measurements into account. CV was derived 
from SD and mean BP, and it might be correlated with mean BP. 
To overcome these disadvantages of the commonly used SD and 
CV, average real variability (ARV), variation independent of 
mean (VIM), residual standard deviation (RSD), and successive 
variation (SV) were established to estimate the prognostic 
significance of BPV. 
[28-31] ARV took the time sequence of 
individual BP measurements into account, and it could also 
estimate the trend of BPV without making any assumptions 
regarding the shape of the relationship between BP values and 
time. 
[28] VIM was a transformation of SD that was uncorrelated 
with mean levels. 
[29] When VIM was used as an index of BPV, it 
could eliminate the effects of mean BP levels. RSD was defined as 
the square root of the residual mean square after fitting a linear 
regression to BP against time 
[30] ; and it was more suitable than 
SD to estimated BPV when the BP fluctuation had an underlying 
trend over time, especially the underlying trend was approxi-
mately linear. SV was defined as the square root of the average 
squared difference between successive BP measurements; and it 
also addressed the time sequence of measurements. 
[31] In this 
study, SD, CV, VIM, ARV, SV, and RSD were used to assess BPV. 
Because the BPV included SBPV and DBPV, we used these indices 
to quantify SBPV and DBPV, respectively. These parameters were 
calculated using the following formulas: </p>

<p>SD ¼ </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
1 
n À 1 </p>

<p>X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>ðX i À XÞ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>ð1Þ </p>

<p>CV ¼ 100 Á 
SD 
X 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>VIM ¼ k⋅SD=X </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>ð3Þ </p>

<p>RSD ¼ </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
P n </p>

<p>i¼2 </p>

<p>ðX i ÀX i Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>n À 2 </p>

<p>v 
u 
u 
u 
t 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>Figure 1. The 3 phases of the cold pressor test. </p>

<p>Xia et al. Medicine (2017) 96:8 
Medicine </p>



<p>ARV ¼ </p>

<p>1 
n À 1 
⋅ 
X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>jX iþ1 À X i j 
ð 5Þ </p>

<p>SV ¼ </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
1 
n À 1 </p>

<p>X nÀ1 </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>ðX iþ1 À X i Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>v 
u 
u 
t 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>Where X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X n represented a set of BP measurement 
values; X was the mean value of the set of BP measurement 
values;X 1 ,X 2 ,...,X n were the fitted values from a linear 
regression of BP against time; k and m were obtained from a 
fitting curve of the form y = kx 
p through a plot of SD BP (y-axis) 
against mean BP (x-axis). </p>

<p>2.5. HR variability assessment </p>

<p>HR variability (HRV) had become a significant method to 
estimate the cardiovascular autonomic regulation. 
[32] We </p>

<p>assessed the HRV from ECG readings. In time-domain, the SD 
of R-R intervals (SDNN) were used to estimate the HRV 
[32] ; in 
frequency-domain, spectrum estimate was calculated from the 
RR interval 
[33] ; we main calculated low frequency (LF, 
0.04-0.15 Hz), high frequency (HF, 0.15-0.4 Hz), and the ratio 
between LF and HF (LF/HF). </p>

<p>2.6. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) 19.0 (SPSS Inc., 
Chicago, IL) was used for statistical analysis. Descriptive statistics 
were presented as mean± SD. Repeated-measures analysis of 
variance (ANOVA) was used to test the differences of parameters 
among the 3 phases of CPT. Pearson correlation coefficients were 
used to investigate the bivariate associations between TAC and 
examined variables. Stepwise multivariate linear regression analysis 
(stepwise criteria: probability of F-to-enter 0.050, probability of F-
to-remove ≥0.100) was used to elucidate the independent deter-
minants of TAC. P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Demographic and clinical characteristics data </p>

<p>Demographic data, BP and HR values of the population were 
listed in Table 1. The 80 subjects included 51 men (63.75%). 
Their age (mean ± SD) was 25.2 ± 2.4 years, and the BMI was 
21.2 ± 2.1 kg/m 
2 . Their SBP was 111.7 ± 9.7 mmHg, and their 
DBP was 62.9 ± 6.6 mmHg. Their HR was 67.1 ± 10.3 beats/min. 
None of them was a smoker. </p>

<p>3.2. Repeated-measures analysis of variance analysis </p>

<p>The beat-to-beat BP, BPV, HR, HRV, and TAC values in the 3 
phases of the CPT were presented in Table 2. The SBP and DBP </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Clinical characteristics of the study subjects. </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Value (mean ± SD, n = 80) </p>

<p>Age, y 
25.2 ± 2.4 
Male, % 
51 (63.75%) 
Smoking, % 
0 
Height, cm 
168.4 ± 7.5 
Weight, kg 
60.4 ± 9.8 
BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>21.2 ± 2.1 
SBP, mmHg 
111.7 ± 9.7 
DBP, mmHg 
62.9 ± 6.6 
HR, beat/min 
67.1 ± 10.3 </p>

<p>BMI = body mass index, DBP = diastolic blood pressure, HR = heart rate, SBP = systolic blood 
pressure, SD = standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>The beat-to-beat blood pressure parameters, heart rate parameters, and total arterial compliance in 3 phases of cold pressor test. </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Baseline 
Cold stimulus 
Recovery 
P 
(mean ± SD) 
(mean ± SD) 
(mean ± SD) </p>

<p>SBP, mmHg 
122.2 ± 13.1 
136.9 ± 13.2 
127.6 ± 12.1 
&lt;0.001 
DBP, mmHg 
70.2 ± 8.7 
81.1 ± 8.8 
73.9 ± 7.9 
&lt;0.001 
SBP_SD, mmHg 
5.35 ± 1.28 
8.53 ± 4.63 
5.45 ± 1.71 
&lt;0.001 
SBP_CV, Unit 
4.42 ± 1.15 
6.25 ± 3.35 
4.29 ± 1.37 
&lt;0.001 
SBP_VIM, Unit 
5.35 ± 1.28 
8.53 ± 4.60 
5.45 ± 1.70 
&lt;0.001 
SBP_ARV, mmHg 
1.68 ± 0.38 
2.05 ± 0.88 
1.72 ± 0.40 
&lt;0.001 
SBP_SV, mmHg 
2.32 ± 0.45 
2.93 ± 1.32 
2.29 ± 0.56 
&lt;0.001 
SBP_RSD, mmHg 
5.04 ± 1.25 
6.79 ± 3.06 
5.15 ± 1.49 
&lt;0.001 
DBP_SD, mmHg 
3.78 ± 0.85 
6.52 ± 2.81 
4.04 ± 1.02 
&lt;0.001 
DBP_CV, Unit 
5.48 ± 1.54 
8.08 ± 3.59 
5.51 ± 1.53 
&lt;0.001 
DBP_VIM, Unit 
3.78 ± 0.87 
6.52 ± 2.80 
4.04 ± 1.02 
&lt;0.001 
DBP_ARV, mmHg 
1.39 ± 0.45 
1.72 ± 0.57 
1.50 ± 0.52 
&lt;0.001 
DBP_SV, mmHg 
1.95 ± 0.57 
2.44 ± 0.85 
2.06 ± 0.66 
&lt;0.001 
DBP_RSD, mmHg 
3.67 ± 0.85 
5.18 ± 1.76 
3.84 ± 0.90 
&lt;0.001 
HR, beats/min 
65.6 ± 8.9 
68.6 ± 9.8 
65.1 ± 8.6 
&lt;0.001 
HR_SD, beats/min 
4.25 ± 1.27 
5.33 ± 1.74 
4.62 ± 1.30 
&lt;0.001 
RR_interval, ms 
939.5 ± 137.9 
899.0 ± 133.9 
940.3 ± 138.7 
0.001 
SDNN, ms 
56.7 ± 21.6 
67.3 ± 26.1 
66.5 ± 26.5 
0.001 
HR_LF, n.u. 
49.0 ± 18.1 
53.4 ± 17.0 
48.3 ± 17.9 
0.034 
HR_HF, n.u. 
50.9 ± 18.1 
46.5 ± 17.0 
51.5 ± 17.9 
0.034 
HR_LF/HF, n.u. 
1.09 ± 0.88 
1.55 ± 1.17 
1.23 ± 1.16 
0.008 
TAC, mL/mmHg 
1.63 ± 0.27 
1.50 ± 0.24 
1.60 ± 0.25 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Baseline, cold stimulus, and recovery represent 3 phases of the cold pressor test, respectively. 
ARV = average real variability, CV = coefficient of variation, DBP = diastolic blood pressure, HF = high frequency, HR = heart rate, LF/HF = the ratio between low frequency and high frequency, LF = low frequency, 
n.u. = normalized unit, RSD = residual standard deviation, SBP = systolic blood pressure, SD = standard deviation, SDNN = standard deviation of RR interval, SV = successive variation, TAC = total arterial 
compliance, VIM = variation independent of mean. </p>

<p>Xia et al. Medicine (2017) 96:8 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>values in the cold stimulus phase were significantly larger than the 
values both in the baseline phase and the recovery phase (P &lt; 
0.001). Moreover, all of the 6 indices of SBPV and DBPV in the 
cold stimulus phase were also remarkably larger than the values 
in the baseline phase and the recovery phase (P &lt; 0.001). 
Similarly, HR values in the cold stimulus phase were larger 
than the values in the baseline phase and the recovery phase (P &lt; 
0.001) significantly. Moreover, SD of HR, SDNN, LF, and LF/ 
HF in the cold stimulus phase were also larger than the values in 
the baseline and recovery phases (P &lt; 0.001, P = 0.001, P = 0.034, 
P = 0.008, respectively). Whereas, the RR interval and HF in the 
cold stimulus phase were smaller than the values in the baseline 
and recovery phases (P = 0.034, P = 0.001, respectively). Similar-
ly, TAC values in the cold stimulus phase were smaller than the 
values in the baseline phase and the recovery phase (P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>3.3. Bivariate correlation analysis </p>

<p>Pearson correlations of TAC with the beat-to-beat BP, BPV, HR, 
HRV, and demographic data in the 3 phases of CPT were shown 
in Table 3. TAC showed a significant correlation with sex, height, 
weight, BMI in all of the 3 phases of CPT. In the baseline phase, 
LF and HF of HR showed a significant correlation with TAC (r = 
0.308, P = 0.010; r = À0.306, P = 0.010, respectively). In the cold 
stimulus phase, both SBP and DBP were related to TAC 
remarkably (r = 0.291, P = 0.009; r = 0.339, P = 0.002; respec-
tively). In the recovery phase, neither SBP nor DBP was correlated 
with TAC remarkably (P ≥ 0.054); whereas, SD, CV, VIM, and </p>

<p>RSD of SBP were associated with TAC significantly (r = 0.271, 
P = 0.015; r = 0.331, P = 0.003; r = 0.285, P = 0.010; r = 0.282, 
P = 0.011; respectively); CV and VIM of DBP were also 
correlated with TAC remarkably (r = 0.285, P = 0.010; r = 
0.221, P = 0.048; respectively). Furthermore, SDNN, LF, and 
HF of HR also showed an important correlation with TAC (r = 
0.234, P = 0.044; r = 0.257, P = 0.032; r = 0.256, P = 0.032; 
respectively) in the recovery phase. </p>

<p>3.4. Stepwise multivariate linear regression analysis </p>

<p>Tables 4 and 5 showed the stepwise multivariate linear regression 
analysis of the TAC with the demographics, beat-to-beat BP 
parameters and HR parameters in the cold stimulus phase and the 
recovery phase, respectively. The independent relationship 
between TAC and BPV was demonstrated in a stepwise </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Pearson correlation of total arterial compliance with demographic data, heart rate, beat-to-beat blood pressure parameters. </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Baseline 
Cold stimulus 
Recovery 
r 
P 
r 
P 
r 
P </p>

<p>Gender, male/female 
0.644 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
0.544 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
0.582 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
Age, y 
0.083 
0.465 
0.019 
0.869 
0.083 
0.464 
Height, m 
0.661 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
0.583 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
0.608 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
Weight, kg 
0.636 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
0.568 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
0.594 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.459 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
0.418 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
0.431 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
SBP, mmHg 
-0.155 
0.169 
-0.291 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>0.009 
-0.172 
0.127 
DBP, mmHg 
-0.170 
0.131 
-0.339 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>0.002 
-0.216 
0.054 
SBP_SD, mmHg 
0.147 
0.194 
-0.059 
0.604 
0.271 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.015 
SBP_CV, Unit 
0.202 
0.072 
0.002 
0.987 
0.331 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>0.003 
SBP_VIM, Unit 
0.161 
0.155 
-0.045 
0.689 
0.285 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.010 
SBP_ARV, mmHg 
-0.103 
0.364 
-0.213 
0.058 
0.010 
0.928 
SBP_SV, mmHg 
0.008 
0.947 
-0.193 
0.086 
0.072 
0.528 
SBP_RSD, mmHg 
0.195 
0.082 
-0.178 
0.114 
0.282 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.011 
DBP_SD, mmHg 
0.093 
0.410 
0.024 
0.833 
0.204 
0.070 
DBP_CV, Unit 
0.158 
0.162 
0.099 
0.381 
0.285 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.010 
DBP_VIM, Unit 
0.108 
0.339 
0.041 
0.718 
0.221 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.048 
DBP_ARV, mmHg 
0.070 
0.535 
0.002 
0.989 
0.078 
0.494 
DBP_SV, mmHg 
0.115 
0.309 
-0.016 
0.891 
0.095 
0.401 
DBP_RSD, mmHg 
0.114 
0.315 
-0.122 
0.281 
0.172 
0.128 
HR, beats/min 
-0.087 
0.459 
-0.185 
0.111 
-0.124 
0.290 
HR_SD, beats/min 
0.052 
0.660 
-0.007 
0.954 
0.169 
0.147 
SDNN, ms 
0.181 
0.120 
0.123 
0.295 
0.234 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.044 
HR_LF, n.u. 
0.308 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>0.010 
-0.180 
0.135 
0.257 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.032 
HR_HF, n.u. 
-0.306 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>0.010 
0.181 
0.134 
-0.256 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.032 
HR_LF/HF, n.u. 
0.207 
0.085 
-0.165 
0.173 
0.129 
0.287 </p>

<p>Baseline, cold stimulus, and recovery represent 3 phases of the cold pressor test, respectively. 
ARV = average real variability, BMI = body mass index, CV = coefficient of variation, DBP = diastolic blood pressure, HF = high frequency, HR = heart rate, LF/HF = the ratio between low frequency and high 
frequency, LF = low frequency, n.u. = normalized unit, RSD = residual standard deviation, SBP = systolic blood pressure, SD = standard deviation, SDNN = standard deviation of RR interval, SV = successive 
variation, TAC = total arterial compliance, VIM = variation independent of mean. 
 *  P &lt; 0.05. 
 *  *  P &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>Independent predictors of total arterial compliance in multivariate 
linear regression analysis during cold stimulus phase of cold 
pressor test. </p>

<p>Variable 
b 
P 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>DBP, mmHg 
-0.529 
&lt;0.001 
0.653 
Gender, male/female 
0.436 
&lt;0.001 
Weight, kg 
0.352 
&lt;0.001 
HR, beats/min 
-0.147 
0.036 </p>

<p>DBP = diastolic blood pressure, HR = heart rate. </p>

<p>Xia et al. Medicine (2017) 96:8 
Medicine </p>



<p>multivariate linear regression model. VIM of DBP was associated 
with TAC independent of DBP, sex and weight in the recovery 
phase of the CPT. Figure 2 showed the linear relationship 
between TAC and VIM of DBP in the recovery phase of CPT. 
Whereas neither SBP nor SBPV showed significant correlation 
with TAC in cold stimulus phase or recovery phase. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, our results offer explicit evidence of the significant 
correlations between vascular elasticity, as estimated by TAC, 
and different measures of beat-to-beat SBPV and DBPV in young 
normal adults during the CPT. It implies that increased beat-to-
beat BPV has an important influence on structural and functional 
vascular properties, and increases the progress of the early 
vascular aging in young normal adults independent of mean BP 
levels. 
In addition, our study also has some other merits. Firstly, the 
association of TAC with beat-to-beat BP has been confirmed in 
the cold stimulus phase of the CPT. Secondly, the augmentation 
of mean beat-to-beat BP and BPV values is confirmed in the cold 
stimulus phase of the CPT. Thirdly, HR and HRV in time-
domain also increase in the cold stimulus phase; the LF and LF/ 
HF in frequency increase, but the HF decrease in the cold stimulus 
phase. Fourthly, in the bivariate correlation analysis, LF and HF 
component of HRV had a significant correlation with TAC in </p>

<p>baseline and recovery phases. Lastly, the reduction of the TAC is 
found in the cold stimulus phase of the CPT. 
These experimental results may have some potential clinical 
implications. Even in normal young adults, the increase of BPV 
has an adverse influence of the vascular elasticity independent of 
BP. So not only keeping the BP in a normal range but also 
decreasing the BPV may be helpful to prevent the early 
cardiovascular diseases and complications. Furthermore, the 
increase of BPV may predict the early vascular lesions, and it can 
be as a mark of premature cardiovascular diseases. The decreased 
BPV may be also advantageous for the treatment of cardiovas-
cular diseases. 
There is a physiological inference to explicate our results. The 
beat-to-beat BPV mainly reflects the effects of the central 
sympathetic drive, arterial or cardiopulmonary reflex, humoral, 
rheological, behavioral, and emotional factors. 
[20] When the 
vascular elasticity reduces, it can be associated with the change of 
the BPV. Moreover, previous studies have explored the 
relationship between vascular properties and short-term BPV 
both in healthy population 
[7] and in patient population. 
[15-19] In 
these studies, PWV was used to assess the arterial stiffness, and 
intima-media thickness (IMT) was a surrogate marker for 
atherosclerosis. Kotsis et al 
[7] studied 115 young healthy 
volunteers; and they manifested that increased 24-hour SBPV 
associated with arterial stiffness in young healthy population. 
Schillaci et al 
[15] explored the relationship between 24-hour BPV 
and aortic stiffness in hypertensive population, and found that 
the association between ARV and PWV was closer than other 
indices; and they thought that ARV focused on the very short-
term BPV between successive readings. Stabouli et al 
[16] studied 
138 children and adolescents patients; and they attested that 
weighted 24-hour and daytime SBPV associated with arterial 
stiffness in children and adolescents. Tatasciore et al 
[17] studied 
the correlation between 24-hour BPV and IMT in 180 untreated 
hypertensive subjects; and they found that awake SBPV was a 
better correlate of IMT than 24 hour SBPV. Mancia et al </p>

<p>[18] </p>

<p>explored 1663 hypertensive patients; they also manifested that 
24-h SBPV was related to IMT. Furthermore, Wei et al </p>

<p>[19] </p>

<p>investigated the relationship between arterial stiffness and BPV 
over different periods in 256 untreated patients; they used ARV, 
VIM, and maximum-minimum difference (MMD) to assess the 
BPV; and they found that the PWV increased with beat-to-beat 
SBP, but did not increase with beat-to-beat SBPV; moreover, they 
also found that the PWV increased with 24-hour SBP and VIM of 
24-hour SBP. In stepwise multivariate linear regression analysis, 
our results showed that VIM of DBP was an independent 
determinant of the vascular elasticity, but the correlation of TAC 
with SBPV was not significant. The different methods to estimate 
the BPV and vascular properties might cause the difference. 
Interestingly, in the present study, some indices of beat-to-beat 
BPV correlated with the TAC in the recovery phase of the CPT; 
whereas, no indices of beat-to-beat BPV associated with TAC in 
the baseline phase and cold stimulus phase in young normal 
adults. The results showed that the BPV increased from the 
baseline phase to the cold stimulus phase, while it decreased from 
the cold stimulus phase to the recovery phase. However, the 
change of TAC was contrary to the change of BPV during the 
CPT. It suggests that the reduced BPV may have an influence on 
the increase in TAC. 
In addition, our results also showed that beat-to-beat BP levels 
and BPV values increased in the cold stimulus phase of the CPT. 
The increased beat-to-beat BP levels and BPV values in the cold 
stimulus phase were due to the increased sympathetic nervous </p>

<p>Table 5 </p>

<p>Independent predictors of total arterial compliance in multivariate 
linear regression analysis during recovery phase of cold pressor 
test. </p>

<p>Variable 
b 
P 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>DBP, mmHg 
-0.516 
&lt;0.001 
0.679 
DBP_VIM, Unit 
0.229 
0.001 
Gender, male/female 
0.444 
&lt;0.001 
Weight, kg 
0.434 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>CPT = cold pressor test, DBP = diastolic blood pressure, VIM = variation independent of mean. </p>

<p>Figure 2. The linear relationship between TAC and VIM of DBP in the recovery 
phase of CPT. CPT = cold pressor test, DBP = diastolic blood pressure, TAC = 
total arterial compliance, VIM = variation independent of mean. </p>

<p>Xia et al. Medicine (2017) 96:8 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>system (SNS) activity. The analysis of HRV is a reliable method to 
assess the autonomic nervous system. 
[32] The LF component 
(0.04-0.15 Hz) is regarded as a marker of SNS, and the HF 
component (0.15-0.4 Hz) mainly reflects the parasympathetic 
nerve system (PNS) activity 
[33] ; the LF/HF is comprehensive 
measure of autonomic balance. 
[32] Our results showed that the 
LF and LF/HF increased, while the HF decreased in the cold 
stimulus phase. It suggested that the cold stimulus increased the 
SNS activity and reduced the PNS activity. The SNS activity 
caused the constriction of resistance vessels and resulted in the 
increase of the BP level and BPV value. 
[24] Weise et al 
[34] also 
investigated the influence of the CPT on short-term fluctuations 
of finger arterial BP; they tested 10 healthy subjects' BP, and 
manifested that the cold stimulus induced significant increases in 
SBP and DBP; whereas, the changes of SBPV and DBPV, assessed 
by SD, were not significant. The small size of the subjects and the 
BPV assessed only by SD might contribute to the changes of BPV 
non-significant in their study. 
Furthermore, the reduction of the TAC during the CPT in young 
normal adults may result from the increased SNS activity and the 
elevated BP. Some evidences show that the TAC decreases with 
aging, BP, CVD, and SNS activity. 
[12,35] The changes of HRV in 
frequency domain during the CPT have confirmed that the cold 
stimulus evoked the increase in SNS activity. Increased SNS activity 
led to the reduction of the TAC. Boutouyrie et al 
[35] used a non-
invasive method to investigate the impact of SNS activity on 
arterial compliance in normal subject; and they also demonstrated 
that SNS activity could induce a reduction of TAC. Furthermore, 
our results exhibited that the TAC had significant correlation with 
LF and HF component during the baseline and recovery phase of 
CPT, while the correlation of TAC with LF and HF component was 
not significant in cold stimulus phase. The reduction of TAC might 
lead to the correlation of TAC with LF and HF component became 
non-significant in cold stimulus phase. 
Notwithstanding the novelty of our results, we should interpret 
the limitations of our study. On the one hand, the current study 
was a cross-sectional study. Given the nature of cross-sectional 
design, we could not elucidate whether the elevated BPV induced 
the reduction of the TAC or versa. Larger longitudinal studies are 
needed to estimate the prognostic implications of beat-to-beat 
BPV on TAC in young normal adults. On the other hand, the 
sample size of the present study was relatively small. The 
relatively small sample size may have some influences on the 
results. </p>

<p>5. Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, the results of this study indicate that the beat-to-beat 
BPV associates with the TAC in the recovery phase of the CPT. As 
TAC reflects the elasticity of the vascular system, it implies that the 
increased beat-to-beat BPV has an impact on vascular elasticity, 
and elevates the progress of the early vascular aging in normal 
young adults. In addition, we have also confirmed that the cold 
stimulus increased SNS activity and evoked the increase in BP levels 
and variability, but reduced the TAC. Furthermore, more clinical 
experiments are needed to confirm the correlations between beat-
to-beat BPV and vascular elasticity not only in healthy population 
but also in hypertensive population. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the volunteers who 
participated in our study. </p>









</text></tei>