<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5234238" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background 
Although intravenous acyclovir therapy is recommended for varicella zoster virus (VZV) 
infection in immunocompromised children, the clinical characteristics and outcomes of 
VZV infection in the acyclovir era have rarely been reported. </p>

<p>Methods 
The medical records of children diagnosed with varicella or herpes zoster virus, who had 
underlying hematologic malignancies, were retrospectively reviewed, and the clinical 
characteristics and outcomes of VZV infection were evaluated. </p>

<p>Results 
Seventy-six episodes of VZV infection (herpes zoster in 57 and varicella in 19) were identi-
fied in 73 children. The median age of children with VZV infection was 11 years (range, 
1-17), and 35 (46.1%) episodes occurred in boys. Acute lymphoblastic leukemia was the 
most common underlying malignancy (57.9%), and 90.8% of the episodes occurred dur-
ing complete remission of the underlying malignancy. Acyclovir was administered for a 
median of 10 days (range, 4-97). Severe VZV infection occurred in 16 (21.1%) episodes. 
Although the finding was not statistically significant, a previous history of hematopoietic 
cell transplantation (HCT) appeared to be associated with the development of more severe 
episodes of herpes zoster (P=0.075). </p>

<p>Conclusion 
Clinical characteristics of VZV infection in immunocompromised children were not sig-
nificantly different from those without it, and clinical outcomes improved after the in-
troduction of acyclovir therapy. However, risk factors for severe VZV infection require 
further investigation in a larger population and a prospective setting. </p>

<p>Primary infection with varicella zoster virus (VZV) in 
children causes varicella, after which VZV maintains latency 
in the dorsal root ganglia [1]. The latent VZV may be re-
activated and cause herpes zoster when host cellular im-
munity is weakened [1], and 27.9% of children diagnosed 
with acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) experience herpes 
zoster during their primary chemotherapy course [2]. Most 
immunocompetent patients spontaneously recover from var-
icella and herpes zoster with only symptomatic therapy and </p>

<p>rarely experience complications [3], whereas morbidity and 
mortality due to varicella and herpes zoster are increased 
in immunocompromised patients [4-7]. Before the in-
troduction of antiviral therapy for VZV infection, 31.7% 
of children diagnosed with varicella during chemotherapy 
for acute leukemia experienced visceral dissemination of 
VZV, and 6.7% of these children died [4]. Without antiviral 
therapy, complications and deaths due to herpes zoster in 
children with cancers occurred in 11.9% and 3.0% of patients, 
respectively [5]. Although a decrease in severe infections 
and deaths due to VZV infection has been noted in im-
munocompromised children treated with antiviral therapy, </p>

<p>Blood Res 2016;51:249-55. </p>

<p>bloodresearch.or.kr </p>

<p> 
Seul-Ki Kim, et al. </p>

<p>reports on the clinical characteristics and outcomes of VZV 
infection in immunocompromised children after the in-
troduction of antiviral therapy are rare [2]. 
This retrospective study was performed to investigate 
changes in clinical characteristics and outcomes of VZV in-
fection in immunocompromised children receiving antiviral 
therapy for VZV infection. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients and data collection </p>

<p>A retrospective review was performed on the medical 
records of children aged 18 years or younger who were 
diagnosed with VZV infection (varicella and herpes zoster) 
between April 2009 and March 2015 at Seoul St. Mary's 
Hospital, Seoul, Korea. Among this group, children with 
underlying hematologic malignancies (acute/chronic leuke-
mia and lymphoma) were included in the present study. 
Demographic characteristics including gender and age and 
clinical characteristics including the type and status of under-
lying hematologic malignancy, chemotherapy administered 
before the development of VZV infection, symptoms accom-
panying VZV infection, severe infections involving organs 
or multiple dermatomes, and the duration of antiviral therapy 
were investigated. Laboratory test results including white 
blood cell (WBC) count; absolute neutrophil, lymphocyte, 
and monocyte counts (not shown); erythrocyte sed-
imentation rate; and C-reactive protein level at the time 
of diagnosis of VZV infection were also investigated. In 
addition, the presence of serum immunoglobulin G (IgG) 
and IgM against VZV, polymerase chain reaction (PCR) test 
results for VZV in the serum, and Tzanck test results were 
investigated. The enrolled children were divided into two 
groups based on the development of complications associated 
with each of the VZV infections: varicella and herpes zoster; 
complicated infections were defined as proven or probable 
organ involvement without evidence of diseases other than 
VZV, or cutaneous dissemination of herpes zoster. The inves-
tigated demographic, clinical, and laboratory characteristics 
were compared between the two groups for each presentation 
of VZV infection. The present study was approved by the 
Institutional Review Board of Seoul St. Mary's Hospital, and 
the requirement for informed consent was waived (Approval 
No.: KC15RISI0233). </p>

<p>Definition </p>

<p>VZV infection included both varicella and herpes zoster. 
The diagnosis of varicella and herpes zoster were performed 
by two independent pediatricians based on clinical 
manifestations. Herpes zoster was diagnosed when pruritic 
papulovesicular skin lesions developed with a dermatomal 
distribution, and varicella was diagnosed when the character-
istic skin lesions were scattered and without a dermatomal 
distribution [8]. Cutaneous dissemination of herpes zoster 
was diagnosed when two or more separated dermatomes 
were involved. Visceral organ involvement was diagnosed </p>

<p>based not on the histologic findings of the biopsied tissue 
but on the clinical and laboratory findings. Pneumonia was 
diagnosed in cases when abnormal breathing sounds were 
heard on auscultation and chest radiography revealed abnor-
mal infiltrations in a child with respiratory symptoms. 
Hepatitis was diagnosed when the serum aspartate trans-
aminase or alanine transaminase levels increased two-fold 
or more during VZV infection compared with the levels 
measured before VZV infection in a child with symptoms 
consistent with acute hepatitis, such as abdominal pain, hep-
atomegaly, nausea, vomiting, and jaundice. Cases in which 
other causes of hepatitis or pneumonia were ruled out via 
respiratory viral PCR or serologic studies were considered 
complicated VZV infections. Meningitis was diagnosed when 
a cerebrospinal fluid sample collected from a child with 
neurological symptoms such as headache, seizures, and para-
lysis showed pleocytosis (WBC count ＞5 cells/μL), and ence-
phalitis was diagnosed when seizures or mental dysfunction 
was present in a child with meningitis. Severe infections 
due to VZV were associated with visceral organ involvement, 
cutaneous dissemination of herpes zoster, and intensive care 
unit (ICU) care and/or deaths. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The enrolled children were divided into two groups de-
pending on whether complications due to VZV infection 
were present, and demographic, clinical, and laboratory char-
acteristics were compared between the two groups. 
Categorical factors were compared between the two groups 
using the χ 
2 test, and continuous factors were compared 
using the Mann-Whitney test. Statistical analysis was per-
formed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 18.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA</rs>), and statistical significance was defined as a </p>

<p>two-tailed P-value＜0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinical and laboratory characteristics of VZV infection in 
children with hematologic malignancies </p>

<p>During the study period, 76 episodes of VZV infection 
were diagnosed in 73 children with hematologic malig-
nancies (Table 1). There were 57 (75.0%) episodes of herpes 
zoster and 19 (25.0%) episodes of varicella, and 3 children 
experienced 2 episodes of herpes zoster. The median age 
of the enrolled children was 11 years (range, 1-17), and 
35 (46.1%) episodes occurred in boys. The ALL was the 
most common underlying malignancy (44 episodes, 57.9%), 
and 56.8% of the children with ALL were categorized into 
a very high-risk group (data not shown). Sixty-nine (90.8%) 
episodes of VZV infection occurred during a state of complete 
remission of the underlying malignancy. A previous history 
of receiving allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation 
(HCT) was identified in 32 (42.1%) episodes, and 1 (1.3%) 
child had received an autologous HCT; in particular, there 
were 15 (15/57, 26.3%) episodes of HCT in cases of herpes 
zoster and 5 (5/19, 26.3%) episodes, in cases of varicella. </p>

<p>bloodresearch.or.kr </p>

<p>Blood Res 2016;51:249-55. </p>

<p>Pediatric varicella zoster infection in the acyclovir era </p>

<p>
Table 1. Characteristics of 76 episodes of varicella zoster virus infection in children with hematological malignancies. </p>

<p>Factor 
Herpes zoster (N=57) 
Varicella (N=19) 
Total VZV infection (N=76) </p>

<p>Male (gender) 
26 (45.6) 
9 (47.4) 
35 (46.1) 
Age, years (median, range) 
12 (1-17) 
7 (4-17) 
11 (1-17) 
Underlying malignancy 
Acute lymphoblastic leukemia 
Acute myeloid leukemia 
Other leukemia 
Lymphoma </p>

<p>28 (49.1) 
20 (35.%) 
3 (5.3) 
6 (10.5) </p>

<p>16 (84.2) 
3 (15.8) 
0 
0 </p>

<p>44 (57.9) 
23 (30.3) 
3 (3.9) 
6 (7.9) 
Status of underlying malignancy 
Complete remission state 
Relapsed/refractory state 
52 (91.2) 
5 (8.8) 
17 (89.5) 
2 (10.5) 
69 (90.8) 
7 (9.2) 
Previous history of HCT 
25 (43.9) 
8 (42.1) 
33 (43.4) 
Administered chemotherapy 
None (naïve state) 
Induction/re-induction 
Consolidation 
Maintenance 
Allogeneic HCT 
Autologous HCT 
Completion of chemotherapy </p>

<p>1 (1.8) 
1 (1.8) 
13 (22.8) 
15 (26.3) 
14 (24.6) 
1 (1.8) 
12 (21.1) </p>

<p>0 
3 (15.8) 
1 (5.3) 
7 (36.8) 
5 (26.3) 
0 
3 (15.8) </p>

<p>1 (1.3) 
4 (5.3) 
14 (18.4) 
22 (29.0) 
19 (25.0) 
1 (1.3) 
15 (19.7) 
Severe infections 
Cutaneous dissemination 
Pneumonia 
Hepatitis 
Meningitis 
ICU care 
Death </p>

<p>1 (1.8) 
1 (1.8) 
1 (1.8) 
1 (1.8) 
0 
1 (1.8) </p>

<p>19 (100) 
1 (5.3) 
2 (10.5) 
2 (10.5) 
2 (10.5) 
1 (5.3) </p>

<p>10 (13.2) 
2 (2.6) 
3 (3.9) 
3 (3.9) 
2 (2.6) 
2 (2.6) 
Duration of antiviral therapy, days (median, range) 
Intravenous acyclovir 
Oral acyclovir 
Total duration </p>

<p>9 (4-97) 
2 (0-9) 
10 (4-97) </p>

<p>7 (2-30) 
0 (0-9) 
9 (6-30) </p>

<p>9 (2-97) 
2 (0-9) 
10 (4-97) </p>

<p>Data are presented as numbers (%) or median (range). 
Abbreviations: HCT, hematopoietic cell transplantation; ICU, intensive care unit; VZV, varicella zoster virus. </p>

<p>VZV infection occurred most frequently during maintenance 
chemotherapy (22 episodes, 29.0%) and after allogeneic HCT 
(19 episodes, 25.0%). Fifteen (19.7%) episodes occurred after 
completion of a course of chemotherapy. Fever was the most 
common symptom accompanying VZV infection (data not 
shown; 34 episodes, 44.7%), and gastrointestinal symptoms 
were the most frequent focal symptoms (9 episodes, 11.8%). 
Thoracic (22 episodes, 38.6%) and cervical (19 episodes, 
33.3%) dermatomes were most commonly involved during 
the 57 episodes of herpes zoster. The presence of serum 
IgG and IgM against VZV was examined during 37 and 
36 episodes, respectively. Tests for IgG were positive in 22 
episodes (59.5%), but tests for IgM were not positive in 
any of the episodes. VZV PCR testing using serum samples 
were performed during 35 episodes, and 18 (51.4%) of the 
tests were positive. Tzanck tests from the skin lesions were 
positive in 17 (68.0%) of the 25 tested episodes. </p>

<p>Clinical outcomes of VZV infection in children with 
hematologic malignancies </p>

<p>In all 76 episodes of VZV infection, the children were 
immediately hospitalized and received intravenous acyclovir 
therapy (10 mg/kg or 500 g/m 
2 of body surface area, 3 times 
daily) for a median of 9 days (range, 2-97). In 40 (52.6%) </p>

<p>episodes, oral acyclovir therapy (20 mg/kg 4 times daily) 
for a median of 2 days (range, 0-9) was additionally ad-
ministered following discharge from the hospital. The entire 
duration of acyclovir therapy was a median of 10 days (range, 
4-97). One patient received acyclovir therapy for a shorter 
duration than recommended because of renal impairment. 
Complicated VZV infection occurred in 16 (21.1%) episodes, 
including 13 (81.2%) in herpes zoster and 3 (18.8%) in vari-
cella (Table 2A, B). Two (2.6%) children received ICU care, 
1 under mechanical ventilation and the other for ence-
phalitis. Cutaneous dissemination occurred in 10 (76.9%) 
of the 13 complicated episodes of herpes zoster. Among 
the 10 episodes, intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) and 
VZV-specific immunoglobulin were administered for 2 
(20.0%) and 1 (10.0%) episodes, respectively. One of the 
children with cutaneous dissemination of herpes zoster died 
of leukemia progression. She experienced herpes zoster after 
reinduction chemotherapy for relapsed ALL within 1 year 
after allogeneic HCT. Although she received intravenous 
acyclovir and IVIG therapy, her skin lesions persisted for 
more than 3 months, and she eventually died of leukemia 
progression. Another child with herpes zoster experienced 
hepatitis, and he recovered with acyclovir and IVIG therapy. 
The remaining 2 children with complicated VZV infections </p>

<p>Blood Res 2016;51:249-55. </p>

<p>bloodresearch.or.kr </p>

<p> 
Seul-Ki Kim, et al. </p>

<p>Table 2A. Comparison between children with and without severe infections presenting with herpes zoster. </p>

<p>Factor 
Uncomplicated (N=44) 
Complicated (N=13) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Male (gender) 
20 (45.5) 
6 (46.2) 
0.965 
Age, years (median, range) 
12 (117) 
10 (217) 
0.311 
Underlying malignancy 
Acute lymphoblastic leukemia 
Acute myeloid leukemia 
Other leukemias 
Lymphoma </p>

<p>22 (50.0) 
13 (29.5) 
3 (6.8) 
6 (13.6) </p>

<p>6 (46.2) 
7 (53.8) 
0 
0 </p>

<p>0.223 </p>

<p>Status of underlying malignancy 
Complete remission state 
Relapsed/refractory state 
40 (90.9) 
4 (9.1) 
12 (92.3) 
1 (7.7) </p>

<p>0.876 </p>

<p>Previous history of HCT 
16 (36.4) 
9 (69.2) 
0.075 
Administered chemotherapy 
None (naïve) 
Induction/re-induction 
Consolidation 
Maintenance 
Allogeneic HCT 
Autologous HCT 
Completion of chemotherapy </p>

<p>1 (2.3) 
0 
9 (20.5) 
14 (31.8) 
9 (20.5) 
1 (2.3) 
10 (22.7) </p>

<p>0 
1 (7.7) 
4 (30.8) 
1 (7.7) 
5 (38.5) 
0 
2 (15.4) </p>

<p>0.221 </p>

<p>Dermatomal distribution of herpes zoster 
Cranial nerves 
Cervical 
Thoracic 
Lumbar 
Sacral </p>

<p>5 (11.4) 
14 (31.8) 
18 (40.9) 
5 (11.4) 
2 (4.5) </p>

<p>4 (30.8) 
5 (38.5) 
4 (30.8) 
5 (38.5) 
4 (30.8) </p>

<p>0.187 
0.742 
0.509 
0.038 
0.020 
Laboratory test 
VZV polymerase chain reaction 
Tzanck test 
6/19 (31.6) 
10/13 (76.9) 
3/6 (50.0) 
3/5 (60.0) 
0.412 
0.473 
White blood cell count, /μL (median, range) 
Absolute neutrophil count, /μL (median, range) 
Absolute lymphocyte count, /μL (median, range) 
Erythrocyte sedimentation rate, mm/hr (median, range) 
C-reactive protein, mg/dL (median, range) </p>

<p>3,910 (170-67,200) 
2,177 (70-7,654) 
834 (70-15,456) 
8 (2-73) 
0.16 (0.02-5.41) </p>

<p>4,000 (30-8,680) 
2,607 (0-5,712) 
605 (0-4,948) 
19 (2-35) 
0.20 (0.06-0.69) </p>

<p>0.864 
0.608 
0.332 
0.448 
0.798 </p>

<p>Data are presented as numbers (%) or median (range). 
Abbreviations: HCT, hematopoietic cell transplantation; VZV, varicella zoster virus. </p>

<p>presenting with herpes zoster experienced meningitis and 
pneumonia, respectively, and both recovered with only acy-
clovir therapy without IVIG. 
Three children experienced complicated varicella infec-
tions. One of them experienced varicella with encephalitis 
during reinduction chemotherapy for relapsed ALL after cord 
blood transplantation. Although he received acyclovir and 
IVIG therapy, his mental function did not recover and even-
tually died of bacterial sepsis in a refractory ALL state. 
Another child experienced varicella with fulminant hepatitis, 
pneumonia, acute respiratory distress syndrome, and ence-
phalitis during maintenance chemotherapy for a third re-
mission of ALL after allogeneic HCT, and he recovered with 
acyclovir and IVIG therapy. The third child experienced 
varicella with fulminant hepatitis after induction chemo-
therapy for ALL, and he recovered with acyclovir and IVIG 
therapy. </p>

<p>Comparison between children with and without 
complications </p>

<p>Between children with and without complicated in-
fections due to VZV infection, there were no significant 
differences regarding age, type of VZV infection, type of 
underlying malignancy, and administered therapy before the 
development of VZV infection (Table 2A, B). Among chil-
dren with herpes zoster, lumbar and sacral dermatomes were 
more frequently involved in children with complications </p>

<p>than in those without complications (P =0.038 and P=0.020, </p>

<p>respectively). The duration of administration of acyclovir 
was longer in children with complications compared to the 
duration in those without complications (P =0.001), and the 
durations were similar in each of the presenting infections, </p>

<p>varicella and herpes zoster (P=0.002, P=0.036, respectively). </p>

<p>IVIG was more frequently administered to children with 
complications than to those without complications (P 
＜0.001). Laboratory test results did not significantly differ 
between the two groups. Clinical details of children with 
complicated VCZ infection are summarized in Table 3. </p>

<p>bloodresearch.or.kr </p>

<p>Blood Res 2016;51:249-55. </p>

<p>Pediatric varicella zoster infection in the acyclovir era </p>

<p>
Table 2B. Comparison between children with and without severe infections presenting with varicella. </p>

<p>Factor 
Uncomplicated (N=16) 
Complicated (N=3) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Male (gender) 
6 (37.5) 
3 (100.0) 
0.047 
Age, years (median, range) 
7 (4-17) 
8 (5-8) 
1.000 
Underlying malignancy 
Acute lymphoblastic leukemia 
Acute myeloid leukemia 
Other leukemias 
Lymphoma </p>

<p>13 (81.3) 
3 (18.8) 
0 
0 </p>

<p>3 (100.0) 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>0.414 </p>

<p>Status of underlying malignancy 
Complete remission state 
Relapsed/refractory state 
15 (93.8) 
1 (6.3) 
2 (66.7) 
1 (33.3) </p>

<p>0.161 </p>

<p>Previous history of HCT 
6 (37.5) 
2 (66.7) 
0.348 
Administered chemotherapy 
None (naïve) 
Induction/re-induction 
Consolidation 
Maintenance 
Allogeneic HCT 
Autologous HCT 
Completion of chemotherapy </p>

<p>0 
1 (6.3) 
1 (6.3) 
6 (37.5) 
5 (31.3) 
0 
3 (18.8) </p>

<p>0 (0.0) 
3 (18.8) 
4 (25.0) 
2 (12.5) 
5 (31.3) 
0 (0.0) 
2 (12.5) </p>

<p>0.118 </p>

<p>Laboratory test 
VZV polymerase chain reaction 
Tzanck test 
6/7 (85.7) 
3/5 (60.0) 
3/3 (100.0) 
1/2 (50.0) 
0.490 
0.809 
White blood cell count, /μL (median, range) 
Absolute neutrophil count, /μL (median, range) 
Absolute lymphocyte count, /μL (median, range) 
Erythrocyte sedimentation rate, mm/hr (median, range) 
C-reactive protein, mg/dL (median, range) </p>

<p>4,145 (860-7,710) 
2,751 (464-5,243) 
971 (275-2,198) 
23 (2-47) 
0.55 (0.04-5.22) </p>

<p>3,465 (30-8,680) 
2,587 (0-5,712) 
577 (0-4,948) 
19 (2-35) 
0.20 (0.06-1.29) </p>

<p>0.171 
0.487 
0.047 
0.933 
1.000 </p>

<p>Data are presented as numbers (%) or median (range). 
Abbreviations: HCT, hematopoietic cell transplantation; VZV, varicella zoster virus. </p>

<p>Table 3. Characteristics of children with varicella zoster virus infection with accompanying complications. </p>

<p>Number 
Gender/ 
Age (yr) 
State of underlying malignancy 
Diagnosis 
Complications 
Treatment 
Outcome </p>

<p>1 
F/15 
ALL, CR1, allogeneic HCT (+8 months) 
Zoster 
Cutaneous dissemination 
AC, 
VZV-specific Ig 
Survived </p>

<p>2 
M/2 
AML, CR1, consolidation chemotherapy 
Zoster 
Pneumonia 
AC 
Survived 
3 
M/6 
ALL, CR2, allogeneic HCT (+5 months) 
Zoster 
Meningitis 
AC 
Survived 
4 
F/14 
AML, CR1, consolidation chemotherapy 
Zoster 
Cutaneous dissemination 
AC 
Survived 
5 
F/6 
ALL, CR1, allogeneic HCT (+4 months) 
Zoster 
Cutaneous dissemination 
AC 
Survived 
6 
M/15 
AML, CR2, allogeneic HCT (+6 months) 
Zoster 
Cutaneous dissemination 
AC 
Survived 
7 
F/16 
AML, CR1, allogeneic HCT (+46 months) 
Zoster 
Cutaneous dissemination 
AC 
Survived 
8 
F/12 
AML, CR1, allogeneic HCT (+18 months) 
Zoster 
Cutaneous dissemination 
AC 
Survived 
9 
M/8 
ALL, CR2, allogeneic HCT, CR4, 
maintenance chemotherapy 
Varicella Fulminant hepatitis, ARDS 
pneumonia, encephalitis 
AC, IVIG, ICU 
Survived </p>

<p>10 
M/8 
ALL, CR2, CBT, re-induction chemotherapy 
Varicella Encephalitis 
AC, IVIG, ICU 
Died 
11 
M/16 
AML, CR1, 1st allogeneic HCT, CR2, 
2nd allogeneic HCT (+1 month) 
Zoster 
Cutaneous dissemination 
AC, IVIG 
Survived </p>

<p>12 
M/10 
ALL, CR1, consolidation chemotherapy 
Zoster 
Cutaneous dissemination 
AC 
Survived 
13 
F/17 
AML, CR1, allogeneic HCT, CR2, 
consolidation chemotherapy 
Zoster 
Cutaneous dissemination 
AC 
Survived </p>

<p>14 
M/11 
ALL, CR1, maintenance chemotherapy 
Zoster 
Hepatitis 
AC, IVIG 
Survived 
15 
M/5 
ALL, CR1, induction chemotherapy 
Varicella Fulminant hepatitis 
AC, IVIG 
Survived 
16 
F/13 
ALL, CR2, allogeneic HCT, 
re-induction chemotherapy 
Zoster 
Cutaneous dissemination 
AC, IVIG 
Died </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ALL, acute lymphoblastic leukemia; CR, complete remission; HCT, hematopoietic cell transplantation; AC, acyclovir; VZV, 
varicella zoster virus; Ig, immunoglobulin; AML, acute myeloid leukemia; IVIG, intravenous immunoglobulin; ICU, intensive care unit; CBT, 
cord blood transplantation. </p>

<p>Blood Res 2016;51:249-55. </p>

<p>bloodresearch.or.kr </p>

<p> 
Seul-Ki Kim, et al. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the present study, clinical characteristics and outcomes 
of VZV infection in children with underlying hematologic 
malignancies who received acyclovir therapy were evaluated. 
Complications due to VZV infection occurred in 21.1% of 
the enrolled children, and 2 (2.6%) children died; however, 
there were no deaths closely associated with VZV infection. 
Clinical manifestations of VZV infection in children with 
hematologic malignancies in the present study were similar 
to those reported previously. Herpes zoster occurred more 
frequently in children with ALL compared to those with 
acute myeloid leukemia or solid tumors [5, 6], and more 
than half of the enrolled children in the present study had 
underlying ALL. In children with ALL, the rate of occurrence 
of herpes zoster differed according to the children's risk 
groups [2], and most of the children with underlying ALL 
in the present study were included in a very high-risk group 
(data not shown). This result may be attributable to differ-
ences in the intensity of administered chemotherapy accord-
ing to the risk group [2]. In addition, older children were 
included in the higher-risk groups, and VZV infection tends 
to occur more frequently in older children compared with 
younger children. In previous studies, VZV infection was 
found to be more severe among HCT recipients than in 
other immunocompromised patients [9, 10], but no statisti-
cally significant difference was observed. Abdominal pain 
preceding the development of skin lesions has been associated 
with an increased severity of VZV infection [7, 11], and 
gastrointestinal symptoms occurred more frequently in chil-
dren with complications than in those without complications 
in the present study, although the difference was not statisti-
cally significant. Some previous studies reported that low 
absolute lymphocyte count (ALC) is associated with develop-
ment of visceral dissemination and increased mortality in 
children with cancer and varicella [4, 6]; similarly, in the 
present study, a low ALC was related to the development 
of complicated varicella (P =0.047). 
Before the introduction of acyclovir therapy for VZV in-
fection, a 6.7% of mortality rate was reported in children 
with ALL with varicella, and a 3.0% mortality rate was 
reported in children with cancer and herpes zoster [4, 5]. 
However, there were no reported deaths due to VZV in-
fection in immunocompromised children receiving acyclovir 
therapy [2, 6]. In the present study, 2 (2.6%) children died; 
their cause of death was not VZV infection but progression 
of malignancies. 
Currently, intravenous acyclovir has been recommended 
for the treatment of VZV infection in children with under-
lying acute leukemia who are receiving HCT [1]; therefore, 
all children enrolled in the present study received intra-
venous acyclovir therapy and were hospitalized immediately 
after the clinical diagnosis of VZV infection. However, uni-
versal hospitalization for intravenous acyclovir therapy 
caused increase of hospital costs and complications related 
to injection as well as concern of the development of hospi-</p>

<p>tal-acquired infection. Considering the favorable therapeutic 
effect of acyclovir on VZV infection in immunocompromised 
children, oral acyclovir therapy could be an option in cases </p>

<p>of uncomplicated VZV infections. Sørensen et al. [2] reported </p>

<p>that there were no cases of visceral involvement and no 
deaths in children with ALL and herpes zoster receiving 
oral acyclovir therapy for 5 to 10 days. Because of its low 
bioavailability in oral acyclovir, studies have been conducted 
on the therapeutic effect of valacyclovir and famciclovir, 
which have improved oral bioavailability [12, 13]. The use 
of oral famciclovir and valacyclovir has been approved for 
varicella and herpes zoster in immunocompetent adults, and 
the therapeutic effect of these agents has been proved in 
immunocompromised adults with VZV infection [12, 13]. 
Although there has been no randomized controlled study 
that has examined the therapeutic effect of valacyclovir and 
famciclovir in immunocompromised children with VZV in-
fection, a therapeutic effect of famciclovir on VZV infection 
in immunocompetent children has been reported [14]. In 
immunocompromised children, it was reported that a ther-
apeutic blood drug level could be maintained with oral vala-
cyclovir therapy [15]. Therefore, further studies evaluating 
the clinical therapeutic effect of oral famciclovir and valacy-
clovir in immunocompromised children with varicella and 
herpes zoster should be performed. Until then, oral acyclovir 
therapy may be applicable in immunocompromised children 
without risk factors for complicated VZV infection. Although 
our study failed to show significant association between pre-
vious history of HCT and development of complicated VZV 
infection, some studies reported that a previous history of 
HCT was related to severe VZV infections [9, 10], and severe 
VZV infection increased in patients with ALL who received 
steroid therapy within 3 weeks [16]. Accordingly, oral acy-
clovir therapy can be tried in cases of immunocompromised 
children who have not undergone HCT and have not recently 
received steroid therapy. 
The present study has several limitations. Because this 
study was conducted retrospectively and restricted to a small 
number of patients and the experience of a single institute, 
the exact incidence of VZV infection was not determined 
according to the type and risk group of underlying hemato-
logic malignancies and the type of administered chemo-
therapy. A previous history of VZV infection and vaccination 
against varicella could not be determined by a review of 
medical records. Patient immune status against VZV could 
not be determined because we did not perform serological 
tests for VZV at the time of diagnosis of hematologic 
malignancy. 
Seropositivity for VZV increased the occurrence rate of 
herpes zoster in children with ALL [2, 9], and the occurrence 
rate of herpes zoster was lower in children who were vacci-
nated for varicella than in those who had varicella [17]. If 
we consider that varicella vaccination has been universally 
administered in Korea since 2005 as part of the National 
Immunization Program, future studies should be performed 
to evaluate the effect of previous vaccination on the incidence 
of VZV infection in immunocompromised children. However, </p>

<p>bloodresearch.or.kr </p>

<p>Blood Res 2016;51:249-55. </p>

<p>Pediatric varicella zoster infection in the acyclovir era </p>

<p>
some children who were seropositive for VZV at the time 
of diagnosis of leukemia became seronegative after chemo-
therapy [18], and 59.5% of the children tested for IgG against 
VZV in the present study were seropositive for VZV despite 
the development of VZV infection. Considering that the 
cellular immunity has an important role in controlling VZV 
infection [1], an estimation of cellular immune responses 
to VZV rather than humoral immunity may be useful for 
predicting the development of VZV infection and its 
complications. In the present study, cases of clinically diag-
nosed VZV infection were investigated. It is known that 
VZV PCR is a very sensitive tool for detecting VZV infection, 
VZV PCR tests with serum were performed in only 35 
(46.1%) episodes of our study and the results were positive 
in 51.5% of tests.The VZV PCR using blood samples is helpful 
to verify the potential risk for viral dissemination, and VZV 
PCR using vesicular swabs is a more accurate tool for the 
diagnosis of VZV infection [19]. Therefore, in future studies, 
the relationship between VZV PCR in the serum and compli-
cated VZV infection should be investigated. 
In conclusion, clinical characteristics of VZV infection 
in immunocompromised children were not significantly 
changed and clinical outcomes were improved after the in-
troduction of acyclovir therapy. However, in the future, 
the risk factors for complicated VZV infections should be 
further investigated in a larger patient population and from 
a prospective viewpoint. In addition, oral antiviral therapy 
may be attempted for immunocompromised children with 
no risk factors for complicated VZV infection. </p>

<p>AuthorsÊ Disclosures of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article 
were reported. </p>



</text></tei>