<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5402591" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Cardiopulmonary function can be adversely affected after a cerebrovascular accident in patients with congestive 
heart failure (CHF). The aim of this study was to investigate the efficacy and feasibility of inspiratory muscle training (IMT) for stroke 
patients with CHF. </p>

<p>Methods: A prospective randomized single-blind controlled trial was conducted in a single tertiary medical center in southern 
Taiwan between May 2011 and July 2015. Forty-one patients were enrolled, of whom 21 completed the study (IMT group n = 11 and 
control group n = 10). Both groups participated in a conventional stroke rehabilitation program. Patients in the IMT group received an 
additional IMT program beginning with an intensity of 30% maximal inspiratory pressure (MIP), then increased by 2cmH 2 O each week 
for 30 minutes daily for at least 5 days a week for 10 weeks. MIP, maximal expiratory pressure, spirometry, resting oxyhemoglobin 
saturation, modified Borg Scale, Fatigue Assessment Scale, and Barthel Index were assessed in each patient. </p>

<p>Results: There were significant differences from baseline in MIP (P = 0.008), percent predicted forced vital capacity (P = 0.033), 
forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) (P = 0.008), percent predicted FEV1 (P = 0.008), and Barthel Index (P = 0.012) in the IMT 
group, and Barthel Index (P = 0.027) in the control group. There were significant differences between groups in MIP (20.91 ± 19.73 vs 
À9.00 ± 26.01, adjusted P value = 0.023) and Barthel Index (24.55 ± 22.30 vs 7.50 ± 8.25, adjusted P value = 0.044). </p>

<p>Conclusion: The 10-week IMT was feasible and effective in improving inspiratory force and activities of daily living for the stroke 
patients with CHF. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CHF = congestive heart failure, FEV1 = forced expiratory volume in 1 second, FEV1/FVC = the ratio of FEV1 to 
FVC, FVC = forced vital capacity, IMT = inspiratory muscle training, MEP = maximal expiratory pressure, MIP = maximal inspiratory 
pressure, MMEF = maximum midexpiratory flow, SpO 2 = resting oxyhemoglobin saturation. </p>

<p>Patients with congestive heart failure (CHF) often have 
generalized weakness or weakness of respiratory muscles </p>

<p>[1,2]   that can restrict ventilation (VE) and lead to the major symptoms 
of orthopnea, dyspnea on exertion, exercise intolerance, fatigue, 
or even poor activities of daily living. 
[3,4] Some clinical studies 
have reported histological and biochemical alterations of the 
diaphragm muscles in patients with CHF, including muscle fiber 
atrophy and reduced mitochondrial oxidative capacity, which 
can induce an increased respiratory load and systemic 
myopathy. 
[5-7] Maximal inspiratory pressure (MIP) is also an 
important prognostic indicator of CHF, and early diaphragmatic 
fatigue with a decrease in MIP has been reported to be related to 
limitations in VE and exercise intolerance. </p>

<p>[8]   Stroke can affect respiratory function and contribute to 
desaturation because of respiratory muscle weakness. In 
addition, chronic weakness of the diaphragm muscles has been 
reported to decrease diaphragm displacement in stroke 
patients. 
[9] Another study showed significant decreases in MIP 
and maximal expiratory pressure (MEP) in community-dwelling </p>

<p>Editor: Ovidiu Constantin Baltatu. </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>a Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, 
b Department of 
Respiratory Therapy, 
c Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, 
Department of Internal Medicine, 
d Department of Respiratory Therapy, 
e Division 
of Cardiology, Department of Internal Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital 
-Kaohsiung Medical Center, Chang Gung University College of Medicine, 
Kaohsiung, Taiwan. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Correspondence: Mei-Yun Liaw, Department of Physical Medicine and 
Rehabilitation, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital-Kaohsiung Medical Center, 
Chang Gung University College of Medicine, No. 123, Ta-Pei Road, Niao-Sung 
District, Kaohsiung 83305, Taiwan (e-mail: meiyunliaw@cgmh.org.tw). </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All 
rights reserved. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-No Derivatives License 4.0, which allows for redistribution, commercial 
and non-commercial, as long as it is passed along unchanged and in whole, with 
credit to the author. </p>

<p>Medicine (2016) 95:37(e4856) </p>

<p>Received: 28 April 2016 / Received in final form: 20 August 2016 / Accepted: 22 
August 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000004856 </p>

<p>Clinical Trial/Experimental Study </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>OPEN </p>



<p>chronic stroke survivors compared with healthy age-matched 
controls. 
[10] The symptoms of CHF can be exacerbated after an 
episode of stroke, resulting in avoidance of activities or exercise, 
thereby resulting in a vicious circle of inactivity and poor fitness. 
Respiratory muscle training has received considerable atten-
tion in the field of pulmonary rehabilitation. 
[11-15] Inspiratory 
muscle training (IMT), performed by generating flow with 
constant and specific intensity through a threshold device, has 
been shown to improve inspiratory muscle function, leading to 
better exercise capacity and endurance in patients with chronic 
airway limitation. </p>

<p>[12,13]   IMT has recently been applied in both patients with stroke </p>

<p>[16]   and CHF 
[17] patients separately, and most of these patients had 
significant improvement in cardiopulmonary functions. Howev-
er, there was no study about IMT in stroke patients combined 
with CHF. According to our clinical observations, many stroke 
patients combined with CHF were too weak to do exercise or 
perform daily activities. We supposed that IMT combined 
conventional regular rehabilitation program could further help 
these patients improve cardiopulmonary functions, thus giving 
rise to better exercise tolerance and performance of daily 
activities. The aim of this study, therefore, was to investigate the 
efficacy and feasibility of IMT in stroke patients with CHF. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Subjects </p>

<p>We recruited stroke patients with stable CHF from a single 
tertiary medical center in southern Taiwan. The inclusion criteria 
were stroke patients aged 20 to 85 years with the diagnosis of 
CHF according to the Framingham criteria, New York Heart 
Association functional classes 
[18] I to III. Computerized tomog-
raphy or magnetic resonance imaging was used to confirm the 
diagnosis of stroke. Patients were excluded if they initially had 
high MIP (≥70% predicted MIP), if they could not tightly place 
their lips over a mouthpiece, or if air leaked during inhaling or 
exhaling through the threshold device, if they had a recent acute 
exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, pneu-
mothorax or large bullae on chest radiography, long-term use of 
oxygen therapy, a history of recent lung surgery (within the past 
12 months), or marked osteoporosis, and if they had unstable 
angina, decompensated CHF, or complicated arrhythmia. 
The study protocol was approved by the Institutional Review 
Board of Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Kaohsiung Medical 
Center (IRB number: 99-3663A3) and was registered at 
ClinicalTrials.gov (Clinical Trial Identifier: NCT02614001). 
All patients signed informed consent forms before they were 
included in this study. </p>

<p>2.2. Study design </p>

<p>This was a prospective randomized single-blind controlled trial 
evaluating the efficacy and feasibility of IMT in stroke patients 
with CHF. The patients were randomly assigned to either the 
IMT group or the control group. </p>

<p>2.3. Interventions </p>

<p>IMT was performed by an experienced respiratory therapist, 
using a pressure threshold device (Threshold IMT HS730, 
RESPIRONICS Inc., Cedar Grove, NJ). This device incorporates 
a flow-independent one-way valve to ensure consistent intensity 
(in cmH 2 O). It has been shown that through training with this </p>

<p>device, respiratory muscle strength, endurance, and exercise 
tolerance can be ameliorated. </p>

<p>[19]   During the training program, the patients were instructed to 
place their lips around the mouthpiece in a sitting position with a 
nose clip (Fig. 1). The patients inhaled with enough force to open 
the valve and exhaled through the mouthpiece, and they 
continued to inhale and exhale without removing the device 
from their mouths. During the initial training session, the patients 
were encouraged to start at an intensity equal to 30% of their 
MIP and then to gradually increase the intensity by 2 cmH 2 O/wk 
as far as the patients could tolerate (or 41 cmH 2 O, the maximum 
load for this device). 
[20] Throughout the first training session, 
oxygen saturation was monitored to ensure the safety of the 
training. The intensity was adjusted if there was any decrease in 
oxygen saturation during loaded breathing. The patients were 
allowed to take intermittent periods of rest whenever they felt 
uncomfortable. If the patient could not complete the training 
session because of increased intensity, the training intensity of the 
last part of the session was maintained with the previous intensity 
setting. The training was immediately stopped if the patient 
experienced any discomfort during inspiration. All of the patients 
were trained for 30 min/d for at least 5 days a week for 10 weeks. 
The training program followed the protocol reported in our 
previous study in patients with bronchiectasis. </p>

<p>[21]   Patients in both the IMT and control groups participated in a 
conventional stroke rehabilitation program for at least 5 days a 
week for 10 weeks; however, the patients in the control group did 
not receive any IMT. Both groups, if not admitted to hospital, 
were monitored by telephone twice a week until the end of the 
study. </p>

<p>2.4. Outcome measures </p>

<p>The outcome measures were evaluated before and after the 
10-week intervention by a technician blinded to the patient 
allocation. The primary outcome measures included MIP and 
MEP. MIP was measured after maximal expiration, and MEP 
was measured after maximal inspiration with the patient in a 
sitting posture wearing a nose clip. The patients were strongly 
urged to achieve maximal inspiration and expiration at or near 
residual volume and total lung capacity. Repeated measure-
ments were made until 2 technically satisfactory measurements 
were recorded, with the higher value being used in the 
analysis. 
[22,23] The secondary outcome measures included the 
following items: </p>

<p>Figure 1. An experienced respiratory therapist instructed the patient in how to 
perform inspiratory muscle training by using a pressure threshold device. 
Arrowhead, nose clip; arrow, pressure threshold device; RT = respiratory 
therapist. </p>

<p>Chen et al. Medicine (2016) 95:37 
Medicine </p>



<p>(1) Pulmonary function: According to the American Thoracic 
Society recommendations, 
[24] the pulmonary function tests 
were performed in a pulmonary function laboratory using a 
standard spirometer (Vitalograph, Serial Spirotrac, Bucking-
ham, UK). The following parameters were measured: 
forced vital capacity (FVC), forced expiratory volume in 
1 second (FEV1), the ratio of FEV1 to FVC (FEV1/FVC), and 
maximum midexpiratory flow (MMEF). FVC, FEV1, and 
MMEF were also presented as percent predicted values. 
(2) Oxyhemoglobin saturation: Resting oxyhemoglobin satura-
tion (SpO 2 ) was measured using a finger pulse oximeter 
(FingerPrint, BCI International, WI), which is a noninvasive 
monitoring technique to estimate the percentage of hemoglo-
bin saturated with oxygen. </p>

<p>[25]   (3) Perceived exertion: Perceived exertion can be used to 
determine physical working capacity. 
[26] The patients were 
asked to rate their perceived exertion using a modified Borg 
Scale ranging from 0 to 10. 
[27] The Fatigue Assessment Scale 
was also used to rate perceived exertion, with scores ranging 
from 5 to 50. </p>

<p>[28]   (4) Activities of daily living: The Barthel Index 
[29] can be used to 
evaluate activities of daily living, including feeding, transfer, 
personal grooming and hygiene, bathing, toileting, walking, 
ascending and descending stairs, and controlling bowel and 
bladder. The score ranges from 0 (totally dependent, needs 
help with every activity of daily living) to 100 (totally 
independent). </p>

<p>2.5. Sample size calculation </p>

<p>Sample size calculation was based on a previous study performed 
in stroke patients by Sutbeyaz et al. 
[30] The mean differences 
between pretraining MIP and posttraining MIP were assumed to 
be 7.87 and 2.90 cmH 2 O in the IMT and control groups, 
respectively, with standard deviations of 6.6 and 1.9 cmH 2 O. 
Applying a statistical power of 80% at a 2-sided significance level 
of 5%, the study required at least 34 participants. Assuming a 
dropout rate of 30%, the required total number of enrolled 
participants was 48. The sample size calculation was performed 
using G  *  Power 3.1.3 (Franz Faul, University of Kiel, Kiel, 
Germany). </p>

<p>2.6. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Per-protocol analysis was conducted to evaluate the treatment 
effect. The baseline characteristics were presented as absolute 
number (percentage) or mean (standard deviation). To compare 
baseline characteristics between groups, the Mann-Whitney U 
test was used for continuous variables and Fisher exact test for 
categorical variables. The Wilcoxon signed-rank test was used to 
compare differences between pre-and posttraining outcomes 
within each group. Changes from baseline of each outcome 
measure between groups were compared using linear regression 
analysis. A 2-tailed P value of less than 0.05 was considered 
significant. All statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
software version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">14.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL). </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>A total of 47 consecutive stroke patients combined with stable 
CHF were assessed for eligibility from May 2011 to July 2015. 
Six of these patients were excluded, 2 because they declined to 
participate in the study and 4 who initially had a high MIP. The </p>

<p>remaining 41 patients were randomly assigned to receive IMT 
with conventional stroke rehabilitation (IMT group, n = 23) or 
conventional stroke rehabilitation only (control group, n = 18). 
After randomization, 3 in the IMT group and 5 in the control 
group did not receive the allocated intervention. Twelve patients 
were lost to follow-up and were also excluded from the final 
analysis. In total, 21 patients completed the study, with 11 in the 
IMT group and 10 in the control group. The reasons for not 
receiving the allocated interventions and being lost to follow-up 
are described in Fig. 2. There were no significant differences in 
most of the baseline characteristics between the 2 groups except 
for percent predicted FVC (P = 0.009) (Table 1). 
The results recorded at the beginning and end of the 10-week 
training program are summarized in Table 2. There were 
significant differences from baseline in MIP (P = 0.008), percent 
predicted FVC (P = 0.033), FEV1 (P = 0.008), percent predicted 
FEV1 (P = 0.008), and Barthel Index (P = 0.012) in the IMT 
group, and in Barthel Index (P = 0.027) in the control group. 
There were no significant changes from baseline in SpO 2 , 
modified Borg Scale, Fatigue Assessment Scale, FVC, FEV1/FVC, 
or MMEF in either group. In addition, there were significant 
differences from baseline between groups in MIP (20.91 ± 19.73 
vs À9.00 ± 26.01, adjusted P value = 0.023) and Barthel Index 
(24.55 ± 22.30 vs 7.50 ± 8.25, adjusted P value = 0.044) after 
adjusting for baseline percent predicted FVC in linear regression 
analysis. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we analyzed 21 stroke patients with stable CHF 
who underwent IMT or not for 10 weeks. Comparing the 11 
patients in the IMT group to the 10 patients in the control group, 
there were no significant differences in most of the baseline 
characteristics except for percent predicted FVC. MIP, percent 
predicted FVC, FEV1, percent predicted FEV1, and Barthel Index 
significantly improved compared to the pretraining status in the 
IMT group, while only Barthel Index significantly improved 
compared to the pretraining status in the control group. 
Moreover, there were significant differences from baseline 
between the 2 groups in MIP and Barthel Index after adjusting 
for baseline percent predicted FVC using linear regression 
analysis. 
IMT has been shown to significantly improve peak oxygen 
consumption, VE/carbon dioxide production slope, quality of 
life, respiratory muscle strength, exertional dyspnea, exercise 
capacity, and blood flow in the extremities during exercise and 
rest in heart failure patients. 
[4,31-35] IMT has also been shown to 
improve FEV1, FVC, vital capacity, MMEF, maximum voluntary 
VE, and peak oxygen consumption in patients with subacute 
stroke 
[30] and to have a short-term effect on inspiratory strength 
and endurance in chronic stroke patients. 
[36] One systematic 
review including 9 randomized controlled trials compared IMT 
versus control interventions in CHF patients. 
[17] Although the 
patients with normal inspiratory muscle strength had improve-
ments in exercise performance after IMT, those with inspiratory 
muscle weakness had greater improvements in maximal and 
submaximal exercise capacity. 
[17] Stroke can be viewed as a cause 
of inspiratory muscle weakness due to peripheral and central 
etiologies. In the peripheral etiology, respiratory muscle 
weakness of the affected side, instability of the chest, and an 
inactive lifestyle can lead to bilateral inspiratory muscle 
weakness. 
[10,37-39] In the central etiology, abnormal magnetic 
evoked potentials, cortical latency, central conduction time of the </p>

<p>Chen et al. Medicine (2016) 95:37 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>Figure 2. Flow diagram of participants through the study. </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics of the patients in the inspiratory muscle training and control groups. </p>

<p>Control (n = 10) 
IMT (n = 11) 
Total (n = 21) 
P </p>

<p>Gender 
1.000 
Female 
6 (60.0) 
7 (63.6) 
13 (61.9) 
Male 
4 (40.0) 
4 (36.4) 
8 (38.1) 
Age, y 
67.50 (10.35) 
63.73 (14.64) 
65.52 (12.61) 
0.459 
Body height, m 
1.57 (0.05) 
1.58 (0.09) 
1.58 (0.07) 
0.915 
Body weight, kg 
60.91 (8.75) 
62.18 (12.76) 
61.58 (10.78) 
0.724 
BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>24.70 (3.82) 
24.94 (5.34) 
24.83 (4.56) 
0.778 
Time since stroke onset, d 
58.30 (58.27) 
71.00 (49.92) 
64.95 (53.07) 
0.481 
Paretic side 
Right 
3 (30.0) 
5 (45.5) 
8 (38.1) 
0.659 
Left 
7 (70.0) 
6 (54.5) 
13 (61.9) 
Lesion type 
Ischemic 
9 (90.0) 
8 (72.7) 
17 (81.0) 
0.586 
Hemorrhagic 
1 (10.0) 
3 (27.3) 
4 (19.0) 
Barthel Index 
23.50 (16.34) 
35.00 (21.10) 
29.52 (19.42) 
0.166 
Baseline cardiopulmonary function 
NYHA class 
1.000 
II 
7 (70.0) 
7 (63.6) 
14 (66.7) 
III 
3 (30.0) 
4 (36.4) 
7 (33.3) 
EF 
61.00 (12.43) 
60.55 (14.29) 
60.76 (13.10) 
0.805 
SpO 2 
97.90 (1.10) 
97.09 (2.98) 
97.48 (2.27) 
0.774 
Modified Borg Scale 
1.10 (0.32) 
1.45 (0.52) 
1.29 (0.46) 
0.080 
MIP, cmH 2 O 
44.00 (20.66) 
33.64 (15.67) 
38.57 (18.52) 
0.237 
MEP, cmH 2 O 
50.00 (17.00) 
56.36 (36.41) 
53.33 (28.34) 
0.746 
FVC, L 
1.72 (0.55) 
2.14 (0.88) 
1.94 (0.76) 
0.139 
FVC (% predicted) 
63.35 (12.04) 
77.64 (19.26) 
70.83 (17.44) 
0.009 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>FEV1, L 
1.43 (0.30) 
1.76 (0.74) 
1.60 (0.59) 
0.139 
FEV1 (% predicted) 
72.14 (14.37) 
83.49 (21.12) 
78.09 (18.70) 
0.078 
FEV1/FVC (%) 
86.30 (12.91) 
83.75 (11.96) 
84.97 (12.18) 
0.526 
MMEF (%) 
72.33 (23.05) 
76.59 (31.56) 
74.56 (27.24) 
0.778 </p>

<p>Values are expressed as mean (SD) or number (%). BMI = body mass index, EF = ejection fraction, FEV1 = forced expiratory volume in 1 second (expressed in liters and in % of theoretical value), FVC = forced 
vital capacity (expressed in liters and in % of theoretical value), IMT = inspiratory muscle training, MEP = maximal expiratory pressure, MIP = maximal inspiratory pressure, MMEF = maximum midexpiratory flow 
(expressed in % of theoretical value), NYHA = New York Heart Association, SD = standard deviation, SpO 2 = resting oxyhemoglobin saturation by pulse oximetry. 
 † P &lt; 0.05. 
 ‡ P &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>Chen et al. Medicine (2016) 95:37 
Medicine </p>



<p>affected hemisphere, and no bilateral motor representation of 
each hemidiaphragm can result in respiratory dysfunction. </p>

<p>[9,38]   Another systematic review including 3 randomized controlled 
trials and 3 cross-sectional studies compared IMT with a control 
intervention in stroke patients, and the results showed that the 
stroke patients had improvement in MIP after the IMT 
program. </p>

<p>[16]   In the present study, we included stroke patients who also had 
stable CHF, and all of the patients had inspiratory muscle 
weakness (inspiratory muscle strength less than 70% predicted 
MIP). We hypothesized that these patients would have a greater 
improvement in MIP compared to those with normal inspiratory 
muscle strength based on the results of a previous study. 
[17] In 
addition, we assumed that patients with respiratory muscle 
weakness, dyspnea, or dyspnea on exertion would have a greater 
motivation to receive IMT training. Furthermore, IMT has been 
suggested to be an alternative modality to treat CHF patients with 
more severe deconditioning. 
[40] These factors formed the </p>

<p>rationale for the selection of these patients for the IMT program. 
The initial intensity of the IMT was 30% MIP, which was then 
increased weekly to achieve a target MIP at the patient's 
maximum load. The training intensity, frequency, and duration 
were similar to those used in other trials (5-6 d/wk for 6-12 
weeks). </p>

<p>[4,14,16,17,35,42]   It was difficult to recruit a sufficient number of patients for our 
IMT program, possibly because stroke patients with CHF were 
more likely to die or have morbidity than stroke patients without 
CHF, 
[41] a general lack of awareness of the IMT and pulmonary 
rehabilitation programs, and poor motivation. Boredom with 
IMT may also have discouraged the patients from training. No 
adverse events were noted throughout the whole IMT program. </p>

<p>4.1. Limitations </p>

<p>There are several limitations to this study. First, there was a 
significant difference in percent predicted FVC between the </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Data analysis before and after the 10-week study in the inspiratory muscle training and control groups. </p>

<p>Baseline 
mean (SD) </p>

<p>Posttreatment 
mean (SD) </p>

<p>Change from 
baseline mean (SD) </p>

<p>P for change 
from baseline </p>

<p>P 
 *  for change </p>

<p>between groups </p>

<p>MIP, cmH 2 O 
Control 
44.00 (20.66) 
35.00 (15.09) 
À9.00 (26.01) 
0.292 
0.023 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>IMT 
33.64 (15.67) 
54.55 (25.83) 
20.91 (19.73) 
0.008 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>MEP, cmH 2 O 
Control 
49.00 (17.29) 
41.00 (20.79) 
À8.00 (14.76) 
0.084 
0.167 
IMT 
56.36 (36.41) 
66.36 (35.85) 
10.00 (15.49) 
0.058 
FVC, L 
Control 
1.72 (0.55) 
1.67 (0.47) 
À0.05 (0.29) 
0.507 
0.056 
IMT 
2.14 (0.88) 
2.30 (1.01) 
0.16 (0.29) 
0.050 
FVC (% predicted) 
Control 
63.35 (12.04) 
64.77 (12.24) 
1.42 (12.17) 
0.959 
0.075 
IMT 
77.64 (19.26) 
82.58 (15.61) 
4.95 (6.75) 
0.033 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>FEV1, L 
Control 
1.43 (0.30) 
1.45 (0.35) 
0.02 (0.23) 
0.859 
0.193 
IMT 
1.76 (0.74) 
1.98 (0.84) 
0.22 (0.28) 
0.008 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>FEV1 (% predicted) 
Control 
72.14 (14.37) 
73.22 (19.91) 
1.08 (11.90) 
0.953 
0.117 
IMT 
83.49 (21.12) 
95.96 (23.99) 
12.47 (13.52) 
0.008 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>FVC/FEV1 (%) 
Control 
86.30 (12.91) 
87.75 (6.73) 
1.45 (11.17) 
0.646 
0.638 
IMT 
83.75 (11.96) 
86.77 (4.21) 
3.02 (8.80) 
0.182 
MMEF (%) 
Control 
72.33 (23.05) 
71.52 (15.02) 
À0.81 (19.48) 
0.959 
0.461 
IMT 
76.59 (31.56) 
83.13 (16.91) 
6.54 (21.00) 
0.091 
SpO 2 
Control 
97.90 (1.10) 
97.30 (1.70) 
À0.60 (1.78) 
0.305 
0.247 
IMT 
97.09 (2.98) 
98.18 (1.33) 
1.09 (3.08) 
0.368 
Modified Borg Scale 
Control 
1.10 (0.32) 
1.00 (0.00) 
À0.10 (0.32) 
0.317 
0.773 
IMT 
1.45 (0.52) 
1.55 (0.82) 
0.09 (0.70) 
0.655 
FAS 
Control 
29.30 (7.42) 
27.60 (8.04) 
À1.70 (9.64) 
0.475 
0.198 
IMT 
29.73 (8.53) 
26.73 (7.50) 
À3.00 (6.88) 
0.218 
Barthel Index 
Control 
23.50 (16.34) 
31.00 (19.12) 
7.50 (8.25) 
0.027 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.044 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>IMT 
35.00 (21.10) 
59.55 (18.09) 
24.55 (22.30) 
0.012 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>FAS = Fatigue Assessment Scale, FEV1 = forced expiratory volume in 1 second (expressed in liters and in % of theoretical value), FVC = forced vital capacity (expressed in liters and in % of theoretical value), IMT 
= inspiratory muscle training, MEP = maximal expiratory pressure, MIP = maximal inspiratory pressure, MMEF = maximum mid-expiratory flow (expressed in % of theoretical value), SD = standard deviation, 
SpO 2 = resting oxyhemoglobin saturation by pulse oximetry. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Adjusted for FVC (% predicted) using linear regression analysis. 
 † P &lt; 0.05. 
 ‡ P &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>Chen et al. Medicine (2016) 95:37 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>groups at the beginning of the study. Although there were no 
significant differences in other baseline characteristics between 
the 2 groups, some discrepancies still existed. Therefore, we 
compared differences in the change from baseline of each 
outcome between groups using linear regression analysis with 
adjustments for baseline percent predicted FVC. Second, the 
sample size was small. Although we calculated the sample size 
with an estimated dropout rate of 30%, there was still 
considerable loss after randomization. Third, data on the 6-
minute walk distance, an important cardiopulmonary index, 
were not reported because the walking distance could be biased 
by the functional status of stroke patients. Fourth, there is 
currently no consensus or recommendations about the training 
protocol of IMT programs in stroke patients with CHF. Our 
training program was based on the protocol of our previous study 
in patients with bronchiectasis, 
[21] and the training intensity, 
frequency, and duration seemed to be adequate to show the 
clinical effectiveness after the IMT, even the statistical power was 
low because of small sample size. Fifth, we did not use sham IMT 
intervention in the control group, which might cause perfor-
mance bias. Despite sham intervention was used in some trials on 
IMT for CHF patients, 
[42-44] we did not use sham intervention in 
the present study because the patients could possibly differentiate 
the sham intervention from the true IMT intervention. In fact, 
blinding is generally regarded as being difficult to carry out in 
trials assessing nonpharmacological treatments. 
[45] Future stud-
ies should address how to deal with this methodological 
challenge. Finally, the follow-up duration in previous IMT trials 
ranged from 4 to 12 weeks, 
[16,17] and no long-term follow-up 
results have been published. Further studies with larger sample 
size and longer duration are warranted to investigate the long-
term efficacy among these patients. </p>

<p>4.2. Future research </p>

<p>As discussed, it was difficult to recruit eligible subjects for this 
study, and only half of those recruited were able to continuously 
perform or tolerate the training programs (either IMT plus 
conventional stroke rehabilitation or conventional stroke 
rehabilitation only) and complete the whole training course. 
This may be explained by the relatively weak study population 
and poor compliance. It is well known that stroke patients with 
CHF have poorer fitness and more complications, which often 
deters the patients from training. In addition, over 30% of the 
patients in our study complained of fatigue and boredom during 
the training program, which consequently led to poor compli-
ance. Therefore, appropriate selection of participants and 
methods to improve compliance (such as virtual reality for 
stroke rehabilitation) should be considered in future studies. </p>

<p>5. Conclusion </p>

<p>In addition to conventional stroke rehabilitation, our results 
suggest that stroke patients with stable CHF can benefit from a 
10-week IMT with regard to inspiratory strength and activities of 
daily living. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We would like to thank Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taiwan 
for financially supporting this research (CMRPG8D0911). We 
would also like to thank Andrew Wei-Hsiang Tiong for his 
assistance for this research. </p>









</text></tei>