<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5328613" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: This study aimed to explore the diagnostic and prognostic values of contrast-enhanced 
ultrasound (CEUS) in breast cancer. Between September 2009 and October 2011, a total of 
143 breast cancer patients and 161 healthy people were selected as case group and control 
group, respectively. After the identification of lesions by conventional ultrasound, all patients 
underwent CEUS. The CEUS images were analyzed, and time-intensity curves (TICs) were 
obtained. Hematoxylin-eosin and immunohistochemistry staining was performed on tissue 
specimens, according to which the expressions of estrogen receptor (ER), c-erb-B2, p53, and 
Ki-67 were measured. Multivariate logistic regression analysis was used to compare CEUS 
and TIC parameters between the two groups. Compared with the control group, cancer patients 
showed high enhancement, heterogeneous enhancement or defects in the central region, expan-
sion of lesion diameter after enhancement and crab-like blur lesion edges. The peak intensity 
(PI), relative start time of enhancement, relative PI, and relative area under the curve in the case 
group were significantly higher than those in the control group. Logistic analysis showed that 
the uniformity of enhancement, expansion of lesion diameter, and relative PI were significant 
diagnostic parameters of breast cancer, with area under the curve being 0.798, 0.776, and 0.919, 
respectively. There were strong associations between CEUS characteristics and expressions of 
prognostic factors in breast cancer: the heterogeneous enhancement was common in c-erb-B2-
positive tumors; the centripetal enhancement occurred more in ER-negative tumors; perforator 
vessels were often seen in tumors at high histological grade; perfusion defects were common in 
ER-negative, c-erb-B2-positive, and Ki-67-positive tumors. CEUS is a useful tool for the early 
diagnosis and prognosis of breast cancer. 
Breast cancer is a heterogeneous disorder and currently is the most common malignancy in 
females. 
1 Systemic symptoms of breast cancer generally include hot flashes, insomnia, and 
mood changes, while its local symptoms include urogenital atrophy and vaginal dryness. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>So far, the etiology of breast cancer has not been fully understood, but it was discovered 
that the development of breast cancer is associated with genetic and environmental factors 
as well as obesity, while hormone replacement therapy may also lead to breast cancer. </p>

<p>3-5 </p>

<p>At present, traditional methods, such as sentinel lymph node biopsy, are typically used to 
determine the staging of breast cancer, but they are associated with high cost and technical 
complexity. 
6 A new technology named contrast-enhanced ultrasound (CEUS) provides 
an earlier assessment of intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma and hepatocellular carcinoma, 
as well as providing a prediction of neoadjuvant chemotherapy efficiency. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>correspondence: Dong-Mei lv 
Department of Ultrasound, second 
hospital, Jilin University, 218 Ziqiang 
street, nanguan District, changchun, 
Jilin 130041, People's republic of china 
Tel +86 0431 8897 5634 
email dongmei_lvv@126.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
22 February 2017 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1124 </p>

<p>Zhao et al </p>

<p>By using the first generation of contrast agents, CEUS 
increases the Doppler signal, the display of blood flow and 
reveals perfusion characteristics in tumor. 
8 In combination 
with high-resolution ultrasound equipment and improved 
ultrasound contrast agents, CEUS has been helpful in studies 
of tumor angiogenesis on the microcirculation level. 
8 CEUS 
is more sensitive to hypoperfusion in normal and abnormal 
tissues compared with conventional Doppler ultrasound, 
and is an effective, as well as noninvasive diagnostic tool 
for disease detection. 
9 CEUS uses abnormal blood perfusion 
or blood vessel filling patterns to diagnose a disease. 
10 It is 
also a topical drug delivery method and has been applied in 
the treatment of prostate cancer, in which CEUS could use 
the contrast imaging to timely evaluate treatment efficacy, 
guide the fiber placement, adjust to appropriate therapy, and 
ensure its safety and efficiency. 
11 However, there are few 
studies that have explored the application of CEUS in the 
diagnosis of breast cancer. This article studied whether CEUS 
can help the diagnosis and prognosis of breast cancer. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
ethics statement </p>

<p>This study was performed in accordance with the approval 
and guidelines from Medicine Ethics Review Committee at 
Second Hospital, Jilin University, and all information was 
collected after written informed consents were obtained 
from all patients. </p>

<p>study subjects </p>

<p>From September 2009 to October 2011, 143 breast cancer 
patients in Second Hospital, Jilin University, underwent 
ultrasonography or CEUS and a complete record of medical 
information was obtained from each patient. The patients 
had no blood relationship with each other. All breast cancer 
patients received their first confirmed histopathologic 
diagnosis at our department. The inclusion criteria were as 
follows: 1) newly diagnosed breast cancer with pathological 
verifications; 2) no history of cancer in other organs; 3) no 
antitumor therapy before the blood samples were collected; 
4) a complete record of baseline information; 5) not restricted 
by age, pathological type, and stage of disease; and 6) no 
antitumor therapy prior to CEUS. The exclusion criteria were 
as follows: 1) allergic to sulfur hexafluoride; 2) pulmonary 
and heart diseases or respiratory distress; 3) severe liver and 
kidney dysfunctions; and 4) during the period of pregnancy 
or breastfeeding. A total of 161 healthy people with no 
history of cancer obtaining CEUS examination during the 
same period at the hospital were selected as the control 
group. The case and control groups were matched for overall </p>

<p>age, age at menarche, age at menopause, fertility profiles, 
residence, ethnicity, and family history of diseases. </p>

<p>ceUs procedures </p>

<p>The detection procedures of CEUS were as follows. Patients 
were lying in a supine position with bilateral upper limbs 
pointing up to fully expose their breasts and bilateral axil-
lae. The conventional ultrasound mode was first used to 
examine both breasts from the edge of breast to the nipple 
in a continuous scanning pattern. The nipple was considered 
as the center, followed by the entire breast being scanned 
in a clockwise direction starting from the outer quadrant. 
Multislice scanning was focused on suspicious lesions, and 
the results were compared with the contralateral breast. The 
lesion location, shape, size, border profile, and internal echo 
were recorded and compared with the surrounding tissues. 
CEUS of lesions were performed using two equipments: the 
iU22 color Doppler ultrasound machine (Philips, Amsterdam, 
the Netherlands) and the Mylab Twice color Doppler 
ultrasound machine (Esaote, Switzerland). The probe type 
and frequency of the iU22 machine were L9-3 linear array 
and 7.5 MHz, respectively, and pulse-inversion harmonic 
imaging with a mechanical index of 0.06-0.08 was used. 
The Mylab Twice machine used a linear array probe with a 
frequency of 7.5 MHz, in which contrast-tuned imaging with 
a mechanical index of 0.06-0.08 was adopted. After chang-
ing to the CEUS mode, the diluted SonoVue contrast agent 
(Bracco, Italy) was continuously shaken for 30 s, and 4.8 mL 
of which was injected into the median cubital vein of each 
patient. Next, 5 mL of normal saline was used to wash the 
injection syringe. Then the scanning direction was adjusted 
again so that the image could capture both the tumor and 
the surrounding normal tissues, followed by shaking of the 
diluted SonoVue, a second vein injection of 3 mL SonoVue 
to patients, washing with 5 mL of saline, and 3 min CEUS 
imaging. Finally, the SonoVue was transferred into the 
ultrasound machines. </p>

<p>image analysis </p>

<p>At 120 s after SonoVue injection, the <rs id="software-0" type="software">QLAB</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">8.1</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Philips</rs>) was used for dynamic image analysis. After obtain-
ing a suitable sample frame, tissue specimens were acquired 
at locations where there are significant enhancements at the 
edge and center of tumor. In addition, normal breast tissues 
at the edge of tumor, which were .5 mm in depth, were also 
obtained. The time-intensity curve (TIC) was acquired and 
analyzed. The relevant parameters were calculated, including 
rise time, which is the time required for perfusion and entry 
of contrast agent into tumor; peak intensity (PI), which is the </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1125 </p>

<p>ceUs and breast cancer </p>

<p>maximum enhanced strength; time to peak, which is the time 
required to reach PI; wash-in slope, which is the maximum 
rate for microbubbles of contrast agent to enter into tumor; 
and mean transit time, which is the average time of contrast 
agent in tumor. </p>

<p>immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Tissue samples were collected in regions with no tumor 
necrosis. The specimens were fixed in 10% formalin, dehy-
drated with water extractor, transparentized with xylene, 
and embedded in paraffin. Hematoxylin-eosin staining and 
immunohistochemical staining were performed. Streptavidin-
perosidase immunohistochemistry was performed using a 
two-step method. The primary and secondary antibodies 
used for determining the expressions of estrogen receptor 
(ER), p53, c-erbB-2, and Ki-67 were ready-to-use antibodies 
produced by Beijing Zhongshan Jinqiao Biotechnology Co., 
Ltd. (Beijing, People's Republic of China), with a concentra-
tion of 1:100. </p>

<p>staining results determination </p>

<p>The stained slides were observed by a professional patholo-
gist under an optical microscope. ER-and p53-positive 
cells were confirmed by brown granules in nucleus, and 
c-erb-B2-positive cells were confirmed by brown granules in 
cell membrane or cytoplasm. The cells were determined as 
positive if the positive staining cells took up .10% of total 
cells; otherwise, the cells were determined as negative. For 
the determination of Ki-67 positivity, if .20% cells showed 
brown granules in nuclei after staining, the samples were 
denoted as Ki-67 positive; otherwise they were denoted as 
Ki-67 negative. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>All data analyses were performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical Product 
and Service Solutions</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">18.0</rs> statistical software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA). The measurement data were presented as 
mean ± standard deviation. The measurement data between 
different groups were compared using unpaired t-test. The 
differences of count data between different groups were 
analyzed using chi-square test. Using pathological results 
as a gold standard, multivariate logistic regression analysis 
was done for parameters obtained in CEUS and quantitative 
parameters of TIC, and constant value (B), standard error 
(SE), Wald chi-square value, degrees of freedom (df), P-value 
(significant), and odds ratio value were calculated. Using the 
control group and the case group as dependent variables, the 
above parameters showing significances were processed by 
forward stepwise binary logistic analyses. After obtaining </p>

<p>the logistic regression equation, the predictive value of each 
parameter was determined. The optimal threshold was set by 
receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve, the survival 
time of patients was analyzed using the Kaplan-Meier 
method and the survival rates of patients were compared by 
the log-rank test. The relative risk of clinical parameters to 
the prognosis was evaluated by multivariate Cox regression 
analysis. The intergroup comparisons of count data were 
done using Pearson χ 
2 or continuous calibration tests. A 
probability value of P,0.05 indicated that the difference 
was statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
comparisons of baseline characteristics 
between the case and control groups </p>

<p>The baseline information in the case and control groups 
was compared. The histological types in the case group 
were 126 cases (88.1%) of infiltrating ductal carcinoma and 
17 cases (11.9%) of other carcinoma. There was no signifi-
cant difference between the case and control groups with 
respect to overall age, menarche age, menopausal status, 
reproductive history, family history of cancer, and body mass 
index distribution (Table 1; all P.0.05). </p>

<p>comparisons of different ceUs 
parameters between the case and 
control groups </p>

<p>After CEUS imaging, the degree and uniformity of enhance-
ment in the lesion, the enhancement characteristics of </p>

<p>Table 1 clinical features of subjects in the case and control 
groups </p>

<p>Features 
Case 
(n=143) </p>

<p>Control 
(n=161) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Age, mean ± SD, years 
49.4±8.6 
50.1±8.2 
,50, n 
69 
83 
0.646 
$50, n 
74 
78 </p>

<p>age at menarche, mean ± sD 
13.6±2.0 
13.8±1.7 
0.347 
age at menopause, mean ± sD 
49.9±2.9 
50.3±2.1 
0.166 
Pregnancy 
no, n (%) 
10 (7.0) 
13 (8.1) 
0.829 
Yes, n (%) 
133 (93.0) 
148 (91.9) 
Menopausal status 
Premenopausal, n (%) 
52 (36.3) 
68 (42.2) 
0.347 
Postmenopausal, n (%) 
91 (63.7) 
93 (57.8) 
Body mass index, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>,24, n 
98 
103 
0.466 
$24, n 
45 
58 
Family history of cancer 
no, n 
128 
141 
0.719 
Yes, n 
15 
20 </p>

<p>Abbreviation: sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1126 </p>

<p>Zhao et al </p>

<p>the lesion edge, and the lesion diameter at peak between 
the case group and the control group were compared and 
all parameters were significantly different between the 
two groups (all P,0.05). But the two groups showed no 
difference in the direction of enhancement (P=0.07). Most 
breast cancer patients showed high enhancement (105/143), 
heterogeneous enhancement or central defects (94/143), 
expansion of lesion diameter after enhancement (103/143), 
or crab-like blur lesion edge (107/143) (Table 2; Figure 1). </p>

<p>comparisons of different Tic parameters 
between the case and control groups </p>

<p>The PI, relative start time, relative PI, and relative area 
under the curve between the case and control groups were 
significantly different (all P,0.05; Table 3). The logistic 
regression analysis of the CEUS and TIC parameters 
showed that the uniformity of lesion, the expansion of 
lesion diameter, and the relative PI were meaningful indi-
cators in the diagnosis of breast cancer (Table 4). More 
specifically, the heterogeneous enhancement, the expanded </p>

<p>lesion diameter after the enhancement, and the relatively 
high PI were all powerful diagnostic parameters for 
breast cancer. </p>

<p>Diagnostic values of different parameters 
in breast cancer evaluated by rOc curve </p>

<p>The uniformity of lesion enhancement (Figure 2), the expan-
sion of lesion diameter (Figure 3), and the relative PI were 
used as test variables (Figure 4), and the ROC analyses of 
these variables were performed using pathological diagno-
sis as the gold standard. The results showed that the area 
under the curves of the uniformity of lesion enhancement, 
the expansion of lesion diameter, and the relative PI were 
0.798, 0.776, and 0.919, respectively. This suggested that the 
diagnostic values of the above three parameters were higher 
than that of the TIC of conventional ultrasound. </p>

<p>associations between ceUs parameters 
and prognostic factors in breast cancer </p>

<p>The CEUS parameters and the expressions of prognostic 
factors of breast cancer were analyzed. The results showed 
that c-erb-B2 expression was related to the uniformity of </p>

<p>Table 2 comparisons of contrast enhanced ultrasonography 
features between the case and control groups </p>

<p>Features 
Case 
(n=143) </p>

<p>Control 
(n=161) </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Level of enhancement 
high 
105 
29 
94.35 ,0.001 
equal or weak 
38 
132 
Uniformity 
even 
49 
116 
43.57 ,0.001 
Uneven 
94 
45 
Radius expansion 
Yes 
103 
38 
71.41 ,0.001 
no 
40 
123 
Edge shape 
Blurry 
107 
44 
68.34 ,0.001 
clear 
36 
117 
Direction of enhancement 
concentric 
108 
137 
4.43 
0.035 
eccentric 
35 
24 </p>

<p>Table 3 comparisons of time-intensity curves between the case 
and control groups </p>

<p>Parameters 
Case 
(n=143) </p>

<p>Control 
(n=161) </p>

<p>Unpaired 
t-test </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Peak intensity 
7.29±2.18 
3.65±1.10 
18.68 
,0.001 
The area under 
the curve </p>

<p>295.76±56.97 285.27±73.58 1.38 
0.169 </p>

<p>start time(s) 
14.53±4.91 
14.15±3.27 
0.80 
0.423 
Peak time(s) 
18.53±4.98 
19.81±6.49 
1.91 
0.057 
rising slope 
0.92±0.32 
0.90±0.19 
0.67 
0.503 
Falling slope 
0.05±0.04 
0.06±0.05 
1.91 
0.057 
relative peak 
intensity </p>

<p>2.97±0.87 
0.96±0.24 
28.14 
,0.001 </p>

<p>relative area under 
the curve </p>

<p>101.32±31.07 43.36±11.23 22.10 
0.010 </p>

<p>relative start time(s) -3.33±0.30 
-0.19±0.06 
129.90 
0.020 
relative peak time(s) 5.53±0.68 
5.64±0.67 
1.42 
0.157 
relative rising slope 0.25±0.05 
0.51±0.04 
1.94 
0.054 
relative falling slope -0.02±0.01 
-0.02±0.01 
0.00 
1.000 </p>

<p>Table 4 logistic regression analysis of contrast-enhanced 
ultrasound parameters on time-intensity curves </p>

<p>Variables 
B* 
SE* Wald df Sig 
OR </p>

<p>Uniformity of enhancement 2.235 0.844 7.007 1 0.008 9.346 
expansion of peak diameter 2.930 0.866 11.458 1 0.001 18.731 
relative peak intensity 
2.414 0.527 20.974 1 0.000 11.178 </p>

<p>Note: *Partial regression coefficient. 
Abbreviations: B, constant value; df, degrees of freedom; Or, odds ratio; 
SE, standard error; partial regression coefficient standard error; Sig, significant. </p>

<p>Figure 1 contrast-enhanced ultrasound images in the case (A) and control 
groups (B). </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1127 </p>

<p>ceUs and breast cancer </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Breast cancers usually consist of a diversity of phenotypic 
cancer cells and are likely to metastasize to regional lymph 
nodes, bone marrow, lungs, and liver. 
13 It was a main mortal-
ity cause for women from late 30 s to early 50 s. 
14 Therefore, 
a more sophisticated ultrasound imaging technique may be 
of clinical significance in the diagnosis and prognosis of 
breast cancer. 
This study found that the lesions of breast cancer were 
highly and heterogeneously enhanced, sometimes with 
central defects, whose diameters were enlarged and edges 
became crab-like and blurry. CEUS is a functional imaging 
technique that provides important diagnostic information and 
has become an alternative method of enhanced computed 
tomography and other imaging methods. 
15 In combination 
with SonoVue, CEUS has shown high performance in detect-
ing both large and small vascularities. 
16 It has been shown that 
CEUS can illustrate the vascular perfusion inside and around 
the breast cancer tissues as well as showing small defects 
undetected by magnetic resonance imaging. 
17 Furthermore, 
CEUS was found to provide a high diagnostic accuracy in 
detecting metastatic sentinel lymph node in breast cancer. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>In addition, Saracco has shown that CEUS can help distin-
guish benign from malignant tumors, taking shorter time 
to reach PI in tumors with higher histological grades and 
quicker transit of contrast agent. 
19 In this study, the logistic 
regression analysis and relevant ROC evaluation found that 
heterogeneous enhancement, lesion diameter expansion, and 
relatively high enhancement were all significant diagnostic 
factors for breast cancer. In addition, the diagnostic values of </p>

<p>lesion enhancement, while positive c-erb-B2 was more 
likely to present heterogeneous enhancement and be seen 
in high histological grade. Centripetal enhancement pattern 
was more common in ER-negative tumors. The perforator 
vessels occurred mainly in tumors in high histological grade, 
and perfusion defects commonly occurred in ER-negative, 
c-erb-B2-positive, and Ki-67-positive tumors in high or 
medium histological grades whose diameter was .2 cm. 
The enhancement shape and enhancement margin of tumors 
were not related to prognostic factors (all P.0.05). The dis-
tributions of CEUS characteristics and prognostic factors in 
breast cancer are displayed in Table 5. </p>

<p>Figure 2 receiver operating characteristic (rOc) curve analysis of the diagnostic 
value of the uniformity of lesion enhancement in breast cancer. </p>

<p>Figure 3 receiver operating characteristic (rOc) curve analysis of the diagnostic 
value of the expansion of lesion diameter in breast cancer. </p>

<p>Figure 4 receiver operating characteristic (rOc) curve analysis of the diagnostic 
value of the relative peak intensity in breast cancer. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1128 </p>

<p>Zhao et al </p>

<p>Table 5 contrast-enhanced parameters and the prognostic factors in breast cancer </p>

<p>Parameters 
ER (+/-) 
c-erb-B2 (+/-) 
p53 (+/-) 
Ki-67 (+/-) 
Maximum diameter 
(#2 cm/.2 cm) </p>

<p>Histology grade </p>

<p>(I/II-III) </p>

<p>Enhancement mode 
Uneven 
52/42 
67/27 
51/43 
56/38 
52/42 
44/50 
even 
35/14 
15/34* 
28/21 
22/27 
32/17 
34/15* 
Perfusion defects 
Yes 
40/45 
56/29 
47/38 
57/28 
40/45 
39/46 
no 
47/11* 
26/32* 
32/26 
21/37* 
44/14* 
39/19* 
Enhancement form 
regular 
52/34 
47/39 
45/41 
49/37 
50/36 
47/39 
irregular 
35/22 
35/22 
34/23 
29/28 
34/23 
31/26 
Enhancement edge 
clear 
21/15 
17/19 
15/21 
15/21 
19/17 
20/16 
Unclear 
66/41 
65/42 
64/43 
63/44 
65/42 
58/49 
Enhancement mode 
concentric 
59/49 
60/48 
60/48 
56/52 
59/49 
54/54 
eccentric 
28/7* 
22/13 
19/16 
22/13 
25/10 
24/11 
Perforator vessels 
no 
27/14 
27/14 
27/14 
27/14 
27/14 
35/6 
Yes 
60/42 
55/47 
52/50 
51/51 
57/45 
43/59* </p>

<p>Note: *The distribution was significantly different (P,0.05). 
Abbreviation: er, estrogen receptor. </p>

<p>ultrasound imaging were superior to conventional ultrasound 
time-intensity analysis for breast cancer, as suggested by 
the ROC results. 
This study also found that CEUS parameters were 
related to the expressions of prognostic factors, including 
c-erb-B2, ER, and Ki-67. c-erb-B2 (also known as HER-2/ 
neu) is a proto-oncogene located on chromosome 17q, whose 
overexpression and amplification is related to neoplastic 
transformation, progression, and poor prognosis in breast 
cancer. 
20,21 The ER-positive cases in all breast cancers 
are ~60% and the prognosis of ER-negative breast cancer is 
poor. 
22 Ki-67 is a prognostic indicator in early breast cancer, 
is a nuclear antigen present in all proliferating cells, and its 
positive expression indicates an active proliferation of tumor 
cells; its high expression is also correlated with lymph node 
metastasis. 
23 It was shown that c-erb-B2 was positive in 
50.96% of malignant breast lesions, and the positive expres-
sion of this gene was associated with high enhancement in 
imaging. 
24 The defects in vascular perfusion are common in 
ER-negative tumors. 
24 Another study has shown that the con-
centric mode of enhancement was common in ER-negative 
tumors, and perfusion defects were generally seen in tumors 
with negative ER expression, positive c-erb-B2 expression, 
and positive Ki-67 expression, 
25 which were consistent with 
this study. 
This study confirmed that high and heterogeneous 
enhancement and lesion diameter expansion were significant </p>

<p>diagnostic factors for breast cancer, and some CEUS 
parameters had strong correlations with the expressions of 
prognostic factors of breast cancer, indicating that CEUS 
had certain diagnostic and prognostic values for breast 
cancer. Taking the successful application of CEUS in various 
disease diagnoses -from liver cancer to prostate and kidney 
diseases -in recent years into consideration, our results 
may be beneficial to finding clinical application of this new 
imaging method in the future regarding the diagnosis and 
prognosis evaluation of more illnesses, particularly gyneco-
logical diseases, including endometrial cancer and myoma 
of uterus. However, the research results should be verified 
in studies with more sample cases to ensure the reliability 
and accuracy. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We would like to acknowledge the helpful comments on this 
paper received from our reviewers. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>