<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5440747" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A B S T R A C T </p>

<p>Mitochondria are the main consumers of molecular O 2 in a cell as well as an abundant source of reactive oxygen 
species (ROS). Both, molecular oxygen and ROS are powerful regulators of the hypoxia-inducible factor-1α-
subunit (HIF-α). While a number of mechanisms in the oxygen-dependent HIF-α regulation are quite well 
known, the view with respect to mitochondria is less clear. Several approaches using pharmacological or genetic 
tools targeting the mitochondrial electron transport chain (ETC) indicated that ROS, mainly formed at the Rieske 
cluster of complex III of the ETC, are drivers of HIF-1α activation. However, studies investigating non-ETC 
located mitochondrial defects and their effects on HIF-1α regulation are scarce, if at all existing. Thus, in the 
present study we examined three cell lines with non-ETC mitochondrial defects and focused on HIF-1α 
degradation and transcription, target gene expression, as well as ROS levels. We found that cells lacking the key 
enzyme 2-enoyl thioester reductase/mitochondrial enoyl-CoA reductase (MECR), and cells lacking manganese 
superoxide dismutase (MnSOD) showed a reduced induction of HIF-1α under long-term (20 h) hypoxia. By 
contrast, cells lacking the mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome channel protein Mpv17 displayed enhanced 
levels of HIF-1α already under normoxic conditions. Further, we show that ROS do not exert a uniform pattern 
when mediating their effects on HIF-1α, although all mitochondrial defects in the used cell types increased ROS 
formation. Moreover, all defects caused a different HIF-1α regulation via promoting HIF-1α degradation as well 
as via changes in HIF-1α transcription. Thereby, MECR-and MnSOD-deficient cells showed a reduction in HIF-
1α mRNA levels whereas the Mpv17 lacking cells displayed enhanced HIF-1α mRNA levels under normoxia and 
hypoxia. Altogether, our study shows for the first time that mitochondrial defects which are not related to the 
ETC and Krebs cycle contribute differently to HIF-1α regulation by affecting HIF-1α degradation and HIF-1α 
transcription where ROS play not a major role. </p>

<p>Oxygen homeostasis is essential for survival and normal function of 
all aerobic living cells and organisms. Adaptation to low oxygen levels 
involves a wide range of responses at different cellular levels. Among 
the first line responses to hypoxia is the reprogramming of gene 
expression by activation of hypoxia-inducible factors (HIFs). HIFs are 
heterodimers, containing an oxygen-dependent α-subunit (HIF-1α, HIF-
2α and HIF-3α) and a constitutively expressed β-subunit (HIF-1β or aryl 
hydrocarbon receptor nuclear translocator (ARNT) [1]. From the three 
α-subunits known to date, HIF-1α is the best characterized. Its </p>

<p>regulation occurs primarily at the level of protein stability; under 
normal oxygen tension HIF-1α is hydroxylated at two specific residues 
(P402 and P564) which allows binding of a VHL-containing ubiquitin </p>

<p>ligase complex that mediates degradation via the ubiquitin/ protea-
some pathway [2,3]. The hydroxylation is carried out by a family of 
proline hydroxylases which are dependent on the availability of 
molecular oxygen, Fe 2+ and α-ketoglutarate [4]. Under low oxygen 
levels the HIF-1α-subunit is stabilized and translocates to the nucleus 
where it regulates more than 800 target genes [5,6]. Interestingly, the 
levels of HIF-α subunits are not only affected by oxygen, but also by 
reactive oxygen species (ROS). One major source of ROS are mitochon-
dria which are important organelles involved in a variety of cellular 
processes, including ATP production, calcium homeostasis, as well as 
cell survival and cell death [7,8]. 
Mitochondria consume oxygen in order to synthesize ATP via 
oxidative phosphorylation (OXPHOS). The OXPHOS machinery consists 
of five multi-subunit enzyme complexes (complex I, II, III, IV and V), </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.redox.2017.05.003 
Received 28 February 2017; Received in revised form 19 April 2017; Accepted 5 May 2017 </p>

<p>⁎ Corresponding author. </p>

<p>E-mail address: Thomas.Kietzmann@oulu.fi (T. Kietzmann). </p>

<p>Redox Biology 12 (2017) 1052-1061 </p>

<p>Available online 08 May 2017 
2213-2317/ © 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/BY-NC-ND/4.0/). </p>

<p>MARK </p>

<p>which are located in the inner mitochondrial membrane [9]. The 
electrons generated in the TCA cycle and which are donated by the 
coenzymes, NADH and FADH2 are passing through the electron 
transport chain (ETC) where oxygen functions as a final acceptor. 
However, if oxygen does not become fully reduced to water, ROS are 
generated as a byproduct of this electron transport process [10]. Several 
reports using pharmacological or genetic approaches targeting the ETC 
indicated that ROS, mainly formed at the Rieske cluster of complex III 
of the ETC, are drivers of HIF-1α activation [11-16]. However, the 
approaches targeting the ETC are expected not only to interfere with 
ROS production, but also to interfere with mitochondrial oxygen </p>

<p>consumption and thus, make it difficult to estimate to which extent 
ROS production or as proposed a shift in oxygen distribution [17] 
accounts for the effects on HIF-1α. 
To better understand the mitochondria´s contribution to HIF-1α 
regulation we hypothesized that non-ETC and non-Krebs cycle mito-
chondrial defects may have different or even no effect on HIF-1α levels. 
Therefore, we investigated in the present work three cell lines with such 
mitochondrial defects with respect to HIF-1α regulation, mitochondrial 
membrane potential, ROS production, and HIF target gene expression 
(Fig. 1). The first cell line under study was devoid of 2-enoyl thioester 
reductase/mitochondrial enoyl-CoA reductase (MECR). MECR is a 
component of the fatty acid synthesis type II (FAS II) complex and 
catalyzes the NADPH-dependent reduction of trans-2-enoyl thioesters. 
Loss-of-function mutations in the MECR gene cause childhood-onset 
dystonia and optic atrophy [18]. The second cell line used was lacking 
Mpv17, a mitochondrial inner membrane channel forming protein 
whose dysfunction causes hepatocerebral mitochondrial DNA depletion 
syndrome including Navajo neurohepatopathy [19,20]. The third cell 
line under study was depleted of manganese superoxide dismutase 
(MnSOD). MnSOD is the second (SOD2) of three superoxide dismutases; 
in contrast to the cytosolic (SOD1), and the extracellular (SOD3), it is 
found in the mitochondrial matrix. All SODs are responsible for the 
dismutation of superoxide anion radicals to hydrogen peroxide and 
oxygen. Importantly, deficiency of MnSOD in several cell types and in 
organs of mice was shown to contribute to carcinogenesis [21,22]. 
Our study shows for the first time that mitochondrial defects which 
are not related to the ETC and Krebs cycle enzymes contribute 
differently to HIF-1α regulation by affecting HIF-1α degradation and 
HIF-1α transcription with ROS being rather indirectly involved. </p>

<p>2. Material and methods </p>

<p>All biochemicals and enzymes were of analytical grade and were 
obtained from commercial suppliers. </p>

<p>2.1. Cell culture </p>

<p>NIH 3T3 were stably transfected with a MECR-shRNA expressing 
vector and a respective scrambled control vector and cultured under 
normoxia (16% O 2 , 79% N 2 and 5% CO 2 [by volume]) in Dulbecco´s 
modified Eagle´s medium (DMEM) supplemented with 10% fetal calf 
serum (FCS) in an Invivo2 400 hypoxia workstation (Ruskin 
Technologies). HepG2-scr and HepG2-MnSOD-KD cells were previously 
described and cultured in minimal essential medium (MEM) supple-
mented with 10% FCS [21]. Mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs) 
Mpv17 +/+ and Mpv17 -/-cells were cultured in DMEM supplemented 
with 10% FCS as described previously [20]. For protein extraction, cells 
were seeded onto 10 cm dishes and cultured under either normoxia or 
hypoxia (1% O 2 , 94% N 2 and 5% CO 2 [by volume]) in an Invivo2 400 
hypoxia workstation (Ruskin Technologies) for 20 h and then har-
vested. </p>

<p>2.2. Western blot analyses and HIF-1α protein half-life studies </p>

<p>Western blot analyses were carried out as described previously [23]. 
In brief, lysates from NIH 3T3-scr, NIH 3T3-MECR-KD, HepG2-scr, 
HepG2-MnSOD-KD, Mpv17 +/+ and Mpv17 -/-cells were collected and 
100 µg of total protein was loaded onto a 7.5% or 10% sodium dodecyl 
sulfate (SDS)-polyacrylamide gel. After electrophoresis and electroblot-
ting onto a nitrocellulose membrane, proteins were detected with 
primary antibodies against human HIF-1α (1:2000; BD Bioscience), 
mouse HIF-1α (1:1000; Novus Biologicals), MnSOD (SOD2) (1:1000; 
Calbiochem), MECR (1:1000; Proteintech), and against α-tubulin 
(1:10.000; Sigma). The secondary antibody was either an anti-mouse, 
an anti-rabbit or an anti-sheep immunoglobulin G conjugated to 
horseradish peroxidase (1:5000; Bio-Rad Laboratories). The ECL system </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Scheme of investigated mitochondrial defects and functional consequences. Acyl-
ACP, acetyl-(acyl-carrier-protein); MECR, mitochondrial trans-E-enoyl-CoA reductase; 
mtFASII, mitochondrial fatty acid synthase system; MnSOD, manganese superoxide 
dismutase; ROS, reactive oxygen species. </p>

<p>A.N. Shvetsova et al. 
Redox Biology 12 (2017) 1052-1061 </p>



<p>(Amersham) was used for detection. 
For half-life studies, NIH 3T3-scr, NIH 3T3-MECR-KD, HepG2-scr, 
HepG2-MnSOD-KD, Mpv17 +/+ and Mpv17 -/-cells were cultured under 
normoxic or hypoxic conditions. After 20 h, cycloheximide (10 µg/ml; 
Sigma) was added to the cell culture medium, cells were scraped in lysis 
buffer (50 mM Tris/HCL, pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 1% Triton X-100, 
2 mM EDTA, 2 mM EGTA, 1 mM PMSF and complete protease inhibitor 
cocktail tablet (Roche)) at indicated time points and protein levels were 
measured by immunoblot analysis. </p>

<p>2.3. TMRE mitochondrial staining </p>

<p>NIH 3T3-scr, NIH 3T3-MECR-KD, HepG2-scr, HepG2-MnSOD-KD, 
Mpv17 +/+ and Mpv17 -/-cells were seeded on a 96-well plate at a 
density of 15,000 cells/well and cultured under normoxic or hypoxic 
conditions. After 20 h, the cells were washed with 1×PBS and stained 
with 1 µM of tetramethyl rhodamine ester (TMRE, Abcam) for 30 min. 
Although these conditions of TMRE usage are considered as being the 
quenching mode, dinitrophenol (DNP) reduced the signal indicating 
validity of the assay. After incubation, cells were washed twice with 
0.2% BSA in 1 x PBS in the hypoxia workstation where the 96-well 
plates were sealed with parafilm and the fluorescence was immediately 
measured using a Tecan infinite M1000Pro microplate reader at an 
excitation wavelength of 549 nm and an emission wavelength of 
575 nm. </p>

<p>2.4. ROS detection </p>

<p>The total ROS content of cells was assessed using 2′,7′-dichlorodi-
hydrofluorescein diacetate (H 2 DCF-DA), whereas DHE was used to 
measure superoxide levels. Cells were seeded onto a 24-well plate at a 
density of 10,000 cells per well and cultured either under normoxia or 
hypoxia. After 20 h, cells were washed with 1 x PBS and incubated with 
10 μM H 2 DCF-DA (Molecular Probes) or 10 μM DHE (Sigma) in 1 x PBS 
for 15 min at 37 °C. After replacement of the reactive agents with 1 x 
PBS in the hypoxia workstation and sealing of the plate with parafilm, 
DCF formation was recorded at λ ex /λ em : 495/529 nm and DHE 
fluorescence at λ ex /λ em : 530/610 nm using a Tecan infinite </p>

<p>M1000Pro microplate reader. Values were corrected for H 2 DCF-DA 
and DHE auto-oxidation in 1 x PBS. </p>

<p>2.5. RNA preparation and reverse transcription </p>

<p>Isolation of total RNA was performed by using the RNeasy Mini Kit 
(Qiagen) following the manufacturer's instructions. Total RNA concen-
tration and purity were measured on a NanoDrop spectrophotometer. 
One μg of total RNA was used for cDNA synthesis using SuperScript II 
Reverse Transcriptase (Invitrogen). </p>

<p>2.6. Quantitative real-time PCR </p>

<p>qRT-PCR was performed with the iTaq SYBR Green Supermix in an 
Applied Biosystems 7500 Real-Time PCR System (Life Technologies, 
Finland). The following primer sets were used: hLDHA-F (TTGA 
CCTACGTGGCTTGGAAG-, hLDHA-R (GGTAACGGAATCGGGCT 
GAAT-, mLDHA-F (ACATTGTCAAGTACAGTCCACAC-, mLD 
HA-R (TTCCAATTACTCGGTTTTTGGGA-, hGLUT1-F (TCTG 
GCATCAACGCTGTCTTC-, hGLUT1-R (CGATACCGGAGCCAATG 
GT-, mGLUT1-F (CTCTGTCGGCCTCTTTGTTAAT-, mGLUT1-R 
(CCAGTTTGGAGAAGCCCATAAG-, hHIF-1α-F (ATCCATGTGA 
CCATGAGGAAATG-, hHIF-1α-R (TCGGCTAGTTAGGGTACACT 
TC-, mHIF-1α-F (GGGGAGGACGATGAACATCAA-, mHIF-1α-R 
(GGGTGGTTTCTTGTACCCACA-, hPGC1-F (TGACTGGCGTC 
ATTCAGGAG-, hPGC1-R (CCAGAGCAGCACACTCGAT-3), mPG 
C1-F (TGACTGGCGTCATTCGGGAG-, mPGC1-R (CCAGAGCA 
GCACACTCTAT- hHPRT-F (CCTGGCGTCGTGATTAGTGAT-, </p>

<p>hHPRT-R (AGACGTTCAGTCCTGTCCATAA -, mHPRT-F (
CGAAGTGTTGGATACAGGCC-, mHPRT-R (GGCAACATCAACAG 
GACTCC-. The experiments for each data point were carried out in 
triplicate. The relative quantification of gene expression was deter-
mined using the ΔΔCt method [24]. </p>

<p>2.7. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Densitometry data were plotted as fold induction of relative density 
units, with the zero value absorbance in each figure set arbitrarily to 1 
or 100%. Statistical comparisons of absorbance differences were 
performed by the Mann-Whitney test (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Statview</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.5</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Abacus Concepts</rs>, 
Berkeley, CA), and p values p &lt; 0.05 were considered significant. All 
data are shown as means ± SD of at least three independent experi-
ments. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. MECR, Mpv17, and MnSOD deficiency influence mitochondrial 
membrane potential, and ROS formation </p>

<p>In order to investigate whether the three different non-ETC mito-
chondrial defects such as loss of MECR, Mpv17, and MnSOD (Fig. 1) 
affect mitochondrial function and ROS levels we cultured the respective 
deficient cells along with their normal counterparts under normoxia 
and hypoxia and measured the mitochondrial membrane potential as a 
parameter of mitochondrial function, and ROS levels. 
To assess the mitochondrial membrane potential, we first labeled 
the intact and active mitochondria with the fluorescent dye tetra-
methylrhodamine ethyl ester (TMRE) and found that hypoxia reduced 
the TMRE signal in all control cells (Fig. 2). Interestingly, loss of MECR 
induced the TMRE signal and abolished the difference caused by 
hypoxia. Loss of Mpv17 also increased the TMRE signal; by about 
60% under normoxia in line with previous reports [20] and by about 
20% under hypoxia. In contrast, cells with a loss of MnSOD showed a 
similar reduction of the TMRE signal under both normoxia and hypoxia 
(Fig. 2). 
To assess whether the loss of MECR, Mpv17 or MnSOD affect the 
mitochondrial ROS levels, we labeled the cells with either dichlorodi-
hydrofluorescein diacetate (DCF), to measure overall ROS levels, or 
dihydroethidium (DHE) to measure superoxide. When we compared 
ROS levels under normoxia with ROS levels under hypoxia, we found 
that hypoxia reduced ROS levels in MECR-Scr and MECR-KD cells as 
well as in MnSOD-Scr and MnSOD-KD cells. By contrast, hypoxia 
increased ROS in Mpv17 +/+ and Mpv17 -/-cells. However, all cells 
with mitochondrial defects displayed higher ROS levels than the 
respective normal control cells either under normoxia or hypoxia 
(Fig. 3A). 
Similar to the ROS levels, we found that hypoxia reduced DHE 
fluorescence indicating superoxide in MECR-Scr and MECR-KD cells as </p>

<p>well as in MnSOD-Scr and MnSOD-KD cells. Again, hypoxia increased 
DHE fluorescence in Mpv17 +/+ and Mpv17 -/-cells under normoxia and 
hypoxia. Further, the cells harboring the mitochondrial defects showed 
enhanced DHE fluorescence under normoxia but not under hypoxia 
when compared to the respective control cells. (Fig. 3B). Together, 
these results suggest that all the mitochondrial defects affect ROS 
formation under normoxia and hypoxia. </p>

<p>3.2. Loss of MECR, Mpv17 and MnSOD affect HIF-1α protein levels with 
ROS playing different roles </p>

<p>We next wanted to know whether loss of MECR, Mpv17, and 
MnSOD have an influence on HIF-1α protein levels and whether ROS 
may be involved in this regulation. To do this, we cultured the 
respective deficient cells along with their normal counterparts under 
normoxia and hypoxia for 20 h and measured HIF-1α protein levels by </p>

<p>A.N. Shvetsova et al. 
Redox Biology 12 (2017) 1052-1061 </p>



<p>Western blot analysis. We found that hypoxia induced the HIF-1α 
protein levels in all three control cell lines (Fig. 4). Cells with a 
knockdown of MECR as well as cells with a knockdown of MnSOD 
showed reduced HIF-1α protein levels under hypoxia (Fig. 4A,B,E,F). </p>

<p>By contrast, knockout of Mpv17 increased HIF-1α protein levels by 
about 2.5-fold under normoxia and by about 7.5-fold under hypoxia 
(Fig. 4C,D). Together, these results indicate that lack of MECR, Mpv17, 
and MnSOD can modulate HIF-1α protein levels. 
To further investigate whether the changed ROS levels in these cells 
affect HIF-1α protein levels, we treated the cells with the antioxidant 
ascorbate, and the oxidant hydrogen peroxide (H 2 O 2 ). In the MECR-Scr 
and MECR-KD cells neither treatment with ascorbate nor with H 2 O 2 had 
an effect on HIF-1α protein levels under both normoxia and hypoxia 
(Fig. 5A). In Mpv17 +/+ cells treatment with ascorbate let to a slight 
reduction in the HIF-1α protein levels by about 30% under hypoxia 
compared to the untreated cells under hypoxia, whereas treatment with 
H 2 O 2 induced the HIF-1α protein levels by about 1.3-fold, but only 
under hypoxia (Fig. 5C). In contrast, ascorbate induced the HIF-1α 
protein levels in Mpv17 -/-cells only under normoxia. Treatment of the 
Mpv17 -/-cells with H 2 O 2 had no effect on HIF-1α protein levels under 
normoxic and hypoxic conditions compared to the untreated control 
(Fig. 5C). In MnSOD-Scr cells ascorbate treatment induced HIF-1α 
under normoxia by about 2-fold and under hypoxia by about 10-fold. 
Treatment with H 2 O 2 let to a reduction by about 50% under hypoxia 
(Fig. 5E). Importantly, knockdown of MnSOD abolished the hypoxia-
dependent HIF-1α induction. Ascorbate treatment of the MnSOD-KD 
cells strongly increased the HIF-1α protein levels by about 7-fold under 
both normoxia and hypoxia. Upon exposure of these cells to H 2 O 2 
almost no HIF-1α protein could be detected (Fig. 5E). Thus, these 
findings indicate that H 2 O 2 and ascorbate can influence the HIF-1α </p>

<p>protein levels differently in the used cells with non-ETC defects. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. MECR-, Mpv17-, and MnSOD-deficiency influences the mitochondrial membrane 
potential. (A) NIH 3T3-scr, MECR-KD, (B) Mpv17 +/+ , Mpv17 -/-, (C) HepG2-scr and 
MnSOD-KD cells were cultured under normoxia (16% O 2 ) and hypoxia (1% O 2 ) for 20 h. 
Mitochondrial membrane potential (ΔΨ m ) was assessed by TMRE fluorescence; dinitro-
phenol (DNP 50 µM) was added when indicated to uncouple the respiratory chain. Results 
are shown as percentage normalized to the control (16% O 2 ). * significant difference 16% 
O 2 versus 1% O 2 , # significant difference NIH 3T3-scr versus MECR-KD, Mpv17 +/+ 
versus Mpv17 -/-, and HepG2-scr versus MnSOD-KD at 16% O 2 ; p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Mitochondrial ROS production is affected by hypoxia and mitochondrial defects. 
NIH 3T3-scr, MECR-KD, HepG2-scr, MnSOD-KD, Mpv17 +/+ , and Mpv17 -/-cells were 
cultured under normoxia (16% O 2 ) and hypoxia (1% O 2 ) for 20 h. The redox state was 
determined by measuring (A) DCF fluorescence, and (B) DHE fluorescence. * significant 
difference 16% O 2 versus 1% O 2 , # significant difference NIH 3T3-scr versus MECR-KD, 
Mpv17 +/+ versus Mpv17 -/-, and HepG2-scr versus MnSOD-KD at 16% O 2 ; p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>A.N. Shvetsova et al. 
Redox Biology 12 (2017) 1052-1061 </p>



<p>3.3. Loss of MECR, Mpv17, and MnSOD reduces HIF-1α half-life </p>

<p>Since HIF-1α is primarily regulated at the level of protein stability, 
we were interested to see whether MECR, Mpv17, and MnSOD 
deficiency affects the half-life of HIF-1α. Therefore, we cultured cells 
for 20 h under hypoxic conditions (1% O 2 ) to stabilize HIF-1α. After 
treatment with cycloheximide (CHX) for several indicated time points, 
we collectively found that deficiency of MECR, Mpv17, and MnSOD 
reduced the HIF-1α protein levels and shortened the half-life with the 
strongest effect in the MnSOD-KD cells (Fig. 6A-F). Together, these 
data show that all non-ETC mitochondrial defects reduce the half-life of 
HIF-1α. </p>

<p>3.4. Loss of MECR, Mpv17, and MnSOD affect HIF-1α mRNA levels and 
HIF-1α target gene expression </p>

<p>The above made observations and the unexpected regulatory 
pattern achieved with respect to ROS-dependent HIF-1α regulation 
made us asking to what extent HIF-1α mRNA levels would be affected 
by the loss of MECR, Mpv17, and MnSOD. Accordingly, we analyzed 
HIF-1α mRNA levels by quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR). The 
obtained data indicated that there were no significant changes in the 
HIF-1α mRNA levels in MECR-Scr cells under hypoxia. However, HIF-
1α mRNA levels were reduced in MECR-KD cells by about 40% under 
both normoxia and hypoxia (Fig. 7A). In Mpv17 +/+ cells hypoxia let to </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Loss of MECR, Mpv17, and MnSOD affects HIF-1α protein levels. (A,C,E) The shRNA-depleted NIH 3T3 MECR (MECR KD) or HepG2 MnSOD (MnSOD KD) cells and their respective 
scrambled controls (Scr) as well as Mpv17 +/+ and Mpv17 -/-mouse embryonic fibroblasts were cultured under normoxia (16% O 2 ) and hypoxia (1% O 2 ) for 20 h. The HIF-1α protein 
levels measured by Western blot under normoxia (16% O 2 ) were set to 1. *, significant difference between control 16% O 2 versus control 1% O 2 ; #, significant difference between control 
16% O 2 versus KD 16% O 2 ; **, significant difference between control 1% O 2 versus KD 1% O 2 ; p &lt; 0.05 (B,D,F) Representative Western blot analysis. 100 µg of total protein lysates were 
analyzed with antibodies against HIF-1α, MECR, MnSOD and α-tubulin. Genotyping of isolated genomic DNA from mouse embryonic fibroblasts indicate lack of Mpv17. </p>

<p>A.N. Shvetsova et al. 
Redox Biology 12 (2017) 1052-1061 </p>



<p>a reduction in the HIF-1α mRNA levels by about 40%. In contrast, loss 
of Mpv17 let to an increase of HIF-1α mRNA levels by about 30% under 
normoxia and by about 25% under hypoxia (Fig. 7A). The MnSOD-Scr 
cells had about 30% induced HIF-1α mRNA levels in response to 
hypoxia. In contrast, MnSOD-KD cells showed a significant reduction in 
HIF-1α mRNA levels by about 60% under normoxia and by 20% under 
hypoxia (Fig. 7A). Next we investigated the mRNA levels of two specific 
HIF-1α target genes, glucose transporter 1 (GLUT1) and lactate 
dehydrogenase A (LDHA), as well as those of master regulator for 
mitochondrial biogenesis peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-</p>

<p>gamma coactivator (PGC)−1alpha (PGC-1α). As expected hypoxia 
induced the mRNA levels of GLUT1 and LDHA in MECR-Scr, Mpv17 
wild-type-and MnSOD-Scr cells. Surprisingly, there were no significant 
changes detectable in the mRNA levels of GLUT1 under hypoxia in the 
MnSOD-Scr cells (Fig. 7B,C). In line with the reduced HIF-1α levels, 
knockdown of MECR significantly reduced GLUT1 as well as LDHA 
mRNA levels under both normoxia and hypoxia (Fig. 7B,C). The 
Mpv17 -/-cells showed an induction of GLUT1 mRNA by about 25% 
under normoxia and by about 40% under hypoxia; LDHA mRNA levels 
showed a similar pattern (Fig. 7B,C). In the MnSOD-KD cells no GLUT1 </p>

<p>Fig. 5. H 2 O 2 and ascorbate influence HIF-1α protein levels. NIH 3T3-scr, MECR-KD, Mpv17 +/+ , Mpv17 -/-, HepG2-scr and MnSOD-KD cells were cultured under normoxic (16% O 2 ) or 
hypoxic (1% O 2 ) conditions for 20 h and then treated with ascorbate (Asc) or H 2 O 2 for 4 h. (A,C,E) In each experiment the untreated HIF-1α protein levels were set to 1. * significant 
difference 16% O 2 versus 1% O 2 , ** significant difference respective 16% O 2 or 1%O 2 control versus respective treatment with H 2 O 2 or ascorbate, # significant difference NIH 3T3-scr 
versus MECR-KD, Mpv17 +/+ versus Mpv17 -/-, and HepG2-scr versus MnSOD-KD; p &lt; 0.05. (B,D,F) Representative Western blot analysis. One hundred micrograms of total protein were 
analyzed with antibodies against HIF-1α and α-tubulin. </p>

<p>A.N. Shvetsova et al. 
Redox Biology 12 (2017) 1052-1061 </p>



<p>mRNA was detectable under normoxia and hypoxia. The LDHA mRNA 
was reduced in the MnSOD-KD cells by about 50% under both normoxia 
and hypoxia (Fig. 7B,C). 
In all cells hypoxia reduced PGC1 mRNA levels. Interestingly loss of 
MECR and Mpv17 increased the PGC1 mRNA levels under normoxic 
conditions by about 3-fold and 3.5-fold, respectively. Again, after 
exposure of these cells to hypoxia the PGC1 mRNA levels decreased 
(Fig. 7D). Further, a reduction of PGC1 mRNA by about 50% could be 
detected in the MnSOD-KD cells when compared to the MnSOD-Scr 
cells. Surprisingly, hypoxia induced the PGC1 mRNA levels in the 
MnSOD-KD cells (Fig. 7D). 
Together, these data show that non-ETC mitochondrial defects 
regulate HIF-1α at the degradation and transcriptional level in pro-
cesses where ROS may play a role. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Over the years, a number of studies have addressed the involvement 
of mitochondria, as well as ROS, in HIF-1α regulation. Although all 
previous reports, even if being conflicting, underlined that mitochon-
dria contribute to HIF-1α regulation and oxygen sensing a complete 
picture about the mechanisms involved has not been reached. This is in 
part likely due to the fact that the majority of studies focused either on 
the depletion of mitochondrial DNA (rho(0)-cells), or on the inhibition 
of the ETC via pharmacological approaches as well as by using cells 
with major ETC defects (for review see [25-28]). To the best of our 
knowledge, no studies considering other mitochondrial defects outside 
the ETC were carried out yet. Although descriptive, the current study is 
the first to show that non-ETC and non-Krebs cycle mitochondrial 
defects contribute to HIF-1α regulation in a different manner. 
Thereby, we describe three entirely new aspects with respect to the 
involvement of mitochondria in hypoxia-dependent HIF-1α regulation. 
First, the data show that three different non-ETC and non-Krebs cycle 
mitochondrial defects contribute to HIF-1α regulation in a different 
manner. Thereby, cells lacking the key enzyme of mitochondrial fatty 
acid synthesis MECR, and cells lacking MnSOD showed a reduced 
induction of HIF-1α under hypoxia. By contrast, cells lacking the 
mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome channel protein Mpv17 dis-
played enhanced levels of HIF-1α already under normoxic conditions. 
Second, our study shows that ROS do not exert a uniform pattern when 
mediating their effects on HIF-1α, although all mitochondrial defects in 
the used cell types increased ROS formation under normoxia. Third, the 
current data indicate that the mitochondrial defects cause the different 
HIF-1α regulation via promoting HIF-1α degradation as well as via 
changes in HIF-1α transcription. Thereby, MECR-and MnSOD-deficient 
cells showed a reduction in HIF-1α mRNA levels whereas the Mpv17 
lacking cells displayed enhanced HIF-1α mRNA levels under normoxia 
and hypoxia. 
The MECR deficiency leading to a reduced mitochondrial fatty acid 
synthesis (mtFAS) affects the function of other important metabolic 
enzymes such as α-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase (KGD), branched-chain 
keto-acid dehydrogenase, 2-oxoadipate dehydrogenase, pyruvate dehy-
drogenase (PDH), and enzymes of the glycine cleavage system. This is 
due to the fact that mtFAS is involved in the synthesis of lipoic acid (LA) 
which is as a covalently bound cofactor essential for the activity of the 
above mentioned enzymes. Hence, a loss of MECR leads to a loss of 
lipoylated proteins [29,30]. With respect to HIFα regulation this may 
be especially relevant if considering KGD activity and the accumulation </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Loss of MECR, Mpv17, and MnSOD affect HIF-1α protein stability. (A,C,E) NIH 
3T3-scr, MECR-KD, HepG2-scr, MnSOD-KD, Mpv17 +/+ , and Mpv17 -/-cells were cultured 
for 20 h under hypoxia (1% O 2 ). After inhibition of protein synthesis with cycloheximide 
(CHX; 10 µg/ml) HIF-1α protein levels were measured by Western blot analysis at the 
indicated time points. The HIF-1α protein levels without CHX were set to 1. *, significant 
difference, p≤0.05. (B,D,F) Representative immunoblots. One hundred micrograms of 
total protein were analyzed with antibodies against HIF-1α and α-tubulin. </p>

<p>A.N. Shvetsova et al. 
Redox Biology 12 (2017) 1052-1061 </p>



<p>of α-ketoglutarate in MECR-deficient cells which could feed the HIF 
hydroxylation reaction and consequently lead to an enhanced degrada-
tion of HIF-1α. This is indeed reflected in our study where MECR 
deficiency reduces the half-life of HIF-1α. Moreover, the reduced HIF-
1α mRNA levels add to this effect and may be seen in conjunction with 
the role of MECR in the regulation of pentose metabolism. Together, the 
findings with respect to MECR and its effect on HIF-1α regulation are in </p>

<p>line with its role in causing an inborn error of metabolism which 
resembles typical mitochondrial disorders with the involvement of 
organs being susceptible to oxygen deficiency such as basal ganglia and 
the optic nerve [18]. 
Our finding that HIF-1α is upregulated in cells lacking Mpv17 was 
at the first glance surprising. This was based on the fact that lack of 
Mpv17 causes mitochondrial DNA depletion, a feature also found in 
cells chemically modified to lack mitochondrial DNA (rho(0)-cells). 
These rho(0)-Hep3B and HEK293 cells were earlier shown to fail to 
induce HIF-1α and to generate ROS in response to hypoxia [12,15,31], 
hence, we expected that Mpv17 deficiency would abolish HIF-1α 
induction. Although we observed the opposite on the overall level of 
HIF-1α, we do not believe that cell-type specific effects as previously 
discussed in a report investigating the rho(0) effect in a human rho(0) 
osteosarcoma cell line with normal induction of HIF-1α [32] account 
for this regulation. We think that, in this particular case, the Mpv17 
Δψm-and ROS-modulating channel activity [20] and its subsequent, so </p>

<p>far unknown, signaling account for these effects. 
In line, we showed in our recent report that the gating properties of 
the Mpv17 channel can be affected by the redox state and that it 
participates in the modulation of the membrane potential (Δψ m ) to 
preserve mitochondrial homeostasis [20]. The data of the current and 
other reports [33] support this view. In particular, we found that 
hypoxia decreases Δψ m in all cell types investigated. Uncoupling of the 
ETC by dinitrophenol (DNP) elicited the expected dye responses 
indicating that the observed changes mirror the activity of the 
respiratory chain, although TMRE was used in a quenching mode. 
Interestingly, lack of MECR and Mpv17 increased Δψ m likely due to 
enhanced ROS formation especially under normoxia and although to a 
lesser extent, under hypoxia; by contrast, MnSOD-deficient cells 
displayed reduced Δψ m but also enhanced ROS formation. Overall, 
these data suggest a mutual relation between Δψ m and ROS where ROS 
levels can change Δψ m and vice versa changes in Δψ m may affect ROS 
production. This may, to a certain extent reflect also the severity of the 
mitochondrial defect and in this regard, the total lack of channel-
forming activity in Mpv17 deficient cells causes mitophagy, a process 
ultimately linked to hypoxic cell death and autophagy [20]. Thus, the 
increase in HIF-1α in Mpv17 lacking cells is in line with the findings 
showing that HIF-1α acts as an inducer of the Bcl2 family members, 
BCL2/adenovirus E1B 19 kDa interacting protein 3 (BNIP3) or BINP3L 
which both promote mitochondrial elimination via autophagosome 
formation [34]. 
Under these conditions, one can expect some quite similar aberra-
tions in ROS levels and by avoiding a reoxygenation phase due to the 
use of an Invivo2 400 hypoxia workstation before ROS measurements 
we found, in line with previous investigations, that hypoxia affects ROS 
levels [35] and thus, the oxidative status of the cell. Interestingly, none 
of the mutations affected the difference in ROS levels obtained upon 
transition of cells from normoxia to hypoxia, and although not entirely 
clear, these differences could simply reflect the different metabolic 
conditions obtained during the 20 h exposure of the cells to hypoxia. 
However and as discussed earlier [26-28], ROS production under 
hypoxia appeared to be cell-type specific and appeared to decrease in 
the respective MECR NIH3T3 fibroblasts and MnSOD HepG2 control 
cells, whereas ROS levels increased in hypoxic Mpv17 +/+ mouse 
embryonic fibroblasts. Interestingly, the loss of function of all the 
genes led to an additional increase in ROS levels under normoxia. By 
contrast, an increase in ROS was only observed with Mpv17 -/-cells 
under hypoxia. Thus, the pattern of ROS, neither H 2 O 2 nor. O 2 
-as </p>

<p>Fig. 7. MECR, Mpv17, and MnSOD deficiency affect HIF-1α and HIF-1α target gene 
expression as well as expression of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma 
coactivator 1-alpha (PGC-1). NIH 3T3-scr, MECR-KD, HepG2-scr, MnSOD-KD, Mpv17 +/ 
+ , and Mpv17 -/-cells were cultured under normoxic (16% O 2 ) or hypoxic (1% O 2 ) </p>

<p>conditions for 24 h. Total RNA was extracted, and relative HIF-1α, GLUT1, LDHA and 
PGC1 mRNA levels were evaluated by quantitative real-time PCR. *, significant difference 
16% O 2 versus 1% O 2 , #, significant difference NIH 3T3-scr versus MECR-KD, Mpv17 +/+ 
versus Mpv17 -/-, and HepG2-scr versus MnSOD-KD at the respective pO 2 ; p≤0.05. </p>

<p>A.N. Shvetsova et al. 
Redox Biology 12 (2017) 1052-1061 </p>



<p>indicated by DCF or DHE fluorescence [21], respectively, did not 
entirely reflect the HIF-1α levels. However, our data also showed that 
H 2 O 2 or the ROS scavenger ascorbate contributed to HIF regulation, 
although with different effects with respect to cell type and mitochon-
drial defect. This is in particular evident in the MnSOD deficient cells 
which do not show an upregulation of HIF-1α under hypoxia but where 
the ascorbate exposure strongly induces HIF-1α under both normoxia 
and hypoxia. 
These findings fit with previous reports from MnSOD overexpressing 
human breast carcinoma MCF-7 cells, where a highly increased MnSOD 
activity promoted HIF-1α appearance and overexpression of H 2 O 2 
metabolizing enzymes prevented HIF-1α induction under hypoxia 
[22]. Since the efficacies of superoxide dismutase and ascorbic acid 
for catalyzing the decay of superoxide radicals in animal tissues are 
similar [36] our data fit with the proposal that an increase in HIF-1α 
could be mediated by mitochondrial hydrogen peroxide. Our earlier 
findings [37,38] and reports from other groups [39-41] support that </p>

<p>this may be partially the case and, as discussed earlier [26], depend on 
the cell type. Our data also support this, since addition of H 2 O 2 to 
Mpv17 +/+ cells increased HIF-1α levels. However, when control and 
deficient MECR NIH 3T3 fibroblasts as well as MnSOD HepG2 cells 
were exposed to H 2 O 2 , HIF-1α was not found to be induced, neither 
under normoxia nor under hypoxia. Although these data fit with the 
idea that ROS can regulate HIF-1α, they appear not to follow the same 
regulatory mechanism influencing PHD-mediated HIF-1α degradation. 
This is based on the observation that the HIF-1α half-life is decreased in 
all cells with mitochondrial defects investigated here, although they all 
displayed enhanced ROS levels. Thus, these findings prompted us to 
look into the HIF-1α mRNA expression pattern. Importantly, we found 
that the HIF-1α mRNA levels correlated with the protein levels; 
decreased HIF-1α mRNA and protein levels in MECR-and MnSOD-
deficient cells and the opposite in Mpv17-lacking cells. Thus, these data 
suggest that, redox sensitive transcription factors could contribute to 
the changes in HIF-1α mRNA. In particular, NFκB [38,42] and Nrf2 
[35] may account for an induction of HIF-1α expression. However, it is 
unlikely that these factors also directly mediate the negative effects on 
HIF-1α mRNA abundance. Thus, it is tempting to speculate that either 
other transcription factors or indirect regulators of NFκB and Nrf2 may 
be involved. 
In addition to other interacting transcription factors, indirect 
regulators may also be miRNAs. Indeed, previous reports suggested 
that several miRNAs, being regulated by hypoxia, ROS, or regulating 
antioxidant responses can contribute to the regulation of oxidative 
phosphorylation, TCA cycle activity as well as transcription factors such 
as HIFs, NFκB, and Nrf2 [43-45]. Thereby, miRNAs such as miR210, 
which during hypoxia represses the iron-sulfur cluster assembly pro-
teins ISCU1/2, affect TCA cycle activity and oxidative phosphorylation 
[46]. Further, miR9 that controls for example the NFκB1/p50 subunit, 
or miR200a that affects the Nrf2 regulator Keap1, or miR126 [47] may 
affect HIF-1α expression and stabilization. Again, cell-type specific 
effects may account for differences. For example, miR126 was found to 
be up-regulated by hypoxia and oxidative stress in nonmalignant 
mesothelial cell lines. By contrast, in malignant H28 mesothelioma 
cells the induction of miR126 by hypoxia and oxidative stress was lost 
[47]. Thus, certain miRNAs, identification of which was not the scope 
of this study, may serve in important feedback loops and future work 
will provide us with the details about those. 
The survival of cells under hypoxia is also accompanied by active 
changes in mitochondrial function. For example, HIF-1α directs pro-
cesses leading to downregulation of complex I activity and complex IV 
activity [48-50]. In addition to limiting the entry of metabolites into 
the TCA cycle, the HIF system was also shown to shut down O 2 -
demanding processes such as fatty acid β-oxidation. Indeed, hypoxia 
reduced the expression of carnitine palmitoyltransferase 1 (CPT-1) 
[51], which catalyzes the rate-limiting step in the mitochondrial import 
of fatty acids for β-oxidation. Moreover, hypoxia exposure reduced </p>

<p>expression of the medium-and long-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenases 
(MCAD and LCAD) [52] and decreased ROS as well as an important 
regulator of β-oxidation proliferator-activated receptor-γ coactivator-
1α (PGC-1) protein levels [51,52]. These findings are concurrent with 
the present study. However, when PGC-1 expression was analyzed 
under normoxia we found that its expression was increased in all cells 
harboring a mitochondrial defect. Since PGC-1 is considered to be one 
of the most, if not the most, important driver of mitochondrial 
biosynthesis these effects constitute likely a feedback mechanism by 
which the cells aim to compensate for their respective deficit in 
mitochondrial function. Mitochondrial number and mtDNA, as well as 
mitochondrial protein composition can vary with the mutations and 
interventions, and PGC-1 variations support this. Further, this also 
correlates well with the enhanced ROS levels under normoxia which are 
known to be activators of PGC-1 [53]. 
Altogether, the current study substantiates that mitochondrial 
integrity is an important modulatory factor of HIF-1α regulation. In 
line with the present findings and the knowledge that HIF-1α can be 
regulated by ROS in different ways (reviewed in [28,54,55]), we show 
that, in addition to the complex network controlling HIF-1α at the level 
of protein stability, mitochondrial defects regulate HIF-1α mRNA 
expression. Thus, the identification of transcriptional and post-tran-
scriptional HIF regulatory networks may provide an additional way of 
controlling HIF-1α levels and may open new therapeutic options to 
modulate the HIF pathway. </p>









</text></tei>