<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5054108" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI) anchor is a common but complex C-terminal 
post-translational modif ication of extracellular proteins in eukaryotes. Here we 
investigate the problem of correctly annotating GPI-anchored proteins for the 
growing number of sequences in public databases. We developed a computa-
tional system, called <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs>, based on the tandem use of a neural net-
work (NN) and a hidden Markov model (HMM). Firstly, NN selects potential 
GPI-anchored proteins in a dataset, then HMM parses these potential GPI sig-
nals and ref ines the prediction by qualitative scoring. <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> correctly pre-
dicted 91% of all the GPI-anchored proteins annotated in the Swiss-Prot database. 
In a large-scale analysis of 29 eukaryote proteomes, <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> predicted that 
the percentage of highly probable GPI-anchored proteins is between 0.21% and 
2.01%. The distinctive feature of <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs>, compared with other systems, 
is that it targets only the C-terminus of a protein, making it less sensitive to 
the background noise found in databases and possible incomplete protein se-
quences. Moreover, <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> can be used to predict GPI-anchored proteins 
in all eukaryotes. Finally, by using qualitative scoring, the predictions combine 
both sensitivity and information content. The predictor is publicly available at 
http://navet.ics.hawaii.edu/∼fraganchor/NNHMM/NNHMM.html. </p>

<p>The complexity of information contained in protein 
sequences is a major challenge for large-scale analy-
sis of proteomics data: some characteristics are easily 
identifiable, such as general hydrophobicity, whereas 
others are well hidden, such as the presence of short 
segments endowed with a specific function but hav-
ing been affected by numerous mutations during their 
evolution. Identifying and classifying correctly these 
characteristics often requires novel approaches that 
assist standard tools of analysis. Furthermore, the 
structure of protein sequences translated from genes is 
not sufficient to assess the overall complexity of their 
functions. Indeed, post-translational modifications 
(PTMs) can spawn, for example, changes of activity, 
cellular localization, or protein interaction (1 ). PTMs 
such as glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI) anchors </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. 
E-mail: guylaine@hawaii.edu </p>

<p>are fundamental for understanding biological func-
tions of proteins; however, studies are suffering from 
a shortage of efficient methods that could allow to 
identify them in large-scale analyses (2 ). The predic-
tion of PTM in protein sequences is then an integral 
part of an in-depth study fostering the understand-
ing of biological functions, which turns out to be an 
important step in the annotation of proteomes. </p>

<p>Glycosylation is one of the most common and com-
plex forms of PTMs (3 , 4 ). It is classified into three 
categories: N-glycosylation, O-glycosylation, and the 
attachment of a glycolipide (GPI) to the C-terminus 
of a protein. A GPI anchor is a type of membrane at-
tachment discovered fairly recently. Its occurrences in 
eukaryotic cells were identified in the 1980s through 
the works of several researchers (5-9 ). Among pro-
teins with GPI anchors one finds enzymes, adhesive 
proteins, receptors, activation antigens, and so on 
(10 , 11 ). Currently the exact function of this at-</p>

<p>Geno. Prot. Bioinfo. Vol. 5 No. 2 2007 </p>

<p>
This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). </p>

<p>FragAnchor for Predicting GPI-Anchored Proteins </p>

<p>tachment is not well characterized (12 ). Nonethe-
less, its conservation across great taxonomic diver-
sity (yeasts, protozoa, plants, vertebrates, and even 
archeo-bacteria) suggests some important functional-
ity (13 ). Proteins with GPI anchors reveal a very 
interesting feature that they are exclusively extracel-
lular. This PTM thus provides interesting informa-
tion for the annotation of new sequences by specifying 
their cellular localizations. Moreover, this property 
of GPI-anchored proteins opens the way to several 
potential applications. For example, in the genome 
of Plasmodium falciparum (human malaria parasite), 
several proteins that are attached to the membrane 
by a GPI anchor can be used as vaccine candidates 
(14 ). 
Proteins linked to the membrane by a GPI an-
chor are not easy to identify with traditional sequence 
alignment and pattern recognition approaches that 
are used in computational biology. Indeed, there 
is no clear constant, approximate, or repetitive pat-</p>

<p>terns, and similarity analysis yields poor results (re-
sults not shown). Nonetheless, some general rules 
have been identified. For example, GPI-anchored 
proteins have an N-terminal signal for translocation 
across the endoplasmic reticulum. However, we dis-
covered that this signal is absent or not clearly pre-
dicted by computational tools in nearly 7% of the 
annotated GPI-anchored proteins in the Swiss-Prot 
database (http://www.expasy.org/sprot/). Besides 
the N-terminal signal, the C-terminal GPI signal, 
cleaved off at the time of the addition of the GPI-
lipid anchor, can be further broken down into 4 re-
gions (15 ): (1) an unstructured linker region of about 
10 residues; (2) a region of small residues, including 
the GPI attachment and cleavage site; (3) a spacer 
region, following the cleavage site, of about 7 amino 
acids (a.a.); (4) a hydrophobic tail next to the spacer 
region, completing the C-terminus (Figure 1). 
Such sequence features suggest that rule-based 
approaches should be efficient in predicting GPI-</p>

<p>Fig. 1 Structure of GPI-anchored proteins. A. Signals of GPI-anchored proteins at the N-terminus and the C-
terminus, respectively. B. The C-terminal signal can be further decomposed, from left to right, as a polar region, a 
sequence of three small amino acids (the anchor site is at position W ), a spacer region, followed by a hydrophobic tail. 
C. Illustration of the structure with a fragment of the DAF HUMAN protein. </p>

<p> 
Geno. Prot. Bioinfo. Vol. 5 No. 2 2007 </p>

<p>Poisson et al. </p>

<p>anchored proteins, but there are many exceptions that 
newly identified GPI-anchored proteins depart from 
these rules (for example, unpredictable N-terminal 
signals, C-terminal signals with overlapping spacer re-
gion and hydrophobic tail, or length of the spacer re-
gion outside the parameters), lowering automatically 
the sensitivity of the predictions based on methods 
using such rules in a strict way. 
Currently, there exist three different predictors 
publicly available: <rs id="software-9" type="software">big-π</rs> (15 ) from the <rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">University of Vienna</rs> (available in two versions, one for meta-
zoa and one for protozoa), <rs id="software-28" type="software">DGPI</rs> from the <rs corresp="#software-28" type="creator">University of Geneva</rs> (retrieved from <rs corresp="#software-28" type="url">http://129.194.185.165/dgpi/</rs>/), and the large-scale annotator <rs type="software">GPI-SOM</rs> (16 ) 
from the University of Bern. The first two also pre-
dict potential cleavage sites while the third does not. 
These tools target the C-terminal and N-terminal sig-
nals of protein sequences, or require verifying the pres-
ence of the N-terminal signal before submitting se-
quences to the predictor. This affects automatically 
their performance in the presence of fragmented or 
partial sequences, which happen to be more and more 
common in databases. In particular, metagenome 
projects generate many fragmented sequences repre-
senting only partial proteins, complicating the anno-
tation process. Moreover, with metagenome projects, 
the inability to relate many of the new sequences to 
a specific taxonomic group does not favor the use of 
a group-specific tool like <rs type="software">big-π</rs>. Therefore, large-scale 
annotation tools, which are able to predict the pres-
ence of a particular motif at different levels of preci-
sion (that is, to assess each prediction in a qualitative 
way) with minimal information, are then needed to 
address this new reality, since tools that are too re-
strictive or specialized often lack the flexibility needed 
to make correct predictions. For example, a recent 
analysis of the P. falciparum proteome shows that 
<rs type="software">big-π</rs>, <rs type="software">DGPI</rs>, and <rs type="software">GPI-SOM</rs> generated poor results in 
predicting proteins selected as biologically validated 
or highly probable candidates (14 ). Accordingly, our 
system was designed to offer the precision of cleavage 
site prediction tools and the flexibility needed for a 
large-scale annotator in a noisy environment. </p>

<p>Results and Discussion </p>

<p>We developed a system, called <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs>, based on 
the tandem use of a neural network (NN) and a hid-
den Markov model (HMM). NN is used to select po-
tential GPI-anchored sequences and HMM classifies </p>

<p>the selected sequences by a qualitative scoring scheme. 
The sequences selected by NN are annotated as highly 
probable (Class 1), probable (Class 2), weakly prob-
able (Class 3), or potential false positive (Class 4). 
HMM is also used to predict the position of the cleav-
age site in the sequence. 
Firstly, NN and HMM were trained separately 
with different training sets. This choice was made 
to ensure an optimal training set for each method. 
For NN, a validation test was performed with 134 
GPI sequences and 134 non-GPI sequences from the 
Swiss-Prot database release 49.0. This test showed 
that, for a threshold of selection set to 0.90 (the pos-
sible values for this threshold range from 0.0 to 1.0), 
NN had a precision of 93% and a positive correlation 
coefficient between prediction and observation (17 ) 
of 0.86, implying that the predictions are quite ac-
curate. With this validation test set, NN was able 
to correctly predict 89.47% of the GPI-anchored se-
quences and 96.27% of the sequences that were not an-
notated as GPI-anchored. These results, along with 
the area under the receiver operating characteristic 
(ROC) curve, are good indicators suggesting that NN 
has an acceptable degree of precision and an interest-
ing generalization power. 
We also performed additional tests of NN with a 
dataset containing 593 sequences annotated as GPI-
anchored in the Swiss-Prot database, 265 membrane 
transport protein sequences, as well as 111 cytoplasm 
and nuclear protein sequences (Table 1). The result 
showed that NN was able to predict 91.06% of the 
annotated GPI sequences in Swiss-Prot. Note that 
the training sequences, as well as the sequences that 
are very similar to some ones present in the train-
ing set, are present in this dataset and these results 
cannot be used to assess precisely the quality of the 
predictor. However, these tests indicated that NN 
had a specificity of 95%, which means that 5% of the 
predictions were false positive. For HMM alone, we 
performed similar tests and the results we obtained 
showed a higher specificity but a lower sensitivity (re-
sults not shown). 
For the tandem system (see Materials and Meth-
ods), we ran a validation test by using four different 
sets of sequences (Table 2). The first two are positive 
sets (GPI-anchored proteins) while the next two are 
negative sets (proteins that are not GPI-anchored). 
The first positive set contains 121 sequences among 
the 134 sequences used to test NN (13 sequences used 
in the training set of HMM were discarded). The sec-
ond positive set contains 30 sequences presented in a </p>

<p>Geno. Prot. Bioinfo. Vol. 5 No. 2 2007 </p>

<p>
FragAnchor for Predicting GPI-Anchored Proteins </p>

<p>Table 1 Prediction results of the neural network on dif ferent sequence sets </p>

<p>Sequence set 
No. of sequences Predicted GPI (%) </p>

<p>Cytoplasm and nuclear 
111 
98.20 
Membrane transport 
265 
92.45 
GPI sequences in Swiss-Prot 
593 
91.06 </p>

<p>Table 2 Prediction results of the tandem system on dif ferent sequence sets </p>

<p>Sequence set 
No. of 
Predicted Class 1 Class 2 Class 3 Class 4 Invalid Rejected 
sequences GPI (%) 
(%) 
(%) 
(%) 
(%) 
(%) by NN (%) </p>

<p>First positive set 
121 
88.43 
66.94 
11.57 
4.13 
5.79 
0.00 
11.57 
P. falciparum 
30 
96.67 
20.00 
26.67 
10.00 
40.00 
0.00 
3.33 
Cytoplasm and nuclear 
1,873 
3.20 
0.21 
0.16 
0.27 
2.56 
0.08 
96.80 
Membrane transport 
4,587 
6.21 
0.76 
0.68 
0.44 
4.29 
0.59 
93.79 </p>

<p>Table 3 Comparative prediction results between big-π, GPI-SOM, and FragAnchor </p>

<p>Sequence set 
No. of 
Predicted GPI (%) 
sequences FragAnchor FragAnchor 
FragAnchor 
GPI-SOM big-π 
(all classes) 
+SignalP 
(Classes 1-3) </p>

<p>First positive set 
121 
88.43 
82.64 
82.64 
82.64 
60.33 
P. falciparum 
30 
96.67 
80.00 
56.67 
73.33 
46.67 
Cytoplasm and nuclear 
1,873 
3.20 
0.85 
0.64 
1.49 
0.54 
Membrane transport 
4,587 
6.21 
3.24 
1.88 
2.83 
0.50 </p>

<p>recent analysis of the P. falciparum proteome (14 ). 
The first negative set contains 1,873 sequences with 
a subcellular localization annotated as "cytoplas-
mic" from the human protein localization database 
(http://locate-human.imb.uq.edu.au/). The second 
negative set contains 4,587 sequences retrieved from 
the Swiss-Prot database by using the keywords 
"transmembrane", "transport", or "secreted" and are 
not annotated as GPI-anchored. </p>

<p>These tests revealed an interesting prediction 
power of the tandem system and more importantly a 
remarkable flexibility offered by the qualitative scor-
ing. The test on the first positive set (121 sequences) 
revealed a sensitivity of 88.43% to the GPI anchor 
signal if we accept all predictions, and 82.64% if we 
want to be stricter by eliminating the potential false 
positive class. The specificity varied from 99.89% 
to 93.89% depending on the type of sequences and 
classes. HMM also gives an annotated prediction with 
a potential cleavage site. A test on 330 sequences 
with an annotated cleavage site showed that the tan-
dem system correctly predicted 75% of them. In the 
25% incorrectly predicted cleavage sites, 58% were 
predicted at a distance of at most three amino acids 
from the annotated anchor site. An important point 
is that many of the GPI anchor sites in the Swiss-Prot </p>

<p>curated database are based on automated prediction. 
In the test performed with 30 sequences of those 
proposed by Gilson et al (14 ) from the P. falciparum 
proteome, <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> was able to predict 29 of them 
as GPI-anchored protein sequences (96.67%). How-
ever, it is interesting to note that 40% of these predic-
tions were classified as potential false positive (Class 
4). 
The tests with the two negative sets gave very 
good results as 96.80% and 93.79% of the sequences 
were rejected by NN, respectively, while HMM clas-
sified most of the incorrectly selected sequences as po-
tential false positives. These examples illustrate the 
importance and usefulness of the qualitative scoring 
of the predictions of <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs>. 
The sequences of the four test sets described above 
were also submitted to two publicly available predic-
tors of GPI-anchored proteins: <rs type="software">big-π</rs> (15 ) and <rs type="software">GPI-
SOM</rs> (16 ) (Table 3). We did not compare <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> 
with <rs type="software">DGPI</rs> because the design of this tool makes large 
dataset analysis difficult. Since <rs type="software">big-π</rs> and <rs type="software">GPI-SOM</rs> 
require the use of <rs type="software">SignalP</rs> (18 ) for the N-terminal sig-
nal peptide prediction, we included an evaluation of 
<rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> combined with <rs type="software">SignalP</rs> to help the com-
parison process. However, the use of <rs type="software">SignalP</rs> is not re-
quired before using <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs>. Compared with big-</p>

<p> 
Geno. Prot. Bioinfo. Vol. 5 No. 2 2007 </p>

<p>Poisson et al. </p>

<p>π, FragAnchor is more sensitive to the GPI-anchoring </p>

<p>pattern even if we consider only the first three classes 
(highly probable, probable, and weakly probable). 
For the first set of 121 GPI-anchored sequences, Fra-
gAnchor correctly predicted 88.43% of them (82.64% 
in Classes 1-3) while big-π accepted 60.33%. For the 
newly analyzed P. falciparum sequences, as pointed 
out in Gilson et al (14 ), most predictors failed to pre-
dict a significant number of sequences known to bear 
GPI anchor. In Table 3, we can see that FragAn-
chor has a very high capacity of prediction with only 
one sequence wrongly predicted. Even when discard-
ing the potential false positive sequences, <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> 
recognizes more GPI-anchored sequences than <rs type="software">big-π</rs> 
does. One of the reasons of the better performance 
of <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> is the fact that it does not need the 
presence of the N-terminal signal, which is not clearly 
detectable in 6 of the 30 P. falciparum sequences. 
On the other hand, <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> shows a lower ca-
pacity of discrimination for the negative sets when 
compared with <rs type="software">big-π</rs>, which is understandable due to 
the high stringency of <rs type="software">big-π</rs>. However, this high strin-
gency is accompanied by a poor capacity of prediction 
for the GPI anchor signal. Nonetheless, we achieved a 
specificity of <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> comparable to that of <rs type="software">GPI-
SOM</rs> and <rs type="software">big-π</rs>. The specificity was computed by 
adding the proportions of the first three classes (Ta-
ble 2), for example, for the cytoplasm and nuclear 
proteins, it is 0.21 + 0.16 + 0.27 = 0.64. For the mem-
brane transport proteins, FragAnchor gave more false 
positive predictions. However, for this set of proteins, 
it is possible that some of them will eventually be 
validated as real GPI-anchored proteins in laboratory 
experiments. 
When compared with <rs type="software">GPI-SOM</rs>, <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> is 
more accurate. <rs type="software">GPI-SOM</rs> predicted fewer GPI-
anchored sequences from the first positive set of 121 
sequences, with a prediction rate of 82.64% compared 
with 88.43% for <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs>. It also failed to predict 
a significant number of the P. falciparum sequences 
with only 73.33% of correctly predicted GPI-anchored 
sequences. For the negative sets, the use of FragAn-
chor combined with <rs type="software">SignalP</rs> showed that <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> 
achieved results close to <rs type="software">GPI-SOM</rs> (better for the first 
negative set, slightly lower for the second negative 
set). 
More interestingly, the analysis of P. falciparum 
GPI-anchored sequences showed that a large portion 
of the GPI-anchored sequences (40%) fell in the po-
tential false positive prediction, proving the useful-
ness of keeping those potentially wrongly predicted </p>

<p>sequences in a specific class. An analysis of the se-
quences rejected by <rs type="software">GPI-SOM</rs> showed that 50% of 
them were found in the potential false positive class 
from <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs>. In addition, the analysis result of 
P. falciparum sequences demonstrated that 4 of the 11 
biochemically validated GPI-anchored sequences did 
not have an N-terminal signal peptide recognized by 
<rs type="software">SignalP</rs>. This fact confirms the effectiveness of an an-
notation not based on the prediction of this signal. In 
short, the comparison with other tools is not easy due 
to the uniqueness of the tandem method. However, 
it reveals an interesting power of prediction where, in 
a single run, <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> can have a very low num-
ber of potential false positive predictions with a much 
higher number of GPI-anchored sequences predicted. 
In Figure 2, we show an example of output from 
the tandem system (<rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> predictor). NN first 
selects a protein sequence and then HMM parses 
the sequence in order to predict a potential cleavage 
site. The first predicted anchor site for that sequence 
(5NTD HUMAN) is at position 549. This is the po-
sition annotated in the Swiss-Prot database. In the 
output, the predictor proposes a maximum of three 
possible anchor sites, ranked by decreasing scores. 
We selected 29 eukaryote proteomes available from 
the EBI Intergr8 portal (19 ) for large-scale analysis. 
The results showed that, in general, the percentage 
of GPI-anchored proteins in a proteome is between 
0.21% and 2.01% when only the highly probable class 
is considered (Table 4). These results are compa-
rable with a study performed by Eisenhaber et al 
(20 ) that estimated the proportion of the Arabidop-
sis thaliana proteome consisting of GPI-anchored pro-
teins at 0.75%. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The comparison of <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> with <rs type="software">big-π</rs> and <rs type="software">GPI-
SOM</rs> shows that <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> can be used at different 
levels of precision, allowing a more selective predic-
tion. In addition, it offers a high level of flexibility 
with respect to the organism considered. Studies like 
the P. falciparum proteome analysis by Gilson et al 
(14 ), where the available predictors failed to predict 
the biochemically proposed new GPI-anchored pro-
teins, show that there is a need for a more flexible 
and universal predictor. The flexibility and accuracy 
achieved by <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> offer an excellent annotator 
for the GPI anchor signal designed for all metagenome 
projects. </p>

<p>Geno. Prot. Bioinfo. Vol. 5 No. 2 2007 </p>

<p>
FragAnchor for Predicting GPI-Anchored Proteins </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Example of the output from <rs type="software">FragAnchor</rs> and comparison to the Swiss-Prot annotation. </p>

<p>One of the main goals of this large-scale predic-
tion tool is to offer greater flexibility to the users. 
We propose a tool that offers different levels of sen-
sitivity to the GPI anchor signal. The tests reveal 
that the combination of the two machine learning ap-
proaches yields very good results. The tandem system 
is a very general (all eukaryotes) tool for the annota-
tion of GPI-anchored proteins on a large scale by us-
ing minimal information. It produces prediction with 
a qualitative annotation allowing the user to choose 
the strength of precision that he/she wants. The less 
sensitive classes may contain sequences with unusual 
GPI anchor signals, which can yield to new discoveries 
in the PTM research area. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Neural network predictor </p>

<p>Neural networks are designed to classify patterns 
through a learning process that allows defining class 
boundaries in a non-parametric way. The basic ele-</p>

<p>ments are artificial neurons that: (1) accept numer-
ical input from other neurons or from the external 
environment; (2) process their input with a transfer 
function; (3) output a value to other neurons or back 
to the external environment. 
The Stuttgart Neural Network Simulator 
(<rs id="software-29" type="software">javaNNS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-29" type="version-number">1.1</rs>) developed at the University of 
Stuttgart (http://www-ra.informatik.uni-tuebingen. 
de/downloads/JavaNNS/) was used to design and 
train our NN predictor. The learning set for this 
experiment is 79 sequences from the Swiss-Prot 
database release 49.0 that are annotated as GPI-
anchored proteins, with a length of the C-terminal 
section to be 50 a.a., and another 79 sequences of pro-
teins that are known not to be GPI-anchored proteins. 
The choice of the length of the C-terminal section was 
based on an analysis of Swiss-Prot GPI-anchored pro-
teins, which showed a maximum length of 45 a.a. for 
the C-terminal signal. To give some flexibility to the 
system, we selected an input vector of 50 a.a. Since 
neural networks accept numerical input, and given the 
importance of molecular weight and hydrophobicity </p>

<p> 
Geno. Prot. Bioinfo. Vol. 5 No. 2 2007 </p>

<p>Poisson et al. </p>

<p>Table 4 Proportion of highly probable GPI-anchored proteins predicted by FragAnchor 
for 29 eukaryote proteomes </p>

<p>Organism 
Proteome size Predicted GPI 
(sequences) 
(Class 1) (%) </p>

<p>Anopheles gambiae 
15,135 
0.61 
Arabidopsis thaliana 
33,862 
0.83 
Ashbya gossypii 
4,720 
0.91 
Aspergillus fumigatus 
9,906 
0.89 
Brachydanio rerio 
11,863 
0.58 
Caenorhabditis briggsae 
13,192 
0.70 
Caenorhabditis elegans 
22,362 
0.66 
Candida glabrata 
5,180 
1.31 
Cryptococcus neoformans 
6,442 
0.90 
C. neoformans var. neoformans 
6,442 
0.90 
Debaryomyces hansenii 
6,311 
0.82 
Dictyostelium discoideum 
13,049 
1.29 
Drosophila melanogaster 
16,302 
0.79 
Encephalitozoon cuniculi 
1,909 
0.21 
Gallus gallus 
11,820 
0.93 
Gibberella zeae 
11,638 
1.13 
Guillardia theta 
598 
0.33 
Homo sapiens 
38,039 
0.74 
Kluyveromyces lactis 
5,312 
1.02 
Leishmania major 
8,010 
1.02 
Mus musculus 
32,901 
0.82 
Paramecium tetraurelia 
6,311 
0.82 
Plasmodium falciparum 
5,253 
0.19 
Plasmodium yoelii yoelii 
7,755 
0.22 
Rattus norvegicus 
11,820 
0.93 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae 
5,801 
0.95 
Schizosaccharomyces pombe 
4,964 
0.68 
Tetraodon nigroviridis 
27,810 
0.55 
Yarrowia lipolytica 
6,525 
2.01 </p>

<p>in the anchoring process, we encoded each amino acid 
with its hydropathy on the Kyte and Doolitle scale 
(21 ), as well as its molecular weight. The last step 
is the normalization of the input vectors. We have 
applied a simple min-max normalization: </p>

<p>v = 
(v − min) 
(max − min) 
 *  (max − min ) + min </p>

<p>where v represents the normalized value of data v, 
min and max represent the minimal and maximal </p>

<p>value of the target interval, while min and max are 
the minimal and maximal value of our actual data in-
tervals: [−4.5, 4.5] for hydropathy, and [75.07, 204.23] 
for molecular weight. 
An alignment of sequences consisting of the last 50 
residues of GPI sequences was done with ClustalW </p>

<p>(22 ). 
It was visually analyzed to target non-
redundant sequences in order to eliminate the risk of 
bias toward a type of sequence too abundantly repre-
sented. We retained 79 sequences annotated as GPI-
anchored from the Swiss-Prot database. In order to 
discriminate accurately between GPI and non-GPI se-
quences for the model, we retained mostly experimen-
tally verified sequences. We also selected a set of 79 
sequences that have a very low probability of being 
GPI-anchored (such as cytoplasm and nucleic pro-
teins) or have similar features but without the GPI 
anchor (membrane transport proteins). The selection 
of the sequences was manually made to ensure a low 
level of similarity and to verify the quality of the an-
notation as not GPI-anchored sequences. The combi-
nation of these two datasets defines our training set. </p>

<p>Geno. Prot. Bioinfo. Vol. 5 No. 2 2007 </p>

<p>
FragAnchor for Predicting GPI-Anchored Proteins </p>

<p>To validate the model, we used a test set composed 
of 134 GPI-anchored sequences. This set features few 
redundant sequences and is disjoint from the training 
set. We also selected 134 sequences with a very low 
probability of being GPI-anchored. </p>

<p>Our validation set of 268 sequences does not rep-
resent the complexity of actual sequence databases. 
Therefore, we selected in the Swiss-Prot database the 
following types of sequences: </p>

<p>(1) Sequences that have structures or physico-
chemical properties relatively similar to GPI-anchored 
and potential false positive proteins. We selected 265 
membrane transport proteins with similar hydropho-
bicity characteristics, making them good candidates 
for discrimination purpose. </p>

<p>(2) Sequences with a very low probability of being 
GPI-anchored. GPI-anchored proteins are exclusively 
extracellular, so we selected 111 cytoplasmic protein 
sequences based on their subcellular localization. </p>

<p>The architecture of the neural network used in 
FragAnchor is a multilayered perceptron using the 
RPROP (Resilient Back Propagation) learning algo-
rithm (23 ). The input layer is composed of 100 neu-
rons, corresponding to 2 input values for each of 50 
amino acids. A hidden layer of 150 neurons encodes 
the classification process, and the output layer con-
tains 1 neuron, giving a score to each sequence. The 
number of neurons in the hidden layer is the optimal 
architecture selected over different test architectures 
(results not shown). </p>

<p>The learning process consisted in gradually adjust-
ing the weights of the processing functions in order to 
obtain good scores on known GPI-anchored proteins. 
A score greater than 0.90 indicates that the network </p>

<p>has identified a potential GPI-anchored protein. </p>

<p>Hidden Markov model predictor </p>

<p>HMM is a probabilistic model equivalent to a regular 
grammar that is built by using machine-learning algo-
rithms, from a set of sequences (amino acid sequences 
in this study) called the training set. Given an amino 
acid sequence, the automaton reads it and computes 
the following data: (1) a score expressing the likeli-
hood that a new sequence is similar to the ones in the 
training set; (2) a most likely path in the automaton 
that highlights possible features of the structure of 
this sequence (24 ). 
Based on the known structure of the GPI signal 
(Figure 1), we designed our HMM predictor follow-
ing the approach used in SignalP (18 ). The underly-
ing graph of HMM is composed of three parts, corre-
sponding to the GPI signal features (Figure 3). The 
score associated to a sequence is the log-score of the 
likelihood, normalized by the length of the sequence. 
The parameters for HMM were estimated by 100 
iterations of the Baum-Welch algorithm (25 ). Pseu-
docounts were used for the two parts of HMM cor-
responding to the spacer region and the hydrophobic 
tail. For each of these regions, the distribution of the 
amino acids after the initial training in the given re-
gion was used to correct for the rare states that had a 
null emission probability for some amino acids. The 
training set for HMM was a set of 87 sequences from 
Swiss-Prot that are annotated as GPI-anchored pro-
teins. The model was validated using 500 bootstrap 
replications on our training set. For each replication, 
a dataset composed of 87 sequences (repetitions al-
lowed) was generated. These models were trained and </p>

<p>Fig. 3 The hidden Markov model for the GPI anchor signal representation. The first three states model the three 
amino acids around the anchor site. From the third state, transitions are possible to states 4 to 13, modeling the 
variable length spacer region. Finally, the hydrophobic tail, also a variable length region, is modeled by states 17 to 41. </p>

<p> 
Geno. Prot. Bioinfo. Vol. 5 No. 2 2007 </p>

<p>Poisson et al. </p>

<p>tested using a validation set of 66 sequences. 
In the experimental setup, each analyzed sequence 
was run through HMM with each putative cleavage 
site. These putative cleavage sites were identified 
with a sliding window that detects groups of three 
amino acids of small molecular weight. This is how 
HMM can also predict cleavage sites. The Forward 
algorithm computed the likelihood of a sequence, and 
the Viterbi algorithm (26 ) computed the most prob-
able path for each sequence. The three best, in terms 
of scores, possible cleavage sites were recorded. </p>

<p>Tandem system </p>

<p>In the tandem system (Figure 4), the sequences se-
lected by NN (the ones with a score greater than 0.90) 
are presented to HMM. The HMM score obtained on 
each sequence is then used to classify the sequence. 
This classification ranges from "highly probable" to </p>

<p>"potential false positive" (Table 5). Each class of an-
notation was defined using a graphical representation 
of false-positive and true-positive predictions at all 
discrimination threshold, the ROC curve. This quali-
tative annotation allows us to keep the high sensitivity 
(proportion of all true positives correctly predicted) 
obtained with NN, together with the specificity (pro-
portion of all true negatives correctly predicted) and 
the capacity of HMM to identify some features of the 
GPI signal, such as the cleavage site. The major ad-
vantage of using the qualitative scoring in a large-
scale annotator is its fast and easy identification of 
the best predictions and the possible false positives. 
NN can detect the GPI anchor motif efficiently but its 
architecture does not give us any information about 
the primary structure of the motif, while the use of 
HMM provides this information. Consequently, we 
can refine the prediction depending on the quality of 
the signal present in the protein sequence. </p>

<p>Fig. 4 The structure of the tandem system. </p>

<p>Table 5 Qualitative annotation of the tandem system </p>

<p>Category 
Class 
HMM score </p>

<p>Probable highly probable (Class 1) 
score ≥ 5.40 
probable (Class 2) 
2.20 ≤ score &lt; 5.40 
weakly probable (Class 3) 
0.20 ≤ score &lt; 2.20 </p>

<p>Potential potential false positive (Class 4) score &lt; 0.20 </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Fathey Sarhan, Mounir Boukadoum, Math-
ieu Blanchette, Pierre Poirier, and Marc LePape for 
reviewing and providing useful comments and sugges-</p>

<p>tions. This work was partly supported by the Na-
tional Institutes of Health of USA (Grant No. 5 P20 
RR16467) and by the GP/PhD scholarship from the 
FCAR (now NATEQ) fund of Canada. </p>

<p>Geno. Prot. Bioinfo. Vol. 5 No. 2 2007 </p>

<p>
FragAnchor for Predicting GPI-Anchored Proteins </p>

<p>Authors' contributions </p>

<p>GP conceived of the study, participated in its design, 
performed the analysis for the neural network and the 
tandem method, and drafted the manuscript. CC par-
ticipated in the design and coordination of the study, 
performed the analysis for the hidden Markov model, 
and also drafted the manuscript. XC performed the 
automation of the method and designed the web site. 
AB participated in the design and coordination of the 
study and also drafted the manuscript. All authors 
contributed to the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>The authors have declared that no competing inter-
ests exist. </p>



<p> 
Geno. Prot. Bioinfo. Vol. 5 No. 2 2007 </p>

</text></tei>