<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5372024" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Introduction: Selecting a suitable wound dressing for </p>

<p>patients with partial-thickness burns (PTBs) is 
important in wound care. However, the comparative 
effectiveness of different dressings has not been 
studied. We report the protocol of a network meta-
analysis designed to combine direct and indirect 
evidence of wound dressings in the management of 
PTB. </p>

<p>Methods and analysis: We will search for </p>

<p>randomised controlled trials (RCTs) evaluating the 
wound-healing effect of a wound dressing in the 
management of PTB. Searches will be conducted in 
MEDLINE, EMBASE, the Cochrane Central Register of 
Controlled Trials, the Cochrane Wounds Group 
Specialised Register and CINAHL. A comprehensive 
search strategy is developed to retrieve articles 
reporting potentially eligible RCTs. Besides, we will 
contact the experts in the field and review the 
conference proceedings to locate non-published 
studies. The reference lists of articles will be reviewed 
for any candidate studies. Two independent reviewers 
will screen titles and abstracts of the candidate articles. 
All eligible RCTs will be obtained in full text to perform 
a review. Disagreement on eligibility of an RCT will be 
solved by group discussion. The information of 
participants, interventions, comparisons and outcomes 
from included RCTs will be recorded and summarised. 
The primary outcome is time to complete wound 
healing. Secondary outcomes include the proportion of 
burns completely healed at the end of treatment, 
change in wound surface area at the end of treatment, 
incidence of adverse events, etc. </p>

<p>Ethics and dissemination: The result of this review </p>

<p>will provide evidence for the comparative effectiveness 
of different wound dressings in the management of 
PTB. It will also facilitate decision-making in choosing 
a suitable wound dressing. We will disseminate the 
review through a peer-review journal and conference 
abstracts or posters. </p>

<p>Trial registration number: PROSPERO </p>

<p>CRD42016041574; Pre-results. </p>

<p>INTRODUCTION 
Partial-thickness burns (PTBs) are burn 
wounds commonly seen in emergency 
rooms. PTBs are characterised as blister, swel-
ling and redness on the skin. These skin 
damages affect the epidermis and structures 
beneath the epidermis such as blood vessels, 
hair follicles and nerves. 
1 PTB is usually cate-
gorised as superficial PTB or deep PTB. 
Superficial PTBs involve damage to the papil-
lary dermis, characterised as intact blisters, 
moderate oedema, a moist surface under the 
blisters, a bright pink or red colour. Deep 
PTBs involve damage to both the papillary 
and reticular dermis, characterised as broken 
blisters, substantial oedema, a wet surface, 
waxy white colour. 
2 The difference between 
superficial and deep PTB is whether the 
burns extend through all skin layers, and 
deep PTBs do. In the USA alone, there are 
486 000 burn injuries (43% caused by fire or 
flame, 34% by scald, 9% by contact, 4% by 
electrical burns, 3% by chemical burns and </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ The comparative effectiveness of different wound 
dressings in the management of partial-thickness 
burn has not been studied; our network 
meta-analysis will be the first to answer the 
question. 
▪ We will conduct this network meta-analysis in a 
Bayesian framework and test robustness of the 
result with multiple meta-regressions and sensi-
tivity analyses. 
▪ We will include trials assessing the effectiveness 
of traditional wound dressings that were treated 
as standard wound care. These trials are usually 
published before the year 2000, the quality of 
which may be generally low. </p>

<p>Jiang Q, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013289. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013289 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Protocol </p>

<p>7% by other reasons) each year. 
3 More than 60% of the 
acute hospitalisations are caused by burn injuries. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Patients suffer pain, scars and mood disturbances like 
distress, anxiety or depression from PTB. Healthcare 
costs for burns are high; a median cost of $44 024 is 
needed for one patient. 
5 Although direct data on cost 
for PTB are not available, they were assumed to be 
costly. 
6 Therefore, efficient and effective wound care for 
PTB management is urgently needed. 
PTB management consists of wound preparation, 
wound cover and postwound care. 
7 Wound dressings, 
covering the wound to accelerate wound healing and 
protect the wound from infection, include modern dres-
sings like hydrocolloids, hydrofibre, silicones, alginates 
and polyurethane and traditional dressings like paraffin 
gauze and silver sulfadiazine (SSD). 
In the wound dressings, modern dressings are reported 
to achieve better burn healing than traditional dressings 
like silver SSD, although quality of the overall evidence is 
low. 
8 Additionally, the relative efficacy and toxicity of 
modern dressings have not been studied. Silver SSD, one 
of the traditional dressings, has been reported as the gold 
standard for PTB management. 
9 However, SSD is under 
criticism for causing wounds to dry up and not supporting 
optimal healing. 
10 Unlike SSD, modern dressings have the 
advantages of keeping a moist environment around burn 
wounds and effectively protecting the wound from expos-
ure to pathogenic bacterium. 
8 Each of these modern dres-
sings has its own features in achieving optimal healing. For 
example, hydrocolloids, one of the modern dressings, 
contain gelatin, pectin and sodium carboxymethylcellu-
lose in an adhesive polymer matrix. When the polymer 
matrix of the hydrocolloid dressings contacting wound 
exudate would form a gel, so they facilitate autolytic 
debridement of wounds. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Polyurethane films are 
adhesive-coated sheets applied directly to burn wounds. 
The advantage of polyurethane lies in that it is permeable 
to water vapour, oxygen and carbon dioxide but not to 
water or pathogenic bacterium. However, polyurethane is 
not suitable for wounds with heavy exudate. 
12 The other 
modern dressings have their own advantages, which leave 
the physicians and patient with a selection dilemma. 
The goal of burn management is to achieve rapid 
wound healing, pain relief, rehabilitation with minimal 
scars and optimal functional ability. Therefore, questions 
are raised: Which are the best wound dressings in 
achieving rapid healing, in relieving pain, in retaining 
optimal functional ability or in leaving minimal scars? 
To answer these questions, we need results from pairwise 
comparisons of different wound dressings, so a network 
meta-analysis is warranted. The network meta-analysis 
combines direct (head-to-head comparisons of different 
dressings) and indirect (we could simulate dressing A vs 
B if they share the same comparator C) evidence. 
13 The 
analysis is usually done with the Bayesian Markov Chain 
Monte Carlo (MCMC) method, since it has multiple 
advantages, such as producing results for all compari-
sons of interest within a connected network, calculating </p>

<p>the probability that each drug is the best treatment and 
adjusting for correlations within multiarm trials. 
14 In 
summary, we will perform a Bayesian network 
meta-analysis to study the comparative effectiveness of 
different wound dressings in the management of PTB, 
providing a reference basis for decision-making. </p>

<p>METHODS 
This systematic review and network meta-analysis has 
been registered (http://www.crd.york.ac.uk/PROSPERO/, 
reference number: CRD42016041574). Figure 1 gives an 
overview of the study process. It is anticipated to be 
finished in December 2016. The review is financially sup-
ported by the Key Program of National Clinical Specialty 
Discipline Construction of China and the Key Clinical 
Specialty Discipline Construction Program of Fujian. It is 
also sponsored by the Science and Technology Key 
Project of Fujian Province, China (reference number: 
2014y0056). This study is designed and reported accord-
ing to the standards of quality for reporting systematic 
review and meta-analysis protocols (PRISMA-P). </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Eligibility criteria 
Types of studies 
We will search for randomised controlled trials (RCTs) 
evaluating the effectiveness of a wound dressing for 
wound healing in patients with PTB, since RCTs are 
recognised as the gold standard in evaluating the effect-
iveness of an intervention. We will include RCTs compar-
ing wound dressings with no intervention, placebo 
dressings or other wound dressings (treated as standard 
wound cover). RCTs with a cross-over design will be 
excluded, since PTB has rapid evolution (superficial 
PTBs usually heal within 2 weeks 
16 ). </p>

<p>Types of participants 
Patients who have burns classified as PTB (including 
superficial and deep PTB) will be included in this </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow chart of the systematic review. </p>



<p>Jiang Q, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013289. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013289 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>review. According to the guideline for management of 
PTBs, 
7 patients with burns that are wet, painful, bliste-
ring, red, white or pink will be included. Patients with 
burns that are dry, painless, grey, white or brownish will 
be excluded, for these burns may be full-thickness 
burns. We will also include patients with burns classified 
as grade II burns, which used to be another name of 
PTB. 
17 We will include both paediatric and adult 
patients who receive treatments in primary, secondary or 
tertiary care settings. Patients who need referral to 
wound-care specialists will be excluded, since using 
wound dressings alone plays a little role in the treat-
ments for these patients. Additionally, we will include 
patients with fresh PTBs (within 72 hours after injury), 
since PTBs beyond 72 hours may be infected and thus 
need special wound care in addition to wound dressings. 
Adolescents (age under 18 years) or elders (aged over 
65 years) with the size of the burn area surpassing 10% 
of the total body surface area (TBSA) or adults (aged 
between 18 and 65 years) with the size surpassing 15% 
of TBSA will be excluded, since these patients also need 
special wound care managed by specialists. </p>

<p>7 18 19 </p>

<p>Patients with burns caused by electric or chemistry or 
with burns located on the face, neck, hands, feet, 
armpits, popliteal region or genitals will be excluded, </p>

<p>since these burns need special wound care in addition 
to local wound dressings. 
7 20 21 Concomitant diseases in 
the endocrine and immune systems (eg, diabetes) 
should be reported in RCTs recruiting patients aged 
over 50 years; otherwise, these RCTs will be excluded. 
Diseases in these two systems will influence time to heal 
PTB. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Types of interventions 
Both traditional and modern wound dressings will be 
assessed in this review. Traditional wound dressings refer 
to paraffin gauze and silver SSD, which are used less 
often now, because they may cause wounds to dry up 
and lead to increased risk of infection. 
7 9 23 However, 
since they have been conventionally used as standard 
wound care in the past 30 years, 
24 we will include them 
as reference comparators. Modern wound dressings, 
such as hydrocolloid, hydrogel, hydrofibre, silicones, 
bioengineered skin substitutes, alginates and polyureth-
ane, will be included for assessment. These modern 
dressings, compared with traditional dressings, have 
several advantages of keeping a moist wound environ-
ment to facilitate healing, providing an effective barrier 
to reduce the risk of infection and maintaining 
maximum contact with the wound to relieve pain. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Additionally, they are easy to use and remove, which 
guarantees a minimal extent of pain during attaching or 
removing dressings. Duration of wound dressings or fre-
quency of changing wound dressings will not be limited. </p>

<p>Types of outcomes 
We will include RCTs evaluating the effects of wound 
dressings with the following outcomes: time to complete 
wound healing, proportion of wounds achieving com-
plete closure at the end of treatment (3-4 weeks), 
change in wound surface area at the end of treatment 
(3-4 weeks), patient's satisfaction with the attachment 
and removal of dressings, proportion of patients 
needing burn care from specialists or surgery, or inci-
dence of adverse events. </p>

<p>Search methods 
We will electronically search in the following database: 
Ovid MEDLINE (from 1966 to 2016), EMBASE (from 
1980 to 2016), the Cochrane Central Register of 
Controlled Trials (from inception to 2016), the 
Cochrane Wounds Group Specialised Register (from 
inception to 2016) and EBSCO CINAHL (from 1980 to 
2016). A comprehensive search strategy has been devel-
oped (table 1). We will also search clinicaltrials.gov for 
RCTs that were registered but not reported (from incep-
tion to 2016), and we will contact the sponsors or princi-
pal investigators of these trials to ask for data. Besides, 
we will contact the experts in the field and review the 
conference proceedings to locate non-published studies. 
The reference lists of articles will be reviewed for any 
candidate studies. </p>

<p>Table 1 Search strategy for MEDLINE (via OVID) </p>

<p>N Search terms </p>

<p>1 
randomized controlled trial.pt 
2 
controlled clinical trial.pt 
3 
randomized.ab 
4 
placebo.ab 
5 
randomly.ab 
6 
trial.ab 
7 
groups.ab 
8 
or/1-7 
9 
exp animals/not humans.sh 
10 8 not 9 
11 exp Bandages, Hydrocolloid 
12 (hydrocolloid$ or hydrofibre or hydrofiber).tw 
13 exp alginate-polyethylene glycol acrylate 
14 (alginate$ or seasorb or sorbalgon or sorbsan or 
tegagen).tw 
15 exp Hydrogel 
16 (hydrogel$ or hydrosorb or novogel or purilon or 
sterigel).tw 
17 exp occlusive dressings 
18 foam dressing$.tw 
19 (retention tape or hypafix).tw 
20 (paraffin gauze).tw 
21 (biosynthetic substitute$).tw 
22 (antimicrobial dressing$ or acticoat).tw 
23 or/11-22 
24 exp burns 
25 (burn or burns or burned).tw 
26 (partial thickness burn$).tw 
27 or/24-26 
28 10 and 23 and 27 </p>

<p>Jiang Q, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013289. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013289 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Identification of studies 
Two reviewers (QJ and S-BW) will independently screen 
titles and abstracts of the retrieved articles for eligible 
RCTs. If it is impossible to determine the eligibility of 
the eligible RCTs through titles and abstracts, we will 
obtain full-text copies for further evaluation. 
Disagreement on eligibility of a RCT will be solved by 
group discussion and arbitrated by a third reviewer 
(X-DC). </p>

<p>Risk of bias assessment 
Risk of bias of included RCTs will be assessed with the 
Cochrane risk of bias assessment tool. We will use this 
assessment tool to determine internal validity of the 
RCTs in six domains: sequence generation, allocation 
concealment, blinding, incomplete outcome data, selec-
tive outcome reporting and other issues. In assessing 
other issues, we will focus on baseline imbalance and 
source of financial support. The baseline imbalance may 
cause overestimation or underestimation of an experi-
mental intervention. 
26 Receiving financial support from 
a commercial company that produces and provides 
active wound dressings may cause overestimation of the 
effect of this wound dressing. Each of the six domains 
will be classified as low risk of bias, high risk of bias or 
unclear risk of bias. Details for this classification are 
described in the Cochrane handbook. 
27 Any discrepancy 
in the risk of bias assessment will be resolved by group 
discussion and arbitrated by a third reviewer (X-DC). 
The overall strength of the body of evidence will be 
assessed using Grades of Recommendation, Assessment, 
Development, and Evaluation (GRADE). </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Data extraction 
Standardised extraction forms will be developed to 
record the following information: study characteristics 
(first author, publication year, study sites, number of par-
ticipants, open label/single blind/double blind, study 
duration, source of financial support), patient's character-
istics (age, gender, diabetes (yes/no), wound infected 
(yes/no), TBSA, body mass index, cause of burn, dur-
ation of burn, burn depth), interventions and compari-
sons (name of experimental or control interventions, 
duration of treatment, frequency of wound changes, 
special wound care (yes/no), healthcare facilities where 
the participants receive wound dressings (primary/sec-
ondary/tertiary care)) and outcomes (definition of an 
outcome, intention-to-treat analysis (yes/no), main results 
and variables for calculating effect size). Extracted data 
will be entered into an electronic system developed with 
the <rs id="software-0" type="software">EpiData EntryClient</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.2.0.7.22</rs>). To lower the risk 
of entry error, double data entry and cross-check will be 
performed in the system. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
We will summarise characteristics of the included RCTs 
and present direct and indirect comparisons between 
different wound dressings. We will check clinical </p>

<p>heterogeneity in the included RCTs through tables and 
visual plots. Examination of the clinical heterogeneity 
will focus on patients' baseline characteristics, healthcare 
facilities where patients receive wound dressings and 
duration of follow-up. Statistical heterogeneity will also 
be investigated with the I 
2 statistics. Different wound 
dressings will first be categorised as different classes like 
hydrocolloid, hydrogel, silicones, etc. We will test the 
agreement in effect size in a specific class, using the I </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>value of 50% as a cut-off point. I 
2 &gt;50% indicates signifi-
cant heterogeneity in the RCTs testing one of the 
wound dressing classes. We will second test the hetero-
geneity in individual wound dressings when possible. If 
the included RCTs show clinically or statistically signifi-
cant heterogeneity, we will give a narrative review. 
Otherwise, we will proceed to a traditional meta-analysis, 
calculating the effect size of different classes of wound 
dressings compared with placebo or active controls. For 
continuous outcomes, standardised mean difference 
(SMD) will be calculated; for dichotomous outcomes, 
ORs will be computed. We will synthesise SMD or OR 
with the DerSimonian-Laird method (random-effects 
model). 
A Bayesian network meta-analysis will be performed to 
combine direct and indirect evidence. In this network 
meta-analysis, measures of relative effect sizes will be 
ORs in the dichotomous outcomes and SMDs in the 
continuous outcomes. Both ORs and SMDs will be 
reported with their 95% credible intervals (95% CI). 
The 95% CI could be elucidated as a 95% probability 
that the true OR or SMD falls in the reported range. 
The network meta-analysis will be performed with a 
random-effect model using <rs id="software-1" type="software">WinBUGS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">1.43</rs> (MRC 
Biostatistics Unit, Cambridge University, UK). Each ana-
lysis will be based on non-informative priors for calcula-
tion of effect sizes and 95% CI. We will use the surface 
under the cumulative ranking (SUCRA) to rank the 
wound dressing classes. The SUCRA presented as per-
centages compare each wound dressing with an inter-
vention presumed as the best treatment without 
uncertainty, so a larger SUCRA means a more effective 
wound dressing class. Transitivity and consistency are the 
two key elements representing the credibility of a 
network meta-analysis. The assumption of transitivity is 
that the distribution of effect modifiers is not different 
in each pairwise comparison in the network. To account 
for transitivity in the network, we will assess participant's 
characteristics (infected or non-infected wounds, 
patients with or without diabetes, smoker or non-smoker, 
with or without long-term use of steroids), study designs 
(duration of follow-up and risk of bias) and interven-
tions (duration of treatment and wound dressings given 
in primary or secondary or tertiary care). Consistency 
between direct and indirect comparisons will be 
assessed. The result of direct comparisons will be 
acquired through the aforementioned traditional 
meta-analysis, whereas the result of indirect comparisons 
will be obtained through excluding those studies with </p>



<p>Jiang Q, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013289. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013289 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>head-to-head comparisons. The consistency will be evalu-
ated with the I 
2 statistics, with an I </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>&lt;25% indicating mild 
inconsistency, an I 
2 between 25% and 50% showing 
moderate inconsistency, and an I </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>&gt;50% representing 
severe inconsistency. Given the feature of Bayesian statis-
tical analysis, p values will not be estimated and reported 
for each comparison. 
Several sensitivity analyses will be performed on the 
primary outcome to investigate the reasons for potential 
heterogeneity. The analyses include exclusion of: trials 
with a high risk of bias (assessed by the Cochrane risk of 
bias tool); trials including patients with diabetes 
( patients with diabetes present with a longer time to 
wound healing); trials including smokers; trials inclu-
ding patients with long-term use of steroids; trials 
comparing different usages of the same wound dressings 
(usages that are different in frequency of changing dres-
sings or ingredients); trials with missing SD or 95% CI; 
trials that are not analysed on an intention-to-treat basis; 
trials with negative findings (in which the experimental 
wound dressings or active comparators are not superior 
to placebo controls). 
Multiple meta-regressions will be performed to study 
the impact of sponsorship (whether the sponsors are 
involved with manufacture of experimental wound dres-
sings or active comparators); mean age of the included 
participants (ageing leads to delayed epithelialisation, so 
elders may need longer healing time than adolescents); 
subtypes of PTB (superficial or deep PTB; patients with 
deep PTB may theoretically need a longer time in 
wound healing than those with superficial PTB), blind-
ing method (open label, single blind, double blind), 
risk of bias (high, unclear, low), TBSA and duration of 
PTB. If a significant impact of these factors is found, we 
will perform subgroup analyses according to these 
factors. </p>

<p>Dealing with the missing data 
We will contact authors who reported trials with missing 
data to ask for original data. If the original data are not 
available, we will try to calculate the missing data 
through other variables given in the articles. For 
example, we will estimate SD through 95% CI or SE. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
This network meta-analysis will summarise the direct 
and indirect evidence aiming to provide a ranking of 
the conservative treatment for PTB. The results of this 
network meta-analysis may help the patients with PTB 
and their physicians select the best option. To the best 
of our knowledge, this will be the first network 
meta-analysis conducted to determine the optimal con-
servative treatment for PTB. This study protocol is 
designed to meet the PRISMA-P standards. 
15 It is 
designed without knowing the study data or results from 
the existing published literature. The results of this 
meta-analysis will help the decision-makers come to </p>

<p>their own conclusions regarding which is the best wound 
dressing for patients with PTB. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements This work is financially supported by the key Program of 
National Clinical Specialty Discipline Construction of China and key Clinical 
Specialty Discipline Construction Program of Fujian, China and also 
sponsored by the science and technology key project of Fujian Province, 
China (NO: 2014Y0056). </p>

<p>Contributors X-DC contributed to the conception and design of the study 
protocol. The search strategy was developed by Z-HC. QJ and S-BW will 
screen the title and abstract of retrieved studies and extract data from included 
trials. X-DC will check the accuracy and completeness of data entry. Z-HC will 
synthesise and analyse the extracted data. All authors drafted this protocol 
and approved it for publication. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement If this systematic review has results, the authors 
would like to share the original data with the public. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Jiang Q, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013289. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013289 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>





<p>Jiang Q, et al. BMJ Open 2017;7:e013289. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013289 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>