<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5338970" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) is a seriously impairing psychiatric condition 
that affects 1%-3% of youth. Investigating the quality of life (QOL) is an important issue for 
treatment planning of this disorder, as targeting symptoms without taking it into account may 
bias assessment and prognosis when the patient presents with reduced symptoms that do not 
correspond to improved QOL. However, QOL in young individuals with OCD has been under-
studied. This meta-analysis summarized current evidence that assessed differences in global, 
social and school QOL dimensions, between children/adolescents with OCD and screened 
controls. Age, sex and OCD severity were examined as moderators. Case-control studies were 
included if children/adolescents with primary OCD were compared with screened controls on 
validated self-reported QOL outcomes. Online databases (January 1966-January 2016) were 
searched. Five case-control studies were included (n=543, 17 effect sizes overall). On global 
QOL, a large effect size emerged (d=−1.16, P,0.001), suggesting that individuals with OCD had 
lower global QOL than controls. Moderate effect sizes emerged for school (d=−0.61, P,0.01) 
and social QOL (d=−0.54, P,0.01), respectively, indicating worse QOL on these domains for 
individuals with OCD. For samples with higher OCD severity, global QOL of individuals with 
OCD was lower than that for controls (β=−0.02, P,0.05). For samples with lower percentages 
of females, global QOL of individuals with OCD was more impaired (β=0.02, P,0.001). Age 
was not correlated with effect sizes. Assessment and treatment should target QOL for young 
males suffering from more severe OCD. The small number of included studies highlighted 
that QOL is under-recognized. Future research should focus on additional QOL domains and 
compare which ones are impaired among individuals with OCD compared with other psychiatric 
conditions. Overall, the results pointed out the importance of addressing QOL in both practice 
and research on assessment and treatment of children/adolescents with this condition. 
Obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) in children and adolescents is a psychiatric 
disease consisting of unwanted, intrusive thoughts or mental images (obsessions) and 
repetitive behaviors or mental acts (compulsions) that are engaged to reduce discomfort 
created by obsessions. 
1 Natural course is chronic and has a first peak around puberty 
and another in early adulthood. 
2 While some studies suggested that age of onset is 
earlier in boys than in girls, 
3 other studies found comparable ages of onset. 
4 Symptoms 
affect ~1%-3% of young individuals, are time-consuming and significantly interfere 
with quality of life (QOL). 
4,5 In addition to OCD, up to 75% of young patients also </p>

<p>correspondence: anna coluccia 
Department of Medical sciences, 
surgery and Neurosciences, santa Maria 
alle scotte University hospital, Viale 
Bracci 16, 53100 siena, italy 
Tel +39 0577 58 6409 
Fax +39 0577 23 3222 
email coluccia@unisi.it </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 
24 February 2017 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>598 </p>

<p>coluccia et al </p>

<p>meet criteria for one or more comorbid disorders, with the 
most frequent being depressive disorders, anxiety disorders, 
attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and disrup-
tive behavior disorders. 
5,6 Moreover, many young people 
suffering from OCD experience difficult peer relationships 
and school difficulties and participate in fewer recreational 
activities than non-affected peers. </p>

<p>7,8   Following some authors, QOL can be defined as "the 
perception of the impact of disease on a variety of dimen-
sions including physical, mental, and social domains". </p>

<p>8   Investigating QOL in young individuals with OCD has 
some implications for assessment and treatment. For the 
clinician performing assessment, knowledge of the patient's 
perceptions of QOL provides important information as 
a subjective estimate of his/her overall functioning with 
regard to prognosis. 
8-10 In addition, targeting OCD symptoms 
without considering QOL of the patient may bias assessment 
as he/she may present with reduced symptoms that do not 
correspond to improved daily functioning. 
8-10 With regard 
to treatment, despite the substantial impairments in QOL 
associated with OCD, treatment outcome evaluations have 
focused almost exclusively on symptom reduction; however, 
focusing on symptom remission may not help the clinician 
to understand whether a clinically significant change has 
occurred. 
8-10 In line with these arguments, symptom improve-
ment observed on standardized measures did not always cor-
respond to clinically significant changes in real-world QOL 
and functioning. 
8-11 Moreover, other studies have shown that 
limited symptom gains were associated with significant QOL 
decreases, or not improved QOL at the end of treatment was 
associated with higher risk for relapse. </p>

<p>8-11   Studying patients' perceptions of QOL appears a relevant 
issue particularly for clinical practice with young individuals, 
as most of the literature indicated that OCD among children/ 
adolescents was mainly characterized by the absence of 
insight of symptoms and the associated impairment. 
5,6 Thus, 
OCD severity and QOL could not have a direct relation. In 
groups of individuals with OCD, some recent studies 
12 found 
that OCD severity was not significantly correlated with QOL. 
On the other hand, other studies 
13 showed that severity of 
obsessions significantly predicted perceived QOL, whereas 
severity of compulsions did not impact on QOL ratings. 
In contrast, a growing body of evidence showed that adult 
individuals with OCD experienced lower QOL relative to 
healthy controls and an inverse relation between QOL and 
OCD symptom severity, suggesting that individuals with less 
severe OCD had poorer QOL than those with more severe 
symptoms. </p>

<p>14,15   While a great body of data have been accumulated on 
QOL among adults, 
15 this topic among youth is under-
recognized and little empirical work has been conducted. </p>

<p>7,8   This aspect appears important as most of the studies indicated 
that the juvenile form of the disorder may present relevant 
clinical differences compared with the adult counterpart in 
terms of severity, comorbidities, insight of symptoms and 
treatment response. </p>

<p>6   Therefore, this systematic review and meta-analysis 
summarized available evidence looking for differences in 
global QOL outcomes between children/adolescents with 
OCD and screened healthy controls. In addition, specific 
QOL dimensions were examined, in particular social and 
school-related QOL. Finally, the effects of OCD symptom 
severity, sex and age were investigated. These variables were 
investigated as moderators, based on previous findings from 
the literature. Previous research on adults suggested that sex 
had a crucial role in moderating the effects of OCD on QOL; 
specifically, female sex was associated with lower QOL. </p>

<p>15   Other data on youth instead found that male individuals with 
OCD had more severe characteristics, including earlier age 
of onset and poorer QOL. 
16 With regard to age, inconsistent 
evidence has been found, with some studies showing differ-
ences in the clinical picture between children and adolescents 
and others not. </p>

<p>3,6   Methods 
eligibility criteria </p>

<p>Following a revised version of the PICOS method for 
observational case-control studies, defined in the PRISMA 
guidelines, 
17 criteria for inclusion of the studies involved the 
following characteristics: 1) characteristics of participants. 
Studies were included if participants were children or ado-
lescents with a primary diagnosis of OCD. Age range for 
children was defined as between 6 and 14 years, whereas ado-
lescence age range was considered as 15-18 years. Diagnosis 
had to be made through a semi-structured interview based 
on standardized diagnostic criteria, such as the Schedule 
for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia for school-age 
children -present and lifetime version (K-SADS-PL). 
18 Thus, 
studies on individuals with subclinical OCD symptoms were 
excluded. Studies were also excluded if they were conducted 
on individuals with the pediatric autoimmune neuropsy-
chiatric disorders associated with streptococcal infections 
(PANDAS), as there are some important clinical differences 
between OCD and this form of neurological condition. </p>

<p>19   Studies on primary compulsive hoarding were excluded, 
since this condition has been included as a separate diagnosis </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>599 </p>

<p>Quality of life in youth with OcD </p>

<p>in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-
fifth edition (DSM-5). 
1 2) Characteristics of outcomes. 
Studies were included if they used self-reported measures 
of global, social and school QOL outcomes with known 
psychometric properties. 3) Characteristics of comparators. 
Studies were included if they used healthy control groups 
consisting of screened participants who have not reported 
any lifetime psychiatric disorder during a clinical interview. 
4) Characteristics of design. Studies were included if they 
used an observational case-control design, where groups of 
individuals with a primary OCD diagnosis were compared 
with healthy control groups. </p>

<p>information sources and search 
procedure </p>

<p>Studies were retrieved through electronic systematic lit-
erature searches, in which keywords related to OCD 
("obsessive compulsive disorder", "obsessions", "compul-
sions", "rituals") were combined through the Boolean opera-
tor "AND" with keywords and text words indicative of the 
QOL construct ("quality of life", "psychological well-being", 
"satisfaction with life", "global functioning", "social func-
tioning", "family functioning", "subjective well-being"). The 
following online databases were searched: PubMed (January 
1966-January 2016), ScienceDirect (January 1966-January 
2016) and PsycINFO (January 1966-January 2016). </p>

<p>Process of selection of the studies </p>

<p>Studies were assessed on eligibility criteria by three indepen-
dent reviewers (FF, AP and AC) during three different stages. 
During the first and the second one, studies were examined 
with regard to inclusion criteria after the reading of the title 
and of the abstract, respectively. During these stages, studies 
were retained when there was no agreement on inclusion 
between the reviewers. Finally, the remaining studies were 
assessed on eligibility criteria after reading the full text of 
the article. At this stage, reasons for inclusion/exclusion and 
potential discrepancy in the judgment were addressed during 
meetings with a fourth independent reviewer (AF) to obtain 
complete agreement on included studies for meta-analysis. </p>

<p>Moderators coding </p>

<p>When inconsistency analyses indicated large and significant 
heterogeneity between the effect sizes, the role of mod-
erators was investigated. Two independent reviewers (FF 
and AP) coded the moderators, extracted the data from 
primary studies and inserted them in an excel worksheet. 
Subsequently, during meetings between the two reviewers, </p>

<p>insertion of the data in the worksheets was checked for 
accuracy, and each potential discrepancy was discussed and 
resolved with a third reviewer (AC). Discrepancy was found 
for coding of mean age and percentage of females/males 
for two studies. It was discussed by the two reviewers and 
resolved through the check of the papers by the third reviewer. 
The following variables were coded as moderators: 1) mean 
age of the sample; 2) sex of the sample, coded as percentage 
of female participants and 3) OCD symptom severity, coded 
as a continuous variable based on the scores on the Children's 
Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale (CY-BOCS). </p>

<p>20   Meta-analysis </p>

<p>Data extraction and summary measures </p>

<p>As we expected noticeable heterogeneity across the included 
studies, the effect sizes were calculated using random-effect 
models. Data requested for the calculation of the effect sizes 
were extracted independently by two meta-analysts (FF and 
AP) through the following formula: ES = M OCD − M CONTROL / 
SD POOLED , where M OCD was the mean of groups with OCD, 
M CONTROL was the mean of controls and SD POOLED was the 
pooled standard deviation. 
21 The effect sizes were weighted 
through the following correction: W zr =1/SE </p>

<p>2 
zr </p>

<p>, where SE </p>

<p>2 
zr </p>

<p>was the standard error of the effect size computed for each 
study. This formula was further corrected through the fol-
lowing formula for sampling error: W′ = W zr ⋅(α QOL )⋅(α OCD ), 
where α QOL was the Cronbach's coefficient 
22 as internal con-
sistency for the QOL measures and α OCD was the coefficient 
for OCD measures. Effect sizes were estimated using a 95% 
confidence interval (95% CI) and interpreted according to the 
criteria by Cohen. 
21 Thus, effect sizes of 0.80 or more were 
assumed to be large, 0.50 moderate and 0.20 small. A global 
effect size was calculated as a mean effect size obtained by 
combining effect sizes related to different QOL measures. 
For those studies using QOL measures related to different 
QOL domains (eg, social and school QOL), a mean effect 
size was calculated for each study as a global QOL outcome. 
Subsequently, effect sizes were computed separately for 
specific domains, social and school QOL, respectively. </p>

<p>inconsistency analysis </p>

<p>In order to assess between-studies heterogeneity, two com-
plementary indices are used, the I 
2 index and the Q-statistic, 
respectively. A value of I 
2 approximating to zero suggests 
homogeneity, whereas values of 25%-50%, 50%-75% and 
75%-100% represented low, medium and large heterogeneity, 
respectively. 
23 Given that inconsistency analysis suggested 
large heterogeneity, an analysis of the above-mentioned </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>coluccia et al </p>

<p>moderators was conducted through weighted least squares 
meta-regressions. </p>

<p>Publication bias </p>

<p>In order to investigate the likelihood that effect sizes were 
subjected to publication bias, the trim and fill procedure of 
Duval and Tweedie 
24 and the visual inspection of the funnel 
plot were used. The meta-analysis was performed using the 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Comprehensive Meta-analysis</rs> software, version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2.00</rs>. </p>

<p>Results 
selection and descriptive characteristics 
of the studies </p>

<p>The electronic search and the search through additional 
sources produced 1,067 records after the removal of 
duplicates. Of those studies, 1,005 were excluded at title 
or at abstract, as they were on irrelevant constructs. Thus, 
62 studies were screened at full text for inclusion. Of those 
studies, nine studies were excluded as they did not report suf-
ficient data to calculate effect sizes (eg, standard deviations), 
and the authors did not reply when they were contacted to 
request for necessary data. Two studies were excluded as 
they did not use measures of QOL. Twenty-three studies 
were excluded as they did not use a case-control design 
(eg, the study did not use a control group). Three studies 
were excluded as they did not use validated QOL measures. 
Two studies were excluded as they used participants with </p>

<p>lifetime OCD diagnosis. One study was excluded as it used 
participants with subclinical OCD symptoms. One study was 
excluded as it used participants with hoarding, and one study 
was excluded as it used the same data as those reported in a 
study already included in the meta-analysis. Sixteen studies 
were excluded since they were conducted on adult samples. 
After this selection, five studies were included in both 
qualitative and quantitative synthesis (n=543, 17 effect sizes 
overall) by consensus of the three independent assessors. The 
flowchart of the selection process is provided in Figure 1. 
All the included studies compared QOL outcomes of 
patients with OCD and screened healthy participants as 
controls. Participants in the OCD groups were outpatients in 
all the studies. Three studies were conducted in the United 
States, 
6,25,26 one in Brazil, 
27 and one in Argentina. 
28 Total </p>

<p>sample sizes ranged from 51 to 225 participants. One study 
was conducted on adolescents 
27 and four on children. </p>

<p>6,25,26,28 </p>

<p>Mean percentage of females was 51.70 ranging from 
44.60 in the study of Geller et al 
6 to 66.20 in the study of </p>

<p>Sousa Vivan et al. 
27 With regard to comorbidities, in the study </p>

<p>of Borda et al, 
28 psychiatric comorbidity included dysthymia </p>

<p>(10% of the clinical group), specific phobias (10%), separation 
anxiety (10%), panic disorder with agoraphobia (4%), eating 
disorders (10%) and selective mutism (4%). In the study of 
Sukhodolsky et al, 
26 56 individuals had OCD and 43 had OCD </p>

<p>with comorbid ADHD. In the study of Sukhodolsky et al, </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>• 
• 
• 
• 
• 
• </p>

<p>Figure 1 PRISMA flowchart of the selection process of the studies. 
Abbreviation: OcD, obsessive-compulsive disorder. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>601 </p>

<p>Quality of life in youth with OcD </p>

<p>41% had comorbid Tourette's disorder, 28% had comorbid 
depression, 41% had comorbid anxiety disorders and 13% 
had comorbid oppositional defiant disorder. In the study of 
Kim et al, 
25 ~45% had a comorbid generalized anxiety dis-
order, 8% had comorbid social anxiety disorder, 12% had 
specific phobias, 8% had separation anxiety disorder, 4% had 
an anxiety disorder not otherwise specified, 8% had major 
depression, 4% had dysthymia, 33% had ADHD, 8% had 
Tourette's disorder, 12% had oppositional defiant disorder 
and 4% had agoraphobia. 
Two studies 
6,27 did not report data on comorbidities. Three 
studies reported scores on the CY-BOCS: mean score was 
18.53 ranging from 11.60 in the study of Sukhodolsky et al </p>

<p>26   to 22.90 in the study of Borda et al. </p>

<p>28   In the study of Borda et al, 
28 OCD subtypes were reported. 
The most frequent obsessions included somatic (43%), 
contamination (39%), aggressive (30%), symmetry (26%), 
religious (9%) and sexual obsessions (4%); 48% also reported 
a variety of additional miscellaneous obsessions (ie, need 
to know and remember, fear of saying certain things, fear 
of not saying the right thing, intrusive images and intrusive 
sounds, words or music). Similarly, a range of compulsions 
were reported, including cleaning (52%), repeating (52%), 
ordering (43%), checking (35%), counting (22%) and other 
mental compulsions (13%); 25% also reported a variety of 
additional miscellaneous compulsions (ie, excessive list 
utilization, superstitious behaviors). 
Only one study reported whether the participants in 
the OCD groups were on medication. 
26 Two studies used 
patient-reported measures of QOL, 
27,28 whereas three used 
parent-reported measures. 
6,25,26 Publication date ranged from 
1996 to 2014. Characteristics for each of the included studies 
are presented in Table 1. </p>

<p>comparison on global QOl between 
individuals with OcD and controls </p>

<p>This analysis included five studies (n=543). Results showed a 
large effect size (d=−1.16, SE =0.32, 95% CI: −1.79 to 0.54, 
P,0.001), suggesting that patients with OCD had signifi-
cantly lower scores on global QOL outcomes compared with 
controls. A large and significant heterogeneity was found 
(I 
2 =89.07, Q (4) =36.61, P,0.001). The forest plot with study 
and mean effect sizes is presented in Figure 2. 
Evidence for a publication bias was not found since the effect 
size did not change when it was adjusted for publication bias 
(d =−1.16; 95% CI: −1.78 to 0.54; number of trimmed studies =0). 
Funnel plot of publication bias is presented in Figure 3. </p>

<p>analysis of moderators </p>

<p>Since significant heterogeneity was found across effect 
sizes of the studies on global QOL, age, sex and OCD symp-
tom severity were assessed as moderators. OCD symptom 
severity resulted to be negatively correlated with effect sizes 
(β=−0.02, SE =0.01, 95% CI: −0.05 to 0.001, P,0.05), sug-
gesting that for samples with more severe OCD symptoms, 
global QOL of patients was significantly lower than that for 
samples of controls. Meta-regression of global QOL as a 
function of OCD severity is presented in Figure 4. 
Age was not correlated with effect sizes (β=0.001, 
SE =0.02, 95% CI: −0.03 to 0.03, P=0.99). Meta-regression 
of global QOL as a function of age is presented in Figure 5. 
Sex was correlated with effect sizes (β=0.02, SE =0.01, 
95% CI: 0.01-0.02, P,0.001), suggesting that for samples 
with higher percentages of males, global QOL of patients 
with OCD was significantly higher. Meta-regression of 
global QOL as a function of sex is presented in Figure 6. A 
summary of analysis of moderators is presented in Table 2. </p>

<p>comparison on social QOl between 
patients with OcD and controls </p>

<p>This analysis included four studies (n=490). Results showed 
a moderate effect size (d=−0.54, SE =0.15, 95% CI: −0.85 
to 0.23, P,0.01), suggesting that patients with OCD had 
significantly lower scores on social QOL compared with 
controls. Evidence for heterogeneity was not found (I </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=56.51, 
Q (3) =6.89, P=0.08). The forest plot with study and mean 
effect sizes is presented in Figure 7. Evidence for a publica-
tion bias was not found since the effect size did not change 
when it was adjusted for publication bias (d=−0.54; 95% 
CI: −0.84 to 0.23; number of trimmed studies =0). Funnel 
plot is presented in Figure 8. </p>

<p>comparison on QOl related to school 
functioning between patients with OcD 
and controls </p>

<p>This analysis included three studies (n=265). Results showed 
a moderate effect size (d=−0.61, SE =0.13, 95% CI: −0.87 to 
0.36, P,0.01), suggesting that patients with OCD had sig-
nificantly lower scores on school QOL outcomes compared 
with controls. Evidence for heterogeneity was not found 
(I 
2 =1.89, Q (2) =2.04, P=0.36). The forest plot is presented in 
Figure 9. Evidence for a publication bias was not found since 
the effect size did not change when adjusted for publication 
bias (d =−0.61; 95% CI: −0.87 to 0.36; number of trimmed 
studies =0). Funnel plot of publication bias is presented in </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>602 </p>

<p>coluccia et al </p>

<p>Table 1 characteristics of the studies included in the meta-analysis (n=5) </p>

<p>Study 
name </p>

<p>Publication </p>

<p>date 
Country Cohort 
(age range) 
Recruitment strategies of OCD patients </p>

<p>Recruitment strategies </p>

<p>of controls </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>Instruments used to </p>

<p>make OCD diagnoses </p>

<p>QOL outcomes </p>

<p>Borda et al </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>2013 
argentina children 
subjects recruited from several sources (eg, primary </p>

<p>care physicians, mental health professionals) </p>

<p>subjects recruited from 
local private schools </p>

<p>OcD patients 
(n=23) 
controls (n=30) </p>

<p>aDis-cV </p>

<p>PQl </p>

<p>geller et al </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>2001 </p>

<p>Usa </p>

<p>children 
all patients referred for clinical evaluation to the 
combined Massachusetts general and Mclean 
hospital pediatric psychopharmacology clinic since 
1991, as well as those participating in federally 
funded research studies of familial factors in pediatric 
OcD, prospective course of tic disorders or aDhD </p>

<p>subjects were recruited 
from general regional 
pediatric clinics </p>

<p>OcD patients 
(n=33) 
controls (n=32) 
DsM-iV (K-saDs) </p>

<p>cBcl </p>

<p>Kim et al </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>Usa </p>

<p>children 
(6-15 years) 
From a childhood anxiety specialty clinic for 
assessment and treatment services </p>

<p>subjects were 
recruited through local 
advertisements for a </p>

<p>research protocol including 
healthy participants </p>

<p>OcD patients 
(n=33) 
controls (n=18) 
DsM-iV (aDis-cP) </p>

<p>cBcl </p>

<p>sousa Vivan </p>

<p>et al </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>2014 </p>

<p>Brazil </p>

<p>adolescents </p>

<p>(14-18 years) 
Participants were recruited from an epidemiological study conducted at high </p>

<p>schools in the city of Porto alegre, southern Brazil </p>

<p>OcD patients 
(n=75) 
controls (n=150) 
DsM-iV (K-saDs) </p>

<p>WhOQOl-BreF </p>

<p>sukhodolsky </p>

<p>et al </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>2005 </p>

<p>Usa </p>

<p>children and 
adolescents 
Patients participating in studies conducted at the 
Yale child study center </p>

<p>subjects randomly selected </p>

<p>on a telemarketing list </p>

<p>OcD patients 
(n=56) 
controls (n=93) 
DsM-iV (K-saDs) </p>

<p>cBcl </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ADHD, attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder; ADIS-CP, Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for Children and Parents; ADIS-CV, Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule -Child Version; CBCL, Child Behavior </p>

<p>Checklist; DSM-IV, Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-fourth 
edition; K-SADS, Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia for school-age children; OCD, obsessive-compulsive disorder; PQL, Pediatric Quality of </p>

<p>Life Inventory -Child Report; QOL, quality of life; WHOQOL-BREF, World Health Organization Quality of Life Instrument. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>603 </p>

<p>Quality of life in youth with OcD </p>

<p>Figure 2 Forest plot of the comparison on global QOl between individuals with OcD and controls. 
Abbreviations: QOL, quality of life; OCD, obsessive-compulsive disorder; Std diff, standard difference; CI, confidence interval; PQL, Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory -
child report. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Funnel plot of effect sizes for the comparisons on global QOl. 
Abbreviations: QOL, quality of life; Std diff, standard difference. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Meta-regression of global QOl as a function of OcD severity. 
Abbreviations: QOL, quality of life; OCD, obsessive-compulsive disorder; Std diff, standard difference; Y-BOCS, Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>604 </p>

<p>coluccia et al </p>

<p>Figure 5 Meta-regression of global QOl as a function of age. 
Abbreviations: QOL, quality of life; Std diff, standard difference. </p>

<p>Figure 6 Meta-regression of global QOl as a function of sex. 
Abbreviations: QOL, quality of life; Std diff, standard difference. </p>

<p>Figure 10. A summary of effect sizes for all the analyses is 
presented in Table 3. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>QOL in children and adolescents with OCD is an under-
studied topic. Investigating QOL is an important issue for 
assessment and treatment, as the patient may present with 
reduced symptoms that do not necessarily translate into 
better QOL. Knowledge about QOL dimensions among 
children and adolescents suffering from this disorder can 
inform practice and research about the use of QOL outcomes 
in trials of pharmacotherapy and psychotherapy. 
8 This study </p>

<p>was the first meta-analysis summarizing differences in 
QOL among children/adolescents with OCD and controls, 
specifically in global, social and school-related QOL dimen-
sions. After an electronic search, five case-control studies 
were included with 543 participants. Findings indicated a 
large effect size without publication bias, suggesting that 
individuals with OCD had significantly lower global QOL 
than controls. In addition, moderate effect sizes were also 
observed for social and school-related QOL. Subsequently, 
analyses of moderators showed a negative relation between 
OCD severity and effect sizes, highlighting that for samples 
with more severe OCD symptoms, QOL was lower than </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>605 </p>

<p>Quality of life in youth with OcD </p>

<p>Table 2 summary of moderators' analysis of effect sizes on 
global QOl </p>

<p>Moderators 
β (P-value) 
95% CI </p>

<p>OcD severity (cY-BOcs scores) 
−0.02 (,0.05) 
−0.05 to 0.001 
age (years) 
0.01 (0.99) 
−0.03 to 0.03 
sex 
0.02 (,0.001) 
0.02 to 0.01 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; CY-BOCS, Children's Yale Brown Obsessive 
Compulsive Scale; OCD, obsessive-compulsive disorder; QOL, quality of life. </p>

<p>Figure 7 Forest plot of the comparisons on social QOl between individuals with OcD and controls. 
Abbreviations: QOL, quality of life; OCD, obsessive-compulsive disorder; Std diff, standard difference; CI, confidence interval; CBCL, Child Behavior Checklist; WHOQOL-
BreF, World health Organization Quality of life instrument. </p>

<p>randomized controlled trials 
30 showed that CBT with parents' 
involvement, where exposure and response prevention are 
enhanced by a parent, can be effective for reducing child/ 
adolescent OCD. 
Sex could have a crucial role in moderating the effects 
of OCD on QOL. Current findings showed that male 
sex was associated with lower QOL. These data were 
in contrast with that found previously on adults, which 
suggested that female sex was associated with lower 
QOL. 
11 A possible explanation for this difference could 
be related to other studies on youth, which instead found 
that among individuals with OCD, males had more severe 
characteristics, including earlier age of onset. 
13 It could be 
hypothesized that differences in QOL between males and 
females corresponded to differences in the clinical picture 
of OCD symptoms. 
With regard to age, the relation with effect sizes was not 
significant. The findings of this study summarized data on 
this relation, as previous data were inconsistent: some studies 
reported differences in the clinical picture, including severity 
and QOL impairment, between children and adolescents and 
others not. 
4,12 Moreover, according to other previous studies, 
young individuals with older age had more comorbid mood 
disorders, 
26 whereas other studies showed that younger 
individuals had stronger separation anxiety and tic disorders 
than the older ones. 
17 The absence of a relation between QOL 
and age found in the present meta-analysis was in line with 
the current literature, indicating that symptom patterns do not 
change across children and adolescents groups. </p>

<p>4   Finally, some important limitations should be consid-
ered. First, the small number of included studies highlighted 
that the topic is still under-studied. The low number of 
studies was a main limitation that leads to low statistical 
power in the analyses, particularly when moderators were </p>

<p>that of controls. This result was in contrast with some 
previous knowledge in the literature indicating that OCD 
among children/adolescents is typically characterized by 
the absence of insight of symptoms and the associated 
impairment. 
7 Results of the previous study of De Caluwé 
and De Clercq 
7 indicated that OCD symptoms were not a 
significant predictor of QOL when impairment was included 
in the regression model. This inconsistency with our findings 
could be attributed to the fact that the study of De Caluwé 
and De Clercq 
7 did not use a case-control design, instead 
investigated the role of OCD symptoms and impairment as 
predictors of QOL in a large sample of community youth 
with OCD without including a clinical group. Another 
explanation could be the use of a father-rated measure of 
QOL and new measure of OCD symptoms in that study, 
7 the 
Youth Obsessive-Compulsive Symptoms Scale (YOCSS), </p>

<p>29   a self-report scale assessing both youth OCD symptoma-
tology and OCD impairment. In addition, these findings 
were not consistent with research data on adults, which 
showed that QOL was lower among individuals with less 
severe OCD. 
11 This finding pointed out the introduction of 
strategies to improve QOL for young individuals with more 
severe symptoms along with treatments focusing on the 
reduction of symptomatology. For example, family-based 
cognitive behavioral therapy could be treatment strategy able 
to improve also family QOL and functioning. Some recent </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>606 </p>

<p>coluccia et al </p>

<p>Figure 9 Forest plot of the comparisons on school QOl between individuals with OcD and controls. 
Abbreviations: QOL, quality of life; OCD, obsessive-compulsive disorder; Std diff, standard difference; CI, confidence interval; CBCL, Child Behavior Checklist. </p>

<p>Figure 10 Funnel plot of the effect sizes on school QOl. 
Abbreviations: QOL, quality of life; Std diff, standard difference. </p>

<p>Figure 8 Funnel plot of effect sizes of comparisons on social QOl. 
Abbreviations: QOL, quality of life; Std diff, standard difference. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>607 </p>

<p>Quality of life in youth with OcD </p>

<p>Table 3 Summary of effect sizes comparing children/adolescents with OCD with controls on QOL </p>

<p>Comparisons 
Outcomes 
k 
n 
d (P-value) 
95% CI 
Q (P-value) 
I </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Evidence of 
publication bias </p>

<p>Children/adolescent patients 
with OcD and controls </p>

<p>global QOl 
5 
543 
−1.17 (,0.001) 
−1.79 to 0.54 
36.61 (,0.001) 
89.07 
Not found </p>

<p>Children/adolescent patients 
with OcD and controls </p>

<p>social QOl 
4 
490 
−0.54 (,0.01) 
−0.85 to 0.23 
6.89 (0.08) 
56.51 
Not found </p>

<p>Children/adolescent patients 
with OcD and controls </p>

<p>QOl related to 
school functioning </p>

<p>3 
265 
−0.61 (,0.01) 
−0.87 to 0.36 
2.04 (0.36) 
1.89 
Not found </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; OCD, obsessive-compulsive disorder; QOL, quality of life. </p>

<p>tested. Consequently, the findings of this study were on 
preliminary evidence and suggested further studies. In this 
meta-analysis, studies comparing individuals with OCD and 
those with other psychiatric disorders were not included. 
It could be argued that the effects of OCD on QOL were 
not specific; instead, it could be attributable to a general 
effect of having psychopathological features. Otherwise, it 
could be interesting to evaluate whether specific domains 
of QOL are impaired among individuals with OCD relative 
to individuals presenting with other psychiatric diagno-
ses. Thus, further studies are required investigating QOL 
dimensions affected in OCD relative to other psychiatric 
disorders, such as schizophrenia and bipolar disorders. In 
addition, most of the studies did not report information 
about other important variables, which could be related to 
QOL in OCD, such as insight, OCD symptoms duration 
and family accommodation. 
10 Therefore, further studies 
investigating the role of these variables appear necessary. 
Since this meta-analysis included only case-control stud-
ies, future prospective studies are required to investigate 
whether these clinical variables could affect QOL outcomes 
over time. Another limitation was the use of parent-and 
patient-reported measures due to the low number of studies 
using only patient-reported measures. Thus, additional stud-
ies are required using patient-reported measures of QOL. 
Additional limitations concerned that other QOL outcomes, 
such as emotional QOL and QOL related to family function-
ing, were not included due a lack of studies investigating 
these aspects. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Preliminary findings from this meta-analysis encouraged 
researchers and clinicians to consider more carefully QOL 
dimensions and target them particularly for young males 
suffering from more severe OCD symptoms. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>