<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5039120" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: We investigated the association between socioeconomic status (SES) and cancer screening in a Kore-
an population aged 40 years or older. 
Methods: This cross-sectional study included 12,303 participants (5,284 men and 7,019 women) who participated 
in the 2010-2012 Korean National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey. Self-reported questionnaires were 
used to assess participant's SES (household income, occupational, and educational status) and cancer screening 
behavior. 
Results: Compared to the lowest household income group, the odds ratios (ORs) (95% confidence intervals [CIs]) 
for overall cancer screening of the highest income group were 2.113 (1.606-2.781) in men and 1.476 (1.157-1.883) 
in women; those for private cancer screening of the highest income group were 2.446 (1.800-3.324) in men and 
2.630 (2.050-3.373) in women, while those for National Cancer Screening Programs (NCSP) in the highest income 
group were 1.076 (0.805-1.439) in men and 0.492 (0.388-0.623) in women. Compared to manual workers, ORs (95% 
CIs) for private cancer screening of office workers were 1.300 (1.018-1.660) in men and 0.822 (0.616-1.098) in wom-
en. In comparison to the least educated men, OR (95% CI) for private cancer screening of the most educated men 
was statistically significant (1.530 [1.117-2.095]). 
Conclusion: Higher economic status was associated with higher rates of overall and private cancer screening in 
both sexes and a lower rate of NCSP in women. Male office workers and more educated individuals underwent pri-
vate cancer screening at a higher rate than manual workers and less educated individuals, respectively. </p>

<p>In South Korea, malignant neoplasm is a leading cause of death and its </p>

<p>incidence has steadily increased over a number of years. According to </p>

<p>the annual report on the causes of death from Statistics Korea, an over-</p>

<p>whelming majority of the Korean patients who died from malignant </p>

<p>neoplasm in 2013 were over 40 years of age. 
1) The age-standardized </p>

<p>cancer incidence rates per 100,000 were 343.6 in men and 316.7 in </p>

<p>women, which are similar to or higher than those of other developed </p>

<p>countries (USA, 347.0 in men and 297.4 in women; UK, 284.0 in men </p>

<p>and 267.3 in women; Japan, 260.4 in men and 185.7 in women) and </p>

<p>are steadily growing. 
1,2) Although the best choice to reduce cancer </p>

<p>mortality is prevention, the second best option appears to be detection </p>

<p>of cancer at an early stage. South Korea has National Cancer Screening </p>

<p>Programs (NCSP) that have been operating since 1999 and have pro-</p>

<p>vided a targeted population with free screening for five common can-</p>

<p>cers in Korea, including stomach, liver, colorectum, breast, and uterine </p>

<p>cervix, every two years. </p>

<p>Socioeconomic status (SES) is associated with various types of can-</p>

<p>cer incidence and morbidities/mortalities, including cancer-related </p>

<p>problems. 
3) In addition, it appears that SES affects health behaviors </p>

<p>such as alcohol consumption, physical activity, cigarette-smoking, and </p>

<p>dietary patterns, which are closely related to cancer development and </p>

<p>outcomes. 
3-5) Socioeconomic deprivation results in reduced access to </p>

<p>healthcare, which is a barrier to early detection of cancer and, thus, to </p>

<p>better outcomes. 
6) Individuals with a low SES seem to be more suscep-</p>

<p>tible to exposure to unhealthy foods, such as high-calorie but poor-nu-</p>

<p>trition foods. Unhealthy environments play an important role in the </p>

<p>development and progression of serious diseases such as malignant </p>

<p>neoplasm, resulting in poor prognosis. </p>

<p>Identifying an association between SES and participation in cancer </p>

<p>screening can be helpful for developing a health policy and distribut-</p>

<p>ing limited public health resources fairly and efficiently. The aim of </p>

<p>this study was to investigate the association of SES (household income, </p>

<p>occupational, and educational status) with cancer screening in a Kore-</p>

<p>an population over 40 years in age, after accounting for age and other </p>

<p>confounding factors. In addition, we examined the relation of each </p>

<p>SES to participation in private cancer screening and NCSP. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>1. Study Population </p>

<p>The Korean Ministry of Health and Welfare periodically conducts the </p>

<p>Korean National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey </p>

<p>(KNHANES), which is a nationwide survey representing the entire Ko-</p>

<p>rean population. This survey includes comprehensive information on </p>

<p>health status, health behavior, socioeconomic demographics, and lab-</p>

<p>oratory test results. Households were selected as the sampling units </p>

<p>based on a stratified, multistage, probability-sampling design accord-</p>

<p>ing to age, sex, and geographic area. Participants were asked to com-</p>

<p>plete four types of questionnaires which are composed of a health in-</p>

<p>terview, health behavior, health examination, and nutrition. Trained </p>

<p>interviewers performed face-to-face health interviews at participants' </p>

<p>houses. Citizens could refuse to participate in this survey according to </p>

<p>the National Health Enhancement Act. Written informed consent was </p>

<p>provided by participants. For further research, the Korea Centers for </p>

<p>Disease Control and Prevention acquired participants' consent to use </p>

<p>blood samples obtained during the health interview survey. Trained </p>

<p>staff followed standardized steps to conduct the unified procedures. </p>

<p>Body weight and height were measured to the nearest 0.1 kg and 0.1 </p>

<p>cm, respectively, while participants wore light indoor clothes without </p>

<p>shoes. Body mass index (BMI) was calculated as the ratio of weight in </p>

<p>kilograms to squared height in meters (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). </p>

<p>This study was based on data from 19,599 adults from the 2010-2012 </p>

<p>KNHANES. We excluded participants younger than 40 years, those </p>

<p>who did not have data regarding socioeconomic variables such as </p>

<p>household income, occupation, education, and marital status, and </p>

<p>those who did not have information regarding cancer screening. After </p>

<p>these exclusions, 12,303 participants (5,284 men and 7,019 women) </p>

<p>were included in the final analysis. The Institutional Review Board of </p>

<p>the Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention approved this </p>

<p>study. </p>

<p>2. Definition of Socioeconomic Variables, Health Check-up, 
and Cancer Screening </p>

<p>Information on SES and health-related behaviors was obtained from </p>

<p>the self-reported questionnaire answers during the interview for the </p>

<p>relevant survey period. Participants answered an open-ended ques-</p>

<p>tionnaire, "What is your average monthly household income including </p>

<p>salaries, property income, pension, government subsidies, and allow-</p>

<p>ance?" The ministry of health and welfare classified individuals into </p>

<p>four groups (lowest, middle-lowest, middle-highest, and highest) ac-</p>

<p>cording to monthly household income. Occupational status was cate-</p>

<p>gorized into three groups: manual workers (clerk, service and sales </p>

<p>workers, skilled agricultural, forestry, and fishery workers, persons </p>

<p>who operate or assemble craft, equipment, or machines, and elemen-</p>

<p>tary workers), office workers (general managers, government adminis-</p>

<p>trators, professionals, and simple office worker), and others (unem-</p>

<p>ployed persons, housekeepers, and students). Educational status was </p>

<p>classified according to duration into less than 6 years, 6-&lt;9 years, </p>

<p>9-&lt;12 years, and ≥12 years. </p>

<p>Participants answered the following question about cancer screen-</p>

<p>ing, "Have you undergone cancer screening within the last two years?" </p>

<p>The participants who answered "yes" were further questioned about </p>

<p>the type of cancer screening. Cancer screening was re-categorized into </p>

<p>private cancer screening or NCSP. Private cancer screening included </p>

<p>cancer screening paid for by examinees at healthcare units including </p>

<p>private general hospitals, health check-up centers, and public health-</p>

<p>care center under the Korean National Health Insurance Corporation. </p>

<p>NCSP was defined as cancer screening that was performed without </p>

<p>payment by the examinee and the entire cost was covered by National </p>

<p>Health Insurance. </p>

<p>Jin-Young Kim, et al. • Socioeconomic Status and Cancer Screening </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4082/kjfm.2016.37.5.287 </p>

<p>www.kjfm.or.kr </p>



<p>Individuals who engaged in vigorous-intensity physical activity at </p>

<p>least three days per week or moderate-intensity physical activity in-</p>

<p>cluding walking at least five days per week were defined as the regular </p>

<p>exercise group. The Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT) </p>

<p>was used to assess alcohol-drinking status. Individuals who smoked </p>

<p>cigarettes during the relevant survey period were categorized as cur-</p>

<p>rent smokers. Daily calorie intake was monitored via 24-hour food re-</p>

<p>call and analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">CAN-Pro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 3.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Korean Nutrition Society</rs>, Seoul, Korea). Marital status was classified into three groups: </p>

<p>married and not separated, those who had married and lived with </p>

<p>their spouse; single, those who were not married, those who were </p>

<p>married but separated, widows/widowers, and divorcees; and non-re-</p>

<p>sponders, those who did not respond. </p>

<p>3. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>To represent the general Korean population with minimal bias, sam-</p>

<p>pling weights were applied to account for complex sampling. All data </p>

<p>from continuous variables such as age, BMI, daily calorie intake, </p>

<p>household income, and AUDIT are presented as the mean and stan-</p>

<p>dard errors (SEs), which were calculated using a complex samples </p>

<p>plan for descriptive analysis. Data from categorical variables such as </p>

<p>smoking status, physical activity, SES (income, occupational, and edu-</p>

<p>cational status), marital status, and cancer screening are presented as </p>

<p>the percentage and SEs. Chi-square tests were used to compare per-</p>

<p>centages for cancer screening within two years according to SES. The </p>

<p>odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CIs) for cancer </p>

<p>screening participation within two years were calculated using weight-</p>

<p>ed multivariate logistic regression analyses after adjustment for age, </p>

<p>each SES, and other covariates. <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> statistical software <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">ver. 9.4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS In-stitute Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC, USA) was used to conduct statistical analyses. All </p>

<p>statistical tests were two-tailed and P-value &lt;0.05 was considered to be </p>

<p>statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The characteristics of the study participants are summarized in Table </p>

<p>1. The mean age was 54.8 years for men and 56.6 years for women. The </p>

<p>participation rate for overall, private cancer screening, and NCSP </p>

<p>within 2 years was 56.6%, 30.5%, and 27.0%, respectively, in men and </p>

<p>66.0%, 39.3%, and 30.3%, respectively, in women. </p>

<p>Figures 1-3 show the percentage of participants who underwent </p>

<p>cancer screening within two years, according to SES. The highest in-</p>

<p>come groups showed the highest percentage of overall cancer screen-</p>

<p>ing in both sexes (63.8% in men and 74.0% in women). Also, the high </p>

<p>income groups underwent the highest percentage of private cancer </p>

<p>screening in both sexes (39.2% in men and 52.7% in women) and the </p>

<p>lowest rate of NCSP (24.3% in men and 23.8% in women) (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Office workers underwent overall and private cancer screening at the </p>

<p>highest frequency for men and women (61.4% and 73.3% of overall </p>

<p>cancer screening, 37.2% and 45.2% of private cancer screening) (Figure </p>

<p>2). Also, the most educated group had the highest participation rate for </p>

<p>Table 1. Subject characteristics </p>

<p>Variable 
Men 
Women </p>

<p>Unweighted no. 
5,284 
7,019 
Age (y) 
54.8±0.2 
56.6±0.2 
Body mass index (kg/m 
2 ) 
24.1±0.1 
24.1±0.1 
Daily calorie intake (kcal) 
2,354±19 
1,649±12 
Household income (USD)* 
4,591±179 
3,997±141 
Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test 
9.79±0.15 
3.04±0.07 
Current smoker (%) 
41.6±0.9 
5.1±0.4 
Regular physical activity (%) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>52.8±0.9 
48.6±0.8 
Occupation (%) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Manual workers 
55.7±1.0 
41.1±0.9 
Office workers 
24.1±0.9 
9.6±0.5 
Others 
20.2±0.7 
49.3±0.8 
Education duration (%) 
&lt;6 y 
20.7±0.8 
40.7±0.9 
6-&lt;9 y 
15.7±0.7 
15.2±0.6 
9-&lt;12 y 
35.4±0.9 
29.9±0.8 
≥12 y 
28.1±1.0 
14.2±0.7 
Marital status (%) </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>Single 
5.9±0.4 
22.8±0.7 
Married and not separated 
90.5±0.6 
76.0±0.7 
Non-responders 
3.6±0.4 
1.2±0.2 
Overall cancer screening within 2 years (%) 
56.6±0.9 
66.0±0.8 
Private cancer screening (%) 
30.5±0.9 
39.3±0.8 
National Cancer Screening Programs (%) 
27.0±0.8 
30.3±0.8 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard error for continuous variables or 
percentage±standard error for categorical variables. 
*1 USD=1,000 Korean won. 
 † Vigorous-intensity activity ≥3 days/wk, moderate-
intensity activity including walking ≥5 days/wk. 
 ‡ Office workers (general managers, 
government administrators, professionals, and simple office worker), manual workers 
(clerk, service and sales workers, skilled agricultural, forestry, and fishery workers, 
persons who operate or assemble craft, equipment, or machines, and elementary 
workers), others (unemployed persons, housekeepers, and students). 
 § Married and 
not separated (individuals who had married and lived with their spouse, single 
(individuals who were not married, those who were married but separated, widows/ 
widowers, and divorcees), and non-responders. </p>

<p>Men 
Women </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>National Cancer 
Screening Programs </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Lowest 
Middle-lowest 
Middle-highest 
Highest </p>

<p>Men 
Women 
Men 
Women 
Private cancer 
screening </p>

<p>Overall cancer 
screening </p>

<p>46.7 54.4 57.6 63.8 
56.4 64.7 68.8 74.0 </p>

<p>19.3 26.3 32.6 39.2 
24.1 36.6 44.2 52.7 </p>

<p>29.0 29.1 
26.6 
24.3 </p>

<p>35.8 </p>

<p>31.7 
29.6 </p>

<p>23.8 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P=0.062 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Percentage of cancer screening within two years according to monthly 
household income. The P-values among monthly household income categories 
(lowest, middle-lowest, middle-highest, and highest group) were determined using 
chi-square test after weighting. </p>

<p>Jin-Young Kim, et al. • Socioeconomic Status and Cancer Screening </p>

<p>
http://dx.doi.org/10.4082/kjfm.2016.37.5.287 </p>

<p>overall and private cancer screening (60.4% in men and 71.8% in </p>

<p>women for overall cancer screening, 36.9% in men and 48.0% in wom-</p>

<p>en for private cancer screening) (Figure 3). </p>

<p>In Table 2, we show the results of multivariate logistic regression for </p>

<p>overall cancer screening after adjusting for age, BMI, daily calorie in-</p>

<p>take, smoking status, AUDIT score, physical activity, and marital status </p>

<p>in addition to each SES including household income, occupational, </p>

<p>and educational status. Compared to the lowest household income </p>

<p>group, ORs (95% CIs) for overall cancer screening of the highest house-</p>

<p>hold income group were 2.113 (1.606-2.781) in men and 1.476 (1.157-</p>

<p>1.883) in women. Compared to manual workers, ORs (95% CIs) of of-</p>

<p>fice workers were not significant for either sex (1.248 [0.982-1.586] in </p>

<p>men and 1.041 [0.750-1.447] in women); ORs (95% CIs) of more edu-</p>

<p>cated groups were also not statistically significant. </p>

<p>In order to further investigate the association between SES and can-</p>

<p>cer screening type, logistic regression analyses were performed after </p>

<p>stratifying private cancer screening and NCSP in Table 3. Compared to </p>

<p>the lowest income group, ORs for private cancer screening of the high-</p>

<p>est income group were statistically higher (2.446 [1.800-3.324] in men </p>

<p>and 2.630 [2.050-3.373] in women), while those for NCSP of women in </p>

<p>the higher household income group were lower (0.735 [0.592-0.911] in </p>

<p>middle-lowest group, 0.619 [0.491-0.781] in middle-highest group, and </p>

<p>0.492 [0.388-0.623] in the highest group). Compared to manual work-</p>

<p>ers, ORs (95% CIs) for private cancer screening of office workers were </p>

<p>1.300 (1.018-1.660) in men and 0.822 (0.616-1.098) in women, while </p>

<p>those for NCSP were not significant. Like occupational status, ORs for </p>

<p>private cancer screening were statistically significant in the most edu-</p>

<p>cated men (1.530 [1.117-2.095]), while ORs for NCSP did not vary be-</p>

<p>tween sexes. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The major findings in this study are that both males and females with </p>

<p>higher household income appear to be more likely to undergo cancer </p>

<p>screening from a nationally representative sample, after controlling for </p>

<p>age, BMI, smoking status, AUDIT score, physical activity, marital sta-</p>

<p>tus, and occupational and education status. In particular, men and </p>

<p>women with higher income had higher odds of partaking in private </p>

<p>Men 
Women </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>National Cancer 
Screening Programs </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Men 
Women 
Men 
Women 
Private cancer 
screening </p>

<p>Overall cancer 
screening </p>

<p>Manual workers 
Office workers 
Others </p>

<p>56.0 61.4 
52.6 </p>

<p>67.3 73.3 </p>

<p>63.4 </p>

<p>29.3 37.2 </p>

<p>25.7 </p>

<p>38.1 45.2 
39.1 </p>

<p>28.4 
29.1 
33.2 
30.6 
27.8 </p>

<p>P=0.002 </p>

<p>22.0 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P=0.036 </p>

<p>P=0.001 </p>

<p>P=0.001 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Percentage of cancer screening within two years according to occupational 
status. The P-values among occupational categories (manual workers, office 
workers, and others) were determined using chi-square test after weighting. </p>

<p>Men 
Women </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>National Cancer 
Screening Programs </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>&lt;6 years 
6 &lt;9 years 
9 &lt;12 years 
&gt;12 years </p>

<p>Men 
Women 
Men 
Women 
Private cancer 
screening </p>

<p>Overall cancer 
screening </p>

<p>53.6 58.4 
54.6 60.4 
58.7 </p>

<p>71.7 71.8 </p>

<p>22.3 32.7 
29.1 36.9 
29.1 44.9 46.1 48.0 </p>

<p>20.7 15.7 35.4 28.1 </p>

<p>33.1 27.9 30.0 25.2 </p>

<p>P=0.017 </p>

<p>68.5 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 
P=0.001 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Percentage of cancer screening within two years according to educational 
status. The P-values for educational categories (&lt;6 years, 6-&lt;9 years, 9-&lt;12 
years, and ≥12 years) were determined using chi-square test after weighting. </p>

<p>Table 2. Odds ratios for overall cancer screening according to socioeconomic status </p>

<p>Variable 
Men 
Women </p>

<p>Household income status 
Middle-lowest vs. lowest 
1.617 (1.265-2.066) 
1.004 (0.806-1.251) 
Middle-highest vs. lowest 
1.630 (1.279-2.077) 
1.063 (0.832-1.357) 
Highest vs. lowest 
2.113 (1.606-2.781) 
1.476 (1.157-1.883) 
Occupational status 
Office workers vs. manual workers 
1.248 (0.982-1.586) 
1.041 (0.750-1.447) 
Others vs. manual workers 
0.906 (0.733-1.121) 
1.132 (0.944-1.358) 
Educational status 
6-&lt;9 y vs. &lt;6 y 
1.261 (0.970-1.641) 
1.028 (0.795-1.330) 
9-&lt;12 y vs. &lt;6 y 
1.028 (0.809-1.307) 
1.033 (0.806-1.324) 
≥12 y vs. &lt;6 y 
1.192 (0.899-1.580) 
0.848 (0.608-1.183) </p>

<p>Values are presented as odds ratio (95% confidence interval). Adjusted for age, body mass index, daily calorie intake, smoking status, Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test 
score, physical activity, marital status, monthly household income quartile, occupational status, and educational status. </p>

<p>Jin-Young Kim, et al. • Socioeconomic Status and Cancer Screening </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4082/kjfm.2016.37.5.287 </p>

<p>www.kjfm.or.kr </p>



<p>cancer screening, while women in the higher income group showed </p>

<p>lower odds of undergoing NCSP. Male office workers and more edu-</p>

<p>cated men seem to receive private cancer screening more often. </p>

<p>Cancer is the leading cause of death in Korea. Cancer mortality can </p>

<p>be reduced if we detect and treat pre-cancerous lesions and cancer at </p>

<p>an early stage through awareness and a cancer screening system. Can-</p>

<p>cer screening programs aim to identify abnormalities suggestive of </p>

<p>pre-cancerous lesions and to determine the type of cancer in order to </p>

<p>promptly manage the disease. A screening program is an effective </p>

<p>method for diagnosis and early intervention of frequent cancers for </p>

<p>which cost-effective and acceptable screening tests and treatments are </p>

<p>available to high-risk populations. Cancer is the most burdensome </p>

<p>disease in Korea. 
7,8) In order to reduce the burden of cancer, NCSP pro-</p>

<p>vide free cancer screening of the stomach for all individuals aged over </p>

<p>40 years, the liver for individuals with hepatitis B or C virus or liver cir-</p>

<p>rhosis, the colorectum for individuals aged 50 years, the breast for </p>

<p>women aged over 40 years, and the uterine cervix for women aged </p>

<p>over 30 years. Screening methods are follows: stomach, gastric endos-</p>

<p>copy or upper gastro-intestinal series, biennially; liver, ultrasound and </p>

<p>serum alpha-fetoprotein, annually; colorectum, fecal occult blood test, </p>

<p>annually; breast, mammography with palpation, biennially; and uter-</p>

<p>ine cervix, pap smear test, biennially. 
9,10) In the private sector, individu-</p>

<p>als pay to undergo cancer screenings or health check-up. Many com-</p>

<p>panies will pay the hospital fee for employees to undergo these wel-</p>

<p>fare-type check-ups. As a result of these efforts in the public and pri-</p>

<p>vate sectors, five-year relative cancer survival rates have steadily in-</p>

<p>creased from 41.2% in 1993-1995 to 66.3% in 2007-2011 based on the </p>

<p>period of diagnosis. </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>SES may influence an individual's health behavior and hospital use </p>

<p>pattern in various ways. Factors known to contribute to socioeconomic </p>

<p>inequality are closely related to different exposure to underlying risk </p>

<p>factors such as smoking, access to screening programs, and diagnosis </p>

<p>and treatment of cancers in a timely manner. 
11) In addition, individuals </p>

<p>with lower SES have economic barriers, informational disparity, and </p>

<p>weak support from their company to access health care. 
12) Hastert et </p>

<p>al. 
3) reported that living in a lower SES area was related to a higher inci-</p>

<p>dence of lung and colorectal cancer and total cancer mortality. Dispar-</p>

<p>ities in cancer screening for breast and uterine cervix in low SES also </p>

<p>exist in Korea, based on the Korea National Cancer Screening Survey. </p>

<p>13) </p>

<p>Several Korean studies have revealed that socioeconomically deprived </p>

<p>populations are associated with worse mortality outcomes for gastric </p>

<p>cancer and female cancers such as breast, uterine, cervix, and ova-</p>

<p>ry. 
4,5,14) The percentage of potential cancer deaths that could be avoided </p>

<p>by elimination of educational and racial disparities in the US is over </p>

<p>30%. 
11) Proper and timely distribution of limited health resources and </p>

<p>better opportunities for free check-ups can improve health indicators. </p>

<p>A Korean qualitative study indicated that barriers to participation in </p>

<p>cancer screening include lack of trust in NCSP and cancer screening </p>

<p>units, knowledge regarding cancer screening necessity, and awareness </p>

<p>of NCSP. 
6) In this study, odds for overall cancer screening were statisti-</p>

<p>cally significant for household income status, but not occupational and </p>

<p>educational status. However, after stratifying cancer screening into pri-</p>

<p>vate and NCSP, ORs for private cancer screening according to house-</p>

<p>hold income status tended to increase in both sexes and occupational </p>

<p>and educational status in men showed statistical significance. Even the </p>

<p>odds for NCSP with household income status in women showed a </p>

<p>downward tendency. The above-mentioned barriers appear to con-</p>

<p>tribute to the current study's findings. Limited healthcare resources </p>

<p>should be efficiently and effectively distributed to the populations that </p>

<p>absolutely require these medical services. Health authorities should </p>

<p>do their best to develop policies to overcome these barriers, increase </p>

<p>awareness of and trust in NSCP, control screening unit quality, and in-</p>

<p>form the population about cancer screening necessity. Providing infor-</p>

<p>mation on cancer screening to the public, especially individuals with </p>

<p>low SES, can increase early detection of cancer, improve treatment </p>

<p>outcomes, promote national health, and reduce social cost. As a virtu-</p>

<p>ous circle, reduced cost should promote national health and welfare. </p>

<p>This study has several limitations that should be considered when </p>

<p>Table 3. Odds ratios for private cancer screening and NCSPs according to socioeconomic status </p>

<p>Variable 
Men 
Women </p>

<p>Private cancer screening 
NCSP 
Private cancer screening 
NCSP </p>

<p>Household income status 
Middle-lowest vs. lowest 
1.580 (1.171-2.133) 
1.299 (1.007-1.675) 
1.428 (1.122-1.818) 
0.735 (0.592-0.911) 
Middle-highest vs. lowest 
1.941 (1.431-2.632) 
1.068 (0.8808-1.413) 
1.888 (1.452-2.454) 
0.619 (0.491-0.781) 
Highest vs. lowest 
2.446 (1.800-3.324) 
1.076 (0.805-1.439) 
2.630 (2.050-3.373) 
0.492 (0.388-0.623) 
Occupational status 
Office workers vs. manual workers 
1.300 (1.018-1.660) 
0.814 (0.631-1.050) 
0.822 (0.616-1.098) 
1.282 (0.934-1.759) 
Others vs. manual workers 
0.980 (0.768-1.250) 
0.887 (0.699-1.126) 
1.260 (1.060-1.497) 
0.871 (0.735-1.031) 
Educational status 
6-&lt;9 y vs. &lt;6 y 
1.567 (1.189-2.066) 
0.856 (0.653-1.122) 
1.264 (0.991-1.613) 
0.778 (0.597-1.013) 
9-&lt;12 y vs. &lt;6 y 
1.160 (0.880-1.529) 
0.888 (0.689-1.145) 
1.064 (0.840-1.347) 
0.902 (0.699-1.166) 
≥12 y vs. &lt;6 y 
1.530 (1.117-2.095) 
0.818 (0.606-1.103) 
0.936 (0.694-1.263) 
0.721 (0.510-1.021) </p>

<p>Values are presented as odds ratio (95% confidence interval). Adjusted for age, body mass index, daily calorie intake, smoking status, Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test 
score, physical activity status, marital status, monthly household income quartile, occupational status, and educational status. 
NCSP, National Cancer Screening Program. </p>

<p>Jin-Young Kim, et al. • Socioeconomic Status and Cancer Screening </p>

<p>
http://dx.doi.org/10.4082/kjfm.2016.37.5.287 </p>

<p>interpreting the findings. First, it was difficult to confirm whether so-</p>

<p>cioeconomic deprivation was a risk factors related to low cancer </p>

<p>screening because of the cross-sectional design of the study. Although </p>

<p>several previous studies have demonstrated that low SES is associated </p>

<p>with low cancer screening participation, advanced cancer detection </p>

<p>by delayed screening can cause economic and occupational depriva-</p>

<p>tion. However, in contrast to economic and occupational status, edu-</p>

<p>cation is rarely affected by previous cancer diagnosis except in terms of </p>

<p>childhood cancer. The causality between SES and cancer screening </p>

<p>does not matter because authorities should be concerned about all </p>

<p>vulnerable social groups. Second, we could not fully exclude the effect </p>

<p>of information bias because the data used in this study were based on </p>

<p>results from self-reported questionnaires. For the reason that self-re-</p>

<p>ported surveys regarding anticipated answers sorted to socially unde-</p>

<p>sirable groups tend to be underestimated, individuals that actually </p>

<p>should have been classified as lower SES might have been classified as </p>

<p>higher SES. Third, cancer type, screening units and methods could not </p>

<p>be identified and differentiated. Some participants were confused </p>

<p>about the type of cancer screening they underwent. </p>

<p>In spite of these potential limitations, this study has several </p>

<p>strengths. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to report </p>

<p>the associations between SES and overall cancer screening within two </p>

<p>years. First, we applied sampling weights to all analyses to retain repre-</p>

<p>sentativeness to the entire Korean population. Second, cancer screen-</p>

<p>ing was reclassified into private cancer screening and NCSP according </p>

<p>to payment methods. Although previous studies have reported the re-</p>

<p>lationship of SES to screening for individual cancer types such as </p>

<p>stomach, breast and cervix cancer, 
13,15-17) they have not integrated any </p>

<p>cancer screening nor stratified cancer screening into private cancer </p>

<p>screening or NCSP. We included integrated cancer screening, not type-</p>

<p>based cancer screening. Third, screening participation data were lim-</p>

<p>ited to the last two years in order to investigate whether SES is associ-</p>

<p>ated with recent cancer screening. </p>

<p>In conclusion, higher economic status is associated with a higher par-</p>

<p>ticipation rate in overall and private cancer screening in both sexes and </p>

<p>a lower participation rate in NCSP in women. Male office workers and </p>

<p>more educated individuals undergo private cancer screening at a higher </p>

<p>rate than manual workers and less educated individuals, respectively. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We appreciate the help of those working for the Korea Centers for Dis-</p>

<p>ease Control and Prevention and individuals participating in the </p>

<p>KNHANES V. </p>



</text></tei>