<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5320029" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Capsule endoscopy (CE) has revolutionized the diagnosis and monitoring of small bowel Crohn's 
disease (CD). The procedure is patient friendly and noninvasive, and compared to cross-sectional 
imaging, CE allows a direct and detailed evaluation of the entire small bowel mucosa with a high 
sensitivity for the earliest lesions of CD. Today, CE is the leading modality for visualizing the 
small bowel in suspected CD, and validated activity indices are available for the follow up of 
patients with established CD. CE of the entire gastrointestinal tract (panenteric CE) was recently 
introduced as a new diagnostic approach in patients examined for CD, and preliminary results are 
promising. There are important limitations, involving mainly capsule retention. Furthermore, a 
diagnostic criterion for CD has never been validated, and lesions detected by CE are not specific 
for CD. Hence, concern has been raised about a low specificity compared to other diagnostic 
modalities. Important questions about the optimal bowel preparation, selection of patients for CE 
and the optimal reading protocol remain to be clarified. The aim of this review is to evaluate the 
performance of CE for diagnosing CD and assess disease activity in known CD; to compare the 
diagnostic accuracy of CE to that of cross-sectional imaging; to discuss limitations; and to define 
the place of CE in the diagnostic algorithm in suspected or known CD. </p>

<p>Before the era of capsule endoscopy (CE), the small bowel was 
considered inaccessible and difficult to examine. Endoscopic 
evaluation of the small bowel was limited to the most distal 
or proximal part, with ileocolonoscopy and push enteroscopy, 
respectively, or in selected cases intraoperative enteroscopy, 
all of which are invasive procedures requiring conscious 
sedation or general anesthesia [1]. Although radiological 
procedures such as magnetic resonance enterography (MRE) 
and ultrasound have improved, they mainly visualize the 
transmural gut inflammation and have limited sensitivity for 
superficial lesions [2,3]. Since its FDA approval in 2001, CE has </p>

<p>revolutionized small bowel imaging and important knowledge 
has been gained about its clinical use. The main indications 
for CE are obscure gastrointestinal bleeding, suspected 
Crohn's disease (CD), assessment of disease activity, mucosal 
healing and disease location in known CD, and discrimination 
between CD and ulcerative coliti s [4-6]. Other indications 
may include celiac disease, small bowel tumors, non-steroid 
anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID) enteropathy, or polyposis 
syndromes. CE is a patient-friendly and noninvasive procedure 
and, compared to cross-sectional imaging, CE allows a direct 
and detailed evaluation of the entire small bowel mucosa with 
detection of the earliest lesions of CD [7]. However, there are 
important limitations, of which capsule retention is the main 
concern (Table 1) [5,8,9]. 
The aim of this review is to evaluate the performance of CE 
for diagnosing CD and assess disease activity in known CD; to 
compare the diagnostic accuracy of CE to that of cross-sectional 
imaging; to discuss limitations; and to define the place of CE in 
the diagnostic algorithm in suspected or known CD. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>An extensive English-language literature search was 
conducted using PubMed to identify peer-reviewed 
original and review articles, using the keywords "capsule 
endoscopy", "suspected or known Crohn's disease, "bowel </p>

<p>Departments of a Internal Medicine, Section of Gastroenterology, 
Lillebaelt Hospital Vejle (Michael Dam Jensen); b Internal Medicine, 
Section of Gastroenterology, Hospital of Southwest Jutland, Esbjerg 
(Jacob Broder Brodersen); c Medical Gastroenterology, Odense 
University Hospital, Odense (Jens Kjeldsen), Denmark </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: None </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Michael Dam Jensen, MD, PhD, Department of 
Internal Medicine, Section of Gastroenterology, Lillebaelt Hospital 
Vejle, Kabbeltoft 25, 7100 Vejle, Denmark, Tel.: +45 7940 6345, 
Fax: +45 7940 6887, e-mail: michael.dam.jensen@rsyd.dk </p>

<p>Received 19 October 2016; accepted 17 November 2016; 
published online 22 December 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: https://doi.org/10.20524/aog.2016.0119 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 30 </p>

<p>Capsule endoscopy in Crohn's disease 169 </p>

<p>cleansing", "activity index", "mucosal healing", "C-reactive 
protein", "fecal calprotectin", "ileocolonoscopy", "magnetic 
resonance imaging", "computed tomography", "ultrasound", 
"postsurgical recurrence", "capsule retention", "quick view", 
"Pillcam colon", and "panenteric capsule endoscopy". The 
references of selected studies were searched manually to 
identify additional relevant studies. Systematic reviews 
and meta-analyses of randomized controlled trials were 
considered the highest level of evidence (www.cebm.net). 
Studies of diagnostic accuracy were reviewed in accordance 
with the QUADAS tool for quality assessment of diagnostic 
accuracy studies [10]. </p>

<p>CE systems </p>

<p>There are currently five CE systems available for visualizing 
the small bowel: Pillcam SB3 (Medtronic, Dublin, Ireland), </p>

<p>EndoCapsule EC-S10 (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan), MiroCam 
MC-1000W (Intromedic, Soul, South Korea), OMOM (Jinshan 
Science and Technology, Chongqing, China), and CapsoCam 
SV3 (CapsoVision, Saratoga, USA) [11]. Furthermore, the 
Pillcam COLON2 (Medtronic, Dublin, Ireland) visualizes 
the small bowel, although it was designed for diagnosing the 
colon. Specifications provided by the manufacturers are shown 
in Table 2. Although CE systems are based on comparable 
technologies, important differences exist: e.g. the number of 
cameras, frame rate, angle of view, viewing direction, image 
resolution, and battery life. Theoretically, these differences 
could influence the diagnostic sensitivity for CD and the 
rate of complete small bowel examinations. However, studies 
comparing different CE systems head-to-head in patients with 
suspected or known CD are currently not available. In CD, the 
majority of studies have been performed with the Pillcam SB1 
and SB2, as this CE system has dominated the world market for 
years. In patients with obscure gastrointestinal bleeding, studies 
comparing Pillcam SB1 with EndoCapsule [12,13], Pillcam 
SB2 with MiroCam [14,15], Pillcam SB2 with CapsoCam [16], </p>

<p>Table 1 Advantages and limitations of small bowel capsule endoscopy (CE) in Crohn's disease (CD) </p>

<p>Advantages 
Limitations </p>

<p>Noninvasive 
Risk of capsule retention in stricturing CD </p>

<p>Patient-friendly 
Inability to take biopsies </p>

<p>Direct mucosal evaluation 
Significant number of incomplete examinations* </p>

<p>Significantly higher diagnostic yield for CD 
compared to other modalities 
Analysis is time-consuming </p>

<p>Better visualization of the proximal small bowel compared to other modalities 
Longer procedure time compared to radiological modalities </p>

<p>*In a systematic review of 2295 CE's performed in suspected or known CD, a completion rate of 85% was reported [55] </p>

<p>Table 2 Specifications of available capsule endoscopy systems for examining the small bowel. The Pillcam COLON2 was designed for studying 
the colon but it also visualizes the small bowel </p>

<p>Specifications 
Medtronic 
Medtronic 
Olympus 
Intromedic 
Jinshan science 
and technology 
CapsoVision </p>

<p>Capsule endoscopy 
system 
Pillcam 
SB3 
Pillcam 
COLON2 
EndoCapsule 
EC-S10 
MiroCam 
MC1000-W 
OMOM 
JS-ME-II 
CapsoCam 
Plus </p>

<p>Size (mm) 
26 × 11 
32 × 12 
26 × 11 
25 × 11 
28 × 13 
31 × 11 </p>

<p>Cameras (n) 
1 
2 
1 
1 
1 
4 </p>

<p>Viewing direction 
Longitudinal 
Longitudinal 
Longitudinal 
Longitudinal 
Longitudinal 
Lateral </p>

<p>Weight (g) 
3.0 
2.9 
3.3 
3.3 
6.0 
4.0 </p>

<p>Minimum battery 
life (h) 
11 
10 
12 
12 
9 
15 </p>

<p>Image sensor 
CMOS 
CMOS 
CMOS 
CMOS 
CMOS 
CMOS </p>

<p>Frame rate 
(frames/s) 
2-6 
4-35 
2 
3 
2 
12-20 </p>

<p>Field of view (°) 
156 
172 
160 
170 
140 
360 </p>

<p>Image 
transmission 
Radiofrequency 
Radiofrequency 
Radiofrequency 
Human body 
communication** 
Radiofrequency 
None*** </p>

<p>**Data are transmitted to sensor electrodes on the skin using the human body as a conductor </p>

<p>***Data are stored in the capsule in an onboard flash memory. The patient retrieves the capsule and returns it to the medical staff for data download </p>

<p>CMOS, complementary metal oxide semiconductor </p>

<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 30 </p>



<p>and EndoCapsule with MiroCam [17] found no significant 
differences in diagnostic yields. </p>

<p>Small bowel cleansing </p>

<p>Numerous studies have examined the effect of bowel 
cleansing regimens on mucosal visualization, diagnostic yield 
and completion rates, and results have been included in several 
systematic reviews and meta-analyses [18-21]. Original studies 
are heterogeneous in terms of included patients and scales used 
for determining the visualization quality. Results of individual 
studies are conflicting and meta-analyses have applied 
different inclusion criteria, with varying recommendations. In 
a meta-analysis of prospective randomized studies, including 
291 patients who had polyethylene glycol (PEG) administered 
before CE and 232 controls, the small bowel visibility was 
significantly better with PEG (odds ratio [OR] 3.11; 95% 
confidence interval [CI] 1.96-4.94), whereas no significant 
difference could be demonstrated between sodium phosphate 
treated patients and those on fasting only [21]. Overall, bowel 
cleansing increased the diagnostic yield compared to fasting 
alone (OR 1.88; 95% CI 1.24-2.84). Simethicone improves 
the mucosal visualization but the effect on diagnostic yield 
remains to be established [22]. Prokinetics do not seem 
to affect the small bowel CE completion rate [20]. Hence, 
the current evidence suggests a bowel cleansing regimen 
containing PEG and simethicone before small bowel CE. 
However, additional studies on this matter are warranted. It 
should be emphasized that studies mainly included patients 
with obscure gastrointestinal bleeding and only a minority 
of patients were examined for CD. Whether bowel cleansing 
improves the mucosal visualization, diagnostic sensitivity and 
disease severity assessment in patients with CD is unknown. 
On the other hand, bowel cleansing causes discomfort, and 
currently, there is no consensus on the use of bowel cleansing 
before CE in patients examined for CD. </p>

<p>Suspected CD </p>

<p>The cardinal lesions are mucosal ulcerations of varying 
severity (Fig. 1); in the earliest stage they present as aphthous 
ulcerations defined by a mucosal break with surrounding 
erythema. Punched out, linear or irregular ulcers with 
cobblestone appearance and stenosis caused by inflammation 
or fibrosis are seen in more severe CD. Other findings, such 
as erythema, edema and loss of villi without ulcerations, are 
considered non-specific [23]. It should be emphasized that 
ulcerations detected by CE are not specific for CD, and CE does 
not allow tissue sampling to support the diagnosis. 
Lesions caused by NSAIDs are an important differential 
diagnosis, because these drugs are frequently used in the 
general population. It is well established that NSAIDs are 
associated with gastrointestinal ulcerations, bleeding and 
strictures, that lesions are visualized with CE and they can </p>

<p>mimic CD [24,25]. The precise number of weeks NSAIDs 
should be stopped prior to CE is unknown, but generally 
4 weeks is recommended [8,26]. 
A surprising finding by Goldstein et al was that 11% 
of healthy volunteers who were not users of NSAIDs had 
mucosal breaks in the small bowel at a baseline CE [25]. In the 
subsequent clinical study, 7% of patients with a normal baseline 
CE developed 1-3 mucosal breaks after placebo treatment. This 
raises an important question about the diagnostic criterion 
and minimum threshold for diagnosing CD in patients 
examined with CE. At this point, no such criterion has 
been validated [23,26]. As suggested by Mow et al, the most 
frequently used diagnostic criterion for CD with CE is the 
presence of &gt;3 ulcerations in patients not using NSAIDs [27]. 
Numerous studies have examined the clinical application 
of CE in patients with suspected or known CD. In the meta-
analysis by Dionisio et al, the diagnostic yield of CE in patients 
with suspected CD was superior to that of small bowel 
radiography (52% vs. 16%, P&lt;0.0001, n=155), computed 
tomography enterography (CTE) (68% vs. 21%, P&lt;0.0001, 
n=53) and ileocolonoscopy (47% vs. 25%, P=0.009, n=59) [28]. 
Compared to MRE, CE had a higher diagnostic yield, but the 
difference did not reach statistical significance (55% vs. 45%, 
P=0.43, n=31). These results suggest that CE is the best modality 
for diagnosing small bowel CD. However, the lack of a gold 
standard comparison may lead to false conclusions, because 
false positive lesions count as true lesions and this tends to favor 
the most sensitive modality. Although the majority of studies 
have used multiple ulcerations as the diagnostic criterion 
for CD, the diagnostic threshold differs between studies and 
some studies included non-specific lesions or the diagnostic 
criterion was not described [29-33]. In a 4-way comparison 
of CE, CTE, small bowel follow-through and ileocolonoscopy, </p>

<p>Figure 1 Crohn's disease of the small bowel detected with capsule 
endoscopy: (A) normal small bowel mucosa, (B) aphthous ulceration, 
(C) linear ulcers, and (D) ulcerated stenosis </p>

<p>D 
C </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 30 </p>

<p>Capsule endoscopy in Crohn's disease 171 </p>

<p>the specificity of CE (53%) was significantly lower compared to 
the other tests, supporting a high diagnostic yield because of 
false positive lesions [30]. A downside of this study, however, 
was that no criterion for diagnosing CD with CE was applied. 
A consensus gold standard based on the clinical presentation 
and results of all four modalities was used, but individual cases 
of disagreement were not discussed. Other prospective studies 
have compared CE with varying gold standards, showing 
a high sensitivity and specificity of CE for diagnosing CD 
(Table 3) [7,29,34]. </p>

<p>Selecting patients for CE </p>

<p>To increase the diagnostic yield and avoid unnecessary 
diagnostic procedures, related expenses and patient discomfort, 
careful selection of patients for CE is of great importance. 
Relevant decision tools in this regard are biomarkers, fecal 
markers and the result of a preceding ileocolonoscopy. 
A prospective study evaluated 72 patients with chronic 
abdominal pain with or without diarrhea and no explanation 
after ileocolonoscopy and upper endoscopy [35]. The 
diagnostic yield of CE was 67% and 21% in patients with or 
without increased markers of inflammation, respectively. 
A diagnosis of CD was obtained in 25% of patients, primarily 
in patients with abdominal pain, diarrhea and elevated 
markers of inflammation. Likewise, in a study by De Bona 
et al, CE detected lesions consistent with CD in 46% of patients 
with suspected CD and elevated biomarkers of inflammation 
compared to 8% in patients with normal biomarkers [36]. An 
elevated C-reactive protein (CRP) level has been shown to have 
sensitivity, specificity and positive predictive value of 73%, 
69% and 89%, respectively, for diagnosing CD in the small 
bowel [37]. However, other studies have provided less favorable 
results. In a retrospective study of 189 patients with known 
small bowel CD, an elevated CRP was poorly associated with 
significant inflammatory lesions detected by CE, consistent 
with the body of evidence in general showing a suboptimal 
sensitivity of CRP for CD [38-40]. Hence, in patients with </p>

<p>gastrointestinal symptoms suggestive of CD but a normal 
ileocolonoscopy, elevated markers of inflammation seem to be 
associated with an increased diagnostic yield of CE, and in this 
situation CE should be considered. However, the sensitivity of 
CRP is inadequate and a normal value does not exclude small 
bowel CD. 
Fecal calprotectin (fCal) is a highly sensitive marker of 
gastrointestinal inflammation, although it is not specific 
for inflammatory bowel disease. A normal value has a high 
negative predictive value and virtually excludes ileocolonic 
CD [41,42]. The utility of fCal for small bowel CD, however, 
has been debated. Some studies have reported lower levels 
of fCal in small bowel CD compared to CD involving the 
colon [43,44], whereas other studies have found equal levels 
and a high sensitivity of fCal for small bowel CD [45]. Similarly, 
data on the ability of fCal to predict findings from CE have 
been conflicting. In a retrospective study by Koulaouzidis 
et al, fCal &gt;100 mg/kg was a good predictor of small bowel CD 
detected with CE in patients with suspected CD but a negative 
bi-directional endoscopy, and fCal &lt;100 mg/kg excluded 
small bowel CD [46]. In subsequent studies, however, fCal 
was an inadequate biomarker for inflammatory lesions in 
the small bowel, with a sensitivity of 59-70% and a specificity 
of 44-71% [38,47]. In a recent meta-analysis that included 
463 patients with a clinically relevant indication for performing 
CE, fCal &gt;50 mg/kg had a sensitivity and specificity of 83% and 
53% for detection of small bowel CD [48]. 
Few studies have examined the benefit of performing 
CE after ileocolonoscopy. In a study comparing CE with 
ileocolonoscopy in patients with suspected small bowel CD, 
diagnostic yields for the terminal ileum and cecum were 
comparable [49]. A total of 25 patients were diagnosed with 
small bowel CD, of whom 11 were diagnosed based solely on 
the result of CE (lesions isolated in the proximal small bowel 
in 3). This study suggests that ileocolonoscopy and CE are 
complementary modalities for diagnosing CD in the terminal 
ileum, that ileocolonoscopy should be the primary diagnostic 
modality, and that CE is of benefit in patients with a negative 
ileocolonoscopy. In contrast, in a study of 93 patients with 
suspected CD, limited diagnostic information was gained with </p>

<p>Table 3 Studies comparing the sensitivity and specificity of capsule endoscopy for diagnosing small bowel CD with different gold standards </p>

<p>Studies 
Study design 
Diagnostic 
lesions at CE 
Gold standard 
n 
Sensitivity (%) 
Specificity (%) </p>

<p>Dubcenco, 2005 [34] 
Prospective 
Ulcerations 
Biopsy from the 
terminal ileum 
39 
90 
100 </p>

<p>Albert, 2005 [29] 
Prospective 
Ulcerations 
Follow up 
25 
92 
100 </p>

<p>Solem, 2008 [30] 
Prospective 
Unknown 
Consensus based on 
the results of CE, CT, 
SB radiography and IC </p>

<p>27 
83 
53 </p>

<p>Tukey, 2009 [88] 
Retrospective analysis 
of CEs performed after 
a negative IC and SB 
radiography </p>

<p>Ulcerations 
Follow up 
102 
77 
89 </p>

<p>Jensen, 2011 [7] 
Prospective 
Ulcerations 
IC 
69 
100 
91 </p>

<p>CE, capsule endoscopy; CT, computed tomography; IC, ileocolonoscopy; SB, small bowel </p>

<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 30 </p>



<p>CE in patients with CD in the colon and a normal terminal 
ileum, or patients with non-complicated CD in the terminal 
ileum detected at ileocolonoscopy [50]. </p>

<p>Diagnostic algorithm in suspected CD </p>

<p>Ileocolonoscopy is the accepted gold standard for 
diagnosing CD located in the colon and terminal ileum and 
is currently recommended as the initial diagnostic modality in 
suspected CD [51]. In the majority of patients, CD is located 
within the reach of the colonoscope, whereas CD isolated 
in the upper small bowel, without involvement of the colon 
or terminal ileum, is uncommon [52]. At the present time, 
international guidelines recommend small bowel imaging in 
all patients with a clinical suspicion of CD, irrespective of the 
findings at ileocolonoscopy (evidence level 5, recommendation 
grad D), and CE should be the first-line investigation in 
patients without obstructive symptoms (Fig. 2A) [8,26,51]. In 
patients with obstructive symptoms or known stenosis, cross-
sectional imaging, such as MRE or CTE is preferred. However, 
additional studies determining the benefit and clinical impact 
of performing CE in adult patients with suspected CD after 
ileocolonoscopy are warranted. Future guidelines should also 
consider noninvasive markers such as fCal as a tool for selecting 
patients for ileocolonoscopy. An alternative algorithm based 
on a single prospective study of fCal, ileocolonoscopy, CE 
and cross-sectional imaging in suspected CD has previously 
been published by our group [50]. Patients with an elevated 
fCal should undergo colonoscopy, including a persistent 
attempt to intubate the terminal ileum. In patients with a 
normal ileocolonoscopy or non-complicated CD in the colon 
and/or terminal ileum, small bowel imaging provides little 
extra information compared to ileoscopy alone. Small bowel 
imaging is primarily indicated if ileoscopy is not achieved and 
CE is the preferred first-line imaging technique. MRE and </p>

<p>CTE are complimentary modalities preferably used in patients 
with stenosis detected at ileocolonoscopy or suspicion of 
extra-intestinal disease complications. Additional studies are 
required to validate this diagnostic approach. </p>

<p>Known CD </p>

<p>In the majority of patients, the phenotype of CD changes 
over time from mainly inflammatory lesions at the time 
of diagnosis to stricturing or penetrating disease [53]. 
Correspondingly, a large number of patients require surgery 
within the first 10 years of diagnosis [53,54], and the utility 
of CE is hampered by the risk of capsule retention. In a 
comprehensive literature review, capsule retention occurred in 
2.6% of patients examined for suspected or known CD [55], 
and retention rates of 4-13% have been reported in patients 
with symptomatic CD [56]. 
In the meta-analysis by Dionisio et al, the diagnostic yield 
of CE in patients with known CD was superior to that of small 
bowel radiography (71% vs. 36%, P&lt;0.00001, n=224) and CT 
enterography (71% vs. 39%, P&lt;0.0001, n=66) [28]. There was 
a trend towards a higher yield compared to ileocolonoscopy 
(70% vs. 57%, P=0.07, n=158), whereas MRE had an equally 
high diagnostic yield (P=0.65). It should be emphasized, 
however, that original studies excluded patients with a 
radiological suspicion of small bowel stenosis. Therefore, CE 
is superior to cross-sectional imaging and ileocolonoscopy in a 
subgroup of patients with non-stricturing CD, which tends to 
favor the most sensitive modality for mucosal inflammation, 
i.e. endoscopy over cross-sectional imaging. 
There is a lack of prospective studies directly comparing the 
feasibility, sensitivity and specificity of CE with that of cross-
sectional imaging in patients with known CD. In retrospective 
studies involving this group of patients, CE was safe and 
added significant diagnostic information in a large number of </p>

<p>Cross-secconal imaging </p>

<p>Cross-secconal imaging </p>

<p>Figure 2 The internationally recommended diagnostic algorithm in patients with (A) suspected Crohn's disease and (B) symptomatic known 
Crohn's disease [8,26] </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 30 </p>

<p>Capsule endoscopy in Crohn's disease 173 </p>

<p>patients, with a subsequent impact on clinical decision [38,57]. 
Compared to cross-sectional imaging, CE detects significantly 
more lesions in the proximal small bowel, primarily in the form 
of mild lesions [7,58]. The clinical significance of this diagnostic 
information has previously been debated [26]. However, a 
recent retrospective study of 108 patients with known CD 
found jejunal lesions in more than half of the patients, and the 
presence of proximal lesions was an independent risk factor 
for future clinical relapse (adjusted hazard ratio of 1.99; 95% 
CI, 1.10-3.61; P=0.02) [59]. Hence, the greater sensitivity of CE 
for proximal small bowel lesions compared to cross-sectional 
imaging seems to have prognostic importance and an impact 
on clinical decision-making. Furthermore, the discomfort 
experienced by the patient is significantly lower with CE 
compared to cross-sectional imaging, and 78% of patients 
would prefer this modality as a future examination [7,60]. </p>

<p>Diagnostic algorithm in known CD </p>

<p>In patients with symptomatic CD, current guidelines 
recommend dedicated small imaging, irrespective of 
the findings at ileocolonoscopy, because the detection of 
lesions may have prognostic and therapeutic implications 
(Fig. 2B) [8,51]. In this group of patients, the prevalence of 
disease complications is high, and cross-sectional imaging is 
the preferred modality for diagnosing inflammatory lesions 
and strictures beyond the reach of the colonoscope, as well 
as fistulas and abscesses. CE should be reserved as a second-
line modality in patients with unexplained symptoms after 
ileocolonoscopy and cross-sectional imaging, if the symptoms 
require further evaluation and findings are expected to alter 
medical treatment. CE should be preceded by either cross-
sectional imaging or examination with a patency capsule to 
avoid capsule retention [8,26]. </p>

<p>Assessment of disease activity and mucosal healing </p>

<p>There are currently two validated indexes available for 
assessing the disease location and severity of small bowel 
CD with CE (Table 4). The Lewis score evaluates three small 
bowel segments for the parameters villous appearance, ulcers 
and stenosis [61]. The Capsule Endoscopy Crohn's Disease 
Activity Index. (CECDAI) evaluates the proximal and distal 
small bowel for the parameters inflammatory lesions, disease 
extension and stenosis [62]. A software application for 
calculation of the Lewis score has been incorporated into the 
<rs type="software">RAPID Reader</rs> platform for Pillcam SB. The following cutoffs 
have been proposed: &lt;135, normal small bowel or clinically 
insignificant inflammation; 135-79, mild disease activity; and 
&gt;790, moderate to severe disease [61]. The CECDAI is simpler 
to calculate, but cutoffs for endoscopic remission and different 
disease severities have not been properly established. However, 
there is a good correlation between the two indexes (r=0.63, 
P&lt;0.0001), and in a retrospective and unblinded single reader </p>

<p>analysis, CECDAI levels of 3.8 and 5.8 corresponded to Lewis 
scores of 135 and 790, respectively [40,63]. 
Although the Lewis score and CECDAI are able to quantify 
the severity of mucosal inflammation, it should be emphasized 
that they cannot be applied as diagnostic tools in general, 
because the parameters included in the scores are not disease 
specific. However, in a retrospective study of 95 patients with 
suspected CD, a normal ileocolonoscopy and follow up as gold 
standard, a Lewis score ≥135 had a sensitivity and specificity 
of 89.5% and 78.9%, respectively, for the diagnosis of CD [64]. 
A Lewis score &lt;135 excluded CD with a negative predictive 
value of 92%. Hence, in patients with suspected CD, a normal 
Lewis score virtually excludes the diagnosis. In patients who 
have findings consistent with CD, i.e. multiple ulcerations, 
both the Lewis score and CECDAI may be applied to quantify 
the disease severity and location. 
A few studies have examined the applicability of CE as a 
tool for monitoring treatment response and mucosal healing 
in small bowel CD. Currently, however, there is no validated 
criterion for mucosal healing with CE [8]. Equivalent to 
ileocolonic CD, achieving clinical remission is only paralleled 
by mucosal healing in a minority of patients with small bowel 
CD. Hence, CE may serve as an objective tool for monitoring 
the treatment response and mucosal healing [40,65,66]. 
The clinical benefit of using CE as a disease monitoring tool 
with treatment escalation in patients who have not achieved 
mucosal healing needs to be shown. No studies have compared 
CE to cross-sectional imaging in relation to these matters. </p>

<p>Post-surgical recurrence </p>

<p>One year after surgical resection of the terminal ileum because 
of CD, inflammatory lesions can be detected endoscopically in 
73-93% of patients, although clinical recurrence only occurs in 
20-37% at this point in time [67,68]. Detection of post-surgical 
recurrence may have important therapeutic implications. 
Boureille et al compared CE to ileocolonoscopy for the detection 
of post-surgical recurrence in 32 patients a median of 6 months 
after an ileocolonic resection [69]. With a composite gold 
standard including both the results of ileocolonoscopy and CE 
analyzed by two observers, the sensitivity of CE was inferior to 
that of ileocolonoscopy for the detection of disease recurrence in 
the neoterminal ileum (62-76% vs. 90%, respectively). However, 
CE detected inflammatory lesions outside the reach of the 
colonoscope in two thirds of patients. The severity of lesions 
detected with ileocolonoscopy and CE correlated significantly 
(r=0.54-0.64, P&lt;0.05). In a similar study by Pons Beltran et al, 
both endoscopic procedures were performed in 22 patients 
6-12 months after ileocolonic resection [70]. Ileocolonoscopy 
and CE detected post-surgical recurrence in the neoterminal 
ileum in 6 and 15 patients, respectively. Lesions beyond the 
reach of the colonoscope were detected in 13 patients with CE, 
including 3 patients without involvement of the neoterminal 
ileum. All patients preferred CE over ileocolonoscopy. 
Hence, data regarding the sensitivity of CE for the detection 
of post-surgical recurrence in the neoterminal ileum are </p>

<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 30 </p>



<p>conflicting, and the applicability of CE in this situation remains 
to be clarified. Currently, ileocolonoscopy is considered the 
gold standard, and the Rutgeerts's score is recommended for 
determining the disease severity [26]. Lesions of increasing 
severity found on ileocolonoscopy are a strong predictor for 
clinical recurrence, and current guidelines of the European 
Crohn's and Colitis Organisation recommend ileocolonoscopy 
6-12 months after surgery in cases where treatment decisions 
may be affected [26]. In patients without obstructive symptoms 
who are unwilling to undergo ileocolonoscopy, CE seems to be 
a safe and patient-friendly alternative with a high diagnostic 
yield for CD recurrence in both the proximal and distal small 
bowel. </p>

<p>Small bowel patency </p>

<p>If a small bowel stenosis is not firmly excluded, the Pillcam 
patency capsule (Medtronic, Dublin, Ireland) can be used 
to confirm small bowel patency before performing CE. The </p>

<p>patency capsule is a dissolvable capsule with the same size as the 
Pillcam SB3 capsule (26 × 11 mm). It is composed of a lactose 
body mixed with barium and a radio frequency identification 
tag. At each end, the patency capsule has a timer plug that is 
designed to erode after 30 h, resulting in disintegration of the 
capsule, and it has been stated that all patency capsules are 
dissolved within 72 h [71]. CE is considered safe if the patency 
capsule is excreted before 30 h, an intact capsule is excreted 
after 30 h, or passage to the colon of an intact patency capsule 
has been radiologically confirmed. 
Herrerias et al evaluated the Pillcam patency capsule in 
106 patients with radiographic evidence of a small bowel 
stricture [72]. Small bowel patency was confirmed in 59, and 
none of these patients experienced capsule retention during a 
subsequent CE. No severe adverse events could be attributed 
to the patency capsule. Furthermore, Yadav et al concluded 
that the Pillcam patency capsule and radiological examination 
were equally reliable for excluding small bowel obstruction or 
strictures [73]. Hence, available studies suggest that the Pillcam 
patency capsule is equal to radiology and is a safe method for 
testing small bowel patency before CE, even in patients with </p>

<p>Table 4 Validated indexes for determining the severity of Crohn's disease in the small bowel with capsule endoscopy </p>

<p>A: Lewis score </p>

<p>Villous appearance (for each small bowel tertile*) 
Number: normal (0) or edematous (1) 
Longitudinal extent**: short segment (8), long segment (12) or whole tertile (20) 
Descriptor: singe (1), patchy (14) or diffuse (17) </p>

<p>Ulcer (for each small bowel tertile*) 
Number: no ulcers (0), one ulcer (3), two to seven ulcers (5) or eight or more ulcers (10) 
Longitudinal extent**: short segment (5), long segment (10) or whole tertile (15) 
Descriptor: &lt;¼ (9), ¼-½ (12) or &gt;½ (18) of the capsule picture occupied by the largest ulcer </p>

<p>Stenosis 
Number: none (0), single (14) or multiple (20) 
Ulcerated (24) or non-ulcerated (2) 
Traversed (7) or not traversed (10) by the capsule </p>

<p>Total Lewis score = score of the worst affected tertile 
(villous appearance × extent × descriptor + ulcer number × extent × size) + stenosis number × ulcerated × traversed </p>

<p>*The small bowel is divided into tertiles according to the transit time </p>

<p>** Short segment: &lt;10% of the tertile; long segment: 11-50% of the tertile; whole segment: &gt;50% of the tertile </p>

<p>B: Capsule endoscopy Crohn's disease activity index (CECDAI) </p>

<p>A. Inflammation score 
0 = None; 1 = Mild to moderate edema/hyperemia/denudation; 2 = Severe edema/hyperemia/denudation; 3 = Bleeding, exudate, aphthae, 
erosion, small ulcer (&lt;0.5 cm); 4 = Moderate ulcer (0.5-2 cm), pseudopolyp; 5 = Large ulcer (&gt;2 cm) </p>

<p>B. Extent of disease score 
0 = None; 1 = Focal disease (single segment); 2 = Patchy disease (multiple segments); 3 = Diffuse disease </p>

<p>C. Narrowing (stricture) 
0 = None; 1 = Single-passed; 2 = Multiple-passed; 3 = Obstruction </p>

<p>Total score = (A1 x B1 + C1) + (A2 x B2 + C2)* </p>

<p>*The small bowel is divided into a proximal (1) and distal (2) segment according to the transit time </p>

<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 30 </p>

<p>Capsule endoscopy in Crohn's disease 175 </p>

<p>a radiologically verified stenosis. However, symptomatic and 
potentially severe capsule retention with the Pillcam patency 
capsule has been reported [74,75]. In a recent multicenter case 
series of 1615 patients examined with the Pillcam patency 
capsule, 20 (1.2%) symptomatic cases of capsule retention 
were identified [76]. One patient required surgery; all other 
patients with a retained patency capsule in the small bowel 
resolved spontaneously or after corticosteroid therapy. Hence, 
symptomatic patency capsule retention is uncommon and the 
prognosis is good. </p>

<p>Reading protocols </p>

<p>A significant limitation with CE is the time-consuming video 
analysis. In previous series, reading times above 40-50 min 
were reported [77]; thus, ways to reduce reading times without 
affecting the diagnostic accuracy would be helpful in clinical 
practice. For CD in particular, increasing the viewing speed 
may be feasible, because this disease is characterized by 
multiple lesions that are most often widespread in the small 
bowel. 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Given Imaging</rs>'s <rs id="software-2" type="software">RAPID Reader</rs> enables alterations of the 
viewing mode from single to dual or quad view, and the frame 
rate can be adjusted from 5 to 40 frames per second (fr/sec). 
Günther et al compared single view at a speed of 10 fr/sec 
with quad view at 20 fr/sec [78]. The mean reading time was 
reduced from 22 down to 12 min, and detection rates of 
angioectasias, erosions, ulcers, and polyps were significantly 
lower with quad view. However, in patients with suspected or 
known CD, overlooked lesions did not change the result of the 
examination. Recently, Nakamura et al compared single view, 
dual view and quad view at different frame rates, using a small 
bowel video sequence with 60 pathological images of small 
bowel angioectasias [79]. Increasing the frame rate from 10 to 
15, 25 and 40 fr/sec resulted in a 33%, 60%, and 72% reduction 
in playing time, respectively, but at the expense of a drop in 
the number of lesions detected. Altering the viewing mode had 
no effect on the reading time for any given frame rate, but the 
detection rate was significantly higher with dual and quad view 
compared to single view. The authors conclude that the optimal 
combination for a high detection rate is 10 fr/sec using dual or 
quad view. 
Another way to decrease reading times is by reducing the 
number of images presented to the capsule endoscopist. The 
quick view function provided by <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Given Imaging</rs>'s <rs id="software-0" type="software">RAPID 
Reader</rs> filters the number of images shown. With a sampling rate 
of 10% (default setting), 10% of images from the original videos 
is shown. Images are filtered according to a specific algorithm 
developed by the manufacturer, and sampling rates between 2% 
and 80% can be chosen. Shiotani et al examined how different 
sampling rates affect the detection rates of quick view CE [80]. 
A variety of preselected lesions were included in the study. With 
sampling rates of 5%, 15%, 25% and 35%, 61%, 74%, 93% and 
98% of lesions were detected. With a 25% sampling rate, only 
7% of lesions were missed, and the reading time was reduced by 
approximately 50%. This setting was considered a proper trade-</p>

<p>off between reading times and detection rates. Koulaouzidis et al 
studied 81 patients with suspected or known CD [81]. A total of 
155 and 71 ulcerations were detected with CE and quick view 
CE, respectively, with a 35% sampling rate, corresponding to 
a miss rate of 54%. In patients with suspected or known CD, 
quick view CE was false negative (i.e. no or non-specific lesions 
or &lt;3 ulcerations) in 1 (7%) and 8 (10%) patients, respectively. 
In a study by our group, including 40 patients with suspected 
CD, standard view CE visualized 171 small bowel ulcerations, 
compared to 102 lesions detected with quick view CE (miss 
rate 40%, P=0.02) [82]. However, with ileocolonoscopy and 
standard view CE as gold standard, quick view CE diagnosed 
15 of 16 patients with small bowel CD, corresponding to a 
sensitivity of 94%, while 39 out of 40 patients were classified 
correctly overall (diagnostic accuracy 98%). Reading times 
varied from 5-18 min (median 10). 
Hence, the available software for analyzing CEs allows for 
faster reading times, either by increasing the frame rate, with 
or without altering the viewing mode, or using the quick 
view function. However, a reduced reading time comes at a 
cost, as increasing the speed results in lower detection rates. 
Data on patients with suspected or known CD are scarce, but 
available data suggest that, despite the fact that fewer lesions 
are detected, the overall sensitivity for CD is acceptable, and 
the quick view function may serve as a method for screening 
for CD lesions, especially in patients with suspected CD. 
Additional studies in patients with suspected or known CD are 
warranted and a generally accepted reading protocol has not 
yet been established [83]. </p>

<p>Panenteric CE </p>

<p>Using CE for evaluating both the small bowel and colon in 
a single noninvasive examination is an attractive diagnostic 
approach. Pillcam colon CE (PCCE) was introduced in 2006 
and soon a panenteric capsule endoscope will be available: 
i.e. the small bowel colon (SBC) capsule (Medtronic, Dublin, 
Ireland). The SBC capsule is similar to the Pillcam COLON2 
in all its hardware components, but it is designed to provide 
complete coverage of the small bowel and colon [84]. Until 
now, few studies have evaluated this modality for diagnosing 
CD in the colon and small bowel. 
Performing CE of the colon requires optimal cleansing, and 
the European Society of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy currently 
recommends a regimen consisting of 4 L of PEG in two divided 
doses and sodium phosphate (Phosphoral) as booster [85]. In 
a prospective study of patients with known CD, the number 
who reported discomfort was significantly lower with PCCE 
compared to ileocolonoscopy [86]. PCCE had a sensitivity 
of 86% for detection of ulcerations in the colon and terminal 
ileum, and lesions outside the reach of the colonoscope were 
detected in 15% of patients. There was a moderate correlation 
between PCCE and ileocolonoscopy for the assessment of 
disease severity. In a prospective study of 38 pediatric patients 
with CD, PCCE was compared to MRE and small intestine 
contrast ultrasonography (SICUS) [87]. The sensitivity of PCCE </p>

<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 30 </p>



<p>for detecting colonic inflammation was 89% and the specificity 
was 100%. In the small bowel, PCCE had 90% sensitivity 
and 94% specificity. The diagnostic accuracies of MRE and 
SICUS were slightly lower compared to PCCE, although the 
differences were not statistically significant. The tolerability 
of PCCE was superior compared to ileocolonoscopy, and the 
interobserver agreement was excellent (κ = 0.91). 
In a recent study, Leighton et al compared the diagnostic 
yield of the SBC capsule with ileocolonoscopy in 66 patients 
with clinically active CD [84]. The per-subject diagnostic 
yield for CD lesions was 83.3% for the SBC capsule and 69.7% 
for ileocolonoscopy (incremental yield 13.6%, 95% CI 2.6-
24.7%). A greater percentage of active lesions was detected in 
each evaluated segment by the SBC capsule as compared with 
ileocolonoscopy, and the overall per-segment diagnostic yield 
was 40.6% for the SBC capsule and 32.7% for ileocolonoscopy 
(incremental yield 7.9%, 95% CI 3.3-12.4%). 
Hence, preliminary data suggest that CE is a feasible diagnostic 
modality in patients examined for non-obstructive CD. 
Additional studies are warranted to evaluate panenteric CE for 
diagnosing CD and to compare the method with ileocolonoscopy 
and radiological modalities in terms of patient-experienced 
discomfort, complications and interobserver agreement. </p>

<p>Concluding remarks </p>

<p>CE has revolutionized the diagnosis and monitoring 
of small bowel CD. The procedure is patient-friendly and 
noninvasive and, compared to cross-sectional imaging, CE 
allows a direct and detailed evaluation of the entire small 
bowel mucosa with a high sensitivity for the earliest lesions 
of CD. Today, CE is the leading modality for visualizing the 
small bowel in suspected CD, and validated activity indices 
are available for the follow up of patients with established CD. 
CE of the entire gastrointestinal tract was recently introduced 
as a new diagnostic approach, and preliminary data show 
high sensitivity, specificity, interobserver agreement and 
tolerability compared to ileocolonoscopy. There are important 
limitations, however, of which capsule retention is the main 
concern. Furthermore, a diagnostic criterion for CD has never 
been validated and lesions detected by CE are not specific for 
CD. Hence, concern has been raised about a low specificity 
compared to other diagnostic modalities. Future studies 
should address important questions about the optimal bowel 
preparation for small bowel and panenteric CE, the selection 
of patients with suspected or known CD, the optimal reading 
protocol and the diagnostic performance of panenteric CE 
compared to cross-sectional imaging. </p>



<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 30 </p>

<p>Capsule endoscopy in Crohn's disease 177 </p>



<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 30 </p>





</text></tei>