<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5247570" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A B S T R A C T </p>

<p>N-acetyl serotonin (NAS) as a melatonin precursor has neuroprotective actions. Nonetheless, it is not clarified 
how NAS protects neuronal cells against oxidative stress. Recently, we have reported that N-palmitoyl 
serotonins possessed properties of antioxidants and neuroprotection. Based on those, we hypothesized that 
NAS, a N-acyl serotonin, may have similar actions in oxidative stress-induced neuronal cells, and examined the 
effects of NAS based on in vitro and in vivo tests. NAS dose-dependently inhibited oxidative stress-induced cell 
death in HT-22 cells. Moreover, NAS suppressed glutamate-induced apoptosis by suppressing expression of 
AIF, Bax, calpain, cytochrome c and cleaved caspase-3, whereas it enhanced expression of Bcl-2. Additionally, 
NAS improved phosphorylation of tropomyosin-related kinase receptor B (TrkB) and cAMP response element-
binding protein (CREB) as well as expression of brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), whereas the 
inclusion of each inhibitor of JNK, p38 or Akt neutralized the neuroprotective effect of NAS, but not that of 
ERK. Meanwhile, NAS dose-dependently reduced the level of reactive oxygen species, and enhanced the level of 
glutathione in glutamate-treated HT-22 cells. Moreover, NAS significantly increased expression of heme 
oxygenase-1, NAD(P)H quinine oxidoreductase-1 and glutamate-cysteine ligase catalytic subunit as well as 
nuclear translocation of NF-E2-related factor-2. Separately, NAS at 30 mg/kg suppressed scopolamine-induced 
memory impairment and cell death in CA1 and CA3 regions in mice. In conclusion, NAS shows actions of 
antioxidant and anti-apoptosis by activating TrkB/CREB/BDNF pathway and expression of antioxidant 
enzymes in oxidative stress-induced neurotoxicity. Therefore, such effects of NAS may provide the information 
for the application of NAS against neurodegenerative diseases. </p>

<p>Alzheimer's disease, one of the neurodegenerative diseases, is 
induced by accumulation of amyloid β-peptides in neuronal cells [1]. 
In early stage, patients of Alzheimer's disease have memory impair-
ment clinically [1]. Besides, the accumulation of amyloid β-peptides in 
neuronal cells is known as generating elevation of reactive oxygen 
species (ROS) [1]. Consequently, oxidative stress leads to cell death in 
neuronal cells [2]. Therefore, the regulation of ROS generation is very 
important to prevent or treat Alzheimer's disease. Meanwhile, gluta-</p>

<p>mate (PubChem CID: 611) treatment of neuronal cells is known to 
cause generation of ROS through receptor-mediated excitotoxicity [3] 
or non-receptor-mediated cytotoxicity [2]. Therefore, the glutamate 
treatment for in intro assay is commonly used for screening antiox-
idant activity of a novel drug candidate in neuronal cells. Scopolamine 
(PubChem CID: 5184) is known as an antagonist of muscarinic 
acetylcholine receptor [4], and causing memory impairment in rodents 
[5,6] and humans [7]. In addition, scopolamine induces oxidative 
stress in brain [8], and reduces formation of brain-derived neuro-
trophic factor (BDNF) in neuronal cells [9]. Therefore, administration </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.redox.2016.12.034 
Received 7 October 2016; Received in revised form 27 December 2016; Accepted 29 December 2016 </p>

<p>⁎ Correspondence to: Department of Food and Nutrition, Chungnam National University, 99 Daehak-ro, Yuseong-gu, Daejeon 34134, Republic of Korea. </p>

<p>1 These authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>E-mail address: mrkim@cnu.ac.kr (M.R. Kim). </p>

<p>Abbreviations: AIF, Apoptosis-inducing factor; Akt, Protein kinase B; Bax, Bcl-2-associated X protein; Bcl-2, B-cell lymphoma 2; BDNF, Brain-derived neurotrophic factor; calpain, 
Ca 
2+ -dependent, non-lysosomal cysteine protease; CREB, cAMP response element-binding protein; DCFDA, 2, 7-Dichlorofluorescein diacetate; ERK, Extracellular signal-regulated </p>

<p>kinase 1/2; GCLC, Glutamate-cysteine ligase catalytic subunit; GSH, Glutathione; HO-1, Heme oxygenase-1; JNK, c-Jun N-terminal kinase 1/2; MAPK, Mitogen-activated protein 
kinase; NAS, N-acetyl serotonin; NQO-1, NAD(P)H quinine oxidoreductase-1; Nrf2, NF-E2-related factor-2; ROS, Reactive oxygen species; TrkB, Tropomyosin-related kinase receptor B </p>

<p>Redox Biology 11 (2017) 592-599 </p>

<p>Available online 06 January 2017 
2213-2317/ © 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/BY-NC-ND/4.0/). </p>

<p>MARK </p>

<p>of scopolamine for in vivo experiment is generally used as a model of 
memory impairment for Alzheimer's disease. 
N-acetyl serotonin (NAS; PubChem CID: 903) as an endogenous N-
acyl serotonin is better known as a precursor of melatonin [10], is 
produced from serotonin by serotonin N-acetyltransferase (EC 
2.3.1.87) [11], and is converted to melatonin by hydroxyindole-O-
methyltransferase (EC 2.1.1.4) in pineal gland [12] and retina cells 
[13]. NAS is known to possess stronger antioxidant activity than 
melatonin [14]. Recently, there have been reports that NAS can protect 
organ-resident cells against ischemic injury in intestine [15] and brain 
[16]. Besides, NAS leads to activation of tropomyosin-related kinase </p>

<p>receptor B (TrkB) in neuronal cells [17]. Moreover, NAS is included in 
a library of 1040 FDA-approved compounds collected by the National 
Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke [16]. Nonetheless, it is 
still not clarified how NAS protects neuronal cells against oxidative 
stress. 
Recently, we found that N-acyl serotonins possessed properties of 
excellent antioxidants and neuroprotection in glutamate-treated neu-
ronal cells [2] and scopolamine-treated mice [9]. Although N-palmitoyl 
serotonin at submicromolar range possessed exceptional neuroprotec-
tive properties, it was not tested clinically. Therefore, it was hypothe-
sized that NAS might have similar properties of N-palmitoyl serotonin. 
In this study, we investigated antioxidant activity and neuroprotective 
action of NAS in glutamate-treated HT-22 cells, a murine hippocam-
pus-derived cell line [18], and scopolamine-induced memory impair-
ment in mice. Finally, we propose novel molecular mechanisms for 
neuroprotective properties of NAS using immunoblotting analysis, and 
hematoxylin and eosin (H &amp; E) staining assay. Herein, we report how 
NAS has neuroprotective properties in oxidative stress-induced apop-
tosis and scopolamine-induced memory impairment. Therefore, such 
effects of NAS may provide further information for the application of 
NAS as a therapeutic or preventive agent for neurodegenerative 
diseases. </p>

<p>2. Material and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Materials </p>

<p>DMEM, 1× PBS and 1× TBS were purchased from Welgene, Inc. 
(Gyeongsan, Gyeongbuk, Korea). FBS, 0.25% trypsin-EDTA, penicillin-
streptomycin and 2,7-dichlorofluorescein diacetate (DCFDA) were 
obtained from Invitrogen (Carlsbad, CA, USA). NAS, scopolamine, 
K252a (a TrkB inhibitor; PubChem CID: 9912412), PD98059 (an 
extracellular signal-regulated kinase 1/2 (ERK) inhibitor; PubChem 
CID: 4713), SP600125 (a c-Jun N-terminal kinase 1/2 (JNK) inhibitor; 
PubChem CID: 8515), SB203580 (a p38 inhibitor; PubChem CID: 
176155) and MK-2206 (an protein kinase B (Akt) inhibitor; PubChem 
CID: 24964624) were purchased from Cayman Chemical Company, 
Inc. (Ann Arbor, MI, USA). EZ-Cytox cell viability assay kit was 
obtained from DAEILLAB SERVICE Co. (Seoul, Korea). Specific 
antibodies against apoptosis-inducing factor (AIF), Bcl-2-associated 
X protein (Bax), B-cell lymphoma 2 (Bcl-2), Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-dependent, non-
lysosomal cysteine protease (calpain), caspase-3, cleaved caspase-3, 
TrkB, phospho-TrkB, phospho-cAMP response element-binding pro-
tein (CREB), heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1), glutamate-cysteine ligase 
catalytic subunit (GCLC), NF-E2-related factor-2 (Nrf2) and β-actin 
as well as a horseradish peroxidase-conjugated IgG secondary antibody </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Inhibitory effect of N-acetyl serotonin on oxidative stress-induced cytotoxicity in HT-22 cells. HT-22 cells were seeded on a 96 well-plate, and then incubated for 24 h. The above 
cells were preincubated with or without NAS (50-500 μM) for 30 min before glutamate challenge (5 mM) or hydrogen peroxide (500 μM). After 12 h, cell viability was measured as 
described in materials and methods. Data are the mean ± SD values of triple determinations. *P &lt; 0.05 and **P &lt; 0.01 versus Glutamate-treated group. A, glutamate; B, hydrogen 
peroxide. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Inhibitory effects of N-acetyl serotonin on glutamate-induced apoptosis and 
depolarization of mitochondrial membrane in HT-22 cells. HT-22 cells were seeded on a 
60 mm dish, and then incubated for 24 h. The above cells were preincubated with or 
without NAS before glutamate challenge. After 12 h, apoptosis or mitochondrial 
membrane potential were analyzed by flow cytometry as described in materials and 
methods. A, apoptosis; B, mitochondrial potential. </p>

<p>J.-M. Yoo et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 592-599 </p>



<p>were purchased from Cell signaling Technology, Inc. (Danvers, MA, 
USA). Specific antibodies against NAD(P)H quinine oxidoreductase-1 
(NQO-1) and cytochrome c were obtained from Abcam, Inc. 
(Cambridge, UK). A specific antibody against BDNF was purchased 
from Santa cruz biotechnology, Inc. (Dallas, TX, USA). Muse </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>Annexin V &amp; Dead Cell Assay Kit and Muse 
TM Mitopotential Assay </p>

<p>Kit were obtained from Merck Millipore, Inc. (Darmstadt, Germany). 
All other chemicals used in this study were analytical grade. </p>

<p>2.2. Animals </p>

<p>ICR mice (5-6 weeks, 25-30 g), known as Swiss CD-1 mice [19], 
were procured from Dehan Biolink Co. (Eumseong, Korea), and housed 
in cages (3 mice per cage) under specific pathogen-free condition (21-
24°C; 40-60% relative humidity) with a 12-h light/dark cycle, and free 
access to standard rodent food (Sangyang Co., Osen, Korea) and water. 
All behavioral experiments were carried out in a room adjacent to the 
same ambient conditions, conducted according to the Guide for Care 
and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Research Council (NRC, 
1996), and approved by the Committee of Animal Care and Experiment 
of Chungnam National University, Korea (CNU-00698). </p>

<p>2.3. Behavior tests </p>

<p>2.3.1. Morris water maze test 
Morris water maze test was performed according to the method 
reported previously [9]. One hour before the trial, mice were admini-
strated with NAS (1 or 30 mg/kg, p.o.). After 3 days, the mice were 
intra peritoneally administrated with scopolamine (2 mg/kg) following 
the treatment with NAS. The dose of NAS was determined in 
consideration of the effective concentration of its in vitro data. </p>

<p>2.3.2. Passive avoidance test 
The passive avoidance test was performed following the method </p>

<p>reported previously [9]. One hour before the acquisition trial, mice 
were orally administrated with NAS prior to the administration with 
scopolamine. </p>

<p>2.4. Hematoxylin and eosin staining assay </p>

<p>The H &amp; E staining assay was performed following the previous 
method [9]. Mice were anesthetized, and perfused with ice-cold PBS 
and then ice-cold 2% paraformaldehyde solution in PBS (pH 7.4). 
Isolated brains were stored in 2% paraformaldehyde solution for one 
week, and then embedded in paraffin. Serial coronal sections (4 μm 
thickness) including dorsal hippocampus were cutted off with a rotary 
microtome (Leica RM 2165, Leica Microsystems Ltd., Wetzlar, 
Germany). Paraffin-embedded sections of brains were deparaffinized 
and rehydrated. After H &amp; E staining, the histopathological changes 
were assessed under a light microscope (400-fold magnification). </p>

<p>2.5. Cell culture </p>

<p>HT-22 cells were maintained in DMEM medium with 10% FBS, 100 
units/ml of penicillin and 100 μg/ml of streptomycin at 37°C in a 
humidified atmosphere of 5% CO 2 . Passages 3-10 of the HT-22 cells 
were used in this study. All the experiments include a vehicle control 
group containing 0.1% DMSO. </p>

<p>2.6. Cell viability assay </p>

<p>Cell viability was evaluated following the previous method [2]. HT-
22 cells were preincubated with or without NAS (50-500 μM) 30 min 
prior to glutamate treatment. After 12 h, cell viability was assessed 
using EZ-Cytox cell viability assay kit according to the manufacturer's 
instruction. The absorbance at 450 nm was measured by a microplate 
reader (DU650, Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Effects of N-acetyl serotonin on expression of anti-or pro-apoptotic factors and activation of TrkB, CREB or BDNF. HT-22 cells were incubated with glutamate in the presence or 
absence of NAS for 12 h. The expression of Bcl-2, Bax, AIF, calpain, cytochrome c (Cyto C), cleaved caspase-3 (CleaCas-3), phospho-TrkB, TrkB, phospho-CREB, BDNF or β-actin was 
determined as described in materials and methods. Similar results were obtained in three independent experiments. *P &lt; 0.05 and **P &lt; 0.01 versus Glutamate-treated group. A, Bcl-2, 
Bax, AIF, calpain, cytochrome c and cleaved caspase-3; B, p-TrkB, TrkB, p-CREB and BDNF. </p>

<p>J.-M. Yoo et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 592-599 </p>



<p>2.7. Flow cytometry analysis </p>

<p>Apoptotic bodies and mitochondrial membrane potential were 
analyzed following the previous method [20]. HT-22 cells were 
preincubated with or without NAS before glutamate challenge. After 
12 h, all the cells were harvested, and then washed with 1× PBS twice. 
Mitochondrial membrane potential and apoptosis were measured using 
Muse 
TM Mitopotential Assay Kit and Muse 
TM Annexin V &amp; Dead Cell </p>

<p>Assay Kit, respectively according to the manufacturer's instruction. 
Stained cells were analyzed by a flow cytometer (Muse 
TM Cell Analyzer, </p>

<p>Merck Millipore, Inc.) with Muse 1.1.2 analysis software. </p>

<p>2.8. Measurement of Intracellular reactive oxygen species level </p>

<p>The intracellular ROS level was measured following the previous 
method [2]. Glutamate-treated HT-22 cells were stained with 10 μM 
DCFDA in Hank's balanced salt solution for 30 min in the darkness, 
and then the fluorescence was measured by a microplate reader 
(Beckman Coulter DTX 880 Multimode Detector, Brea, CA, USA) at 
an excitation wavelength of 485 nm and an emission wavelength of 
525 nm. </p>

<p>2.9. Measurement of Intracellular glutathione </p>

<p>The intracellular glutathione (GSH) levels were measured following 
the previous method [2]. Supernatants separated from cell homoge-
nates were analyzed for GSH level using a Quanticrom Glutathione 
Assay Kit obtained from BioAssay Systems (Hayward, CA, USA) 
according to the manufacturer's protocol. </p>

<p>2.10. Extraction of Nuclear and Cytosolic protein </p>

<p>Nuclear and cytosolic proteins were performed following a process 
reported previously [2] with a Nuclear Extraction Kit from Cayman 
Chemical Company, Inc. (Ann Arbor, MI, USA). Nuclear and cytosolic 
proteins were fractionated according to the instructions of the manu-
facturer. Briefly, cells were harvested and centrifuged (300×g, 5 min) at 
4°C. The cell pellets were mixed with hypotonic buffer containing 
phosphatase and protease inhibitors. After 10 min incubation on ice, 
10% Nonidet P-40 Assay Reagent was added to the cells. Nuclei were 
recovered by centrifugation (14,000×g, 30 sec), and the supernatant 
was kept as cytoplasmic extract at −80°C until use. The nuclei were 
extracted with Nuclear Extraction Buffer for 30 min on ice. Insoluble </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Effect of N-acetyl serotonin on ROS generation, glutathione deprivation, antioxidant enzymes and Nrf2 translocation. Experimental proceedings were described in Fig. 1 or 
Fig. 3. The levels of intracellular ROS and GSH were measured as described in materials and methods. Data are the mean ± SD values of triple determinations. Separately, the expression 
of HO-1, NQO-1, GCLC, Nrf2, Lamin B or β-actin was determined as described in materials and methods. Similar results were obtained in three independent experiments. *P &lt; 0.05 and 
**P &lt; 0.01 versus Glutamate-treated group. A, ROS; B, GSH; C, HO-1, NQO-1 and GCLC; D, nuclear and cytosolic Nrf2. </p>

<p>J.-M. Yoo et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 592-599 </p>



<p>material was removed by centrifugation (14,000×g, 10 min). Finally, 
the supernatant was used as a nuclear extract. </p>

<p>2.11. Immunoblotting analysis </p>

<p>Immunoblotting analysis was evaluated following the previous 
method [2]. PVDF membranes including blotted proteins were visua-
lized by WEST One 
TM western blot detection system (iNtRON </p>

<p>Biotechnology, Inc, Gyeonggi-do, Korea). The level of target proteins 
was compared to that of a loading control (β-actin or non-phosphory-
lated proteins), and the results were expressed as a ratio of density of 
each protein identified by a protein standard size marker (BIOFACT, 
Daejeon, Korea). The relative density of the protein expression was 
quantitated by <rs id="software-1" type="software">Matrox Inspector</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 2.1</rs> for Windows; 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Matrox Electronic Systems Ltd.</rs>., Dorval, Quebec, Canada). </p>

<p>2.12. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The experimental results were listed as means ± SD for in vitro 
studies or SEM for in vivo studies. One-way ANOVA was used for 
multiple comparisons (<rs id="software-2" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 5.03</rs> for Windows, San 
Diego, CA, USA). If there was a significant variation between treated 
groups, the Dunnett's or Turkey's tests were applied. Differences at the 
*P &lt; 0.05 and **P &lt; 0.01 levels were considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Protective effect of N-acetyl serotonin on oxidative stress-induced 
apoptosis in HT-22 cells </p>

<p>NAS is known to have properties of antioxidant and neuroprotec-
tion [14-16]. In this regard, we investigated effect of NAS on glutamate 
or hydrogen peroxide-induced cell death in HT-22 cells. When HT-22 
cells were preincubated with NAS (50-500 μM) before glutamate 
challenge (5 mM), NAS dose-dependently inhibited glutamate-induced 
cell death in HT-22 cells, and NAS at 250 μM almost restored cell 
viability (Fig. 1a). Likewise, NAS protected neuronal cells from 
hydrogen peroxide-induced cytotoxicity (Fig. 1b). Moreover, NAS not 
only reduced apoptotic bodies (Fig. 2a), but also recovered mitochon-
drial membrane potential in glutamate-treated HT-22 cells (Fig. 2b). 
Based on these results, it is suggested that NAS possesses neuropro-
tective action against oxidative stress-mediated apoptosis in neuronal 
cells. </p>

<p>3.2. Regulatory effects of N-acetyl serotonin on expression of pro-
apoptotic factors and activation of TrkB/CREB/BDNF pathway </p>

<p>Since we found that NAS exerted anti-apoptotic action, we further 
investigated effect of NAS on expression of apoptosis-related factors 
and activation of TrkB/CREB/BDNF pathway in glutamate-treated HT-</p>

<p>Fig. 5. Effects of inhibitors of intermediate proteins on cell viability and nuclear translocation of Nrf2. HT-22 cells were preincubated with or without N-acetyl serotonin in combination 
with each inhibitor of intermediate proteins for 30 min before glutamate challenge. After 12 h, cell viability was measured as described in materials and methods. Data are the mean ± SD 
values of triple determinations. Separately, HT-22 cells were preincubated with or without N-acetyl serotonin and MK-2206 (5 μM) for 30 min before glutamate challenge. After 2 h, the 
expression of Nrf2 or Lamin B was determined as described in materials and methods. Similar results were obtained in three independent experiments. *P &lt; 0.05 and **P &lt; 0.01, or #P &lt; 
0.05 and ##P &lt; 0.01 versus Glutamate-treated group, or glutamate with NAS-treated group, respectively. A, cell viability; B, nuclear and cytosolic Nrf2. </p>

<p>J.-M. Yoo et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 592-599 </p>



<p>22 cells. As shown in Fig. 3a, NAS dose-dependently reduced expres-
sion of pro-apoptotic factors such as Bax, calpain, cytochome c, cleaved 
caspase-3 and AIF while it restored the level of Bcl-2, an anti-apoptotic 
factor. Especially, NAS at 500 μM completely blocked all the pro-
apoptotic factors, and recovered Bcl-2 level. In addition, NAS recovered 
phosphorylation of TrkB and CREB as well as expression of BDNF 
(Fig. 3b). Interestingly, the compound at 500 μM also restored the 
levels of p-TrkB or p-CREB to control group. Overall, it is suggested 
that NAS protects neuronal cells against oxidative stress-induced 
apoptosis by regulating both expression of apoptosis-related factors 
and activation of TrkB/CREB/BDNF pathway. </p>

<p>3.3. Inhibitory effect of N-acetyl serotonin on the generation of 
reactive oxygen species induced by glutamate </p>

<p>After we found that NAS regulated the expression of apoptosis-
related factors and the activation of TrkB/CREB/BDNF pathway, we 
turned to the effect of NAS on the generation of ROS in glutamate-
treated HT-22 cells because NAS is known as possessing antioxidant 
activity [14-16]. As shown in Fig. 4, NAS dramatically reduced ROS 
level at ≥50 μM (Fig. 4a), and significantly recovered GSH level at 
≥100 μM (Fig. 4b) in glutamate-treated HT-22 cells. Concerning such 
effect of NAS, we further investigated the effect of NAS on expression of 
antioxidant enzymes such as HO-1, NQO-1 and GCLC. As shown in 
Fig. 4c, NAS dose-dependently enhanced the expression of the enzymes 
at 12 h. Meanwhile, in early stage (2 h), it enhanced nuclear transloca-
tion of Nrf2 while decreasing the Nrf2 level in cytosol (Fig. 4d). It is 
suggested that NAS can promote the expression of antioxidant enzymes 
by activating nuclear translocation of Nrf2. Consequently, NAS pos-
sesses strong antioxidant activity. </p>

<p>3.4. Effect of N-acetyl serotonin on activation of intermediate 
proteins </p>

<p>Since we observed that NAS regulated expression of antioxidant 
enzymes by translocating Nrf2 into nucleus, we were interested in the 
intermediate protein related to nuclear translocation of Nrf2. Thus, we 
further examined effect of NAS on activation of intermediate proteins 
such as ERK, JNK, p38 or Akt, because the activation of the proteins is 
known to be related to Nrf2 translocation in neuronal cells [2]. When 
HT-22 cells were preincubated with NAS in combination with each 
inhibitor of ERK (PD98059), JNK (SP600125), p38 (SB203580) or Akt 
(MK-2206) before glutamate treatment, SP600125, SB203580 or MK-
2206 significantly neutralized neuroprotective effect of NAS, but not 
PD98059 (Fig. 5a). Especially, MK-2206 among those inhibitors 
remarkably reversed the action of NAS. Moreover, it significantly 
reduced nuclear translocation of Nrf2 induced by NAS, and increased 
the levels of cytosolic Nrf2 (Fig. 5b). Collectively, these results suggest 
that the activation of Akt is closely associated with nuclear transloca-
tion of Nrf2 in neuronal cells. Therefore, NAS can regulate expression 
of antioxidant enzymes mainly through activation of Akt/Nrf2 path-
way. </p>

<p>3.5. Protective effect of N-acetyl serotonin on memory and neuronal 
cells in scopolamine-treated mice </p>

<p>Finally, after we demonstrated that NAS possessed neuroprotective 
properties by activating BDNF/TrkB/CREB pathway, and promoting 
Akt/Nrf2/antioxidant enzymes pathway in in vitro tests, we evaluated 
the action of NAS in scopolamine-induced memory impairment model, 
an animal model of Alzheimer's disease [5,6]. When mice were orally 
administrated with NAS (1 or 30 mg/kg) 30 min prior to scopolamine </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Protective effect of N-acetyl serotonin on memory in scopolamine-treated mice. Mice were orally administrated with NAS (1 or 30 mg/kg) before scopolamine treatment (2 mg/ 
kg, intraperitoneally). After 1 h, the animals were tested for passive avoidance (Acquisition trial) or Morris water maze. Data are the mean ± SEM values of sextuple determinations. **P 
&lt; 0.01 versus Scopolamine-treated group. A, Escape latency time; B, number of platform area crossing; C, Latency time. </p>

<p>J.-M. Yoo et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 592-599 </p>



<p>challenge, NAS at 30 mg/kg not only reduced the escape latency time 
(Fig. 6a), but also improved the number of platform (Fig. 6b) as well as 
the latency time (Fig. 6c) in scopolamine-induced memory impairment 
in mice. Moreover, NAS at the same dose enhanced the number of 
neuronal cells in CA1 (Fig. 7a) and CA3 regions (Fig. 7b). Taken 
together, NAS exerts neuroprotective action by protecting neuronal 
cells in the animal model of Alzheimer's disease. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>NAS, which is known to be a melatonin precursor [10] is an </p>

<p>endogeneous N-acyl serotonin, and possesses some bioactive effects 
such as antioxidant activity [14], anti-ischemia [15,16] and TrkB 
activation [17]. Nonetheless, the effect of NAS on antioxidant enzymes 
in neuronal cells is unknown. Recently, we reported that N-acyl 
serotonins exerted neuroprotection against oxidative stress-induced 
cytotoxicity by activating antioxidant enzymes [2]. Above all, N-
palmitoyl serotonin was known to possess strong antioxidant activity. 
However, its clinical application is limited because it has been not 
tested clinically yet. Instead, we turned our interest to the action of 
NAS, because NAS is one of N-acyl serotonin, and one of the 1040 
FDA-approved compounds [16]. In this respect, NAS may be used for </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Protective effect of N-acetyl serotonin on neuronal cells in hippocampal CA1 and CA3 regions of scopolamine-treated mice. Experimental proceedings were described in Fig. 6. 
Neuronal cells staining in tissue sections were determined as described in materials and methods. Similar results were obtained in three independent experiments. **P &lt; 0.01 versus 
Scopolamine-treated group. A, CA1 region; B, CA3 region. </p>

<p>J.-M. Yoo et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 592-599 </p>



<p>clinical study for neurodegenerative diseases. 
Glutamate cytotoxicity in nerve cells is associated with ROS 
generation through receptor-mediated excitotoxicity or non-receptor-
mediated oxidative toxicity [2,3], and is involved in neuronal apoptosis 
including caspase-dependent and independent signaling cascades 
[21,22]. In this respect, it was supposed that the neuroprotective 
action of NAS might be related to regulation of pro-apoptotic factors 
induced by glutamate in neuronal cells. In support of this, NAS not only 
reduced formation of apoptotic cells, but also restored mitochondrial 
membrane potential by regulating pro-apoptotic factors such as Bax, 
calpain, cytochrome c, cleaved caspase-3 and AIF as well as anti-
apoptotic factor such as Bcl-2 in glutamate-treated neuronal cells. All 
these results support the above hypothesis. 
Concerning neuroprotective action of NAS, one possible mechanism 
may be related to TrkB/CREB/BDNF pathway. In support of this, NAS 
is known to induce TrkB activation [17] and BDNF formation [23]. In 
addition, BDNF is known to activate Trk receptors, and to protect 
neuronal cells from oxidative stress-induced cell death [24-26]. 
Moreover, we found that N-palmitoyl serotonin promoted activation 
of TrkB and formation of BDNF in glutamate-treated neuronal cells 
(Unpublished data) as well as in scopolamine-treated mice [9]. 
Actually, in this study, NAS also led to the activation of TrkB/CREB/ 
BDNF pathway in glutamate-treated HT-22 cells, as well as the 
improvement of memory and the increase in the number of neuronal 
cells in scopolamine-treated mice. Based on these, it is suggested that 
an important mechanism for neuroprotection of NAS may be due to the 
activation of TrkB/CREB/BDNF pathway in neuronal cells. 
Another possible mechanism for neuroprotection of NAS may be 
associated with the regulation of antioxidant enzymes. In support of 
this, NAS is known to possess antioxidant activity in in vitro and in 
vivo tests [14-16]. Consistent with this, we reported that N-acyl 
serotonins reduced ROS generation, and enhanced expression of 
antioxidant enzymes in neuronal cells and the brain tissue of mice 
[2,9]. Such effect of N-acyl serotonins is concerned with nuclear 
translocation of Nrf2 [2]. In the present study, NAS not only inhibited 
ROS generation, but also enhanced expression of antioxidant enzymes 
through activation of Akt/Nrf2 pathway in neuronal cells. Therefore, it 
is suggested that NAS may activate expression of antioxidant enzymes 
mainly through activation of Akt/Nrf2 pathway. Such effect of NAS is 
another important mechanism for its neuroprotective actions, although 
the expression of antioxidant enzymes by NAS is not clarified in the 
relation with TrkB signaling pathway. Although NAS shows a neuro-
protective action similar to that of N-palmitoyl serotonin, the effective 
concentration of NAS is much higher than that of N-palmitoyl 
serotonin. Thus, there may be a great difference in the fate of NAS. 
In this respect, the further study on the metabolism or pharmacoki-
netics of N-acyl serotonins may be necessary to reveal the efficacy of 
NAS and other N-acyl serotonins in in vivo system. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>The present study demonstrates that NAS exerts neuroprotective 
actions by regulating activation of both TrkB/CREB/BDNF pathway 
and Akt/Nrf2/antioxidant enzymes pathway. These findings may reveal 
a new feature for the mechanism of NAS in preventing neuronal cells 
against oxidative stress-induced cytotoxicity. Such effects may provide 
further information regarding the application of NAS with BDNF-
promoting and antioxidant enzyme-promoting actions as a neuropro-
tective agent. Further, other animal models of neurodegenerative 
diseases may be required to confirm the neuroprotective actions of 
NAS with BDNF-promoting and antioxidant enzyme-promoting ac-
tions for potential clinical purpose. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Research Foundation of 
Korea (NRF) grant funded by the Korea government (MSIP) 
(2014R1A2A2A04005236). </p>



<p>J.-M. Yoo et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 592-599 </p>



</text></tei>