<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5214516" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Self-management is becoming increasingly important in COPD health care although 
it remains difficult to embed self-management into routine clinical care. The implementation 
of self-management is understood as a complex interaction at the level of patient, health care 
provider (HCP), and health system. Nonetheless there is still a poor understanding of the 
barriers and effective facilitators. Comprehension of these determinants can have significant 
implications in optimizing self-management implementation and give further directions for the 
development of self-management interventions. Data were collected among COPD patients 
(N=46) and their HCPs (N=11) in three general practices and their collaborating affiliated 
hospitals. Mixed methods exploration of the data was conducted and collected by interviews, 
video-recorded consultations (N=50), and questionnaires on consultation skills. Influencing 
determinants were monitored by 1) interaction and communication between the patient and HCP, 
2) visible and invisible competencies of both the patient and the HCP, and 3) degree of embed-
ding self-management into the health care system. Video observations showed little emphasis 
on effective behavioral change and follow-up of given lifestyle advice during consultation. 
A strong presence of COPD assessment and monitoring negatively affects the patient-centered 
communication. Both patients and HCPs experience difficulties in defining personalized goals. 
The satisfaction of both patients and HCPs concerning patient centeredness during consultation 
was measured by the patient feedback questionnaire on consultation skills. The patients scored 
high (84.3% maximum score) and differed from the HCPs (26.5% maximum score). Although 
the patient-centered approach accentuating self-management is one of the dominant paradigms 
in modern medicine, our observations show several influencing determinants causing difficulties 
in daily practice implementation. This research is a first step unravelling the determinants of 
self-management leading to a better understanding. 
According to the World Health Organization, COPD is listed among the top three 
leading causes of death in 2030. 
1 COPD is currently ranked sixth in the Dutch mortality 
ranking list. 
2,3 Because of the aging population, it is expected that the number of COPD 
patients will increase by 38% between 2005 and 2025. 
4 Apart from the expected 
loss in both years of life and health-related quality of life among many patients, this </p>

<p>Correspondence: Chantal F Hillebregt 
Jan van es Institute (JVeI), netherlands 
Expert Center Integrated Primary Care, 
Wisselweg 33, 1314 CB Almere, 
the netherlands 
Tel +31 36 767 0360 
email hillebregt77@gmail.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of COPD 
23 December 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>124 </p>

<p>Hillebregt et al </p>

<p>development influences both the accessibility and afford-
ability of COPD care. Consequently, self-management is 
becoming increasingly more important, 
5 referring to the 
individual's ability to manage symptoms, treatment, physical 
and psychosocial consequences, and lifestyle changes inher-
ent in living with a chronic disease. 
6 Over the last decade, an 
increase is seen in general practice-based nurse specialists, 
improving consultation to chronic care patients, transferring 
knowledge of lifestyle awareness and optimized prevention. </p>

<p>7   Furthermore, a variety of (e-health) interventions and tools 
are available for COPD patients, supporting in handling 
symptoms, maintenance of physical functioning, and medi-
cal management. 
8 These self-management interventions are 
understood as all programs and techniques enabling patients 
to assume responsibility for managing one or more aspects of 
COPD. 
9 The majority of those interventions are based on the 
cognitive behavioral therapy 
10-15 increasing problem solving 
and gaining confidence in one's own ability to perform a 
particular behavior, called self-efficacy. </p>

<p>16   Another used model refers to the willingness and motiva-
tion of individuals to change behavior. 
17,18 Interventions based 
on this theory focus on exploring the motivation for behavior 
change and next adjusting the treatment to this. 
Although achieving behavior change is the ultimate goal, 
a most challenging task is influencing it. There are numerous 
determinants affecting health behavior and lifestyle, which 
can be explained by a complex interaction at the level of the 
patient, health care provider (HCP), health care system, and 
community. 
19,20 First, it is essential that patients feel sup-
ported in the clinical encounter, increase their motivation and 
self-efficacy preferably in an equal patient-HCP partnership 
making shared decisions possible. 
21 The patient's perspective 
is essential, and the role of the HCP shifts from a leading to a 
more coaching role during consultation. 
22 This commitment 
to equality in which there occurs a rearrangement of tasks and 
responsibilities is also called "patient empowerment". </p>

<p>23   Second, both the patients and the HCPs need competen-
cies to optimally interact during this encounter. Spencer and 
Spencer 
24 distinguish visible and less-visible underlying 
competencies indicating ways of behaving or thinking, which 
generalizes across a wide range of situations and endures for 
long period of time. Among these visible competencies are 
the degree of knowledge, general and communication skills 
of both patients and HCPs. Examples of less visible under-
lying competencies of both patients and HCPs are: beliefs 
(attitudes), motivation, values, motives, and personality 
characteristics. These can influence the consultation encoun-
ter to a large extent. The degree of self-efficacy can also be </p>

<p>seen as one of these invisible competencies. Within chronic 
disease management, it is seen as one of the most essential 
competencies to achieve behavioral change. </p>

<p>25,9   A third important mechanism empowering patients is 
the embedding of self-management in the organizational 
care process 
26 as understood according to the chronic care 
model. 
27,28 Because of the numerous health care professionals 
involved in COPD treatment in both primary care and 
hospital care, good cooperation and coordination between 
the patient and the various levels of health care are essential. 
Another less accentuated influencing organizational factor is 
the duration of the consultation time on self-management. 
Despite the many new developments, the wide range of 
available (e-health) tools and the efforts made by the patients 
and HCPs, accomplishing changes in lifestyle and optimal 
self-management, seem not feasible for everyone. This is 
evidenced by the high level of medication noncompliance, </p>

<p>29-33   the lower psychic well-being, and decreased quality of 
life, reported among people with a wide range of chronic 
diseases. 
34-38 Improving the patient's motivation must always 
be the first step in developing an intervention promoting 
self-management. 
39 Yet, this critical area of concern is often 
lacking in today's self-management interventions. 
40 More-
over, the implementation of (e-health) self-management 
interventions seems to be still having difficulties embedding 
into routine health care and normal standard care. 
41,42 While 
effectiveness has been demonstrated of using action plans in 
early detection of exacerbations, 
43,44 just a minority of 14% 
of the COPD patients in the Netherlands actually use them. 
The action plans are still highly focused on medical regimes 
and to a lesser extent on adapting lifestyle and setting up 
personal goals. 
45 Similar modest numbers apply to used 
motivational interviewing techniques during consultation by 
general practitioners and community nurses. 
46 There is still a 
poor understanding of both the effective facilitators as barriers 
concerning the implementation of self-management. A bet-
ter comprehension of these facilitators and barriers can have 
significant implications for the direction of further develop-
ment of self-management interventions and the optimization 
of the implementation of self-management in health care. 
In the current study, we adopted a mixed methods 
approach investigating possible effective facilitators and 
barriers for the implementation of self-management in both 
general practices and their affiliated hospitals. The focus of 
the study lied on the extension of self-management imple-
mentation and was affected by 
1. the interaction and "communication" between the patient 
and the HCP, </p>

<p>23,45   International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>Self-management barriers and facilitators among COPD patients </p>

<p>2. the visible and invisible "competencies" of both the 
patient and the HCP, </p>

<p>24   3. the degree of "self-management embedding" into the 
health care system. </p>

<p>19,27,26   Methods </p>

<p>The theoretical model is based on the chronic care model, 
providing a framework for understanding and addressing 
chronic illness care, whereas self-management is further 
explained according to the social cognitive behavioral 
theory. 
27,16 A model is used in identifying the numerous deter-
minants affecting health behavior and lifestyle. Influencing 
factors are subdivided at patient, HCP, health care system, 
and community level (Figure 1). 
47 Participants of the research 
were both patients and their HCPs of Dutch general practices 
and their affiliated outpatient lung clinics with a follow-up 
period of a year. Data were used from baseline question-
naires, interviews, and observations of consultations with 
patients and HCPs; collected sequentially in three different 
phases (exploratory, inventory, and feedback phase) accord-
ing to the three-dimensional typology of mixed methods 
designs (Figure 2). 
48 The study protocol was approved by 
the Medical Ethical Board of the University Medical Center 
Utrecht (UMC Utrecht) prior to commencement. </p>

<p>Participant selection and setting </p>

<p>General practices and outpatient clinics were recruited by 
contacting the medical director or highest responsible person 
asking to participate in the research. Three matching couples 
were formed based on their regional collaboration, each 
couple consisting of a general practice with their affiliated </p>

<p>hospital. The HCPs of the participating organizations 
recruited primary care patients and hospital outpatients 
according to the inclusion criteria doctor-diagnosed COPD, 
aged 18 years or older and willingness to participate. The 
HCPs informed the patients by telephone; subsequently 
detailed information about the study was sent by post. Written 
informed consent was obtained from every participant, and 
the research assistant double-checked the compliance with 
the study criteria. </p>

<p>Data collection and analysis </p>

<p>exploratory phase </p>

<p>Insight is gained of the perspectives of both patients and 
caregivers about possible influencing factors to promote and 
implement self-management in daily practice. The initially 
planned patient focus groups in each participating primary 
care and outpatient clinic were rescheduled into individual 
interviews, after one focus group of five persons was held. 
In the interviews, it was easier to elaborate on the topics. 
Ten caregivers with different professional backgrounds 
and 12 patients from primary care and outpatient clinics 
were purposively selected and participated in semistructured </p>

<p>Figure 1 Influencing factors of self-management. </p>

<p>Feedback phase </p>

<p>Inventory phase </p>

<p>Self-management </p>

<p>Primary health care 
Outpatient lung clinic </p>

<p>Focus group/interviews: 
patients (n=12); 
health care providers (n=10) </p>

<p>Questionnaire </p>

<p>Observations; 
consultations 
(n=24) </p>

<p>Feedback meetings 
Feedback meetings </p>

<p>Observation matrix </p>

<p>Literature 
research </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>Recommendations </p>

<p>Self-management </p>

<p>Questionnaire </p>

<p>Observations; 
consultations 
(n=26) </p>

<p>GPI 2A/2B </p>

<p>GPI 1 </p>

<p>GPI 3 </p>

<p>Outpatient clinic 1 </p>

<p>Outpatient clinic 3 </p>

<p>Outpatient clinic 2 </p>

<p>Exploration phase </p>

<p>Figure 2 Flowchart of research approach. 
Abbreviation: GPI, general practice institute. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>Hillebregt et al </p>

<p>interviews. All interviews were conducted by the same 
researcher using a topic list developed according to the prin-
ciples of Kvale. 
49 Recordings were transcribed verbatim by an 
independent transcription service and subsequently compared 
with the audio recordings for completeness and accuracy. 
Both content and thematic analyses were used based on the 
framework approach. 
50 Interviews were coded by two sepa-
rately working researchers with the use of the data analysis 
software of <rs type="software">Dedoose</rs>, a web-based program for mixed methods 
research. The top 9 most-coded key concepts (%) from both 
the patients and the HCPs were collected and compared. </p>

<p>Inventory phase </p>

<p>Influencing factors of implementing and promoting self-
management were observed in real-life settings by video-
taping consultations (N=50) obtained by 46 patients and 
11 HCPs (4 patients had a second consult) both from the 
participating general practices and their affiliated outpatient 
clinics. Perceived patient-centeredness during consultation 
was measured afterwards by both the patients and the HCPs 
by the validated 16-item (4-point scale) dyadic patient feed-
back questionnaire on consultation skills (PFC; Table 1). </p>

<p>51   The PFC questionnaire has two parallel versions: a patient 
feedback version and a HCP self-assessment version. </p>

<p>51   An observation matrix was used analyzing the video 
content of the consultations. Development of the matrix was </p>

<p>based on the most common-coded key concepts extracted from 
HCPs and patients' interviews in the exploratory phase, com-
bined with the foremost contemporary literature concerning 
self-management. Newman's subdivision of essential compo-
nents of self-management was used in "giving information", 
"behavior change", "maintaining behavior change", "enhanc-
ing social support", "managing emotions", "skills training", 
"enhancing communication skills", and "self-monitoring". </p>

<p>8   Selections of video clips were encoded in accordance with the 
observation matrix, using the analysis program Dedoose. 
Baseline demographic, clinical and contextual measures 
of the 46 patients and 11 HCPs were obtained by a self-
administered questionnaire, including the dyadic PFC. </p>

<p>51   Descriptive analyses were used to describe the character-
istics of the patients and HCPs, to calculate the mean PFC 
score per possible confounder, and to provide insight into 
the percentage of patients and HCPs who were fully satis-
fied with the consultation. Questions with a score of ,90% 
full satisfaction were used in extra analyses. Bivariate and 
multivariate logistic regression analyses were used to find any 
covariates that might explain the variance in PFC scores for 
the patients and HCPs. Dummies were created for employ-
ment status. All covariates were recoded into 2 classes, for 
example age ,70 years and age $70 years. The mean score 
on the PFC questionnaire was only calculated if a patient or 
HCP had answered 10 or more questions out of the 16. All 
data were analyzed in SPSS version 19. </p>

<p>Feedback phase </p>

<p>The results of the research were shared with participating 
patients and HCPs in five feedback meetings (two gen-
eral practices and three outpatient clinics). The responses 
and comments were integrated into the discussion of the 
research. </p>

<p>Results 
Patient and hCP characteristics </p>

<p>The characteristics of the studied group of patients and 
observed HCPs consultations are shown in Tables 2 and 3. 
A total of 60.9% patients were male, low-educated (50.0%), 
had an mean age of 70 years, and were mostly of Dutch 
ethnicity (93.5%). Most of the participating HCPs were 
women (81.8%) with a mean overall work experience in their 
profession of 20 years, compared with 9 years specifically 
in pulmonary medicine. </p>

<p>Qualitative results </p>

<p>Figures 3 and 4 represent the top 9 most coded key concepts 
(%; inner circle top 4) analyzed from the interviews with </p>

<p>Table 1 Patient feedback questionnaire on consultation skills; 
4-point scale (completely, mostly, a little, not at all) </p>

<p>1. To what extent was your main problem(s) discussed today? 
2. How satisfied were you with the discussion of your problem? 
To what extent did: 
3. The health care provider listen to what you had to say? 
4. The health care provider explain this problem to you? 
5. You and the health care provider discuss your respective roles? 
6. The health care provider explain the treatment? 
7. The health care provider explore how manageable this treatment 
would be for you? 
8. how well do you think your health care provider understood you 
today? 
9. To what extent did the health care provider discuss personal or 
family issues that might affect your health? 
10. To what extent was there an atmosphere of trust during the 
consultation? 
To what extent did: 
11. The health care provider show his/her concern? 
12. The health care provider invite you to ask all the questions you 
wanted to ask? 
13. The health care provider give you clear information and 
explanation? 
14. The health care provider act in a structured way? 
15. The health care provider give you new or better insight into your 
problem? 
16. The health care provider give you clear treatment advice? </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>127 </p>

<p>Self-management barriers and facilitators among COPD patients </p>

<p>the patients and the HCPs. The most coded concepts in 
common were "organization of care", "interventions self-
management", "perceived barriers to self-management", 
"patient, caregiver interaction", "communication", and 
"need for change in care". These concepts were used in 
developing the observational matrix, together with the essen-
tial self-management concepts according to Newman et al. </p>

<p>8   After analyzing the consultations using the observation 
matrix, simultaneous triangulation was applied with the </p>

<p>outcome of the analyzed interviews, 
52 resulting in the fol-
lowing seven main themes. </p>

<p>Use of self-management tools </p>

<p>Both professionals from the primary care and outpatient 
clinics stated not often using self-management interven-
tions. This corresponds with the observed consultations, 
revealing no use is made of an individual care plan, e-health 
application, or any other intervention, though there is a desire 
among some organizations to apply e-health applications in 
the nearby future. Although the patients have heard the pos-
sibility of using e-health applications, not many actually use 
it for several reasons. Some patients say they are too old to 
learn new things. Some have tried but found the confrontation 
with their disease unpleasant, having to log into the e-health 
application daily. </p>

<p>Organization of health care </p>

<p>Participating general practices and outpatient clinics had 
not yet imbedded self-management at the organizational 
level supported by an integrated approach, such as a 
COPD program. However, some transmural agreements 
were made between organizations concerning the refer-
ral of patients or the use of a uniform referral form. The 
majority of the participating organizations had a special-
ized COPD consultation service in both primary care and 
outpatient clinics. 
Patients did not elaborate much about the organization 
of health care, but the patients who did were positive about 
the collaboration between the general practitioner and the 
pulmonologist. </p>

<p>Consultation structure </p>

<p>The focus of the consultations accentuated on information 
and knowledge exchange, where controlling and monitoring 
health-related outcomes were emphasized. We observed 
no difference between primary care and outpatient clinics, 
(pulmonary) physicians, nurse practitioners, or community 
nurses. Aspects of changing lifestyle were discussed thor-
oughly by nurse practitioners and community nurses, in a 
lesser extent observed by physicians. The degree of shared 
decision making is low; the HCPs had a proactive role during 
consultations. Some HCPs continue their own consultation 
structure without considering the type of questions patients 
may have. Others adapt their structure and topics according 
to the patients' input. 
Patients stress the importance of the HCP giving per-
sonal attention in an atmosphere where there is enough time 
taken for the person beside the disease. Patients indicate that </p>

<p>Table 2 Patients' social and demographic characteristics (N=46) </p>

<p>Patients' characteristics 
Patients </p>

<p>Institute, n (%) 
general practice 1 
3 (6.5) 
general practice 2a 
6 (13.0) 
general practice 2B 
4 (8.7) 
general practice 3 
9 (19.6) 
Outpatient clinic 1 
9 (19.6) 
Outpatient clinic 2 
8 (17.4) 
Outpatient clinic 3 
7 (15.2) 
gender, n (%) 
Male 
28 (60.9) 
Female 
18 (39.1) 
Age in years, mean (range) 
70 (53-87) 
Duration of disease in years, mean (range) 
6.3 (0.2-20) 
CCQ score, mean (range) 
1.9 (0.3-4.7) 
gOlD scale, n (%) 
gOlD 1 
10 (21.7) 
gOlD 2 
18 (39.1) 
gOlD 3 
12 (26.1) 
GOLD 4 
5 (10.9) 
Missing data 
1 (2.2) 
employment status, n (%) 
Working 
9 (19.6) 
retired 
22 (47.8) 
Not working, not retired 
13 (28.3) 
Missing data 
2 (4.3) 
Marital situation, n (%) 
Single 
15 (32.6) 
Living together 
29 (63.0) 
Missing data 
2 (4.3) 
ethnicity, n (%) 
Dutch 
43 (93.5) 
Missing data 
3 (6.5) 
exercise, n (%) 
less than 30 minutes per day 
7 (15.2) 
30 minutes per day 
10 (21.7) 
More than 30 minutes per day 
26 (56.5) 
Missing data 
3 (6.5) 
educational level, n (%) 
none 
2 (4.3) 
elementary school or low vocational education 
23 (50.0) 
secondary school or intermediate vocational education 9 (19.6) 
Higher vocational education or university 
10 (21.7) 
Missing data 
2 (4.3) 
Support from caregiver, n (%) 
Poor support 
3 (6.5) 
Moderate support 
8 (17.4) 
support 
6 (13.0) 
good support 
16 (34.8) 
Missing data 
13 (28.3) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CCQ, Clinical COPD Questionnaire; gOlD, global Initiative for 
Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>128 </p>

<p>Hillebregt et al </p>

<p>they appreciate the information and advice given during 
consultation. </p>

<p>Self-management components </p>

<p>Compared to the various essential components of self-
management 
8 during consultations, much attention is given 
to the components: "information provision", "training 
skills", and "self-monitoring". Other components, such 
as "maintaining behavior change", "social support", and </p>

<p>"managing emotions" are to a lesser extent raised in the 
consultation by either the HCP or the patient. </p>

<p>Connecting to patients' goals and expectations </p>

<p>In 54% of the observed consultations (N=26), HCPs made 
an inventory of patient-centered goals or asked patients 
if they had any general questions. The majority of the 
patients (88.5%) responded not having questions or goals 
to mention at all. It is one of the reasons HCPs report </p>

<p>Table 3 Health care providers' social and demographic characteristics </p>

<p>Health care providers' characteristics 
Total health care 
providers (N=11) </p>

<p>Health care 
providers (%) </p>

<p>Total observations 
(N=50)* </p>

<p>Observations 
(%) </p>

<p>Institute 
general practice 1 
2 
18.2 
5 
10.0 
general practice 2a 
1 
9.1 
6 
12.0 
general practice 2B 
1 
9.1 
4 
8.0 
general practice 3 
1 
9.1 
9 
18.0 
Outpatient clinic 1 
2 
18.2 
9 
18.0 
Outpatient clinic 2 
2 
18.2 
10 
20.0 
Outpatient clinic 3 
2 
18.2 
7 
14.0 
Occupation 
Pulmonologist 
3 
27.3 
13 
26.0 
Pulmonary nurse specialist 
3 
27.3 
13 
26.0 
general practitioner 
1 
9.1 
2 
4.0 
nurse practitioner 
2 
18.2 
10 
20.0 
Practice nurse 
2 
18.2 
12 
24.0 
gender 
Male 
2 
18.2 
Female 
9 
81.8 
Age in years, mean (range) 
44 (28-56) 
Work experience in years, mean (range) 
20 (7-39) 
Work experience in pulmonary disease in years, mean (range) 
9 (3-20) 
Working hours per week, mean (range) 
33 (20-50) </p>

<p>Note: *Fifty videotaped observed consultations were obtained from 46 patients and 11 HCPs (4 patients had a second consult). </p>

<p>Figure 3 Key topics of interviewed patients. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>129 </p>

<p>Self-management barriers and facilitators among COPD patients </p>

<p>having difficulties in formulating patient-centered goals 
with the patients. </p>

<p>Indeed I try with a patient sometimes like […] "Do you </p>

<p>have a goal or activity you would like to do, or cannot do </p>

<p>anymore for the last five years?" But actually […] it doesn't </p>

<p>work […] because they are quite satisfied with their life </p>

<p>now. I think it is pretty difficult! [HCP 0] </p>

<p>Used resources for information transfer </p>

<p>Despite the observed great emphasis on transferring infor-
mation and knowledge during consultation, little use was 
made of assistive devices, such as written information, 
brochures, decision aids, or video materials. The exchange 
of information between HCPs and patients remains mainly 
verbal. </p>

<p>Patient-centered communication </p>

<p>Both HCPs and patients express the importance of acces-
sibility and communication on the basis of equality. 
Connecting with the patients' social background usually 
occurred on an intuitive basis. In the interviews, some 
HCPs expressed experiencing difficulties in estimating 
what motivated patients to take an active or inactive role 
in their self-management. </p>

<p>Me searching for the connection with the patient [...]is </p>

<p>sometimes like a blackbox. [HCP 1] </p>

<p>Where do you find your motivation [as a patient] when you </p>

<p>don't feel related to your disease? [HCP 2] </p>

<p>Also patients explained several difficulties taking the 
self-management role. After analyzing they were subdivided 
into three categories: 
1. low level of experienced burden of the disease, 
2. wishing not to be confronted with disease, 
3. dealing with external social problems. </p>

<p>I don't want to be confronted with my disease constantly. </p>

<p>I do not need to know everything about my illness, but </p>

<p>prefer the HCP to dose this information when explaining </p>

<p>it to me. [Patient 1] </p>

<p>Having a disease [...] costs a lot of time. You have to go </p>

<p>to the doctor, nurse, dietician, general practitioner [...] </p>

<p>rehabilitation care [...]. At some point you think your whole </p>

<p>life is centered around that. [Patient 2] </p>

<p>Quantitative results </p>

<p>Table 4 provides insight into the response pattern of the 
patients and HCPs (in %) of the PFC questionnaire, subdi-
vided into the response categories "Completely", "Mostly", 
"A little", and "Not at all". It can be seen that the mean 
score in the highest category "Completely" is much higher 
among the patients (84.3%) than the mean score of the 
HCPs (26.5%). Of all patients, 40% (N=20) answered with 
the maximum score for all questions. Furthermore, 64% of 
all patients (N=32) had the maximum score and/or did not 
answer some questions. Further analyses of the patient scores 
per question item with an mean score of ,90% full satisfac-
tion (questions 5, 6, 7, 9, 12, 15, and 16) did not significantly </p>

<p>Figure 4 Key topics of interviewed health care providers (hCPs). </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>130 </p>

<p>Hillebregt et al </p>

<p>Figure 5 PFC scores of patient and hCP (mean/sD). 
Note: Question details are available in Table 1. 
Abbreviations: hCP, health care provider; PFC, patient feedback questionnaire on consultation skills; sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 4 Answering pattern and response rate for the patient feedback questionnaire on consultation skills (%) </p>

<p>Question 
Completely 
Mostly 
A little 
Not at all 
Nonresponse </p>

<p>Pt 
HCP 
Pt 
HCP 
Pt 
HCP 
Pt 
HCP 
Pt 
HCP </p>

<p>1 
90 
34 
6 
60 
0 
6 
0 
0 
4 
0 
2 
96 
38 
2 
52 
0 
10 
0 
0 
2 
0 
3 
96 
34 
0 
62 
0 
2 
0 
0 
4 
2 
4 
92 
8 
4 
62 
0 
28 
0 
0 
4 
2 
5 
80 
24 
10 
46 
0 
30 
0 
0 
10 
0 
6 
78 
16 
6 
48 
0 
18 
4 
6 
12 
12 
7 
58 
12 
8 
60 
0 
22 
4 
4 
30 
2 
8 
92 
18 
2 
56 
0 
24 
0 
0 
6 
2 
9 
78 
18 
6 
50 
2 
22 
2 
10 
12 
0 
10 
96 
56 
0 
42 
0 
2 
0 
0 
4 
0 
11 
90 
44 
4 
54 
0 
2 
0 
0 
6 
0 
12 
86 
36 
4 
46 
0 
14 
0 
4 
10 
0 
13 
94 
34 
2 
64 
0 
2 
0 
0 
4 
0 
14 
90 
26 
6 
52 
0 
20 
0 
0 
4 
2 
15 
60 
4 
14 
40 
4 
40 
6 
10 
16 
6 
16 
72 
22 
8 
58 
0 
14 
4 
0 
16 
6 
Mean (%) 
84.3 
26.5 
5.1 
53.3 
0.4 
16.0 
1.3 
2.1 
9.0 
2.1 </p>

<p>Notes: n=50 consultations. Question details are available in Table 1. 
Abbreviations: hCP, health care provider; Pt, patient. </p>

<p>explain variance in communication scores (P=0.05; Figure 5). 
In a bivariate model the variance (P=0.09, 0.056, and 0.039) 
could be explained by the variables duration of illness, gender, 
and HCPs' experience in lung diseases. However multivariate 
regression analysis did not show any significant results. </p>

<p>Discussion and practice implications </p>

<p>The study identified a number of complex underly-
ing mechanisms and determinants at patient, HCP, and </p>

<p>organizational levels mutually interacting with each other 
as described in Figure 1. These insights yield important 
conclusions and have significant practice implications which 
we will discuss. 
We can conclude that during consultation a traditional 
health care approach is still commonly used in which HCPs 
take the leading role. Despite the great amount of attention 
paid to lifestyle change and advice during consultation, 
less emphasis was seen on effective behavioral change and </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>Self-management barriers and facilitators among COPD patients </p>

<p>follow-up of the advice given, which is quite understandable 
given the fact that patients see their HCP once or twice a year. 
It can be questioned if the low frequency in patient-HCP 
contact is a good breeding ground for building mutual trust 
and effectively achieving behavior change. 
Earlier research has shown that solely providing 
information and lifestyle advice are not sufficient enough 
to actually change lifestyle and behavior. 
53-55 Emphasis 
should be placed on connecting to the goals and motivation 
of the patient using shared decision making. 
21 From the 
qualitative data-exploration it can be seen that both patients 
and HCPs experience difficulties defining personalized 
goals and expectations. Significant influencing factors are 
causing this disadvantage. Newman's self-management 
component, social support, is little observed 
8 in the con-
sultations, which relates to the extent social context and 
participation level in everyday life have been explored. 
This basic understanding of one's personal life, daily 
activity level, motivation, and values is essential to make 
a personalized plan in improving health, which are in tune 
with the perceived limitations and possibilities in daily 
living activities. Verhage et al 
56 point out the necessity of 
a detailed patient assessment with the recognition of the 
diversity of patients in their knowledge and skills, health 
perception, level of communication, and the motivation 
to work on their self-management. A customized self-
management approach where the patient's social context, 
individual background, desires and capabilities are taken 
into account is lacking. </p>

<p>5   Another negatively influencing aspect observed in 
patient-HCP interaction is the profoundly structured con-
sultation, where explicit attention is given to monitoring and 
assessment aspects of the COPD. This tendency toward a 
more rationalized, biomedical medicine, based on protocols 
and guidelines is a movement which has distinguished itself 
in the last 15 years. 
57 The patient-HCP interaction is subse-
quently changing where the HCP is more proactive, whereas 
the patient is unwittingly pushed into a more passive role. 
This is a very contradictory development. Equality between 
patient and HCP during consultation must be pursued and 
is most essential in patient-centered communication. Con-
sequently patients feel more uninhibited, which results in 
them taking a proactive role, sharing their ideas, worries, and 
questions, and making shared decisions possible. 
One success factor seems to be the high satisfaction of 
the patients with the experienced patient-centered commu-
nication during consultation, where a total of 84.3% of the 
patients (N=46) gave full maximum scores against 26.5% </p>

<p>of the HCPs (N=11) answering the PFC. However the high 
percentage of maximum patient scores made it difficult to 
measure effects (ceiling effect). While there is no straight-
forward answer for this observed discrepancy between the 
perceived patient-centered communication between patient 
and HCP, one interpretation could be that the HCPs are 
more critical about themselves concerning their consultation 
compared with how patients judge this. On one hand, we see 
satisfied patients with the traditional consultation structure; 
and on the other hand, we have HCPs indicating having 
difficulties in formulating patient-orientated goals. We can 
identify the fact that patients are not yet well accustomed to 
their new role as a proactive patient, which is also hampered 
by the overall observed traditional and medically oriented 
type of consultation structure. Further research is necessary 
for evaluating the needs of patients regarding self-direction, 
interaction, and communication with HCPs. 
This study has both strengths and limitations. The strength 
of this study lies in the inclusion of both the patients' and 
HCPs' perspectives gaining insight into the similarities and dif-
ferences of mutual opinions concerning self-management. 
Limitations are the small simple size, which restricted 
performing subgroup analyses. Patients and HCPs took part 
in the research on a voluntary basis. It is, therefore, likely 
that we only reached patients and HCPs who appreciate 
the importance of supporting self-management. The single 
recruitment source, via the respiratory community nurse, 
limited the degree of generalizing the results of the study. 
No conclusions can be drawn about self-management among 
various ethnic populations because the majority of the partici-
pants had Dutch ethnicity. Finally, we identified high patient 
scores on the PFC, from which we can conclude patients 
being very satisfied with the degree of patient-centered 
communication in the consultation. But giving socially desir-
able answers to the questions must be considered as another 
possible explanation. </p>

<p>58-60   In summary, although the patient-centered approach 
being one of the dominant paradigms in modern medicine </p>

<p>61-64   our observations accentuate difficulties implementing self-
management in daily practice. Both patients and HCPs are 
still very much framed in a traditional consultation structure 
according to the biomedical perspective though an observed 
discrepancy in the satisfaction level of the consultation was 
seen between patients and their HCPs. 
Influencing determinants were identified from the inter-
views and consultations affecting implementation of self-
management at patient, HCP, and organizational level. Seven 
main themes could be identified: "use of self-management </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>132 </p>

<p>Hillebregt et al </p>

<p>tools", "organization of care", "consultation structure", "self-
management components", "connecting to patients' goals and 
expectations", "used resources for information transfer", and 
"patient-centered communication". 
More research is needed of the influencing factors of 
self-management and for gaining insight into finding the 
right balance between the implementation of patient-centered 
medicine in a predominant evidence-based setting. To our 
knowledge this research was the first study focusing on the 
interaction between patients and HCPs according to the imple-
mentation of self-management, integrating the opinion and 
perspectives of both, and is a first step in better understanding 
and unravelling the determinants of self-management. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The Patient Empowerment Programme is a cooperative ven-
ture between patient organization the Dutch Lung Foundation 
(Longfonds), the health insurance company Achmea, and 
AstraZeneca to improve the position of patients with COPD 
in the care process by means of shared decision making 
and patient empowerment. We would like to express our 
warm thanks to the participating patients, the HCPs, and 
the members of the Patient Empowerment Programme who 
contributed to the research. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>NHC has had temporary consulting roles on the advisory 
boards of Novartis, Chiesi, Boehringer Ingelheim, and Pfizer. 
OCPvS has received unrestricted research grants from Pfizer 
and Boehringer Ingelheim. NHC and OCPvS have had tem-
porary consulting roles on the advisory board of the Patient 
Empowerment Programme. The authors report no other 
conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>International Journal of COPD </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-chronic-obstructive-pulmonary-disease-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of COPD is an international, peer-reviewed 
journal of therapeutics and pharmacology focusing on concise rapid 
reporting of clinical studies and reviews in COPD. Special focus is given 
to the pathophysiological processes underlying the disease, intervention 
programs, patient focused education, and self management protocols. </p>

<p>This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine and CAS. The 
manuscript management system is completely online and includes a 
very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>