<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5376127" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We describe the spontaneous formation of composite chalcogenide materials that consist of two-dimensional (2D) 
materials dispersed in bulk and their unusual charge transport properties for application in hydrogen evolution reac-
tions (HERs). When MoS 2 as a representative 2D material is deposited on transition metals (such as Cu) in a controlled 
manner, the sulfidation reactions also occur with the metal. This process results in remarkably unique structures, that 
is, bulk layered heterojunctions (BLHJs) of Cu-Mo-S that contain MoS 2 flakes inside, which are uniformly dispersed in 
the Cu 2 S matrix. The resulting structures were expected to induce asymmetric charge transfer via layered frameworks 
and tested as electrocatalysts for HERs. Upon suitable thermal treatments, the BLHJ surfaces exhibited the efficient HER 
performance of approximately 10 mA/cm 2 at a potential of −0.1 V versus a reversible hydrogen electrode. The Tafel 
slope was approximately 30 to 40 mV per decade. The present strategy was further generalized by demonstrating the 
formation of BLHJs on other transition metals, such as Ni. The resulting BLHJs of Ni-Mo-S also showed the remarkable 
HER performance and the stable operation over 10 days without using Pt counter electrodes by eliminating any pos-
sible issues on the Pt contamination. </p>

<p>In principle, electrolysis of water into oxygen and hydrogen can offer a 
clean, renewable energy resource. The cost-effective and efficient 
splitting of water is a critical issue in technologies and economies with 
energy delivery systems that use hydrogen, enabling zero emission of 
greenhouse gases (1). A key challenge in the electrocatalyst design is 
the performance-cost trade-off of using the platinum-group metals as 
a cathode for the hydrogen evolution reaction (HER) (2-5). Two differ-
ent approaches have constituted the major branches of science in this 
domain of research. One approach is to use less or optimized amounts 
of precious elements, such as nanoparticulate Pt on carbon supports (6). 
The other approach is to find new alloy compositions based on Pt. In 
exploring new alloy composition, computational simulations are bene-
ficial in the development of previously unknown single-phase systems 
(7, 8). Although more complex surface structures involving platinum 
have exhibited experimental improvements (9-11), efficient electroca-
talysts consisting of nonprecious elements have recently been more ac-
tively studied (12-15). Transition metal chalcogenide-based systems, 
such as MoS 2 , provide many possibilities for HER because they have 
unique anisotropic surface/transport properties and provide surfaces 
with the desired binding energy/site for H + (16-21). However, a 
material equivalent to platinum in terms of the onset potential, the Tafel 
slope, and the long-term stability has not yet been developed. 
The activation processes on the catalyst surfaces were believed to be 
the essential mechanisms for HER, and thus, surface energies matter in 
the development of HER catalysts with high efficacy. This would be true 
as for the case of monometallic Pt (22), and seeking platinum-like 
surfaces seems rational among cost-effective elements. Recent research 
activities have been headed in this direction accordingly. However, </p>

<p>when nonmetallic catalysts are involved, the charge transfer resistance 
rather than surface reactions themselves would play a significant role 
and should be considered. A recent study by Voiry et al. (23) experi-
mentally exhibited that the catalytically inert basal plane of 2H MoS 2 
can be active by controlling the charge transfer resistance of the system. 
Beyond identifying platinum-like surfaces, we propose here a novel 
electrocatalytic concept consisting of two-dimensional (2D) materials 
in bulk; we refer to this concept as the inorganic bulk layered hetero-
junction (BLHJ). Our approach is based on a simple fabrication techni-
que for the direct growth of MoS 2 on self-supported metallic substrates 
via sequential gas-phase reactions, which result in the spontaneous for-
mation of dense BLHJ structures via spontaneous sulfidation reactions. 
These structures contain MoS 2 flakes, which are dispersed in the Cu 2 S 
matrix (resembling "straw in mud plaster"). The present system not on-
ly features distinctive inorganic, dense BLHJ structures, which are dif-
ficult to prepare experimentally using any other methods, but also has 
layered 2D materials as the key anisotropic components that trigger un-
usual charge transfer processes. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>We selected MoS 2 as the representative 2D component with the feasi-
bility of anisotropic transport properties (17). Incorporating the target 
layered materials into the bulk chalcogenide host with secure contact 
interfaces between suitable nanoscale junctions in a controlled manner 
is difficult (Fig. 1B). We used the sequential gas-phase surface reaction 
technique for which the reactants, such as Mo or S, are independently 
delivered into the substrates so that only the surface-limited reactions 
occur. Because the substrate metal used for the self-supporting electrode 
is simultaneously sulfidizable, this growth mode is expected to incorpo-
rate a layered system into the bulk chalcogenide host. In the design of 
the BLHJ, another important consideration is to select two chalcogenide 
systems that are thermodynamically immiscible at given temperatures. 
For example, copper as the substrate material and Mo for sulfidation 
will lead to the desired immiscible phase separation to form an in-
organic BLHJ with MoS 2 at relatively lower temperatures (&lt;300°C) 
(24). In addition to the formation of thermodynamically immiscible </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Energy Science, Sungkyunkwan University, Suwon 440-746, Republic of 
Korea. 2 Korean National Research Foundation Shinjin Scientist Program, Sungkyunkwan 
University, Suwon 440-746, Republic of Korea. 3 Institute of Applied Physics, University of 
Hamburg, Jungiusstrasse 11, 20355 Hamburg, Germany. 4 Department of Chemical and 
Biomolecular Engineering, Yonsei University, 50 Yonsei-ro, Seodaemun-gu, Seoul 120-
749, Republic of Korea. 
*These authors contributed equally to this work. 
 †Corresponding author. Email: changdeuck@skku.edu (C.B.); hshin@skku.edu (H.S.) </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Bae et al., Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602215 </p>

<p>
systems, it is Earth-abundant and cheap. Moreover, the quality of Cu as 
the electrochemical electrode has been verified in the field of battery, 
and thus, the possible side effects could be ruled out. 
First, we established the sequential gas-phase surface reaction tech-
nique for the precursors on SiO 2 /Si substrates in a flow-type reactor 
(about 150 mm in diameter), analogous to the atomic layer deposition 
(ALD) procedure. To obtain a preliminary result, for example, we used 
MoCl 5 and H 2 S as the reactants and separated their alternating exposures 
by N 2 purging (fig. S1). The nucleation and growth along the basal planes </p>

<p>were strongly affected by the gas flow from the inlet of the chamber (fig. S2). 
Remarkably, the uniformity of thickness was not maintained across the 
substrates under the given process conditions (fig. S2). This result has 
not been reported previously in the context of ALD studies (25, 26), but 
it is understandable on the basis of the strong structural anisotropy of 
the resulting materials. The resulting MoS 2 layers have distinctive 
features that are dependent on the distance from the chamber inlet 
not only in thickness but also in terms of the morphologies (fig. S2D). 
Larger uniform growth zones were optimized by increasing the pulse time </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The anisotropic charge transport in the bulk and the spontaneous formation of Cu-Mo-S-based dense nanocomposites during deposition of MoS 2 directly on 
Cu foils. (A) Illustration of a typical bulk heterojunction (BHJ). A bulk heterojunction consists of particulate/granular structures connected to the electrodes with different chemical 
potentials (green and red plates). When either electrons or holes are generated, they are then separated isotropically (black arrows). (B) Illustration of the anisotropic charge 
transport in bulk. The BLHJ concept uses layered chalcogenides inside the bulk chalcogenides. When charges are injected into the layered chalcogenides from one electrode (for 
example, red plate), they would undergo fast transfer because of the strong anisotropy in the transport properties. (C) Image of the as-grown CMS layers on Cu foil. (D) Plan-view 
SEM of the as-deposited CMS. (E) Cross-sectional scanning transmission electron microscopy (TEM) image of the resulting CMS layer. (F) Bright-field TEM image of the cross-
sectioned TiO 2 /CMS/Cu, where the topmost layers consist of Pt particles and carbon deposited as protection for focused ion beam sectioning. (G) High-resolution TEM (HR-TEM) 
image of the Chevrel phase of Cu 2.76 Mo 6 S 8 formed at the interface of MoS 2 and Cu 2 S. The inset shows that the electron diffraction patterns collected in the dashed orange circle 
confirm formation of the Chevrel phase. ZA, zone axis. </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Bae et al., Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602215 </p>

<p>
(t p ) for MoCl 5 (fig. S3), and we used this phenomenon in the present 
strategy for preparing BLHJ structures. 
On the basis of the chemical reaction of MoCl 5 and H 2 S in the gas 
phase, we suspect that chloride ions are inevitably left in the films during 
the reaction; thus, the resulting MoS 2 nanoflakes incorporate Cl as an 
impurity. Evidence for the presence of Cl was confirmed by the chem-
ical analysis techniques of energy-dispersive x-ray (EDX) spectroscopy 
and x-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) (fig. S4, A to E), although 
the layered nature was preserved (figs. S4F and S7). Approximately 5 to 
10 atomic % of chloride ions were detected. Mott-Schottky measure-
ments revealed the significant amount of negatively charged species, 
such as Cl ions, that had a density of ~10 23 /cm 3 (fig. S8). This order 
of magnitude is consistent with the chemical analysis results. The dop-
ing density was measured using the Hall measurement technique with 
van der Pauw geometry and indicates that the Cl dopants are not fully 
thermally activated (with an electron density of ~10 19 /cm 3 ; fig. S9). This 
result is simply a consequence of the low growth temperature (that is, 
250°C). In a recent study by Yang et al. (27), this Cl doping was reported 
to decrease the contact resistance through a significant reduction of the 
Schottky barrier width. Therefore, the fact that our methodology is in-
trinsically capable of Cl doping should be beneficial in the design of the 
present BLHJ structures with efficient charge transport characteristics, 
as will be discussed later. 
The aforementioned processes were used to directly deposit MoS 2 
onto copper foil (~20 mm in thickness). The corresponding surface re-
actions were visible across a large area (approximately 10 cm × 10 cm; 
Fig. 1C). As shown in Fig. 1D, scanning electron microscopy (SEM) 
image is the representative morphology of the resulting materials on 
Cu (see fig. S11 for more details). Well-dispersed nanoparticles (bright 
contrast) embedded in the matrix were observed. A representative 
scanning transmission electron micrograph shows that the layered 
structures were densely incorporated into the matrix (that is, CuS x ) dur-
ing the reactions (Fig. 1E). The embodiment of MoS 2 and the sulfidation 
of Cu simultaneously occurred during the fabrication of MoS 2 , resulting 
in the formation of Cu x S and MoS 2 (hereafter termed as CMS), which 
are immiscible according to their phase diagram at the given tempera-
ture (24). The sulfidation of Cu can be understood in the context of the 
adsorbate-induced surface band bending (28), charge transfer by the 
H 2 S molecules, and the subsequent diffusion processes of sulfur inside. 
We observed a much higher growth rate of CuS x /CMS than that of 
MoS 2 by comparing the resulting thicknesses of MoS 2 and CMS layers 
(fig. S12). The degree of sulfidation of Cu was also affected by the flow 
during the reaction, as in the case of MoS 2 , whereas the amounts of 
MoS 2 (determined by detecting Mo) inside the CMS layers remained 
nearly constant (fig. S12C). This independence offers valuable benefits 
to the rapid optimization of the MoS 2 concentration within the bulk 
layers when the present system is applied to the HER. Within the thick-
ness gradient investigated, the HER activities showed few differences 
(fig. S13). A comparison of the resulting thicknesses of the deposited 
hybrid composites confirmed that we could generate BLHJs of Cu-
Mo-S with controlled amounts of MoS 2 . 
The subsequent thermal annealing at 500°C (for ~1 hour under N 2 
flow; see Materials and Methods for more details) allowed further con-
trol over the heterojunction structures of CMS by local alloying at the 
interfaces between Cu x S and MoS 2 (fig. S14). Investigation by TEM re-
vealed the formation of Chevrel Cu x Mo 6 S 8 clusters at the Cu 2 S/MoS 2 
interfaces (see the superlattices marked as blue arrows in fig. S15). No-
tably, according to the bulk phase diagram of the Cu-Mo-S system, al-
loying Cu x Mo 6 S 8 is expected at higher temperatures, that is, temperatures </p>

<p>greater than ~700°C (24). Therefore, the Chevrel phase formation was 
understood to be the local alloying effect at the interfaces even upon an-
nealing at 500°C (Fig. 1G). Although their presence was evident in the 
TEM investigation, the clear detection of the smaller portions of both 
MoS 2 and Cu x Mo 6 S 8 was limited to the x-ray diffraction (XRD) patterns 
(fig. S16) (29). Upon being subjected to further heat treatment processes, 
the Chevrel phase was unambiguously observed to be Cu 2.76 Mo 6 S 8 in the 
XRD patterns (fig. S16). Note that the overall distribution of Mo was 
uniform across the CMS layers (figs. S17 to S19). These observations fur-
ther imply that the CMS surfaces were also partly terminated by both the 
MoS 2 nanoflakes and the Chevrel clusters, elucidating the CMS/TiO 2 
interface in detail (fig. S20). 
We constructed a conventional three-electrode measurement setup 
in homemade Teflon cells (fig. S21) using a CMS/Cu cathode, a Pt an-
ode, an Ag/AgCl reference electrode, and a sulfuric acid electrolyte. The 
cathode was first protected with amorphous TiO 2 , which was grown by 
ALD to achieve initial protection (fig. S22, A and B) (30). Notably, this 
TiO 2 coating can initially function as an efficient electronic transport 
layer for HER (31) and serve the initial activation processes (for exam-
ple, electrical annealing) of the CMS layers, as will be discussed later. 
HER activity was investigated at different processing steps and com-
pared with control samples (Fig. 2, A to C). Although Cu and Cu 2 S 
themselves exhibit little HER activity under the given measurement 
conditions, the as-grown CMS that was exhibited substantially 
enhanced the HER activity. The annealed CMS shows further improve-
ment in the HER. Notably, although the surfaces of Cu 2 S showed neg-
ligible HER activities, the presence of the MoS 2 inside certainly 
contributed to the enhancement of the charge transfer characteristics. 
After one more junction of TiO 2 was added not only as a protective 
layer but also as an efficient charge transport layer, remarkably, our 
CMS material exhibited a nearly zero onset potential and a Tafel slope 
of ~39 mV/decade (dec) (Fig. 2C). These values are comparable with 
those of our sputtered Pt films and the literature values of Pt (22, 32). 
To the best of our knowledge, the present study shows the best 
performance record for HER activities among any other reported 
materials' systems using nonprecious elements in terms of both the 
onset potential and the Tafel slope. Note that the resulting high current 
density did not stem from the large specific surface area and represents 
the material's property itself. Normalizing the porosity in the HER 
performance simplifies comparisons among intrinsic properties (32). 
The roughness factor of our system was estimated to be ~1.3 by 
electrochemically active surface area with double-layer capacitance 
measurements (fig. S23). Surface roughness of our planar structure is 
5 to 8 nm in root mean square roughness (R RMS ) measured by atomic 
force microscopy (AFM) (fig. S22C). Moreover, the TiO 2 /CMS/Cu 
samples were operated stably as HER cathodes for well over a 10-day 
run at −0.1 V (Fig. 2E). Possible issues on the contamination of Pt were 
ruled out by carefully analyzing XPS results before and after stability 
tests (figs. S24 to S26). These superior performances that are compara-
ble with that of Pt were reproducibly observed in samples from four 
different batches (fig. S27). Nonetheless, a lingering suspicion on the 
subtle amounts of Pt contamination would be the electrochemical re-
deposition of Pt during HER under a harsh condition (33) (that is, 
cycling at larger voltages than −0.1 V versus reversible hydrogen 
electrode (RHE) used for stability tests, for example, similar to fig. 
S25). Therefore, we present the HER results by both the conventional 
three-electrode measurements using Pt counter electrodes as the stan-
dard methodology (that is, BLHJ-Ag/AgCl-Pt) and the three-electrode 
measurements with BLHJ as monolithic electrodes [that is, BLHJ-SCE </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Bae et al., Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602215 </p>

<p>
(saturated calomel electrode)-BLHJ]. The HER results of the CMS 
layers with a non-Pt counter electrode showed similar performance 
(fig. S28). How to intrinsically avoid the usage of Pt electrodes will 
also be demonstrated below with the development of Ni-Mo-S (NMS) 
systems. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>A question naturally arises as to what the present mechanisms are. Note 
that this experimental value of the Tafel slope (around 30 mV/dec) has 
been observed on Pt(111), assuming extreme coverage of hydrogen and 
the Tafel reaction (34-36). Our observation might indicate that the rate-
determining steps are not simply based on the surface species adsorbed 
(that is, binding energy matters), but the electron transfer kinetics 
through the bulk should be seriously considered. One clue is that the 
impedance analysis exhibited a systematic reduction in the resistance 
of the whole system as a result of thermal treatment and the addition 
of distinctive junction interfaces (Fig. 2D). We ascribe the observed high 
performance for HER to not only the macroscopic mechanism based on 
band diagrams but also the microscopic structures of our unique sys-
tem. To measure the work functions of our CMS layers and other con-
trol samples, we first complementarily used ultraviolet photoelectron 
spectroscopy (UPS) (fig. S29). The order of the work function values 
(F s ) was MoS 2 &gt; Cu 2 S &gt; CMS. This implies the reduction of energy 
barriers when electrons transfer from the Cu electrode and is consistent 
with the impedance analysis. The presence of Cl in the MoS 2 and its 
diffusion in the resulting BLHJ structures should be addressed. If the </p>

<p>MoS 2 flakes are to be formed inside the BLHJs in a similar way, then 
the Cl-doped MoS 2 nanoflakes should contribute to improved transport 
properties (figs. S5 and S6). The estimated small energy gap from an 
Arrhenius plot also supports easy processes for the thermal activation 
of electrons (fig. S10). Therefore, the presence of Cl and the resulting 
electrical doping effect will play a key role in the charge transfer via 
the inner frameworks consisting of the MoS 2 flakes. Moreover, the 
XPS results on the annealed CMS would testify a possibility of Cl dif-
fusion into Cu 2 S if larger amounts of Cl were detected out of the surfaces 
of CMS than those of MoS 2 . We observed the higher portions of Cl 
when compared with those expected in the MoS 2 nanoflakes. From this 
observation, we could therefore conclude the presence of Cl even in the 
Cu 2 S matrix, and similar electrical effects, such as a reduction of the 
Schottky barrier width by doping, are expected. At the interface between 
TiO 2 and electrolytes, both scenarios are possible. One is the transfer via 
the surface Cu 2 S because the conduction level of TiO 2 is well below that 
of Cu 2 S. The other is the transport through the conductive TiO 2 . The 
optical absorption measurements were carried out to estimate the band-
gap of our TiO 2 layers (fig. S30). Although whether the ALD-grown, 
amorphous TiO 2 has direct or indirect transitions is not clear, we believe 
that the charge transfer mechanism occurs below the conduction band 
of TiO 2 through the defect sites (fig. S31). The detailed transport mecha-
nisms of the ALD-grown, amorphous TiO 2 are under debate (37-39). 
Nonetheless, the coating of TiO 2 overlayers resulted in the formation of 
ideal interfaces with our CMS layers in terms of electron transfer and 
initial activation. The former is further understood as a framework of the 
formation of Cu 2 S/TiO 2 ohmic junctions. Notably, all the other control </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Electrochemical analysis and HER of the CMS layers. (A) Linear sweep voltammetry. (B) Onset HER potentials. (C) Tafel curves of the CMS layers (as-grown, cyan; 
annealed, orange; annealed with TiO 2, red) together with those of the control materials (Cu, black; MoS 2 , green; Pt, blue). (D) Nyquist plots. (E) Chronogalvanometry of MoS 2 and 
CMS/TiO 2 . The legend colors in (E) are common to all. </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Bae et al., Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602215 </p>

<p>
junctions, such as MoS 2 /TiO 2 , exhibited no improvement in charge 
transfer during HER (fig. S32). A very recent report demonstrated that 
TiO 2 layers grown via the same ALD chemistry exhibited significant 
improvement in electron collection efficacy, with a shift (greater than 
0.2 V) of the open-circuit voltage in InP heterojunction solar cells 
(40). The Cu 2 S/TiO 2 control junctions solely exhibited clear improve-
ment for HER (fig. S32). Note that the amorphous titania layers were 
not kept on the CMS layers upon long-term operation by detecting no 
XPS signal of titania (fig. S26). Nevertheless, this layer functioned for 
initial activation of the underlying CMS layers for long-term stability. 
We believe that the presence of TiO 2 surface layer contributes to the 
initial charge extraction processes from the CMS BLHJs as follows. 
We suspect that the long-term operation at the high current density 
(about tens of microampere per square centimeter) resulted in the elec-
trical annealing of the CMS layers (41), and the performance would be-
come stable possibly by improving the electrical connectivity of the 
frameworks of MoS 2 . This argument could be supported by comparing 
the XPS results after ~100-hour testing (fig. S26) and the chronogalva-
nometry results for ~10 days (Fig. 2). Moreover, these currents could be 
further localized for their pass only through the MoS 2 frameworks [see 
the results of conductive AFM (C-AFM) below]. 
Second, the unique microstructures inside our system are synergisti-
cally responsible for the observed HER activity. The local probe measure-
ments on the resulting CMS layer confirmed that the MoS 2 nanoflakes 
were likely manifested in the transport mechanisms. We carried out 
C-AFM and Kelvin probe force microscopy (KPFM) measurements on 
the surfaces of the CMS. The potential maps that were thus monitored 
indicated the successful formation of nanoscale spatial junctions on the 
surfaces, indicative of the direct modification of the surface energy by 
embedding 2D materials inside (fig. S33). The local conduction results 
also imply the presence of selective pathways in the conduction 
throughout the CMS layers, probably via the MoS 2 nanoflakes (Fig. 3, 
A to C). Notably, these measurements are sensitive to the ideality factor 
of the junctions between the tip and the sample (42). Our systematic </p>

<p>measurements also demonstrate the formation of conductive junction 
interfaces even at very small loading forces (fig. S34). In addition to the 
presence of an anisotropic trigger for charge transport, the inhomo-
geneity in the energy landscape might help evolve H 2 because of the 
asymmetric charge injection for HER. The ingeniously arranged local 
nucleation in a nanometer/micrometer spatial regions would be bene-
ficial for HERs (43). All these findings result in synergetic contributions 
in determining the charge transfer kinetics for HER. 
Therefore, we propose operation principles that might be account-
able for the efficient HER performance observed in this study. The pre-
sent mechanisms have been proposed first by recognizing the fact that 
the surfaces were mostly terminated by electrocatalytically nonactive 
materials. Therefore, the classical Volmer-Heyrovsky-Tafel mechanism 
for HER activity at metal interfaces cannot explain the high HER activ-
ity observed here. Although the Tafel reaction having the ideal surface 
coverage resulted in the theoretical kinetic description to be an ideal 
Tafel slope of ~30 mV/dec, the estimated Tafel slope of ~39 mV/dec 
from our BLHJs could not directly assign the rate-determining step 
(36). As a result, we suggested that the present BLHJ systems have lo-
calized transport paths with reduced charge transfer resistance, which 
serve as the true active site for HER on the basis of the abovementioned 
observations. By spontaneous sulfidation reactions, followed by heat 
treatment, the dense BLHJ structures were prepared, and the resulting 
microstructure exhibited the successful formation of internal networks 
consisting of the MoS 2 and the Chevrel phases. The presence of MoS 2 
nanoflakes with strong anisotropy inside the bulk can boost the internal 
transport of charge carriers across the CMS layers inside during the sur-
face reactions. That is, the metal substrate serves as a self-supported 
cathode, injecting electrons into the CMS layer. In general, the drift 
and diffusion processes are responsible for the major transport mecha-
nisms during HER. Because the MoS 2 is rather confined in the BLHJ, the 
strong anisotropy should lead to an enhancement in the spatial charge 
transport via different mechanisms, thereby enabling the design of 
unique electrocatalysts. Moreover, the mobility of MoS 2 is strongly </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Selectivity of transport properties of the resulting CMS BLHJs. (A) AFM height image of CMS. (B) Corresponding current map by C-AFM at a sample bias of −0.5 V. 
(C) Simplified model of BLHJ structures, highlighting localized transport paths of 2D materials (blue). (D) Proposed mechanisms on energy (e) barrier lowering by the localized 
electric fields. </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Bae et al., Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602215 </p>

<p>
dependent on the dielectric screening of its surroundings (44). The re-
sulting MoS 2 nanoflakes were embedded in the Cu 2 S matrix; thus, this 
situation should be advantageous to the anisotropic charge transport. 
As previously discussed, the Cl doping of MoS 2 would modify the 
structures, lower the energy barriers, and shorten the barrier widths 
with its contact materials, if any (45). Moreover, the Chevrel Cu x Mo 6 S 8 
clusters formed between the MoS 2 and Cu 2 S should facilitate the trans-
fer of charge carriers, operating as gradient junctions. The nanoscale 
dimensions of the resulting MoS 2 flakes in the bulk CMS should lead 
to the environmental pinning at the Fermi levels inside the bulk and the 
further lowering of the barrier heights (45). Despite the complex geo-
metries in defining the contact interfaces, the energy band diagrams </p>

<p>suggest ideal junction interfaces with negligible barrier heights (fig. 
S31) (46). As shown in Fig. 3D, the embedded MoS 2 flakes can function 
as sharp tips at the near surfaces and are additionally responsible for 
energy barrier lowering by the localized fields as proposed mechanisms. 
The present strategy reported here differs from conventional electroca-
talytic concepts that seek the optimum surface binding energy to H + , 
not only experimentally but also theoretically (table S1). To date, no 
such electrocatalysts exist, satisfying both the ideal catalyst surface (that 
is, the onset potential and the Tafel slope) and the long-term stability 
(fig. S35). 
Furthermore, it could offer a general tool to explore other efficient 
composite electrocatalysts with 2D chalcogenide materials inside the </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Electrochemical analysis and HER of the NMS layers. (A) Polarization curves. (B) Onset HER potentials. (C) Tafel analysis (NMS, red) together with those of the control 
materials (bare Ni form, gray; sulfurized Ni form, green; Pt, blue). (D) Nyquist plots. The legend colors in (A) are common to all, except for (E). (E) Stability tests of NMS materials both 
at 10 mA/cm 2 and at −0.1 V versus RHE when using Pt as counter electrode for about 100 hours. (F) Long-term stability of our NMS samples for about 1 month where Pt was 
replaced by the other sheet of NMS (see the inset image). </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Bae et al., Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602215 </p>

<p>
bulk. We applied the present strategy to the porous Ni form as another 
transition metal where the similar incorporation is expected as well as to 
the BLHJs of NMS. The difference between Cu and Ni is the cohesive 
energy (47), and the degree of sulfidation should be different when 
MoS 2 was grown under identical conditions. Because Ni has greater 
bonding strength than Cu, the formation of NiS x was suppressed and 
the relative amounts of MoS 2 were found to be larger by its spontaneous 
incorporation as in the CMS case (fig. S36). The BLHJs of NMS also 
showed the remarkable HER performance without postthermal treat-
ments (Fig. 4). The resulting NMS plates were tested without using Pt 
counter electrodes to eliminate any possible issues on the trace amount 
of Pt contamination. Three-electrode measurements [that is, NMS as a 
working electrode, NMS as a counter electrode, and SCE as a reference] 
were carried out and exhibited similar performance and superior stabil-
ity (Fig. 4F). These results explicitly testify that the outstanding HER 
performance undoubtedly comes from our BLHJ structures. Further-
more, any issues on the contamination of Pt can be completely ruled 
out by substituting the counter Pt electrode as our NMS, indicative of 
the technical feasibility of direct utility of the present systems for HERs. 
The simultaneous incorporation of 2D chalcogenides during sulfidation 
of desired metals should also open a new path for research in nanocom-
posites that are currently difficult or not possible to synthesize. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>ALD of MoS 2 and TiO 2 
MoS 2 was grown on SiO 2 /Si substrates at 250°C using a commercially 
available ALD system (Lucida D100, NCD). MoCl 5 (99.6%; Strem 
Chemicals) and H 2 S (3.99%, balance N 2 ; JC Gas) were used as reactants. 
The MoCl 5 was kept in a stainless canister at 140°C and delivered into 
the chamber. Ultrahigh-purity N 2 (5 N; JC Gas) was used as both the 
carrier and the purging gas. The total flow rate was 200 standard cubic 
centimeters per minute (sccm). A full cycle consisted of t p (MoCl 5 ) of 
0.5 to 5 s and t p (H 2 S) of 1 s, followed by N 2 purging for 30 s. The CMS 
was also prepared using the same configuration with MoS 2 on Cu foil 
(I 2 B ~20 mm, battery grade, ILJIN Materials). After ALD, the chamber 
was cooled to room temperature, and the samples were removed from 
the chamber. Using MoCl 5 allowed for sufficient vapor pressure at the 
low temperature used (that is, 140°C); however, it also resulted in dop-
ing by Cl via the following chemical reactions: MoCl 5 + H 2 S ⇄ MoSCl 3 + 
2HCl and MoSCl 3 + H 2 S ⇄ MoS 2 Cl + 2HCl. 
Once the conditions for growing MoS 2 have been established, we 
further optimized the number of ALD cycles. The progressive improve-
ment was shown in linear sweep voltammetry (fig. S37), and we took 
3000-cycle CMS layers in the present study. The annealing conditions 
have been studied in the temperature range of 300° to 700°C and chosen 
to give an optimum BLHJ structure (figs. S38 and S39). As-grown CMS 
samples were annealed in a tube furnace in a flow of inert gas (HTF-
Q50, Hantech Co.). The furnace was first evacuated down to less than 
3 × 10 −2 torr for more than 30 min before introducing 250 sccm of N 2 
(5 N; JC Gas), and the N 2 flow was continuously maintained during 
annealing. The ramping rate was 5°C/min until the desired tempera-
ture increased, and the temperature was kept for 1 hour. The furnace 
was then cooled down to room temperature naturally. 
TiO 2 was deposited using a separate, commercial ALD chamber 
(Ozone, ForALL) at 120°C. Titanium(IV) isopropoxide (TTIP; 99.99%; 
UP Chemical) and deionized H 2 O were used as the metal reactant 
and oxygen source, respectively. The TTIP and water were kept in stain-
less bubblers at 70°C and room temperature, respectively. A cycle con-</p>

<p>sisted of t p of 2 s for both reactants and Ar (5 N) purging for 8 s at a total 
flow rate of 200 sccm. The growth rate of TiO 2 was determined to be 0.4 
Å per cycle. 
NMS was synthesized in the same way with CMS except on porous 
Ni foam (0.8 mm thick; Wellcos Corporation). First, Ni foams were so-
nicated in ethanol for 30 min and then thermally treated at 800°C for 
2 hours under the reducing atmosphere with a mixture gas of 5% H 2 in 
Ar. Three thousand ALD cycles of MoS 2 were applied on cleaned Ni 
foam at 250°C under the identical conditions with the case of CMS. </p>

<p>Structural characterization and surface analysis 
The physical dimensions and morphologies were observed by field-
emission SEM (JSM7500F, JEOL). The structures were investigated 
by HR-TEM (JEM 2100F, JEOL) equipped with an EDX spectrometer 
(AZtec, Oxford Instruments). Thin sections of the samples for TEM 
were prepared by focused ion beam etching (SMI3050TB, SII). Surface 
chemical compositions were analyzed using XPS (ESCA Sigma Probe, 
Thermo VG Scientific), and surface work functions were estimated by 
UPS (AXIS Ultra DLD, Kratos Inc.) using a He I photon source (hv = 
21.2 eV). </p>

<p>Electrochemical measurements 
Electrochemical measurements were carried out with a three-electrode 
system. Pt wires were used as the counter electrode, Ag/AgCl (MF-2052 
for H 2 SO 4 ; Bioanalytical Systems Inc.) as the reference electrode, and 
the CMS (as controls, Pt, Cu, and MoS 2 ) as working electrodes. The 
electrochemical properties were recorded using a commercially availa-
ble potentiostat (VMP-300, Bio-Logic). Cyclic voltammograms were re-
corded at a scan rate of 5 mV/s either in 0.5 or 1 M H 2 SO 4 electrolyte. 
The virgin curves were discarded, and the third results were routinely 
displayed, unless otherwise specified. The polarization curves were re-
plotted as the overpotential (h) versus logarithmic current density, log|j|, 
to obtain the Tafel slopes. The reference electrode was calibrated to RHE 
potential in the electrolyte of 1 M H 2 SO 4 , that is, E(RHE) = E(Ag/AgCl) + 
0.21 V. Electrochemical impedance analysis was carried out at a bias volt-
age of −0.2 versus Ag/AgCl, in the frequency range from 100 mHz to 
100 kHz, at a voltage amplitude of 6 mV, and at room temperature. 
NMS was used as both working and counter electrode, and SCE for 
alkaline electrolytes was used as a reference. The three-electrode con-
figuration with Pt counter electrode was also used for comparison. 
The reference electrode was calibrated to RHE in the electrolyte of 
1 M KOH (pH 14), according to E(RHE) = E(SCE, alkaline) + 0.971 V. 
Electrochemical impedance analysis was carried out at a bias voltage 
of −0.2 versus RHE with a voltage amplitude of 10 mV, in the frequency 
range from 100 mHz to 100 kHz. 
Chronoamperometry and chronopotentiometry were carried out at 
a constant potential of −0.1 V versus RHE and a constant current den-
sity of −10 mA/cm 2 , respectively. Mott-Schottky plots were attained at a 
frequency of 7.8 Hz, from −0.6 to 0 V versus RHE. The impedance spec-
troscopy results were analyzed and fitted using <rs type="software">EC-Lab</rs> software. All the 
measurements were carried out under dark conditions and mild 
magnetic stirring (200 rpm, unless otherwise specified). </p>

<p>Local probe measurements 
A commercial atomic force microscope (SPA-400, SII) was used for 
C-AFM and KPFM measurements using Au-coated tips [SI-DF3-A, 
with a spring constant (C) of ~0.2 N/m; SII NanoTechnology Inc.] 
and Pt/Ir-coated cantilevers [CONTPt-W, with a resonance frequency 
( f ) of 25 to 27 kHz and C = 1.9 N/m; NanoWorld), respectively. KPFM </p>

<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Bae et al., Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602215 </p>

<p>
images were acquired at scan rates of 0.1 to 0.2 Hz with an applied volt-
age of 1 V (peak-to-peak) and alternating current frequencies near the 
f value of the cantilevers. We simultaneously measured the topography 
and surface potential/conduction map of the samples under ambient 
conditions and in the dark. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS </p>

<p>Supplementary material for this article is available at http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/ 
content/full/3/3/e1602215/DC1 
fig. S1. Schematic illustration of the deposition system. 
fig. S2. Sequential gas-phase reaction of MoS 2 on Si wafers. 
fig. S3. Influence of t p of MoCl 5 on the uniform growth zone. 
fig. S4. Elemental and structural analyses of thin MoS 2 films. 
fig. S5. Elemental analysis of annealed CMS layers. 
fig. S6. High-resolution XPS spectra of the annealed CMS layers in Mo (3d), S (2p), Cu (2p), and 
Cl (2p) regions. 
fig. S7. Raman spectra of MoS 2 (300 cycles) grown on Au. 
fig. S8. The Mott-Schottky measurement of MoS 2 on an Au/Si substrate. 
fig. S9. The Hall effect measurements of MoS 2 on 500-nm-thick SiO2/Si. 
fig. S10. Arrhenius plot of the resistivity from Hall effect measurements on ALD-grown MoS2/ 
SiO2 (500 nm)/Si. 
fig. S11. SEM images of the as-grown CMS layers. 
fig. S12. Thickness dependence of ALD films and Mo contents as a function of position. 
fig. S13. HER activities from the CMS samples with thickness gradient. 
fig. S14. Schematic illustration of the structural evolution of BLHJs upon annealing. 
fig. S15. Low-magnification TEM micrograph of our CMS layers upon annealing (500°C for ~1 
hour under N 2 flow) to give an overview of the structures that consist of layered MoS 2 and the 
superstructures of Chevrel clusters (marked by yellow and blue arrows, respectively). 
fig. S16. XRD patterns of our CMS on Cu subjected to different thermal treatments. 
fig. S17. EDX elemental analysis of our TiO 2 /CMS/Cu structures. 
fig. S18. EDX line scan results for the TiO 2 /CMS/Cu structures. 
fig. S19. Detailed elemental maps of our CMS layers shown in Fig. 1E (main text), indicative of 
the origin of local variations in the detected elements. 
fig. S20. HR-TEM image of annealed CMS to give an overview of the local surface termination. 
fig. S21. Schematic of our three-electrode cell used for HER experiments. 
fig. S22. Surface morphology of TiO 2 -coated annealed CMS. 
fig. S23. Estimation of electrochemically active surface area of our CMS material by double-
layer capacitance measurements. 
fig. S24. XPS analyses of CMS materials to check possible contamination of noble metals. 
fig. S25. Stability against scanning of the present CMS system (10,000 times). 
fig. S26. XPS analyses of TiO 2 /CMS after stability tests. 
fig. S27. Reproducibility tests in the electrocatalytic performance of CMS and NMS materials. 
fig. S28. Electrochemical analysis and HER of the CMS layers with a non-Pt counter electrode 
(that is, graphite). 
fig. S29. UPS spectra. 
fig. S30. Optical absorption of amorphous TiO 2 grown on quartz glass. 
fig. S31. Energy band diagrams and the corresponding circuit models of various structures. 
fig. S32. HER measurements of our 40-nm-thick TiO 2 with different control samples. 
fig. S33. KPFM study of our CMS on Cu. 
fig. S34. Local transport study of our annealed CMS/Cu samples. 
fig. S35. Comparison between our CMS/TiO 2 and various HER materials (32) in the 
electrocatalytic performance. 
fig. S36. TEM image of the NMS layer as prepared to give an overview of the structures that 
densely consist of layered MoS 2 . 
fig. S37. ALD cycle-dependent HER performance of annealed CMS. 
fig. S38. HR-TEM image of a CMS layer annealed at 700°C. 
fig. S39. Linear sweep voltammetry of the CMS layers annealed at different temperatures. 
table S1. Summary of the catalytic performance of various materials for the hydrogen 
evolution reaction, reported in the literature. 
Reference (48) </p>



<p>S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Bae et al., Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602215 </p>



<p>
S C I E N C E A D V A N C E S | R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Bae et al., Sci. Adv. 2017; 3 : e1602215 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>