<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5345981" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Malignant melanoma (MM) is the most dangerous type of skin cancer with annually </p>

<p>increasing incidence and death rates. However, chemotherapy for MM is restricted by low 
topical drug concentration and multidrug resistance. In order to surmount the limitation and 
to enhance the therapeutic effect on MM, a new nanoformulation of paclitaxel (PTX)-loaded 
cholic acid (CA)-functionalized star-shaped poly(lactide-co-glycolide) (PLGA)-d-α-tocopheryl 
polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate (TPGS) nanoparticles (NPs) (shortly PTX-loaded CA-
PLGA-TPGS NPs) was fabricated by a modified method of nanoprecipitation. The particle 
size, zeta potential, morphology, drug release profile, drug encapsulation efficiency, and loading 
content of PTX-loaded NPs were detected. As shown by confocal laser scanning, NPs loaded 
with coumarin-6 were internalized by human melanoma cell line A875. The cellular uptake 
efficiency of CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs was higher than those of PLGA NPs and PLGA-TPGS NPs. 
The antitumor effects of PTX-loaded NPs were evaluated by the MTT assay in vitro and by a 
xenograft tumor model in vivo, demonstrating that star-shaped PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS 
NPs were significantly superior to commercial PTX formulation Taxol ® . Such drug delivery 
nanocarriers are potentially applicable to the improvement of clinical MM therapy. 
Malignant melanoma (MM), which develops in pigment cells (eg, melanocytes), 
mainly occurs in the skin and is prone to blood metastasis and mortality. Moreover, 
the incidence and death rates of MM are increasing annually, and thereby, MM has 
become an obvious public health threat. Recently, MM has mainly been treated 
by surgical resection, chemotherapy, radiotherapy, and immunotherapy. However, 
in case of metastasis, surgical resection leads to unsatisfactory therapeutic effects, 
even if various chemotherapeutic agents are used concomitantly. Thus, it is of great 
significance to boost the clinical efficacy of chemotherapy on MM. Paclitaxel (PTX) 
has well-documented significant effects on MM treatment. 1,2 As a highly effective 
anticancer drug, it can stabilize microtubules, block cancer cell cycle in the G2/M 
phase, and finally induce apoptosis. 3 However, PTX has an extremely hydrophobic 
structure that limits its aqueous solubility (0.4 μg/mL) and significantly reduces 
its bioavailability. This drawback can be circumvented by dissolving PTX in a 
Cremophor-EL ® /ethanol (polyoxyethylene castor oil and ethanol) (1/1, v/v) mixture 
commercially named Taxol ® . Nevertheless, Polyoxyethylene castor oil causes severe 
side reactions (hypersensitivity, cardiotoxicity, peripheral neuropathy, etc.). 4 In order </p>

<p>correspondence: hui liu 
Department of Burn and Plastic 
surgery, The People's hospital of 
Baoan Shenzhen Affiliated to Southern 
Medical University, shenzhen 518101, 
People's republic of china 
Tel/fax +86 755 2778 8311 
email huiliu22@163.com </p>

<p>ni Xie 
core laboratory, shenzhen second 
People's Hospital, First Affiliated Hospital 
of shenzhen University, shenzhen 
518035, People's republic of china 
Tel/fax +86 755 8300 3435 
email kejiaoke100@163.com </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Drug Design, Development and Therapy 
6 March 2017 </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>660 </p>

<p>su et al </p>

<p>to reduce adverse events, researchers have endeavored to 
replace Polyoxyethylene castor oil for delivering PTX. 
In recent years, nanomedicine in the form of particu-
late carriers (eg, nanoparticles [NPs], micelles, liposomes, 
nanoemulsions) offers bright promise for the delivery of 
anticancer drugs, 5-8 by which drugs can be synthesized and 
administered in different ways. Several nanosized delivery 
systems, such as polymeric NPs and lipid nanocapsules, have 
shown enhanced bioavailability of PTX after injection. It is 
quite convincing that cancer nanotechnology significantly 
contributes to enhancing the bioavailability of chemothera-
peutic drugs. 9 Furthermore, the nanosized delivery systems 
used as drug carriers allow sustained release, have high 
encapsulation efficiency (EE), and accumulate preferentially 
at tumor sites owing to the enhanced permeability and reten-
tion (EPR) effect. 10,11 Kretzer et al reported that lipid nano-
emulsions which bind to low-density lipoprotein receptors 
could be used as carriers of PTX, and they decreased toxicity 
and increased the antitumor efficacy of PTX. 12 Battogtokh 
and Ko reported the PTX-loaded polymeric NPs showed 
sustained release and high cytotoxic efficacy comparable to 
that of free PTX on B16F10 melanoma cell lines, suggest-
ing the PTX nanocarriers are potentially applicable to the 
treatment of melanoma. 13 
Currently, biodegradable drug-loaded polymeric NPs 
have been spotlighted due to passive and active drug-targeted 
therapeutic effects after intravenous administration into 
human body. 14,15 Branched copolymers, such as star-shaped 
copolymers, hyper-branched copolymers, and dendrimers, 
have been highlighted owing to excellent mechanical and 
rheological properties. 16,17 Star-shaped block copolymer is a 
branched polymer, the branches of which all extend to form a 
core. 18 The drug carriers based on star-shaped polymers have 
smaller hydrodynamic radii as well as high EEs and loading 
contents (LCs) than those of the linear polymers with similar 
molecular weights. 19,20 
In this study, cholic acid (CA)-functionalized poly(lactide-
co-glycolide) (PLGA)-d-α-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 
1000 succinate (TPGS) (shortly CA-PLGA-TPGS), a star-
shaped copolymer, was employed to prepare drug carriers 
applicable to biomedicine. PLGA is one of the most widely 
accessed biodegradable polymers that have been applied to 
the biomedical field. 21,22 As a water-soluble vitamin E deriva-
tive and also an excellent emulsifier, TPGS is prepared by 
esterifying vitamin E succinate with polyethylene glycol 1000. 
It is an excipient that overcomes multidrug resistance and a 
P-glycoprotein (P-gp) inhibitor that augments the oral bioavail-
ability and cytotoxicity of anticancer drugs. 23-25 CA, which </p>

<p>is the main bile acid in human body, was selected as the 
poly-hydroxy initiator due to good biocompatibility. 26 PLGA, 
TPGS, and CA have been approved by the US Food and Drug 
Administration and used in pharmaceutical products. 9,27 
Although NPs prepared from PLGA and TPGS-PLGA 
have been widely researched as drug delivery vehicles, 
linear copolymers were used in most cases. In this study, to 
fabricate a versatile drug carrier with satisfactory drug EE 
and LC for MM therapy, CA-PLGA-TPGS was selected as 
the vehicle for chemotherapeutic drug PTX. Drug-loaded 
NPs were prepared and characterized, and their in vivo and 
in vitro antitumor effects were evaluated. Commercial PTX 
formulation Taxol, PLGA, and PTX-loaded linear copolymer 
PLGA-TPGS NPs were selected for comparison. 28,29 </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Materials </p>

<p>TPGS, MTT, and coumarin-6 (C6) were bought from Sigma-
Aldrich (St Louis, MO, USA). PTX powders with about 98% 
purity (HPLC grade) were obtained from Shanghai Jinhe 
Bio-Technology Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, People's Republic of 
China). Star-shaped copolymer CA-PLGA-TPGS and linear 
copolymer PLGA-TPGS were kindly supplied by Graduate 
School at Shenzhen, Tsinghua University (People's Republic 
of China). PLGA (M n ≈20,000, lactic acid [LA]:glycolic acid 
[GA] =75:25) was provided by Jinan Daigang Biomaterial 
Co., Ltd. (Jinan, People's Republic of China). Besides HPLC-
grade chromatographic solvents, all the other chemicals 
were of the commercially available highest grade. Distilled 
deionized water was utilized throughout this study. Human 
melanoma cell line A875 was purchased from American Type 
Culture Collection (ATCC, Manassas, VA, USA). </p>

<p>Preparation of PTX-loaded nPs </p>

<p>PTX-loaded NPs were fabricated by a modified method of 
nanoprecipitation as described by Zeng et al. 9,30 In brief, 
20 mg PTX and 200 mg copolymer CA-PLGA-TPGS, PLGA-
TPGS, and PLGA were dissolved by vortexing and sonica-
tion in 16 mL of acetone, respectively. Under stirring, the 
resulting mixture was added dropwise into a 200 mL aqueous 
solution containing 0.03% TPGS. Then, the suspension was 
stirred uncovered overnight to completely remove acetone, 
centrifuged for 15 min at 20,000 rpm, and washed three 
times to eliminate the unencapsulated anticancer drug PTX 
and the emulsifier TPGS. In the end, the dispersed solution 
was freeze-dried for 48 h prior to use. By a similar method, 
fluorescent molecule C6-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS, PLGA, 
and PLGA-TPGS NPs were prepared, for which C6 instead </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>661 </p>

<p>PTX-loaded copolymer nanoparticles for melanoma chemotherapy </p>

<p>of PTX was used. Before use, the freeze-dried NPs were 
redispersed in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). </p>

<p>characterizations of PTX-loaded nPs </p>

<p>Zeta potential, particle size, and morphology </p>

<p>Zeta potential and particle size were detected by Malvern 
Mastersizer 2000 (Zetasizer Nano ZS90; Malvern Instru-
ments Ltd., Malvern, UK). Freshly prepared NPs were diluted 
appropriately before measurements that were performed at 
room temperature after 10 min of equilibration. The average 
of three independent measurements was recorded. Surface 
morphology was observed by field emission scanning elec-
tron microscopy (FESEM; JEOL JSM-6301F; JEOL, Tokyo, 
Japan). For sample preparation, the particles were fixed with 
a double-sided sticky tape on a stub and thereafter coated 
by a platinum layer for 60 s using JFC-1300 automatic fine 
platinum coater (JEOL). </p>

<p>Drug lc and ee </p>

<p>Under vigorous vortexing, PTX-loaded NPs (5 mg) were 
dissolved in 1 mL of dichloromethane. 31 The solution was 
then transferred to a 5 mL mobile phase comprising deionized 
water and acetonitrile (50:50, v:v). Dichloromethane was 
evaporated by introducing a nitrogen stream for about 15 min, 
yielding a clear solution for subsequent high-performance 
liquid chromatography (HPLC) (LC 1200; Agilent Technolo-
gies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). HPLC was conducted with a 
reverse-phase C 18 column (150×4.6 mm, 5 μm, C 18 ; Agilent 
Technologies) at 35°C, using mobile phase at the flow rate of 
1 mL/min. With a UV detector, the effluent was determined 
at λ max of 227 nm. Drug LC was defined as the percentage 
of the weight of incorporated PTX to that of NPs, and EE 
was defined as the percentage of PTX weight in NPs to its 
initial feeding amount. The measurements were performed 
in triplicate. </p>

<p>Drug release profiles in vitro </p>

<p>In vitro drug release from PTX-loaded NPs was tested as 
described by Wang et al. 32 Briefly, PTX-loaded NP powders 
(5 mg) were suspended in 1 mL of PBS containing 0.1% 
Tween 80 (release buffer) and then transferred to a dialysis 
membrane bag (molecular weight cut-off =3,500 Da; Spectra 
Por ® ; Spectrum Laboratories, Inc., Rancho Dominguez, CA, 
USA). Tween 80 was utilized to raise the solubility of PTX 
in this buffer and to prevent its binding to the tube wall. 
Then, the bag was immersed into a centrifuge tube containing 
15 mL of release buffer. The tube was thereafter placed in an 
orbital shaker water bath and shaken at 37°C and 120 rpm, </p>

<p>and the entire release buffer was collected and refreshed at 
indicated time intervals. Released PTX was quantified by 
HPLC with the method already mentioned. The relationship 
between cumulative PTX release from drug-loaded NPs and 
time was determined. </p>

<p>cell culture </p>

<p>In a humidified 5% CO 2 atmosphere, A875 cells were 
cultured at 37°C in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium 
(DMEM) supplemented with 1% penicillin/streptomycin and 
10% fetal bovine serum. </p>

<p>cellular uptake of c6-loaded nPs </p>

<p>As a model fluorescent molecule, C6 can be encapsulated 
in the prepared NPs and then internalized by A875 cells. 
The cells were incubated with 100 μg/mL C6-loaded CA-
PLGA-TPGS NPs for 2 h at 37°C, washed three times with 
cold PBS, and fixed for 20 min in methanol. Afterwards, they 
were stained for 30 min with propidium iodide (PI), washed 
with PBS twice, and finally observed using confocal laser 
scanning microscopy (CLSM; LSM 410; Carl Zeiss AG, 
Oberkochen, Germany) equipped with an imaging software. 
The cell images were captured by a differential interference 
contrast channel, and the images of C6-loaded NPs and PI-
stained nuclei were recorded with the following channels: 
fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC) channel (C6) excited at 
485 nm and PI channel excited at 530 nm. 33 For quantitative 
analysis, A875 cells were seeded in 96-well plates at the 
density of 1×10 4 cells/well and incubated overnight, and 
then 50, 100, and 200 μg/mL C6-loaded NPs were added, 
respectively, and equilibrated for 1 h with Hank's buffered 
salt solution at 37°C. After 2 h of incubation, the culture 
medium was discarded, and the wells were washed by 50 μL 
of cold PBS solution three times. The cells were thereafter 
lysed by adding 50 μL of 0.2 N sodium hydroxide containing 
0.5% Triton X-100 into each well. </p>

<p>in vitro cytotoxicity assay of PTX-
loaded nPs </p>

<p>A875 cells were inoculated at the density of 5×10 3 cells/well 
in 96-well plates and incubated in 100 μL of medium over-
night. Then, they were incubated with the suspension of 
PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs, that of PLGA-TPGS 
NPs, or polyoxyethylene castor oil and ethanol at equiva-
lent PTX concentrations of 0.25-25 μg/mL for 24 and 48 h, 
respectively. PTX-free CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs with the same 
NPs dose were also tested. The formulations were replaced by 
5 mg/mL MTT-containing DMEM at indicated time intervals. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>662 </p>

<p>su et al </p>

<p>After incubation of the cells for 4 h, MTT was aspirated off, 
and formazan crystals were dissolved by adding dimethyl sul-
foxide. The absorbance was detected by a microplate reader 
at 570 nm. The absorbance was calibrated to zero by using 
untreated cells with 100% viability as control and the cells 
without MTT addition as blank. IC 50 , the drug concentration 
that inhibits the growth of 50% cells, was calculated. This 
value was assessed through curve-fitting of the cell viability 
data and comparing them with those of control. 34 </p>

<p>In vivo antitumor efficacy of PTX-
loaded nPs </p>

<p>Female nude mice (BALB/c-nu, 15-20 g, 6 weeks old) were 
bought from Guangdong Medical Laboratory Animal Center 
(People's Republic of China). The protocols for animal 
assays were approved by the Animal Ethics Committee of 
Southern Medical University. Guidelines of the institutional 
animal ethics committee were followed for in vivo experi-
ments. Each mouse was subcutaneously injected with 100 μL 
of medium containing about 2×10 6 A875 cells into the back. 
The subcutaneous tumor growth after inoculation of A875 
cells was frequently observed. Tumor length and width were 
measured with a vernier caliper, and the three-dimensional 
volume of an ellipsoid tumor tissue (V) was calculated 
according to the formula 4π/3× (length/2) × (width/2) 2 . 35,36 
Treatment was initiated when the volume reached approxi-
mately 100 mm 3 (referred to as the 0th day). The tumor-
bearing mice were divided into three groups randomly 
(n=6) and subjected to tail intravenous injection with saline 
(control) or PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs and polyoxy-
ethylene castor oil and ethanol in PBS at the dose of 10 mg 
PTX/kg on the 0th, 4th, and 8th days, respectively. The tumor 
size and body weight of each mouse were measured every 
2 days. Twelve days after treatment, they were sacrificed by </p>

<p>cervical decapitation. The antitumor activity was evaluated 
by measuring the terminal tumor weight. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Unless stated otherwise, all the experiments were performed 
at least three times. The experimental data are expressed as 
mean ± standard deviation. Statistical analysis was performed 
using one-way analysis of variance followed by Bonferroni 
test with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS</rs>) 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16.0</rs> software. *P0.05 was considered as statistically signif-
icant and **P0.01 as extremely statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results and discussion 
characterization of star-shaped 
copolymer </p>

<p>The structure of prepared copolymer CA-PLGA-TPGS was 
detected by 1 H nuclear magnetic resonance ( 1 H NMR; Bruker 
AMX 500) and CDCl 3 used as a solvent. The molecular 
weight and molecular weight distribution were confirmed 
by gel permeation chromatography (GPC; Waters Corp., 
Milford, MA, USA). As shown by 1 H NMR in Figure 1A, 
five peak signals can be observed: a (δ =1.62 ppm, LA 
repeating unit: -CHCH 3 ), b (δ =5.21 ppm, LA repeating 
unit: -CHCH 3 ), c (δ =4.82 ppm, GA repeating unit: -CH 2 -), 
d (δ =0.50-2.40 ppm, CA moiety: -CH 2 -and -CH-), and 
e (δ =3.65 ppm, TPGS repeating unit: -CH 2 CH 2 O-). The 
evidence indicated that the copolymer CA-PLGA-TPGS with 
a well-defined structure was synthesized successfully. The 
GPC analysis of CA-PLGA-TPGS is presented in Figure 1B, 
from which it could be further confirmed that the copolymer 
CA-PLGA-TPGS was prepared successfully. Figure 1B 
showed that the peak for CA-PLGA-TPGS appeared at 
19.3 min. Moreover, the polydispersity index (PDI) of the 
copolymers was 1.27, which is rather narrow. </p>

































<p>
Figure 1 characterization of copolymer ca-Plga-TPgs: (A) typical 1 h nMr spectra and (B) gel permeation chromatographic analysis. 
Abbreviations: ca, cholic acid; Plga, poly(lactide-co-glycolide); TPgs, d-α-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate; 1 h nMr, 1 h nuclear magnetic resonance. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>663 </p>

<p>PTX-loaded copolymer nanoparticles for melanoma chemotherapy </p>

<p>characterizations of nPs </p>

<p>Particle size, zeta potential, morphology, and drug 
lc and ee </p>

<p>The particle sizes and size distribution of PTX-loaded NPs 
were detected by dynamic light scattering (DLS), and the 
results are listed in Table 1. The surface properties and 
particle sizes of NPs play a crucial role in drug release 
and cellular uptake together with biodistribution and 
pharmacokinetics in vivo. 37,38 The average hydrodynamic 
sizes of PTX-loaded NPs ranged from 125.6 to 179.5 nm 
in diameter, and so they can easily accumulate in the 
tumor vasculature due to the EPR effect. 9,39,40 CA-PLGA-
TPGS NPs had a much smaller size than those of PLGA 
and PLGA-TPGS NPs, which can be ascribed to the 
constrained, star-shaped copolymer geometry. Moreover, 
all the PTX-loaded NPs had narrow size distributions 
(PDI 0.2), which is beneficial to clinical nanomedical 
applications. The size distributions of PTX-loaded PLGA-
TPGS, CA-PLGA-TPGS, and PLGA NPs detected by DLS 
are shown in Figure 2A. The in vivo stability of NPs through 
electrostatic repulsion is also reflected by zeta potential. 
PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS, PLGA-TPGS, and PLGA 
NPs had the zeta potentials of −11.5±1.8, −16.8±2.5, </p>

<p>and −28.7±3.4 mV, respectively. With ionized carboxyl 
groups from polyglycolic acid and polylactic acid segments, 
all the NPs had negative surface charges. 41 Furthermore, 
the zeta potentials of PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS and 
PLGA-TPGS NPs were decreased by TPGS segment 
compared with that of PLGA NPs. 30 
The morphology of all NPs was then observed by 
FESEM. As exhibited in Figure 2B, PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-
TPGS NPs had near-spherical shapes and the mean size of 
around 90 nm that is obviously smaller than that detected 
by DLS. Probably, dry NPs were vulnerable to shrinkage 
and collapse. 42 
The drug LC and EE of CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs exceeded 
those of PLGA and PLGA-TPGS NPs because of the 
stronger binding between the star-shaped core PLGA and 
the hydrophobic drug PTX. Besides, the drug LC and EE 
of CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs were 10.46% and nearly 100%, 
respectively, meeting the requirements of nanomedical and 
clinical applications. </p>

<p>stability of PTX-loaded nPs </p>

<p>During nanoformulation storage, drug-loaded NPs are prone 
to aggregation because the absolute value of zeta potential 
decreases. Therefore, their size distribution becomes nonuni-
form, and only the fresh NPs are suitable for therapy. In this 
study, to investigate the stability of PTX-loaded NPs (stored 
at 4°C), their mean size, size distribution, and zeta potential 
were measured every 10 days until the 90th day after prepara-
tion. During 3 months of storage, the size or zeta potential of 
PTX-loaded NPs hardly changed at 4°C (Figure 3), indicating 
that all these NPs were fairly stable. </p>

<p>Table 1 characterizations of PTX-loaded nPs (n=3) </p>

<p>Polymer 
Size (nm) PDI 
ZP (mV) LC (%) EE (%) </p>

<p>Plga 
179.5±7.5 
0.166 −28.7±3.4 7.98 
80.21 
Plga-TPgs 
160.4±6.7 
0.152 −16.8±2.5 8.22 
88.43 
ca-Plga-TPgs 125.6±5.3 
0.131 −11.5±1.8 10.46 
98.52 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: PTX, paclitaxel; nPs, nanoparticles; PDi, polydispersity index; ZP, zeta 
potential; LC, loading content; EE, encapsulation efficiency; PLGA, poly(lactide-co-
glycolide); TPgs, d-α-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate; ca, cholic acid. </p>





























<p>
Figure 2 characterizations of PTX-loaded ca-Plga-TPgs nPs: (A) Dls size distribution of nPs and (B) FESEM image of NPs. Magnification ×50.0 k. 
Abbreviations: PTX, paclitaxel; ca, cholic acid; Plga, poly(lactide-co-glycolide); TPgs, d-α-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate; nPs, nanoparticles; Dls, 
dynamic light scattering; FESEM, field emission scanning electron microscopy. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>664 </p>

<p>su et al </p>

<p>Drug release profiles in vitro </p>

<p>Figure 4 presents the accumulative drug release profiles 
of PTX-loaded NPs in vitro in pH 7.4 PBS containing 
0.1% (w/v) Tween 80 in the first 14 days. After initial 
burst releases, all NPs exhibited continuous, steady release 
patterns. In the initial 2 days, 51.72%, 35.19%, and 28.67% 
of PTX were released, respectively, from drug-loaded CA-
PLGA-TPGS NPs, PLGA-TPGS NPs, and PLGA NPs. After 
2 weeks, their accumulative drug releases were 78.69%, 
57.14%, and 47.53%, respectively. Following typical 
biphasic release patterns, the NPs released PTX rapidly in 
the initial 2 days because this drug was only beneath the 
periphery or entrapped poorly. Subsequently, PTX was 
sustainably released mainly through diffusion from the rigid </p>

<p>core. 9 Accumulative PTX releases in the 14 days followed a 
descending order of CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs  PLGA-TPGS 
NPs  PLGA NPs, suggesting that CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs 
released PTX faster than PLGA-TPGS NPs did, although 
they had similar molecular weights. CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs 
released drug most rapidly because of the highest LC, the 
smallest particle size, and the hydrophilicity of TPGS outer 
shell. PTX release from polymeric NPs with higher density 
and drug LC was promoted because this was a diffusion 
process in vitro. At the same time, the release decelerated 
owing to the reduced drug density inside the inner shell. With 
a higher hydrophilicity, the TPGS outer shell facilitated the 
penetration of release medium into the cores of NPs and thus 
led to matrix swelling. Similar to the results of Baimark 43 
and Zhu et al, 44 the drug release concentrations of star-shaped 
copolymer CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs were better kept at thera-
peutic levels than those of other NPs in the same periods. </p>

<p>cellular uptake of c6-loaded nPs </p>

<p>Usually, drug-loaded NPs exert therapeutic effects on cancer 
cells depending on internalization and sustained retention. 45 
In vitro investigation provides indirect evidence for verify-
ing the advantages of nanoformulation in comparison with 
free anticancer drug, although it is different from in vivo 
bioprocess. In this study, cellular NPs uptake was observed 
by replacing PTX with C6 in the nanocarriers. 46 To this end, 
A875 cells were incubated with NPs loaded with C6. Figure 5 
presents their CLSM images after incubation with the suspen-
sion of C6-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs in DMEM for 2 h 
(NPs concentration: 100 μg/mL). The images were captured 
from PI channel (red), FITC channel (green), or the overlay </p>































































<p>
Figure 3 in vitro stability of PTX-loaded nPs: (A) size distributions of PTX-loaded ca-Plga-TPgs, Plga-TPgs, and Plga nPs during 90 days of storage; and (B) zeta 
potentials of PTX-loaded ca-Plga-TPgs, Plga-TPgs, and Plga nPs during 90 days of storage. error bars denote standard deviation. 
Abbreviations: PTX, paclitaxel; nPs, nanoparticles; ca, cholic acid; Plga, poly(lactide-co-glycolide); TPgs, d-α-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate. </p>































<p>
Figure 4 In vitro drug release profiles of PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS, PLGA-
TPgs, and Plga nPs. error bars denote standard deviation. *P0.05; **P0.01. 
Abbreviations: PTX, paclitaxel; ca, cholic acid; Plga, poly(lactide-co-glycolide); 
TPgs, d-α-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate; nPs, nanoparticles. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>665 </p>

<p>PTX-loaded copolymer nanoparticles for melanoma chemotherapy </p>

<p>of them. Given that green C6-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs 
were located closely surrounding the red cell nuclei (stained 
by PI), these NPs were considered to have been internalized 
effectively into A875 cells. 
The cellular uptake efficiencies of C6-loaded NPs were fur-
ther quantified (Figure 6), which reduced with rising concentra-
tion of incubated NPs from 50 to 200 μg/mL. Such efficiencies 
of CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs were 1.33-, 1.43-, and 1.50-fold 
those of PLGA-TPGS NPs after incubation with 50, 100, and 
200 μg/mL NPs, respectively, which can be ascribed to the 
higher cell adherence and smaller size. The cellular uptake effi-
ciencies of PLGA-TPGS and CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs surpassed 
that of PLGA NPs owing to the smaller hydrodynamic sizes 
of the former two and the TPGS segment. TPGS overcame 
the multidrug resistance of A875 cells by suppressing P-gp, 
which may decrease the excretion of fluorescence molecule 
C6. Taken together, with higher cellular uptake efficiency 
and smaller hydrodynamic size, CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs can 
feasibly be applied in cancer therapy as drug carriers. </p>

<p>in vitro cytotoxicity of PTX-loaded nPs </p>

<p>A875 cells were employed to study the cytotoxicity of PTX-
loaded NPs in vitro and to demonstrate whether PTX encap-
sulated into these NPs was maintained bioactive. Based on the 
achievable plasma PTX levels in human body, the cells were 
treated by suspensions of PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS, 
PLGA-TPGS, and PLGA NPs or polyoxyethylene castor oil 
and ethanol for 24 and 48 h at equivalent PTX concentra-
tions of 0.25, 2.5, and 25 μg/mL, respectively. 32,47 PTX-free 
CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs with the same NPs dose were used as 
well. The percentage of viable cells was detected by the MTT 
assay (Figure 7). First, CA-PLGA-TPGS seemed nontoxic 
to and biocompatible with cells and tissues because all the 
PTX-free CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs at different concentrations 
did not show significant cytotoxicity. Second, with increas-
ing incubation time and drug dose, the cytotoxicities of all 
the four formulations were augmented. Third, PTX-loaded 
CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs had the most evident in vitro cyto-
toxicity. After incubation for 24 h at the drug concentration 
of 2.5 μg/mL, the cell viability was 64.78% for CA-PLGA-
TPGS NPs, 67.53% for PLGA-TPGS NPs, 68.38% for 
PLGA NPs, and 69.78% for polyoxyethylene castor oil and 
ethanol. However, after incubation for 48 h, the cytotoxicity 
of PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs was 23.62% higher 
than that of polyoxyethylene castor oil and ethanol. With 
prolonged incubation, the therapeutic effects of PTX-loaded 
CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs were boosted compared with those 
of other drug-loaded NPs and polyoxyethylene castor oil 
and ethanol because of faster drug release and higher cel-
lular uptake. Moreover, CA-PLGA-TPGS had more TPGS 
which was also cytotoxic and thus able to cooperate with 
chemotherapeutic drug PTX. 23,48 
The cytotoxicities of the four PTX formulations against 
A875 cells were further quantified based on IC 50 values. IC 50 
values of A875 cells treated with PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-
TPGS, PLGA-TPGS, and PLGA NPs and polyoxyethylene 
castor oil and ethanol for 24 and 48 h are summarized in 
Table 2. The IC 50 values of polyoxyethylene castor oil 
and ethanol and PTX-loaded nanocarriers were similar 
after incubation for 24 h. Nevertheless, the IC 50 values 
of PTX-loaded nanocarriers after 48 h, especially that 
of PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs, were obviously 
lower than that of polyoxyethylene castor oil and ethanol, 
demonstrating that these nanocarriers were much more 
cytotoxic against A875 cells because of continuous drug 
release. Moreover, the therapeutic effects of PTX-loaded 
CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs were superior to those of PLGA and 
PLGA-TPGS NPs, although the copolymer vehicles had 
similar molecular weights. </p>









<p>Figure 5 confocal laser scanning microscopy images of a875 cells after 2 h of 
incubation with c6-loaded ca-Plga-TPgs nPs. c6-loaded nPs were green, and 
the cells were stained by Pi (red). The cellular uptake was observed by overlaying 
images obtained by FITC channel (green) and PI channel (red). Magnification ×0.5 k. 
Abbreviations: c6, coumarin-6; ca, cholic acid; Plga, poly(lactide-co-glycolide); 
TPgs, d-α-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate; nPs, nanoparticles; 
PI, propidium iodide; FITC, fluorescein isothiocyanate. </p>



































<p>Figure 6 Cellular uptake efficiencies of C6-loaded NPs at different NPs concentrations. 
error bars denote standard deviation. *P0.05; **P0.01. 
Abbreviations: c6, coumarin-6; nPs, nanoparticles; ca, cholic acid; Plga, poly-
(lactide-co-glycolide); TPgs, d-α-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>666 </p>

<p>su et al </p>

<p>In vivo antitumor efficacy </p>

<p>Based on the satisfactory cytotoxicity against A875 cells 
in vitro, CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs may be an eligible vehicle 
for MM treatment. In the present study, the antitumor effects 
of PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs were also assessed in 
A875 cells-bearing nude mice. Figure 8A presents the 12-day 
tumor growth of mice injected with PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-
TPGS NPs, polyoxyethylene castor oil and ethanol, and 
saline (control). Every 4 days, the mice were subjected to tail 
intravenous injection with PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs 
and polyoxyethylene castor oil and ethanol for four consecu-
tive cycles. Every 2 days, the tumor volume and body weight 
were recorded until the 12th day. As shown in Figure 8A, 
polyoxyethylene castor oil and ethanol and PTX-loaded CA-
PLGA-TPGS NPs sharply slowed down the growth of tumors 
in mice compared with saline. Furthermore, the PTX-loaded 
CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs group had slower tumor growth than 
those of the other two groups. In short, PTX was effectively 
released from PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs, with its </p>

<p>bioactivity well retained. This is of great significance to clini-
cal MM therapy. 
In the development of novel drug delivery systems, it 
is imperative to reduce the adverse events of drug-loaded 
NPs. The systemic adverse effects on animals can be 
evaluated by measuring body weight changes. Figure 8B 
presents changes in the body weights of all nude mice. The 
polyoxyethylene castor oil and ethanol group significantly 
lost weight, whereas the mice injected with PTX-loaded 
CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs gained weight. Throughout the 
experiment, the mice treated by PTX-loaded NPs remained 
vigorous and healthy, but those treated by polyoxyethylene 
castor oil and ethanol exhibited weakened vitality, one of 
which even died. Hence, the mice injected with PTX-loaded 
CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs were less susceptible to side effects 
than the polyoxyethylene castor oil and ethanol-treated mice, 
which is consistent with the results of Zhao et al. 31 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs for MM treatment were 
fabricated by a slightly modified method of nanoprecipita-
tion. Their hydrodynamic size was measured by DLS as 
125.6±5.3 nm, which was smaller than those of PLGA and 
PLGA-TPGS NPs. CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs exhibited higher 
drug LC and EE than those of PLGA and PLGA-TPGS NPs, 
with much faster drug release. In vitro cellular uptake study 
indicated that the NPs were internalized by A875 cells and 
that the cellular uptake efficiency of CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs 
was maximum. PTX-loaded CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs exerted 
markedly better antitumor effects in vitro and in vivo than </p>







































































<p>Figure 7 Viability of a875 cells incubated with PTX-loaded nPs in comparison with that of Taxol at the same drug dose and drug-free ca-Plga-TPgs nPs with the same 
amount of nPs: (A) 24 h and (B) 48 h. error bars denote standard deviation. *P0.05; **P0.01. 
Abbreviations: PTX, paclitaxel; nPs, nanoparticles; ca, cholic acid; Plga, poly(lactide-co-glycolide); TPgs, d-α-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate. </p>

<p>Table 2 ic 50 values of PTX-loaded ca-Plga-TPgs, Plga-
TPgs, and Plga nPs and Taxol ® , on a875 cells following 24 and 
48 h of incubation, respectively (n=3) </p>

<p>Incubation 
time (h) 
IC 50 (μg/mL) </p>

<p>CA-PLGA-
TPGS NPs </p>

<p>PLGA-
TPGS NPs </p>

<p>PLGA NPs Taxol </p>

<p>24 
9.04±0.63 
13.56±0.82 
16.27±0.79 
22.15±1.04 
48 
0.84±0.05 
2.16±0.25 
4.3±0.58 
17.86±2.57 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ic 50 , drug concentration that inhibits the growth of 50% cells; PTX, 
paclitaxel; ca, cholic acid; Plga, poly(lactide-co-glycolide); TPgs, d-α-tocopheryl 
polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate; nPs, nanoparticles. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>667 </p>

<p>PTX-loaded copolymer nanoparticles for melanoma chemotherapy </p>

<p>those of polyoxyethylene castor oil and ethanol. In summary, 
PTX-loaded star-shaped CA-PLGA-TPGS NPs are promis-
ing vehicles for MM chemotherapy. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This project was supported by the Natural Science 
Foundation of Guangdong (2016A030313029), Scientific 
Plan Program of Guangdong (2014A020212038), Innova-
tion Program of Shenzhen (JCYJ20150330102720122), 
and International Cooperation Foundation of Shenzhen 
(GJHZ20160301163138685). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>References </p>



































































<p>
Figure 8 (A) Tumor growth curves of nude mice bearing a875 cells xenograft after intravenous injection of PTX-loaded ca-Plga-TPgs nPs, Taxol, and saline. (B) Variations 
in body weights of nude mice bearing a875 cells xenograft treated with PTX-loaded ca-Plga-TPgs nPs, Taxol, and saline. error bars denote standard deviation. *P0.05; 
**P0.01 (n=6). 
Abbreviations: PTX, paclitaxel; ca, cholic acid; Plga, poly(lactide-co-glycolide); TPgs, d-α-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate; nPs, nanoparticles. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/drug-design-development-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal that spans the spectrum of drug design 
and development through to clinical applications. Clinical outcomes, 
patient safety, and programs for the development and effective, safe, 
and sustained use of medicines are the features of the journal, which </p>

<p>has also been accepted for indexing on PubMed Central. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>668 </p>

<p>su et al </p>



</text></tei>