<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5144680" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>There is growing recognition that small open reading frames (sORFs) encoding peptides shorter 
than 100 amino acids are an important class of functional elements in the eukaryotic genome, 
with several already identified to play critical roles in growth, development, and disease. 
However, our understanding of their biological importance has been hindered owing to the sig-
nificant technical challenges limiting their annotation. Here we combined ultra-deep sequencing 
of ribosome-associated poly-adenylated RNAs with rigorous conservation analysis to identify a 
comprehensive population of translated sORFs during early Drosophila embryogenesis. In total, 
we identify 399 sORFs, including those previously annotated but without evidence of transla-
tional capacity, those found within transcripts previously classified as non-coding, and those 
not previously known to be transcribed. Further, we find, for the first time, evidence for transla-
tion of many sORFs with different isoforms, suggesting their regulation is as complex as longer 
ORFs. Furthermore, many sORFs are found not associated with ribosomes in late-stage 
Drosophila S2 cells, suggesting that many of the translated sORFs may have stage-specific 
functions during embryogenesis. These results thus provide the first comprehensive annotation 
of the sORFs present during early Drosophila embryogenesis, a necessary basis for a detailed 
delineation of their function in embryogenesis and other biological processes. </p>

<p>Now that the genomes of many organisms have been sequenced, 
their comprehensive annotation is required to fully understand the 
functional elements that are encoded therein. 
1-3 Although the focus </p>

<p>of much of this annotation is of longer open reading frames (ORFs), 
there is growing appreciation that the much less studied small ORFs 
(sORFs), historically defined as &lt;100 amino acids (aa) in length, 
may prove to be as widely significant in many biological processes as 
the larger class. 
4-16 For example, the tarsal-less (tal) gene in </p>

<p>Drosophila, which was previously thought to be a long non-coding 
RNA (lncRNA), has been found to contain four conserved sORFs 
encoding three 11-aa and one 32-aa peptides, that are required for 
embryonic tracheal development and leg morphogenesis. </p>

<p>5,13,17 </p>

<p>Similarly, a conserved 56-aa peptide encoded by the Toddler gene in 
zebrafish has been found to function as a mitogen to promote cell mi-
gration during gastrulation. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>However, what has primarily hindered our appreciation of the ex-
tent to which the sORFs are biologically significant is, in fact, their 
reliable identification, the necessary first step before any detailed 
functional characterization. 
19,20 In general, strictly bioinformatic </p>

<p>approaches require a large number of experimentally validated 
ORFs to serve as a training set to enable subsequent de novo predic-
tion, but there are presently not a sufficient number of identified 
sORFs for this purpose. Alternatively, ORFs can be identified based 
on conservation alone, but for that, reliable prediction generally re-
quires sequences that encode peptides that are longer than 100-aa. </p>

<p>21-</p>

<p>26 Direct identification of translated peptides in the cell by proteomic </p>

<p>methods is also often highly effective, however these methods are 
well known to be inefficient at detecting proteins of small size. </p>

<p>10,27,28 </p>

<p>Thus, it is highly likely that many sORFs have been misclassified as 
lncRNAs or missed entirely from present annotation. 
Several attempts have been made to identify sORFs on a genome-
wide scale in model organisms such as Drosophila using more tar-
geted bioinformatics approaches. 
29-32 Yet, while this work suggests </p>

<p>that there may be thousands of sORFs translated in these organisms, 
there is presently a lack of experimental translational verification for 
the majority of the predictions. Perhaps the most successful experi-
mental method to identify sORFs so far has been deep sequencing of 
ribosome-associated RNA. 
10,31-33 However, recent work has sug-</p>

<p>gested that ribosome occupancy alone is insufficient to unequivocally 
conclude that a potential sORF is indeed translated. 
34,35 Instead, </p>

<p>combining deep sequencing of ribosome-associated RNAs with bio-
informatics analysis has emerged as a powerful approach to identify 
translated sORFs, genome-wide. </p>

<p>34-37 </p>

<p>Of the few well characterized sORFs, a surprisingly large fraction, 
like tal and Toddler mentioned above, has been found to play vital 
roles during development. 
14,16-18,38,39 We thus speculated that there </p>

<p>might be a large number of presently unannotated sORFs that per-
form critical functions during development, and that identifying the 
complete repertoire of translated sORFs during embryogenesis 
would prove both a useful strategy to identify a large set of sORFs to 
aid de novo sORF prediction as well as a necessary resource to un-
derstand this fundamental biological process. 
Thus, to this end, we have performed ultra-deep sequencing of 
ribosome-associated poly-adenylated RNAs together with conserva-
tion analyses to identify conserved translated sORFs during the first 
4 hours of embryogenesis in Drosophila, the period during which 
control shifts from maternal-to zygotic-encoded transcripts. </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Overall, we have identified 399 sORFs that are translated during 
early embryogenesis, which substantially increases the number of </p>

<p>verified sORFs in Drosophila. Of these, 128 were previously pre-
dicted sORFs but lacked experimental support, 22 are located in 
transcripts previously classified as lncRNAs, and 45 are novel sORFs 
found on transcripts not previously known to be transcribed. 
Further, among the sORFs that were previously annotated, we pro-
vide the first evidence of translation for sORFs with multiple iso-
forms. We tested the translational capability of randomly selected 
sORFs identified here in Drosophila S2Rþ cell lines using an eGFP-
tagged transfection assay, and found that most (22 out of 23) were 
highly translated, attesting to the validity of our combined experi-
mental and bioinformatics approach. Thus, with this work, we pro-
vide the first comprehensive annotation of sORFs during early 
Drosophila embryogenesis, which we anticipate will aid our under-
standing of early development as well as the functions of sORFs in 
biological processes in general. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Drosophila embryo collections </p>

<p>Early (0-4 h) Canton S embryos were collected from egg laying 
dishes. The embryos were then dechorionated by treatment with 
50% bleach for 3-5 min and washed thoroughly with phosphate 
buffer solution (PBS buffer, pH7.4). 
41 The embryos were then trans-</p>

<p>ferred into Eppendorf tubes. </p>

<p>2.2. Ribosome material preparation </p>

<p>To obtain the ribosome material, the dechorionated embryos were 
immediately incubated with 100 mg/ml cycloheximide in PBS for 
5 min on ice, then the embryos were homogenized with a plastic pel-
let pestle in 100 ml of a mild ribosome lysis buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl, 
pH 7.4, 140 mM KCl, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.5 mM DTT, 1% Triton X-
100, 100 mg/ml cycloheximide, 0.5 U/ml RNasin) and incubated for 
10 min on ice. The nuclei and whole cells were removed by centrifu-
gation at 16,000 Â g for 10 min at 4 
C, and the lipid and other mem-</p>

<p>branes were filtered out from the supernatant using a 100 mm sieve 
mesh. Finally, the cytosolic supernatant was loaded onto 20-50% 
continuous sucrose density gradients with the lysis buffer (20 mM 
Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 140 mM KCl, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.5 mM DTT), fol-
lowed by ultracentrifugation at 35,000 rpm for 2.5 h in a SW41 ro-
tor at 4 
C (OptimaL-100 XP 2100 Ultracentrifuge, Beckman). </p>

<p>Absorbance in each layer of the sucrose density gradient was mea-
sured at an optical density of 254 nm using the Piston Gradient 
Fractionater (BioComp). The RNA components and the amount of 
ribosomes were determined based on distinct peaks in the polysome 
profiling. Ribosome material was collected by pooling both the 80S 
(monosome) and the polysome peaks identified in the profile. The 
polysome profiling of the material treated with EDTA was obtained 
as above, except that the cytosolic supernatant was treated with 
50 mM EDTA for 5 min on ice before loading onto the sucrose 
gradient. </p>

<p>2.3. Strand-specific RNA-seq library construction </p>

<p>The ribosome-associated RNA was extracted by adding an equal vol-
ume of Trizol reagent (Invitrogen) to the ribosome material, followed 
by chloroform extraction and ethanol precipitation. The RNA con-
centration was quantified by Nanodrop2000 (Thermo Scientific) and 
the RNA quality was detected by Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 
(Shanghai Biotechnology Corporation). The method to purify poly-
adenylated RNA of ribosome-associated RNA was optimized using </p>

<p> 
Ultra-deep sequencing of ribosome-associated poly-adenylated RNA </p>

<p>the RiboMinus Eukaryote Kit for RNA-Seq (no. A10837-08, 
Ambion) to delete ribosomal RNAs (rRNAs) and Dynabeads oligo 
(dT) 25 (no. 61002, Life Technologies) purification to select RNAs 
with poly-adenylated tails (Supplementary Fig. S1). The strand-
specific RNA-seq library of the ribosome-associated poly-adenylated 
RNA was prepared using the Illumina TruSeq Stranded mRNA 
Sample Preparation Kit (A10837-08, Ambion). The library was se-
quenced on the Illumina HiSeq 2000 (Shanghai Biotechnology 
Corporation) to a depth of about 70 M reads per library. </p>

<p>2.4. Preparation of total RNA and cytosolic RNA </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated by homogenization of dechorionated em-
bryos, followed by the RNA extraction protocol with Trizol. The total 
RNA was then treated with DNase I to eliminate genomic DNA con-
tamination. Cytosolic RNA was isolated from the supernatant of the 
embryo extract before loading onto sucrose gradient. The enrichment 
of both total RNA and cytosolic RNA for poly-adenylated RNAs was 
also performed using Dynabeads oligo (dT) 25 purification. Both sam-
ples were sequenced as the ribosome-associated RNA above. </p>

<p>2.5. Transcript assembly </p>

<p>The ribosome-associated RNA, total RNA, and cytosolic RNA deep 
sequencing reads were each separately aligned using the TopHat 
v2.0.9 package. 
42 We used a built-in strategy of TopHat for a higher </p>

<p>mapping rate. Raw data were first mapped to the Drosophila mela-
nogaster transcriptome (FlyBase r5.57 release) using the '-G' parame-
ter with other parameters set as default. The read pairs that were not 
completely mapped were then aligned to the D. melanogaster ge-
nome (dm3) for a second run. Only the uniquely aligned and concor-
dant read pairs were used for further analysis. We used <rs id="software-4" type="software">Cufflinks</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">v2.2.1</rs> with parameters set as default except using '-G' parameter to 
assemble transcripts in the ribosome RNA, total RNA, and cytosolic 
RNA separately, 
43 and merged the three assembled gtf files and </p>

<p>Flybase r5.57 annotation into a comprehensive transcriptome anno-
tation, from which all further analysis was based. The raw read 
counts were normalized by the FPKM (fragments per kilobase of 
exon model per million mapped fragments) for each transcript based 
on the Flybase r5.57 gene models. The FPKM values were calculated 
using the Cufflinks v2.2.1 package with parameters set as default. </p>

<p>2.6. Estimation of detectable level of transcription </p>

<p>A machine learning algorithm described by Ramskö ld et al. 
44 was </p>

<p>first used to determine an optimal FPKM cutoff by comparing the ex-
pression levels of all annotated genes with that of randomly selected 
intergenic regions. The intergenic regions were at least 5 kb away 
from any annotated genes of FlyBase and the length distribution of 
the selected intergenic regions was the same as the distribution of the 
annotated exons to avoid a FPKM calculation bias. In this way, we 
identified a threshold FPKM value of 0.15 (Supplementary Fig. S2). 
To increase the confidence of the expression, we further required 
that the read counts be &gt;20 reads. This value was determined based 
on an analysis of the annotated genes in our data of length between 
0.2 and 0.6 kb, assuming that background reads for a gene would 
follow a geometric distribution. 
45 Small RNAs (shorter than 200 nt) </p>

<p>were excluded because these were not efficiently captured and would 
be more likely resulting in assembly artifacts. For translation detec-
tion, we also required that the transcripts exhibit an expression level 
of ! 0.15 FPKM and ! 20 reads in our ribosome-associated RNA 
data. </p>

<p>2.7. Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction </p>

<p>Total RNA or ribosome RNA was reverse transcribed into cDNAs 
with SuperScript III Reverse Transcriptase (Invitrogen) and oligo 
(dT) 20 VN primer. cDNAs were used to amplify the RNA targets by 
polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using the internal gene-specific pri-
mers and DNA Taq polymerase (no. DR100A, Takara). </p>

<p>2.8. Evaluation of translational evidence for annotated 
sORFs </p>

<p>We considered as evidence of translation for a given annotated sORF 
as either: (i) the peptide fragment corresponding to the sORF was 
present in the most-recent proteomic screen (FlyBase r5.57 release); 
or (ii) the sORF was identified as a translated sORF in a previous ri-
bosome profiling study in Drosophila S2 cells. </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>2.9. Analysis of translated potential by PhyloCSF </p>

<p>To identify conserved translated sORFs, we utilized two annotated 
datasets to estimate the PhyloCSF threshold, comparing with 11 
other Drosophila species: (i) the positive dataset was the annotated 
sORFs in FlyBase; and (ii) the negative dataset was all the sORFs 
contained in annotated lincRNAs based on the assumption that all 
of these sORFs are non-translated. From the histogram of the 
PhyloCSF score distribution in each set, we found an optimal 
PhyloCSF score of 50 which could discriminate annotated sORFs 
from untranslated sORFs (Supplementary Fig. S3). We then used the 
PhyloCSF package to evaluate the coding potential of ORFs con-
tained in ribosome-associated lncRNAs and novel transcripts with 
parameters '12flies -orf ¼ ATGStop -frames ¼ 3 -minCodons ¼ 10', 
which was intended to find all ORFs longer than 10-aa in frame. To 
avoid any influence of annotated ORFs, we excluded the ORFs 
which overlapped with annotated ORFs in the same or opposite 
strand. The multi-alignment file of 12 flies species were downloaded 
from the <rs type="software">Galaxy</rs> cloud tool. </p>

<p>47-49 </p>

<p>2.10. Identification of embryo specific sORFs </p>

<p>For the annotated sORFs, we compared them directly with the trans-
lated sORFs identified in the S2 cell line. Due to the lack information 
of sORFs in lncRNA and novel transcripts, we manually examined 
for the presence of at least one read in the S2 ribosome data mapped 
to the identified sORF regions. </p>

<p>2.11. Calculation of arginine frequency of the identified 
sORFs </p>

<p>We calculated the arginine frequency by counting the number of ar-
ginines within all sORFs in each set. For the random control, we de-
termined the expected frequencies of arginine based on that encoded 
from a random distribution of nucleotides. 
50 For this calculation we </p>

<p>used, as observed frequencies of the four DNA bases in nature, as 
0.22 of uracil, 0.303 of adenine, 0.217 of cytosine, and 0.261 of 
guanine. </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>2.12. eGFP-tagged sORF construction </p>

<p>The eGFP-tagged sORF vectors were based on the full-length cDNA 
of the corresponding sORFs. The full-length cDNAs were amplified 
by gene-specific full-length primers that introduced two different re-
striction enzyme digestion sites at the two ends. The cDNAs were 
then cloned into the pGEM T-easy vector, inserting an AvrII enzyme 
digestion site before the stop codon. The sequence of the eGFP </p>

<p> 
H. Li et al. </p>

<p>coding regions (CDS) which did not contain start or stop codons of 
the CDS was amplified-tagged with AvrII digestion sites at the two 
ends. CDS sequences of eGFP were digested by AvrII and cloned into 
the AvrII linearized sORF vector in-frame. These eGFP-sORF se-
quences were excised by double restriction enzyme digestion and 
directionally cloned into pUAST. </p>

<p>2.13. Transfections and immunoblotting </p>

<p>S2Rþ cells were grown in Schneider's medium (no. 21720-024, 
Invitrogen) with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (no. 
16140-071, Gibco). S2Rþ cells were transfected with reconstructed 
pUAST plasmid using X-tremeGENE HP DNA Transfection 
Reagent (no. 06366244001, Roche). After 48 h, proteins were ex-
tracted with RIPA Buffer (no. R0278, Sigma) containing protease in-
hibitor (no. 04693159001, Roche). The cell extract was then run in 
12% Bis-Tris gels. Immunoblots were incubated with anti-GFP 
(1:1,000; no. M048-3, MBL) and then the secondary antibody Alexa 
Fluor 680 donkey anti-mouse lgG (1:1,000; no. A10038, Life 
Technologies). Controls were incubated with anti-a-tubulin 
(1:1,000; no. PM054, MBL) and then secondary antibody Alexa 
Fluor 680 goat anti-rabbit lgG (1:1000; no. A21076, Life 
Technologies). </p>

<p>2.14. Localization of eGFP-fusion peptide </p>

<p>After 48 hr post transfection, the cells were fixed for 10 min with 4% 
paraformaldehyde and then mounted in antifade mountant with 
DAPI (no. P36962, Life Technologies). Imaging was acquired using a 
Nikon A1Si confocal microscope with a CFI Plan Fluor 40 Â 
objective. </p>

<p>3. Results and discussion </p>

<p>3.1. Ultra-deep sequencing identifies an exhaustive set 
of ribosome-associated RNAs </p>

<p>To globally identify translated sORFs in the 0-4 h Drosophila em-
bryos, we performed ultra-deep sequencing of ribosome-associated 
poly-adenylated RNAs isolated using density gradient velocity sedi-
mentation (see Materials and methods) (Fig. 1A). 
41 Our ribosome </p>

<p>profile revealed the presence of ribosomal subunits (40S and 60S) as 
well as monosomes (80S) and polysomes (Fig. 1B). To verify the 
identity of this ribosome material, prior to the sucrose gradient sepa-
ration, we treated the embryo extract with 50 mM EDTA, which is 
known to dissociate intact ribosomes into their constituent subu-
nits. 
51,52 As expected, this treatment completely eliminated the peaks </p>

<p>of the intact ribosomes in the profile, while the peaks associated with 
the 40S and 60S subunits increased significantly (Fig. 1C). For our 
analysis, we collected not only polysomes as is typical with this ap-
proach but also monosomes as well, with which some short 
transcripts are only associated. 
53,54 Further, we purified only </p>

<p>the poly-adenylated RNAs from this ribosome material, since non-
poly-adenylated RNAs, a large proportion of the transcriptome, do 
not likely contain translated ORFs. 
55 The ribosome-associated poly-</p>

<p>adenylated RNAs were converted into cDNA libraries for strand-
specific, paired-end 100 base-pair (bp) sequencing with HiSeq 2000. 
Overall, we obtained a total of 71.2 million (M) aligned reads, of 
which 68.9 M (96.8%) were uniquely mapped to the Drosophila ge-
nome (Dm3), representing a $460-fold coverage of the Drosophila 
transcriptome. To enable the calculation of ribosome association effi-
ciency (see below), we also deep sequenced the poly-adenylated </p>

<p>RNAs from the total RNA population from the 0-4 hr Drosophila 
embryos in a similar way as described for the ribosome-associated 
RNAs. We also deep sequenced the cytosolic RNA from this same 
embryonic sample to maximize the annotation of the translated tran-
scripts (see 'Materials and methods' section). In total, 213.9 M 
paired-end aligned reads were obtained in the combined dataset, of 
which 91.7% were uniquely aligned to Dm3, nearly 10-fold higher 
in depth than previously obtained transcriptomic datasets of this 
stage. 
46,56,57 Following a procedure detailed in the Materials and </p>

<p>methods, we finally identified 20,614 unique transcripts from 9,582 
loci with high confidence in the 0-4 h Drosophila embryo 
(Supplementary Table S1). Comparing this with the latest release of 
the Drosophila transcriptome (FlyBase r5.57), we found that 18,613 
transcripts (90.3%) are identical to the annotated transcripts, attest-
ing to the high quality of our assembly. We further validated this as-
sembly by randomly selecting a set of 18 of the novel transcripts 
using reverse transcription-PCR (RT-PCR) and found that 17 tran-
scripts are indeed detected in the 0-4 h embryo (Supplementary Fig. 
S4 and Supplementary Table S3). 
From among the 20,614 unique transcripts identified in the com-
bined dataset, we found that 17,166 from 8,803 loci are ribosome-
associated (Supplementary Table S1). We directly compared the 
FPKM values for each transcript in the ribosome RNA data with the 
corresponding average intensities measured in a previous microarray 
study of 0-2 h embryos, 
41 and found a high degree of correlation </p>

<p>(Spearman correlation coefficient 0.76). These ribosome-associated 
transcripts thus represent a large fraction of the Drosophila tran-
scriptome (83.3%). We classified these transcripts into three catego-
ries based on the annotation in FlyBase: protein-coding transcripts 
including novel variant isoforms (16,576), lncRNAs that also include 
novel variant isoforms (349), and assembled novel transcripts (241). 
We validated the ribosome association of 35 randomly selected tran-
scripts in the latter two categories with RT-PCR, and found that 34 
transcripts could indeed be detected in the 0-4 h embryo 
(Supplementary Fig. S5 and Supplementary Table S3). </p>

<p>3.2. Ribosome association provides translational 
evidence for annotated sORFs </p>

<p>The 16,576 ribosome-associated protein-coding transcripts corre-
spond to 11,092 different ORFs, including 332 sORFs 
(Supplementary Table S2). Of the latter, inspection of FlyBase re-
vealed that there was prior evidence of translation for only 204 an-
notated sORFs (Fig. 2A). 
46 Thus, our data provides the first </p>

<p>necessary translational evidence for 128 annotated sORFs, substan-
tially increasing the number of sORFs in Drosophila with evidence 
of translation. We note that the well-studied functional sORFs in 
Drosophila, tal and scl, were highly enriched in our ribosome-
associated fraction (Fig. 2B), lending further confidence in the quality 
of our data. 
Much of this previous translational evidence for the annotated 
sORFs was obtained from Drosophila S2 cells, which are derived 
from late stage embryos (20-24 h). 
46,58 Of the 332 sORFs in our </p>

<p>data, 148 are not translated in the S2 cell line. Though cultured cells 
can exhibit phenotypes different from the original cells from which 
they are derived, these results indicate that a substantial fraction of 
the sORFs might be translated specifically during defined develop-
mental stages. This comparison also suggests that a detailed charac-
terization of the ribosome-associated RNAs at the other stages of 
development might uncover evidence for the translation of other 
sORFs. </p>

<p> 
Ultra-deep sequencing of ribosome-associated poly-adenylated RNA </p>

<p>One advantage of our experimental approach is that we obtain 
the identity of the full-length of the ribosome-associated transcripts, 
enabling the detection of specific gene isoforms. Of the 332 different 
sORFs (corresponding to 313 genes), there were 17 genes with two 
different sORFs and 1 gene with three different sORFs. In addition, 
there were 177 genes with more than one annotated isoforms and 86 
genes with variant isoforms not previously described. This is, in fact, 
the first detection of variant isoforms of translated sORFs. For exam-
ple, with the gene CG40228, we found five isoforms with (in total) 3 
different sORFs, including a variant isoform not previously charac-
terized with a unique 5 
0 untranslated region (UTR) that is 19 bp up-</p>

<p>stream of all other isoforms. Variant isoforms in longer ORFs are 
usually associated with their highly regulated, differential transla-
tion, 
59,60 and so this observation of variant sORF isoforms suggests </p>

<p>that the translational processing of the sORFs may be as complex as 
that governing their longer counterpart. Ribosome profiling might 
prove useful in this regard, since a recent study employing this 
method thoroughly characterized stop codon readthrough in many 
genes in early Drosophila embryos. </p>

<p>61 </p>

<p>3.3. Ribosome-associated RNA sequencing identifies 
translated sORFs among the lncRNAs </p>

<p>Transcripts that do not encode peptides and lack a 100-aa ORF are 
usually classified as lncRNAs. 
62,63 Although a number of these </p>

<p>transcripts have been found to indeed function in a non-coding </p>

<p>capacity, 
64-67 it remains to be determined whether at least some of </p>

<p>these transcripts are misclassified and actually encode sORFs. 
20,68 In </p>

<p>this regard, it is interesting that we have found 349 lncRNA tran-
scripts associated with 264 genes that are associated to ribosomes, 
which corresponds to 76.9% of the expressed lncRNAs in these early 
embryos (Fig. 2C), an amount that is consistent with previous find-
ings in different species. </p>

<p>69 </p>

<p>We reasoned that if these lncRNAs actually encode for peptides, 
then they may be associated to ribosomes to a similar extent as estab-
lished protein-coding genes. We thus evaluated the degree to which 
these lncRNAs and the protein-coding genes are associated with ri-
bosomes compared with their total level of expression (their 'ribo-
some association efficiency'). We found that, although these 
ribosome-associated lncRNAs are expressed at a much lower level 
than the protein-coding genes (Wilcoxon test, P-value &lt; 2.2e-16) 
(Fig. 3A), their ribosome association efficiency is not significantly dif-
ferent from that of the protein-coding genes (Wilcoxon test, P-value 
&gt; 0.05) (Fig. 3B). Thus, these apparently lncRNA transcripts are in-
deed associated to ribosomes to a similar extent as bona fide protein-
coding transcripts. 
Although it is likely that many of these transcripts are indeed non-
coding, 
70-72 we reasoned that at least some of these transcripts may </p>

<p>encode sORFs and thus examined these transcripts with a bioinfor-
matics approach for potential sORFs. In particular, we first identified 
ORFs with an ATG start codon and an in-frame stop codon, using 
the longest ORF for each stop codon. We then discarded those ORFs </p>

<p>Figure 1. Isolation procedure of ribosome-associated RNA. (A) Schematic procedure for the preparation of ribosome material from 0-4 hr Drosophila embryos. 
(B) Polysome profiling of this sample enables clear resolution of the monosome and polysome fractions that were isolated for deep sequencing of the ribo-
some-associated RNA. (C) Validation of the identification of the monosome and polysome peaks. As expected, treating the sample with 50 mM EDTA before 
loading the sample onto the sucrose gradient caused the intact ribosomal peaks to disappear and those of the 40S and 60S subunits to increase. </p>

<p> 
H. Li et al. </p>

<p>that encode for peptides smaller than 10-aa or that overlapped anno-
tated ORFs in the same or opposite strand. In this way, we identified 
1,784 putative sORFs (median length of 20-aa) and 9 potential long-
ORFs in 347 out of the 349 ribosome-associated lncRNAs (Fig. 3C). 
As a stricter criterion, we examined the conservation at the amino-
acid level of these putative sORFs using PhyloCSF, which has been 
demonstrated to be a highly effective method to identify sORFs. </p>

<p>69,70 </p>

<p>Using annotated sORFs and lincRNAs to establish rigorous thresh-
old values in this approach (see 'Materials and methods' section), we 
identified 28 ORFs located in 21 ribosome-associated lncRNA genes 
as conserved translated ORFs. Of these, 22 are sORFs 
(Supplementary Table S2), including 3 that are poly-cistronic like tal 
and scl. 
5,16,17 We note that among these 22 novel sORFs, 64% are </p>

<p>not found in the late-stage Drosophila S2 cell line, and thus may be 
specific for early embryos. The finding of a fair number of ribosome-
associated lncRNAs that lack coding potential is intriguing and re-
mains to be resolved. Based on the current understanding, one might 
speculate that they may play roles in RNA localization, RNA non-
sense mediated decay, translational regulation, or they may produce 
non-canonical proteins that are quickly degraded. 
71-73 Alternatively, </p>

<p>these lncRNAs may encode proteins with non-AUG start </p>

<p>codons. 
74,75 . However, one should also not exclude the possibility </p>

<p>that a further analysis would yield functions that are not yet known. </p>

<p>3.4. Ribosome-associated RNA sequencing identifies 
translated sORFs in novel transcripts </p>

<p>Of the 350 assembled novel transcripts identified in this study, 241 
are associated with the ribosomes (Fig. 2D). Similar to the ribosome-
associated lncRNAs, we found that these ribosome-associated novel 
transcripts are as tightly associated to the ribosomes as the protein-
coding genes (Wilcoxon test, P-value &gt; 0.05) (Fig. 3B), although 
their expression level is much lower than those known to encode for 
peptides (Wilcoxon test, P-value ¼ 3.638e-12) (Fig. 3A). Examining 
these transcripts for potential ORFs similarly to the lncRNAs de-
scribed above, we identified 2,521 putative ORFs, most of which 
(98.5%) were sORFs (median length of 24-aa) (Fig. 3C). Analysing 
these putative ORFs in terms of their conservation using PhyloCSF, 
we identified 66 different conserved translated ORFs contained 
within 32 of these novel transcripts (Supplementary Table S2). Of 
these, 45 are sORFs, most (87%) of which were present only in the 
early embryos and not in the S2 cell line. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Ribosome-associated sORFs, lncRNAs and novel transcripts. (A) Among the annotated sORFs associated with ribosomes, we provide evidence of 
translation for 128 previously predicted Drosophila sORFs. (B) The well-studied Drosophila genes, tal and scl which were previously thought to be lincRNAs but 
then shown to encode functional sORFs, are well-resolved in our ribosome-associated RNA data. (C) Proportion of expressed lncRNAs that are ribosome-associ-
ated. (D) Proportion of expressed novel transcripts that are ribosome-associated. For both the lncRNAs and the novel transcripts, there was a large fraction of 
the total number of expressed transcripts that were found to be associated to the ribosomes. </p>

<p> 
Ultra-deep sequencing of ribosome-associated poly-adenylated RNA </p>

<p>3.5. Translational validation of identified translated 
sORFs </p>

<p>As a low frequency of arginine occurrence is a common feature of 
proteins, and has been used as an indicator of the translational ca-
pacity of potential ORFs, 
46 we compared the arginine usage of our </p>

<p>identified translated ORFs with that expected from the aa frequen-
cies associated with randomly distributed nucleotides. 
50 We indeed </p>

<p>found that, like the annotated sORFs, the novel translated ORFs in 
both the previously identified lncRNAs and in the novel transcripts 
exhibit a much lower usage of arginine than this random distribu-
tion, consistent with the notion that these are indeed translatable 
sORFs (Fig. 4A). 
To provide additional support for this translational capacity, we 
examined the ability of 23 randomly selected sORFs, including 15 
annotated sORFs without evidence for translation, 4 sORFs in </p>

<p>lncRNAs, and 4 sORFs in novel transcripts, to be translated in 
Drosophila S2Rþ cells (Supplementary Table S3). We generated 
eGFP-fusion vectors that contained all of the translation-related ele-
ments of the sORF, including the 5 
0 UTR and 3 
0 UTR, together with </p>

<p>the enhanced green fluorescent protein (eGFP) coding sequence 
(CDS) in-frame following the sORF (Fig. 4B). Thus, translation of 
this eGFP-tagged sORF would produce an eGFP-fusion protein, for 
which we examined using Western blotting and fluorescence micros-
copy. Overall, we found that 22 of the 23 candidates were well trans-
lated (Fig. 4C-E and Supplementary Fig. S6). Of these, 3 were clearly 
localized in both the nucleus and cytoplasm as observed with eGFP 
control (Supplementary Fig. S6), while the other 19 were mainly lo-
calized in cytoplasm (Fig. 4C-E and Supplementary Fig. S6). Of note 
though, the cytoplasmic localization did not appear to be the same 
for all of the fusions, with some enriched in a single, large subsection </p>

<p>Figure 3. Characterization of the ribosome-associated lncRNAs and novel transcripts. (A) There was a lower abundance of the lncRNAs and novel transcripts on 
the ribosomes than the protein-coding RNAs. (P-value &lt; 2.2e-16 (***); P-value ¼ 3.638e-12 (**); Wilcoxon rank-sum test). (B) Despite their lower ribosome occu-
pation, the ribosome association efficiency of the lncRNAs and novel transcripts was not significantly different from that of the protein-coding RNAs (all P-val-
ues &gt; 0.05 relative to the protein coding RNA). Here, the ribosome association efficiency is defined as the ratio of the abundance of the ribosome-associated 
RNA to the total RNA. (C) Overall, the length of ORFs contained within these lncRNAs and novel transcripts are, in general, shorter than the annotated sORFs. </p>

<p> 
H. Li et al. </p>

<p>of the cytoplasm (Fig. 4C and Supplementary Fig. S6d, e, h, i, s), 
others with a more punctate distribution scattered throughout the cy-
toplasm (Fig. 4D and Supplementary Fig. S6c, f, g, o), and others 
with a more uniform distribution within the cytoplasm except for 
punctate locations (Fig. 4E and Supplementary Fig. S6f, l, m, n, p, q, 
t, u). Such a wide range of localizations is thus likely owing to the 
sORF-encoded peptide and not the eGFP, since the latter is present 
in all of the fusions (Supplementary Fig. S6b). Taken together, these 
results indicate that most of the identified translated sORFs could in-
deed be translated into peptides in vivo. </p>

<p>4. Conclusion </p>

<p>In this study, we provide the first genome-wide annotation of the 
translated sORFs population that is present during the very early 
stages of Drosophila embryogenesis, thus setting the stage for de-
tailed characterizations of their functions during this fundamental bi-
ological process. The 399 sORFs identified here significantly 
expands the population of known sORFs in this model organism, 
which we anticipate will aid in future bioinformatics approaches for 
de novo predictions of sORFs both in Drosophila, as well as in much 
less well studied organisms, such as humans. 
10,76 Determining if their </p>

<p>translation is indeed as complex as the longer ORFs, or if they form 
and evolve by mechanisms distinct from their longer counterparts, or 
indeed if their spectrums of biological functions are as diverse as the 
longer ORFs will be fascinating to now resolve. </p>

<p>5. Availability </p>

<p>RNA-seq data have been submitted to the EMBL with the accession 
numbers E-MTAB-4571. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors thank Professor Nan Liu from the Shanghai Institute of Organic 
Chemistry, Chinese Academy of Sciences, for providing the S2Rþ cell line and 
vectors. We also thank Professor Andrew C. B. Cato from the Karlsruhe 
Institute of Technology, Institute of Toxicology and Genetics, for providing 
the pUAST vector. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>None declared. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at www.dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Technology of China 
(2014YQ090709 and 2013CB967402); the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (91129000, 11374207, 91229108, 31370750, 21273148, 
31501054, 91529302, and 21303104); Science and Technology Commission of </p>

<p>Figure 4. Translation validation of identified sORFs. (A) The novel identified translated sORFs contained in lncRNAs and novel transcripts have a much lower ar-
ginine frequency compared with that expected from random sequences of nucleotides, similar to annotated sORFs. (B) Schematic of the transfection construct 
of the eGFP-tagged sORFs. (C-E) Translational validation of CG34136, CR44101 and pncr004:X. For each of the fusions, the number of reads in the ribosome-as-
sociated RNA data of the corresponding sORF is shown in the left panel, whereas a typical image from fluorescence microscopy (DAPI: DNA; eGFP: translated 
sORF) and the results from the Western blot are presented in the middle and right panels, respectively. In each Western DNA, the upper panel is the a-tubulin 
control detected with an anti-a-tubulin antibody and the molecular weight standard corresponds to 49 kDa. The lower panel in each Western blot is the fused-
sORF detected with anti-eGFP and the molecular weight standards refer to 38 kDa (top) and 28 kDa (bottom). The expected molecular weights of the sORFs are 
36.6, 30.8, and 30.3 kDa, respectively. Scale bar: 2.5 mm. </p>

<p> 
Ultra-deep sequencing of ribosome-associated poly-adenylated RNA </p>

<p>Shanghai Municipality (15142201200), Shanghai Jiao Tong University 
(YG2012MS58), and the K.C. Wong Education Foundation (H.K.). </p>



<p> 
H. Li et al. </p>



<p> 
Ultra-deep sequencing of ribosome-associated poly-adenylated RNA </p>

</text></tei>