<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5019270" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: During the past several decades, resistance to single or multiple anticancer agents has 
posed a great challenge in cancer therapy. Dedicator of cytokinesis 1 (DOCK1), the first identi-
fied member in DOCK family, plays diverse roles in cellular processes, including tumorigenesis. 
In this study, we explored the biological role of DOCK1 in the chemotherapeutic resistance in 
bladder cancer and its underlying mechanism. Our results showed that the bladder cancer cell 
lines UM-UC-3 and J82 with higher DOCK1 are more resistant to cisplatin, whereas B87 cells 
with the lowest expression of DOCK1 exhibited the highest sensitivity to cisplatin. Down-
regulation of DOCK1 with small interfering RNA (siRNA) increased the cisplatin sensitivity 
in bladder cancer cells. Moreover, treatment with cisplatin induced epithelial-mesenchymal 
transition (EMT), while transfection with Twist siRNA restored the chemosensitivity to 
cisplatin. In addition, we found that downregulation of DOCK1 reversed EMT program in 
bladder cancer cells. However, cotransfection with DOCK1 siRNA could not further enhance 
the cisplatin sensitivity and cellular phenotypic changes in tumor cells. Taken together, these 
results demonstrate that downregulation of DOCK1 could increase the chemosensitivity in 
bladder cancer cells via preventing cisplatin-induced EMT, suggesting that DOCK1 may serve 
as a potential therapeutic target in bladder cancer. 
Bladder cancer is the most common urinary tract malignancy and remains one of the 
costliest diseases to manage from diagnosis to death. 
1 In accordance with the invasion 
degree, patients with bladder cancer can be diagnosed as nonmuscle-invasive or muscle-
invasive tumor. 
2 In addition to the radical cystectomy, cisplatin-based neoadjuvant 
chemotherapy serves as an important therapy option and shows increased response 
rate and prolonged survival in patients with bladder cancer. 
3 However, cisplatin resis-
tance in the past several decades has become a great challenge for clinical treatment 
of bladder cancer, highlighting the urgency to investigate the molecular mechanism 
underlying the drug resistance. </p>

<p>4   The dedicator of cytokinesis (DOCK) family with eleven mammalian members 
belongs to the atypical Rho guanine nucleotide exchange factors. Emerging 
evidences reported the critical roles of DOCK in various cellular processes such as 
actin cytoskeleton and cell adhesion and migration. 
5,6 As the first identified member 
of DOCK protein family, DOCK1 plays crucial roles in cytoskeletal organization, 
myoblast fusion, and phagocytosis via Rac1 activation in Caenorhabditis elegans and 
Drosophila. 
7-9 The expression of DOCK1 is upregulated in ovarian cancer correlated </p>

<p>correspondence: Jiang-hua chen 
Kidney Disease center, The First 
Affiliated Hospital, Zhejiang University 
school of Medicine, 79 Qingchun road, 
hangzhou 310003, Zhejiang Province, 
People's republic of china 
Tel +86 138 5809 9862 
email jhchen10@126.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Drug Design, Development and Therapy 
8 September 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2846 </p>

<p>chen et al </p>

<p>with aggressive phenotype and poor patient survival. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Moreover, engulfment and cell motility 1 (Elmo1) syner-
gistically with DOCK180 promote cell motility in ovarian 
carcinoma. 
11 Functional studies reveal that DOCK1 is asso-
ciated with tumorigenesis, growth, and invasion of glioma, 
suggesting that DOCK1 could be a potential therapeutic 
target for malignant brain tumor. 
12-14 However, the biological 
function of DOCK1 in bladder cancer has not been investi-
gated. Thus, this study aimed to explore the role of DOCK1 
in the chemotherapeutic resistance in bladder cancer and its 
underlying mechanism. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
cell culture </p>

<p>Three bladder cancer cell lines (UM-UC-3, J82, and B87) 
were purchased from the American Type Culture Collection 
(Manassas, VA, USA) and cultured in Dulbecco's Modified 
Eagle's Medium (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, 
USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum and 1% 
penicillin/streptomycin. All cells were maintained at 37°C in 
5% CO 2 incubator. All experiments included in this research 
were in compliance with the defined policies and protocols, 
and the Ethical Committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of 
Zhejiang University approved the research protocol. Cispla-
tin was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Co. (St Louis, MO, 
USA). The DOCK1 small interfering RNA (siRNA) and 
Twist siRNA were purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnol-
ogy Inc. (Dallas, TX, USA). </p>

<p>ccK-8 assay </p>

<p>Cells at 3.0×10 
3 cells/well were seeded into 96-well plates. Then, 
10 µL/well Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8) solution (Dojindo, 
Kumamoto, Japan) was added, the plates were incubated for 
3 hours, and absorbance was measured at 450 nm using an MRX 
II microplate reader (Dynex, Chantilly, VA, USA). </p>

<p>edU incorporation assay </p>

<p>DNA incorporation synthesis was calculated using EdU 
(5-ethynyl-2-deoxyuridine) incorporation assay. Measure-
ment of inhibitive rate of cell proliferation was carried out 
using a Click-iT EdU Imaging Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific) 
according to the procedure described previously. </p>

<p>15   sirna transfection </p>

<p>Bladder cancer cells were transfected with DOCK1 siRNA 
and Twist siRNA using Lipofectamine 2000 (Thermo Fisher 
Scientific) according to the manufacturer's instruction. </p>

<p>The transfection medium (Opti-MEM; Thermo Fisher 
Scientific) was replaced with complete medium 12 hours 
after transfection, and the cells were incubated for the 
indicated times. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence </p>

<p>Bladder cancer cells were seeded into 48-well plates at 
6.0×10 
3 cells/well. Slides were blocked with bovine serum 
albumin and incubated with mouse anti-human vimentin or anti-
human E-cadherin primary antibodies (Cell Signaling Tech-
nology, Danvers, MA, USA) at 4°C overnight. After washing, 
the slides were incubated with goat anti-mouse fluorescein 
isothiocyanate-conjugated secondary antibody (Abcam, 
Cambridge, UK). After incubation with 4',6-diamidino-
2-phenylindole (DAPI), cells were observed with a fluores-
cence microscope (Olympus Corporation, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Western blotting </p>

<p>Cells were lysed, and protein concentration was determined 
using a BCA kit (Beyotime, Nanjing, People's Republic of 
China). Afterward, protein samples were separated by 10% 
sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis 
and transferred to polyvinylidene di fluoride membranes 
(EMD Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA). The membranes were 
incubated with anti-DOCK1, anti-E-cadherin, anti-vimentin, 
and anti-Twist (Cell Signaling Technology) antibodies at 4°C 
overnight. The membranes were washed three times with Tris-
buffered saline-Tween 20 and then incubated with the appro-
priate horseradish peroxide-conjugated secondary antibodies. 
The protein bands were detected by chemiluminescence (GE 
Healthcare Bio-Sciences Corp., Piscataway, NJ, USA). </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Each experiment was performed in triplicate and repeated 
at least three times. Experimental data were presented as 
mean ± standard deviation and treated for statistics analysis 
by <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> program. Comparison between groups was made 
using analysis of variance, and statistically significant dif-
ference was defined as P,0.05. </p>

<p>Results 
Different cisplatin chemosensitivity 
in bladder cancer cells </p>

<p>First, we determined the protein expression of DOCK1 in three 
bladder cancer cell lines, including UM-UC-3, J82, and B87, 
using Western blotting. The protein levels varied in these three 
bladder cancer cell lines (Figure 1A). Interestingly, CCK-8 
assay (Figure 1B) and EdU incorporation assay (Figure 1C) </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2847 </p>

<p>DOcK1 regulates chemoresistance in bladder cancer cells via eMT </p>

<p>Figure 1 Different cisplatin chemosensitivity in bladder cancer cells. 
Notes: (A) Protein expression of DOcK1 in bladder cancer cells. Three bladder cancer cell lines, including UM-Uc-3, J82, and B87, were incubated with cisplatin for 
48 hours. cell viability and Dna synthesis were measured using ccK-8 method (B) and edU incorporation assay (C), respectively. Magnification: ×200. ***P,0.001. 
Abbreviations: DOcK1, dedicator of cytokinesis 1; h, hours. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2848 </p>

<p>chen et al </p>

<p>showed that UM-UC-3 and J82 cells with higher DOCK1 are 
more resistant to cisplatin, whereas B87 cells with the low-
est expression of DOCK1 exhibited the highest sensitivity to 
cisplatin. These results implied that DOCK1 may be involved 
in the chemoresistance to cisplatin in bladder cancer. </p>

<p>Downregulation of DOcK1 sensitized 
bladder cancer cells to cisplatin </p>

<p>UM-UC-3, J82, and B87 cells were transiently transfected 
with DOCK1 siRNA or control siRNA. After 48 hours, the 
expression of DOCK1 was obviously suppressed in these 
three cancer cell lines (Figure 2D). As a result, we found 
that downregulation of DOCK1 increased the cisplatin sen-
sitivity in bladder cancer cells (Figure 2A-C). These data 
demonstrated that decreased expression of DOCK1 sensitized 
bladder cancer cells to chemotherapy agents. </p>

<p>DOcK1 regulated eMT in bladder cancer 
cells </p>

<p>EMT program is involved in various tumor behaviors, such 
as growth, invasion, metastasis, and drug resistance. </p>

<p>16,17   Immunostaining and Western blot assay showed that cisplatin 
treatment inhibited the expression of E-cadherin (epithelial 
marker) and promoted the expression of vimentin (mes-
enchymal marker) in bladder cancer cells (Figure 3A). In 
order to block EMT in bladder cancer cells, Twist level was 
suppressed through transfection of Twist siRNA into tumor </p>

<p>cells (Figure 3B). Consequently, the cisplatin sensitivity was 
remarkably enhanced after EMT blockage in bladder cancer 
cells (Figure 3C). 
Next, we tested the hypothesis that DOCK1 regulated 
EMT in bladder cancer cells. Western blot analysis showed 
that EMT-related markers varied in different cell lines 
(Figure 4A). Interestingly, we observed that B87 cells with 
lower DOCK1 exhibited a significant increase of E-cadherin 
protein and reduced expression of vimentin. In addition, we 
found that downregulation of DOCK1 via siRNA transfec-
tion reversed EMT as shown by upregulation of E-cadherin 
and downregulation of vimentin in bladder cancer cells 
(Figure 4B). Based on these findings, we concluded that 
DOCK1 could regulate EMT in bladder cancer cells. </p>

<p>DOcK1 inhibition enhanced cisplatin 
sensitivity via eMT </p>

<p>To further define the role of DOCK1 in cisplatin-induced 
EMT, we detected the expression level of DOCK1 in 
cisplatin-treated cells. Western blot analysis revealed that cis-
platin treatment promoted the expression of DOCK1 in UM-
UC-3, J82, and B87 cells (Figure 5A). However, cisplatin 
addition failed to induce EMT in DOCK1-knockdown cells 
(Figure 5B), suggesting that EMT induction by cisplatin 
was dependent on DOCK1 in bladder cancer cells. To 
further elucidate the effects of DOCK1-regulated EMT on 
cisplatin sensitivity, bladder cancer cells were transfected </p>

<p>Figure 2 Downregulation of DOcK1 sensitized bladder cancer cells to cisplatin. 
Notes: Three bladder cancer cell lines, including UM-Uc-3, J82, and B87, were transfected with DOcK1 sirna and incubated with cisplatin for 48 hours. The ccK-8 assay 
was performed to determine cell viability in UM-Uc-3 (A), J82 (B), and B87 (C) cells. (D) Protein expression of DOcK1 in bladder cancer cells transfected with DOcK1 
sirna. ***P,0.001. 
Abbreviations: DOcK1, dedicator of cytokinesis 1; sirna, small interfering rna. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2849 </p>

<p>DOcK1 regulates chemoresistance in bladder cancer cells via eMT </p>

<p>with Twist siRNA alone or in combination with DOCK1 
siRNA. CCK-8 assay showed that DOCK1 inhibition could 
not further sensitize tumor cells to cisplatin after transfection 
with Twist siRNA (Figure 6A-C). On the molecular level, 
Western blot analysis showed that Twist knockdown led to 
a reduction of the mesenchymal marker vimentin in bladder 
cancer cells. However, cotransfection with DOCK1 siRNA 
had no obvious effects on the expression of cellular pheno-
type markers in Twist siRNA-transfected bladder cancer 
cells (Figure 6D). Taken together, these results confirmed 
that downregulation of DOCK1 sensitized bladder cancer 
cells to cisplatin via regulation of EMT. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Emerging evidences point that a wide range of pro-oncogene 
and antioncogene alterations are involved in the pathogenesis of 
bladder cancer. 
18 Despite significant progress in diagnosis and </p>

<p>treatment, the molecular mechanism of bladder carcinogenesis 
still remains elucidated, and specific therapeutic targets for blad-
der cancer are currently limited. In this study, we demonstrated 
that downregulation of DOCK1 increased cisplatin sensitivity 
via inhibition of EMT in bladder cancer cells. 
To our knowledge, this study for the first time demon-
strated the regulatory effect of DOCK1 on cisplatin sensitivity 
in bladder cancer cells, which we think is of biological impor-
tance given its potential therapeutic intervention for patients 
with bladder cancer resistant to chemotherapeutic agents. 
Functioning as a guanine nucleotide exchange factor, 
DOCK1 activates Rac1 and controls multiple cellular behav-
iors, including cell growth, motility, and survival, in both 
normal and pathological conditions. 
19,20 Previous exploration 
in gliomas demonstrated that DOCK1 is required for platelet-
derived growth factor receptor α-stimulated glioma cell 
migration and survival in vitro and tumor growth, survival, </p>

<p>Figure 3 cisplatin treatment induced eMT in bladder cancer cells. 
Notes: Three bladder cancer cell lines, including UM-UC-3, J82, and B87, were incubated with cisplatin for 48 hours. Immunofluorescence (A) was used to detect the 
expression of EMT-related markers, including E-cadherin and vimentin. Magnification: ×200. (B) Protein expression of Twist in bladder cancer cells transfected with Twist 
sirna. (C) ccK-8 assay was performed to determine the response of Twist sirna-transfected cells to cisplatin. ***P,0.001. 
Abbreviations: eMT, epithelial-mesenchymal transition; sirna, small interfering rna. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2850 </p>

<p>chen et al </p>

<p>Figure 4 DOcK1 regulated eMT in bladder cancer cells. 
Notes: Western blot analysis of e-cadherin and vimentin expression in UM-Uc-3, J82, and B87 before (A) and after transfection with DOcK1 sirna (B). ***P,0.001. 
Abbreviations: DOcK1, dedicator of cytokinesis 1; eMT, epithelial-mesenchymal transition; sirna, small interfering rna. </p>

<p>and invasion in the brain. 
13 A recent study has revealed 
that DOCK1 is also critical for epidermal growth factor 
receptor (EGFR) vIII-driven glioma growth and invasion via 
EGFRvIII-PKA-DOCK180-Rac1 signaling axis, providing 
a novel target to develop potential therapeutic strategies 
for malignant gliomas. 
12 Immunohistochemistry analysis 
shows the upregulation of DOCK1 in ovarian cancer, which 
is correlated with aggressive phenotype and poor patient 
survival. 
10 Documented biological role of DOCK1 in breast 
cancers demonstrates that DOCK1-Rac signaling is essential 
for HER2-mediated breast cancer progression to metastasis 
and offers a therapeutic opportunity to limit cancer spread. </p>

<p>21   Moreover, the low molecular weight heparin enoxaparin 
sensitizes human lung cancer cells to gefitinib through inhi-
bition of DOCK1 expression. 
22 All these findings suggest 
the oncogenic property of DOCK1 in human cancer. In our 
study, we found that the expression of DOCK1 varied in three 
bladder cancer cell lines, and its downregulation enhanced 
the cisplatin sensitivity, suggesting that DOCK1 is involved 
in the chemoresistance in bladder cancer. </p>

<p>A large number of studies demonstrate that EMT is 
of paramount importance in a plethora of cancer-related 
events, such as cancer metastasis, invasion, and refractory 
responses to chemotherapy. 
23-27 During EMT, epithelial 
markers such as E-cadherin decrease, while mesenchymal 
markers such as vimentin increase. 
28 In our study, we found 
that cisplatin treatment induced EMT in bladder cancer 
cells, while transfection with Twist siRNA restored the 
chemosensitivity to cisplatin. Moreover, the expression of 
EMT-related markers E-cadherin (epithelial) and vimentin 
(mesenchymal) varied in UM-UC-3, J82, and B87 cells. 
Interestingly, B87 cells with low-level DOCK1 exhibited 
a significant increase of E-cadherin and reduced vimentin. 
Based on these findings, we hypothesized that DOCK1 may 
regulate EMT in bladder cancer cells. Unsurprisingly, our 
results showed that DOCK1 knockdown reversed EMT 
program after DOCK1 siRNA transfection into bladder 
cancer cells. 
Drug resistance in bladder cancer involves a complex 
interplay of various factors, including the accumulation of </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2851 </p>

<p>DOcK1 regulates chemoresistance in bladder cancer cells via eMT </p>

<p>Figure 5 cisplatin-induced eMT was dependent on DOcK1. 
Notes: (A) Western blot analysis of DOcK1 expression in bladder cancer cells exposed to cisplatin. (B) after transfection with DOcK1 sirna, the expression of DOcK1, 
e-cadherin, and vimentin was determined in the presence of cisplatin. ***P,0.001. 
Abbreviations: eMT, epithelial-mesenchymal transition; DOcK1, dedicator of cytokinesis 1; sirna, small interfering rna. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2852 </p>

<p>chen et al </p>

<p>oncogenes and loss of tumor repressors. 
29-31 Serving as a 
potential oncogene, the expression of DOCK1 was increased 
in bladder cancer cells exposed to cisplatin. However, 
downregulation of DOCK1 prevented cisplatin-induced 
EMT in DOCK siRNA-transfected cells. Moreover, down-
regulation of DOCK1 failed to further enhance the cisplatin 
sensitivity in bladder cancer cells transfected with Twist 
siRNA. We also found that Twist knockdown attenuated the 
mesenchymal phenotype of bladder cancer cells. However, 
DOCK1 downregulation resulted in no further changes in 
cellular phenotype in Twist siRNA-transfected cells. Taken 
together, these results confirmed that DOCK1 knockdown 
sensitized bladder cancer cells to cisplatin via EMT. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, this study showed that downregulation of 
DOCK1 enhances the cytotoxicity of cisplatin in bladder 
cancer cells through preventing cisplatin-induced EMT. 
Thus, these findings may provide evidences to define DOCK1 
as a potential therapeutic target in bladder cancer. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was supported by Zhejiang Provincial Education 
Department Program (491010-G21410): Biological role 
and mechanism investigation of DOCK1 in chemoresis-
tance in bladder cancer, and Zhejiang Medical Science and 
Technology Program (2014KYA057): Biological effect and </p>

<p>Figure 6 DOcK1 knockdown sensitized bladder cancer cells to cisplatin via eMT. 
Notes: after transfection with Twist sirna alone or in combination with DOcK1 sirna, ccK-8 assay was performed to determine the cell viability of UM-Uc-3 (A), B87 (B), 
and J82 (C) cells. (D) Western blotting was used to measure the protein expression of DOcK1, Twist, e-cadherin, and vimentin in bladder cancer cells. **P,0.01; 
***P,0.001. 
Abbreviations: DOcK1, dedicator of cytokinesis 1; eMT, epithelial-mesenchymal transition; sirna, small interfering rna. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/drug-design-development-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal that spans the spectrum of drug design 
and development through to clinical applications. Clinical outcomes, 
patient safety, and programs for the development and effective, safe, 
and sustained use of medicines are the features of the journal, which </p>

<p>has also been accepted for indexing on PubMed Central. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2853 </p>

<p>DOcK1 regulates chemoresistance in bladder cancer cells via eMT </p>

<p>mechanism investigation of Th17 cells, the new T cell sub-
sets, on the early acute renal transplant rejection </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>