<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5424272" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are single-stranded, small RNAs (21-23 
nucleotides) that function in gene silencing and translational 
inhibition via the RNA interference mechanism. Most miRNAs 
originate from host genomic regions, such as intergenic regions, 
introns, exons, and transposable elements (TEs). Here, we fo-
cused on the palindromic structure of medium reiteration fre-
quencies (MERs), which are similar to precursor miRNAs. Five 
MER consensus sequences (MER5A1, MER53, MER81, 
MER91C, and MER117) were matched with paralogous tran-
scripts predicted to be precursor miRNAs in the horse genome 
(equCab2) and located in either intergenic regions or introns. 
The MER5A1, MER53, and MER91C sequences obtained from 
RepeatMasker were matched with the eca-miR-544b, eca-miR-
1302, and eca-miR-652 precursor sequences derived from 
Ensembl transcript database, respectively. Each precursor form 
was anticipated to yield two mature forms, and we confirmed 
miRNA expression in six different tissues (cerebrum, cerebellum, 
lung, spleen, adrenal gland, and duodenum) of one thorough-
bred horse. MER5A1-derived miRNAs generally showed signifi-
cantly higher expression in the lung than in other tissues. 
MER91C-derived miRNA-5p also showed significantly higher 
expression in the duodenum than in other tissues (cerebellum, 
lung, spleen, and adrenal gland). The MER117-overlapped 
expressed sequence tag generated polycistronic miRNAs, which 
showed higher expression in the duodenum than other tissues. 
These data indicate that horse MER transposons encode miR-
NAs that are expressed in several tissues and are thought to 
have biological functions. </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">UCSC Genome Browser</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://genome.ucsc.edu</rs><rs id="software-1" type="software">Ensembl</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">84</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www.ensembl.org</rs><rs type="software">UCSC 
table Browser</rs><rs id="software-3" type="software">RepeatMasker</rs><rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">3.3</rs><rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">http://www.re-peatmasker.org</rs><rs id="software-4" type="software">RNAfold</rs><rs corresp="#software-4" type="url">http://rna.tbi.univie.ac.at/cgi-bin/RNAfold.cgi</rs><rs id="software-5" type="software">miRNAfold</rs><rs corresp="#software-5" type="url">http://evryrna. ibisc.univ-evry.fr/miRNAFold</rs><rs id="software-6" type="software">MatureBayes</rs><rs corresp="#software-6" type="url">http://mirna.imbb.forth.gr/Mature-Bayes.html</rs><rs type="software">MatureBayes</rs>This work was supported by a grant from the ministry of 
Education, Republic of Korea (NRF-2015R1D1A1A01056650). </p>



</text></tei>