<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5032163" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Aim of the study: The purpose of this 
retrospective study is to evaluate the 
clinicopathological features and treat-
ment results of male breast cancer 
presented to our tertiary referral cen-
ter. 
Material and methods: Between Janu-
ary 1998 and December 2005, a total 
of 39 men with breast cancer treated 
at Alexandria Main University Hos-
pital and their medical records were 
reviewed. 
Results: The median age of patients 
was 59 years. Only 3 (7.7%) patients 
had positive family history. All patients 
presented by breast swellings that 
were associated with axillary mass in 
about one third of them. Around 80% 
had hormone receptor positive (estro-
gen and/or progesterone receptors). 
Two third of patients had advanced 
T-stage (T3 and T4). Left sided breast 
cancer occurred in 51.3%. Infiltrat-
ing ductal carcinoma was the most 
common type of histology encoun-
tered and grade 2 was the predomi-
nant grade of tumor. Modified radical 
mastectomy was the most common 
(87.2%) type of surgery done followed 
by chemotherapy for 32 patients and 
loco-regional radiotherapy for 20 pa-
tients. Tamoxifen was administered in 
31 patients. Distant relapse occurred 
in 7 patients (17.9%) and local recur-
rence occurred in 2 patients (5.1%). 
The 5-year disease-free survival (DFS) 
was 82% and the 5-year overall sur-
vival (OS) rate was 84%. Only nega-
tive axillary lymph node and positive 
hormone receptor status were signifi-
cantly associated with favorable DFS 
and OS. T-stage, grade of tumor and 
type of chemotherapy given had no 
statistically significant impact on ei-
ther DFS or OS. 
Conclusions: Male breast cancer is 
still under-investigated and further 
researches are warranted. </p>

<p>The incidence of male breast cancer (MBC) is low, constituting less than 
1% of all breast cancer cases [1, 2]. In central and eastern Africa breast cancer 
rates are higher and reach 6% of cancers in men, which could be explained 
by hyperestrogenism due to endemic hepatic infectious disease [3]. A large 
epidemiological study has shown a growing incidence of male breast cancer 
of 1% in one year [1]. The male-to-female ratio of incidence in breast cancer 
is about 1% in western countries, but it was markedly higher in North Africa 
-2.7% and even higher in Sub-Saharan countries -4.9%. Moreover, in Africa 
the age at diagnosis of breast cancer was seven years later in men than in 
women [4]. 
The most important risk factors are family history and mutations of BRCA. 
More than twice the proportion of males with breast cancer have a family his-
tory, compared with 7% in the overall male population [5]. 
Other important risk factors are: Klinefelter syndrome, oestrogen or tes-
tosterone use, orchitis/epididymitis, obesity, lack of exercise, and exposure to 
radiation [6]. 
Invasive ductal carcinoma constitute approximately 90% of breast cancers 
in men, whereas only 1.5% of cases are lobular cancers, compared to about 
15% of cases in women, which could be explained by the lack of lobules and 
acini in male breast tissue [5, 7]. 
The most common type of male breast cancer is hormone receptor posi-
tive -82%, 15% are human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-positive 
(young patients more likely), and 4% are triple negative. An interesting phe-
nomenon is that non-Hispanic black males are more frequently triple negative 
-9% compared to Hispanic -6% and non-Hispanic white -3%. A study has 
shown that non-Hispanic black males had the worst outcomes [8]. 
Optimal treatments are still vague, and further work is clearly needed to 
better understand this disease [1-3, 9, 10]. 
The surgical, systemic, and radiation treatment of males with breast cancer 
are similar to the rules in the approach for women and depends on the extent 
of disease at presentation and other risk factors. 
Due to the relative rarity of MBC, prospective randomised trials are lacking, 
and management of MBC is based on either retrospective series or extrapo-
lation from that of females [1, 11]. Therefore, we try in this retrospective study 
to evaluate the clinicopathological features and treatment results of MBC pre-
sented to our tertiary referral centre. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>In this retrospective study, the medical files of 39 men with pathologically 
proven breast cancer, who presented to the Clinical Oncology department, </p>



<p>contemporary oncology </p>

<p>Alexandria Main University Hospital during the period 
from January 1998 to December 2005, were reviewed. Pa-
tients with clinical evidence of distant metastases at the 
time of presentation have been excluded. Data regarding 
history and clinical presentation, investigations, and treat-
ment received were collected and correlated to local recur-
rence, distant metastasis, and survival. 
The overall survival (OS) was calculated from the date 
of diagnosis to the date of death or last follow-up. Dis-
ease-free survival (DFS) was defined as time from date </p>

<p>of diagnosis to date of local recurrence or distant failure, 
depending on what occurred earlier. Patients without dis-
ease recurrence were censored at last follow-up. 
Survival was estimated using the Kaplan-Meier prod-
uct-limit method using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v. 22</rs>) software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA). Patient and tumour characteristics, 
namely age, T-stage, grade of tumour, axillary lymph node 
(LN) status, and hormone receptor status, were studied to 
determine the effect of each variable on survival rates. The 
two-sided log-rank test was used to test the association 
between patient variables and survival. P ≤ 0.05 was con-
sidered as significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Patients' characteristics </p>

<p>Thirty-nine patients were included in this analysis. The 
median age of patients was 59 years (range: 33-80 years). 
Only three patients (7.7%) had positive family history. All 
patients presented by breast mass and about one third of 
them had axillary mass. Only six patients experienced nip-
ple discharge. Around 80% had positive hormone recep-
tor (oestrogen and/or progesterone receptors). Two thirds 
of patients had advanced T-stage (T3 and T4). Left-sided 
breast cancer occurred in 51.3%. Infiltrating ductal carcino-
ma (IDC) was the most common type of histology encoun-
tered, and grade 2 was the predominant grade of tumour. 
Table 1 shows the characteristics of the patients. Figures 
1-6 shows paraffin and immunostained sections of two 
patients. </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>The majority of patients (87.2%) underwent modified 
radical mastectomy (MRM). Adjuvant chemotherapy CMF 
(cyclophosphamide, methotrexate, 5-fluorouracil) and CAF 
(cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, 5-fluorouracil) regimens 
were given for 11 and 21 patients, respectively. Loco-region-
al radiotherapy was offered to 20 patients. Tamoxifen was 
administered in 31 patients as an adjuvant after chemo-
therapy and/or radiotherapy. </p>

<p>Disease-free survival </p>

<p>Seven patients (17.9%) suffered a distant relapse 
and two patients suffered a local recurrence (5.1%). The 
commonly involved sites were bone (four patients), lung 
(three patients), and liver (two patients; one patient de-
veloped multiple metastatic sites). The five-year DFS for 
the entire group was 82% (Fig. 7A). DFS at five years for 
axillary node-negative patients was 100% and for axillary 
node-positive patients was 44% (p = 0.001). Patients with 
positive hormone receptors had significantly better five-
year DFS (88%) compared to those with negative hormone 
receptors (25%; p = 0.000). T-stage (p = 0.541), grade 
(p = 0.835), and type of adjuvant chemotherapy received 
(p = 0.447) had no impact on the five-year DFS (Fig. 8). </p>

<p>Overall survival </p>

<p>The five-year overall survival rate of patients was 84% 
(Fig. 7B). In univariate analysis, patients with negative ax-</p>

<p>Table 1. Patients and disease characteristics of male breast cancer </p>

<p>Characteristics 
No. (%) </p>

<p>Age (median) 
59 years (range: 33-80) </p>

<p>Family history </p>

<p>Positive 
3 (7.7) </p>

<p>Negative 
36 (92.3) </p>

<p>Side </p>

<p>Right 
19 (48.7) </p>

<p>Left 
20 (51.3) </p>

<p>Presentation </p>

<p>Breast mass 
39 (100) </p>

<p>Axillary swelling 
11 (28.2) </p>

<p>Nipple discharge 
6 (15.4) </p>

<p>T-Stage </p>

<p>T1 
1 (2.6) </p>

<p>T2 
10 (25.6) </p>

<p>T3 
8 (20.5) </p>

<p>T4 
20 (51.3) </p>

<p>N-Stage </p>

<p>Positive 
16 (41) </p>

<p>Negative 
18 (46.2) </p>

<p>Unknown 
5 (12.8) </p>

<p>Histology </p>

<p>IDC 
36 (92.3) </p>

<p>Others 
3 (7.7) </p>

<p>Grade </p>

<p>1 
1 (2.6) </p>

<p>2 
30 (76.9) </p>

<p>3 
2 (5.1) </p>

<p>Unknown 
6 (15.4) </p>

<p>Hormone receptor status </p>

<p>ER+ and/or PR+ 
31 (79.5) </p>

<p>ER-and PR-
7 (17.9) </p>

<p>Unknown 
1 (2.6) </p>

<p>Surgery </p>

<p>Lumpectomy 
5 (12.8) </p>

<p>MRM 
34 (87.2) </p>

<p>IDC -infiltrating ductal carcinoma; MRM -modified radical mastectomy; ER -
oestrogen receptor; PR -progesterone receptor </p>



<p>Male breast cancer: a clinicopathological study of an Egyptian population (Alexandria experience) </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Immunostaining for PR receptor showing negative nuclear up-
take in all malignant cells (original magnification 200×) </p>

<p>Fig. 5. immunostained section from ER receptor showing negative 
nuclear uptake in all malignant cells (original magnification 200×) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. A case of infiltrating ductal carcinoma of no special type (NST) 
Grade II showing streaks &amp; ductules of pleomorphic and hyperchro-
matic ductal carcinoma cells among collagenic stroma (H&amp;E, original 
magnification 200×) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Immunostained section for ER receptor showing a strong 
nuclear uptake in almost all of the malignant cell nuclei (original 
magnification 200×) </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Immunostained section for PR receptor showing weak nuclear 
staining in 20% of the malignant cell nuclei (original magnification 
200×) </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Paraffin section for another case of infiltrating ductal carci-
noma of no special type (NST) Grade II showing groups and nests 
of pleomorphic and hyperchomatic ductal carcinoma cells (original 
magnification 200×) </p>



<p>contemporary oncology </p>

<p>Fig. 7. A) Disease-free survival and B) overall survival rates for men with breast cancer </p>

<p>Fig. 8. Disease-free survival rates for men with breast cancer according to LN status (A), hormone receptor status (B), chemotherapy regimen 
(C), and T-stage (D) </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
12 
24 
36 
48 
60 </p>

<p>Time (months) </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
12 
24 
36 
48 
60 </p>

<p>Time (months) 
Cumulative disease free survival </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
12 
24 
36 
48 
60 </p>

<p>Time (months) 
Cumulative disease free survival </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
12 
24 
36 
48 
60 </p>

<p>Time (months) 
Cumulative disease free survival </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
12 
24 
36 
48 
60 </p>

<p>Time (months) 
Cumulative disease free survival </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
12 
24 
36 
48 
60 </p>

<p>Time (months) 
Cumulative disease free survival </p>

<p>Cumulative overall survival </p>

<p>censored </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>-ve LN </p>

<p>+ve LN </p>

<p>censored </p>

<p>censored </p>

<p>LN status </p>

<p>+ve </p>

<p>-ve </p>

<p>censored </p>

<p>censored </p>

<p>Hormone receptor </p>

<p>T1-T2 </p>

<p>T3-T4 </p>

<p>censored </p>

<p>censored </p>

<p>T-stage </p>

<p>CMF </p>

<p>CAF </p>

<p>censored </p>

<p>censored </p>

<p>Chemotherapy </p>



<p>Male breast cancer: a clinicopathological study of an Egyptian population (Alexandria experience) </p>

<p>illary node had significantly better OS compared to those 
with positive axillary node (p = 0.001). The subset of pa-
tients with positive hormone receptors had significantly 
better five-year OS compared with those with negative 
hormone receptors (p = 0.000). There was no statistically 
significant difference in OS based on T-stage, grade of tu-
mour, or type of chemotherapy given. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The earliest recorded case of MBC is described in the 
Edwin Smith papyrus from Egypt (3000-2500 BC); in mod-
ern times, the British physician John of Arderne is reported 
to be the first to discover this disease in a male patient in 
the 14 th century [12, 13]. Male breast cancer, despite being 
increased in the last decades, is still a rare disease and un-
der-evaluated [1]. Thus, collection of comprehensive data 
on the presentation and management of MBC may help to 
optimise the outcome of patients. 
The median age of our patients was 59 years, which is 
consistent with that reported by Crichlow [11]. Unlike fe-
male breast cancer, the age at diagnosis in men had no 
impact on DFS or OS in our series, and this is agreement 
with that reported by Borgen et al. [14]. 
Consistent with literature [1, 15, 16], we have demon-
strated that men tend to have more advanced disease 
with larger tumour size and more frequent lymph node 
involvement (about 50% of our patients). This could be 
explained by the lack of a screening program (unlike for 
women), smaller breast tissue, unawareness of patients, 
and lack of expectation among treating physicians; fur-
thermore, the stigma of cancer in general, and breast 
cancer (a disease of woman) in particular, make men seek 
medical advice later. 
Men are significantly more likely to have hormone re-
ceptor-positive disease than women. Similar to that re-
ported by Giordano et al. [1], 80% of men had hormone 
receptor-positive tumours in our series, compared with 
67-76% in women [9, 17, 18]. 
Oestrogen receptor is expressed in 75-97%, progester-
one receptor in 59-96%, and HER2 in 1.7-29% in MBC in 
different series [19]. 
Surgery is the keystone in the treatment of MBC fol-
lowed by adjuvant therapy [20-22]. Post-operative che-
motherapy was given in about 80% of patients depending 
on the extent of tumour (T-&amp; N-stage), hormone receptor 
status, age, performance status of the patients, and asso-
ciated co-morbidities. Adjuvant radiotherapy was applied 
in about half of our patients due to any of the following: 
involvement of the skin and/or pectoral muscle and areola, 
inadequate margins, and metastatic spread to the axillary 
lymph nodes. Tamoxifen was the only adjuvant hormonal 
therapy experienced in our patients with hormone recep-
tor-positive disease. 
The five-year survival rate of patients was 84%, which 
is consistent with that reported by previous studies [2, 
14]. Survival is comparable with reports form developed 
countries and higher than other series from Africa [23, 24]. 
Borgen et al. [14] found that the five-year OS was 85%. Re-
lapse-free survival at five years for axillary node-negative </p>

<p>patients was 87% and for node-positive patients was 30%. 
Five-year survival was 100% for the node-negative sub-
set and 60% for the node-positive subset. Like in female 
breast cancer, we found that the most powerful predictors 
of outcome in men were axillary lymph nodes status and 
hormone receptors status. However, T-stage did not im-
pact the survival because only one patient had T1, and we 
analysed T1 &amp; T2 together [20, 25]. 
The current study documents improved survival rates 
compared to those that have been historically reported for 
male breast cancer patients, and these may be a reflection 
of the proper adjuvant treatment received in most of our 
patients [21, 22, 26-29]. The survival figures reported are 
similar to currently accepted figures reported for female 
breast cancer [2, 14]. 
To our knowledge, this is the first trial from our heav-
ily populated city with more than four million persons 
to address this issue. We know that our study has some 
limitations, being a retrospective trial with selection bias, 
small sample size, and a lack of information on risk fac-
tors such as testicular disease, benign breast conditions, 
and the Klinefelter syndrome. Moreover, pathological 
data regarding BRCA1, BRCA2, Her2/neu, and Ki-67 are not 
available [30]. Multivariate analysis was not performed to 
determine the independent effect of each variable in the 
presence of other variables. 
In conclusion, MBC is very similar to female breast can-
cer but has certain unique features, which should be fur-
ther explored in future research. In the absence of solid ev-
idence, adjuvant treatment should be strongly considered 
and should be based on the greater base of knowledge 
available for carcinoma of the female breast. </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>





<p>contemporary oncology </p>



<p>Address for correspondence </p>

<p>Marcin Hetnał 
Amethyst Radiotherapy Centre 
Złotej Jesieni 1 
31-826 Krakow, Poland 
e-mail: marcin.hetnal@gmail.com </p>

<p>Submitted: 13.03.2016 
Accepted: 1.08.2016 </p>

</text></tei>