<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5440634" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Introduction: Vaginismus is mostly unknown among clinicians and women. Vaginismus causes women to have 
fear, anxiety, and pain with penetration attempts. 
Aim: To present a large cohort of patients based on prior published studies approved by an institutional review 
board and the Food and Drug Administration using a comprehensive multimodal vaginismus treatment program 
to treat the physical and psychologic manifestations of women with vaginismus and to record successes, failures, 
and untoward effects of this treatment approach. 
Methods: Assessment of vaginismus included a comprehensive pretreatment questionnaire, the Female Sexual 
Function Index (FSFI), and consultation. All patients signed a detailed informed consent. Treatment consisted of 
a multimodal approach including intravaginal injections of onabotulinumtoxinA (Botox) and bupivacaine, 
progressive dilation under conscious sedation, indwelling dilator, follow-up and support with office visits, phone 
calls, e-mails, dilation logs, and FSFI reports. 
Main Outcome Measures: Logs noting dilation progression, pain and anxiety scores, time to achieve inter-
course, setbacks, and untoward effects. Post-treatment FSFI scores were compared with preprocedure scores. 
Results: One hundred seventy-one patients (71%) reported having pain-free intercourse at a mean of 5.1 weeks 
(median ¼ 2.5). Six patients (2.5%) were unable to achieve intercourse within a 1-year period after treatment 
and 64 patients (26.6%) were lost to follow-up. The change in the overall FSFI score measured at baseline, 
3 months, 6 months, and 1 year was statistically significant at the 0.05 level. Three patients developed mild 
temporary stress incontinence, two patients developed a short period of temporary blurred vision, and one patient 
developed temporary excessive vaginal dryness. All adverse events resolved by approximately 4 months. One 
patient required retreatment followed by successful coitus. 
Conclusion: A multimodal program that treated the physical and psychologic aspects of vaginismus enabled 
women to achieve pain-free intercourse as noted by patient communications and serial female sexual function 
studies. Further studies are indicated to better understand the individual components of this multimodal 
treatment program. Copyright Ó 2017, The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of the International Society for Sexual Medicine. 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Key Words: Vaginismus; Female Sexual Pain; Penetration Disorder; Genito-Pelvic Pain/Penetration Disorder; 
Vaginismus Treatment; Dyspareunia </p>

<p>INTRODUCTION </p>

<p>Vaginismus is a subset of the genito-pelvic pain/penetration 
disorder and is currently defined by the Diagnostic and Statistical 
Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition as a penetration dis-
order in which any form of vaginal penetration such as tampons, 
digit, vaginal dilators, gynecologic (GYN) examinations, and 
intercourse is often painful or impossible. 
1 Genito-pelvic pain/ 
penetration disorder further collapses dyspareunia and vagi-
nismus into one entity. 
2 Based on data that spasm is not always 
present in vaginismus, 
3 Basson et al 
4 proposed an alternative 
definition of persistent or recurrent difficulties in vaginal entry of </p>

<p>Received January 6, 2017. Accepted February 20, 2017. 
1 Dunbarton, NH, USA; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Statistics, Des Moines University, Des Moines, IA, USA </p>

<p>Presented in part at the 2013 Annual Scientific Meeting of the American 
Urogynecologic Society, Las Vegas, Nevada, USA, October 13, 2013 (control 
ID 1699686) and the combined annual meeting of the International Uro-
gynecological Association and the American Urogynecologic Society, 
Washington, DC, USA, July 24, 2014. </p>

<p>Copyright ª 2017, The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of 
the International Society for Sexual Medicine. This is an open access 
article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.esxm.2017.02.002 </p>

<p>e114 
Sex Med 2017;5:e114ee123 </p>

<p>a penis, finger, or other object despite the desire to do so. 
Vaginismus is a psychologic disorder manifested by fear and 
anxiety to penetration 
5 and a physical disorder as noted by 
vaginal spasm 
6,7 and is distinct from other sexual pain disorders 
such as vulvodynia or vestibulodynia. 
7 The diagnosis of vagi-
nismus is made by history. 
7 Women who cannot tolerate a GYN 
examination might have an examination under anesthesia during 
which any vaginal spasm disappears. Then, the patient is told 
that the examination was "normal." After one such patient was 
hospitalized for a suicide attempt, another patient told her par-
ents she was going to commit suicide. Symptoms of vaginismus 
vary according to the severity of vaginismus. Symptoms include 
fear, anxiety, and pain of vaginal penetration; inability to use a 
tampon (often noted at a young age); inability to remove a 
tampon that gets "stuck" (the proximal portion of the tampon 
swells with blood and cannot be extracted through the area of 
introital spasm, at times necessitating removal under anesthesia); 
severe pain with penetration; complaints that attempted inter-
course is like "hitting a wall"; and an inability to tolerate a GYN 
examination. These symptoms help differentiate vaginismus 
from vulvodynia and provoked vestibulodynia and are suggestive 
of spasm at the level of the introitus. 
6e8 Vaginismus can be mild, 
in which different treatment approaches are effective, or severe, 
making treatment difficult. 
6,7 The findings of vaginal spasm 
support other studies that have noted active vaginal contractions 
in response to stimuli. 
9,10 Compared with other sexual pain 
disorders such as vulvodynia and vestibulodynia, the treatment of 
vaginismus has potential for a high rate of success. </p>

<p>6e8,11,12   Stratifying the severity of vaginismus helps the clinician choose 
among numerous treatment options to better understand what 
the patient is experiencing and what she is capable of doing. </p>

<p>6e8,13   We have noted that women with milder forms of vaginismus 
can cooperate with different treatment suggestions, whereas 
women who are terrified by any attempted vaginal penetration 
have difficulty following treatment suggestions. </p>

<p>6e8   Reasons for sexual pain such as herpes virus, lichen sclerosis, 
and other medical conditions need to be ruled out as a source of 
sexual pain, as do vulvodynia and vestibulodynia. 
14 Despite its 
description more than a century ago, 
15 vaginismus is rarely taught 
in medical school, residency training, and medical meetings. </p>

<p>7   Vaginismus can be categorized as primary, in which the 
patient has never experienced non-painful intercourse, or sec-
ondary, in which the patient has previously experienced non-
painful intercourse but subsequently experiences pain. </p>

<p>16   The prevalence rate of vaginismus in a clinical setting has been 
estimated as 5% to 17%, and it is believed to be one of the more 
prevalent female sexual dysfunctions. 
17 Different psychological 
factors have been associated with vaginismus, such as traumatic 
sexual experiences, sexual abuse, a strict religious and/or strict 
sexual upbringing, fear and/or anxiety issues, 
18,19 and being held 
down at a young age during catheterization or enemas, 
7 but it is 
not always associated with psychological issues and some patients 
give a negative history for those factors. </p>

<p>Women with vaginismus experience shame and embarrass-
ment. 
7,8 A patient with 12 years of attempted and failed treat-
ments noted how this was among the "darkest and most 
embarrassing periods of my life causing me to live with vagi-
nismus in silence and shame" (personal communication). Other 
women have noted how they think about their vaginismus during 
the entire day and before they go to sleep. Vaginismus frequently 
leads to marital problems and depression and to feelings of 
isolation, is a major cause of unconsummated marriages, is an 
inability to tolerate GYN examinations, 
7 and is not tolerated in 
cultures with arranged marriages, often resulting in an annulment. </p>

<p>Vaginismus treatments include the widespread use of vaginal 
dilators, physical therapy with or without biofeedback, biofeed-
back, sex and relationship counseling, psychotherapy, cognitive 
behavioral therapy, therapist-aided exposure, hypnotherapy, and 
lubricants. </p>

<p>7   The successful use of Botox (onabotulinumtoxinA; Allergan, 
Irvine, CA, USA) injections to treat secondary vaginismus was 
first described as a case report in 1997 
7 and later developed by 
different investigators. 
6e8,11,12,20e23 Abbott et al 
23 using a 
placebo-controlled study of onabotulinumtoxinA showed that all 
eight women who had onabotulinumtoxinA 25 U injected into 
the bulbospongiosum achieved intercourse compared with none 
of the five women in the placebo group, with no recurrence or 
reinjection in the follow-up period of 8 to 14 months. Ghazizadeh 
and Nikzad 
20 used Dysport (abobotulinumtoxinA; Galderma 
Laboratories, Fort Worth, TX, USA) to treat 23 women with 
Lamont grade 3 and 4 refractory vaginismus 
13 and reported a 
75% success rate of pain-free intercourse in these women were 
followed for a mean of 12.3 months (range ¼ 2e24). </p>

<p>The purpose of this report was to discuss a large cohort of 
women, many with failed prior treatments, who were treated 
using a program approved by an institutional review board (IRB) 
and the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for continued 
research, which included a multimodal program of intravaginal 
injections of Botox and bupivacaine, progressive dilation under 
conscious sedation, use of an indwelling dilator, and post-
procedure counseling, support, and follow up. </p>

<p>6e8,11,12 </p>

<p>AIMS </p>

<p>1. To present a large cohort of patients based on published IRB-
and FDA-approved studies for continued research 
11,12 using a 
comprehensive multimodal vaginismus treatment program to 
treat the physical and psychologic manifestations of women 
with vaginismus. 
2. To record successes, failures, and untoward effects of this 
treatment approach. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>IRB and FDA Approval </p>

<p>IRB approval (Veritas Ethica Clinical Research, Quebec, QC, 
Canada) and FDA approval including investigational new drug </p>

<p>Sex Med 2017;5:e114ee123 </p>

<p>Vaginismus Treatment 
e115 </p>

<p>approval were granted in 2010 to initiate a study of 31 patients 
titled "Pilot Study Protocol BTX-PV-01: Open Label, Single 
Center, Pilot Study of the Use of Botox Injections, Sensorcaine 
Injections and Progressive Dilation Under Anesthesia for the 
Treatment of Primary Vaginismus" (NCT01352546). </p>

<p>11   Appendix 1 presents the original eligibility criteria of the 31 
women who were enrolled. Results of this study showed a 90.3% 
success rate of women who could achieve intercourse 
12 and 
exhibit greater levels of sexual function as measured by the 
Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI) within 1 year after treat-
ment and as noted in the daily log diaries and personal com-
munications in this cohort study. The FSFI is a 19-item 
questionnaire assessing sexual function during the previous 4 
weeks. It contains six subscales related to desire, arousal, lubri-
cation, orgasm, satisfaction, and pain. Each question is answered 
on a five-point Likert scale, with varying response choices and 
anchors. Weighted subscale scores range from 1.2 to 6. 
24 The 
present study is a larger cohort of this FDA-approved study, 
includes improvements in the evaluation and care of these 
women, and elaborates on the findings of 241 treated women of 
377 evaluated for vaginismus. All patients signed a comprehen-
sive permit before treatment. </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>Participants were women who reported very painful inter-
course or intercourse that was impossible because of pain who 
contacted this private plastic surgery center for treatment 
through our website and women who were referred by clinicians, 
friends, or relatives. </p>

<p>Diagnosis </p>

<p>The diagnosis of vaginismus was made after evaluation of a 
comprehensive medical and psychosexual questionnaire devel-
oped in this practice (Appendix 2) and the FSFI. Most women 
were from out of state or a different country. Therefore, further 
assessment consisted of preprocedure phone calls and Skype calls 
before evaluation in the office. History included pain and anxiety 
scores for insertion of a cotton-tipped applicator, tampon, 
dilator, finger, GYN examination and intercourse (Figure 1); self-
evaluation of pelvic examination experiences based on the 
Lamont-Pacik classification system 
6,8,13 (Figure 2); prior treat-
ments for vaginismus; prior diagnoses of sexual pain; discussion 
with the patient and referring clinicians; previous diagnoses of 
vulvodynia or vestibulodynia; and review of the patient's libido 
and relationship issues. 
7 All patients signed a detailed informed 
consent. </p>

<p>Evaluation of Vaginismus Severity </p>

<p>It was helpful to evaluate the severity of vaginismus before 
treatment to better support these women during treatment. 
Women with severe vaginismus have greater fear and anxiety to 
pelvic touch and have more difficulty with treatment recom-
mendations than women with milder forms of vaginismus. </p>

<p>7,8   The penetration history in conjunction with pelvic examina-
tion responses indicated the severity of the vaginismus. It was 
noted throughout the study that women with Lamont levels 3 
and 4 
13 and Pacik level 5 
6e8 had considerable difficulty with 
pelvic examinations and that often such an examination was 
impossible. </p>

<p>After answering yes or no, please rate each of the following items with pain scores (1=Okay no 
pain, 
5= Moderately uncomfortable, 10=impossible or extremely painful, N/A-not applicable, no 
experience) 
and anxiety scores 1-10 (1=none, 5=moderate, 10=severe, N/A). This is an important part of 
your evaluation. </p>

<p>PAIN SCORE 
ANXIETY SCORE 
1. Insertion of tampons: Yes 
No 
2. Insertion of Q-Tip 
Yes 
No 
3. Insertion of finger: Yes 
No 
4. GYN exams: 
Yes 
No 
5. Use of dilators: 
Yes 
No 
Size </p>

<p>6. Intercourse 
Yes 
No 
6A. Tip only? 
Yes 
No 
6B. Partial? 
Yes 
No 
6C. Full? 
Yes 
No </p>

<p>6D. Age first attempted intercourse? 
6E. Age first aware of problems with any penetration? 
Details: </p>

<p>7. Anal Intercourse: Yes 
No 
Not Applicable </p>

<p>Source: Pacik Patient Questionnaire 
Figure 1. Penetration history from Pacik Penetration Questionnaire. </p>

<p>Sex Med 2017;5:e114ee123 </p>

<p>e116 
Pacik and Geletta </p>

<p>Baseline patient demographics and condition characteristics 
are listed in Table 1. The average age was 30 years (range ¼ 
17e72) with an average duration of vaginismus of 7.8 years 
(range ¼ 1e37) from time of discovery. In filling out their 
questionnaires, 168 patients (70%) noted they had Lamont level 
4 or Pacik level 5 at baseline, indicating severe vaginismus. Only 
58.5% of women reported penetration with a finger and only 
50% could complete a GYN examination. Fewer than 40% of 
patients could use tampons and only 83 patients (34%) reported 
attempts at intercourse. Patients who attempted coitus remarked 
that it was extremely painful or impossible and often further 
noted that only the tip of the penis could be inserted, which 
suggests penetration as far as the vestibule but not intravaginal. </p>

<p>Table 2 lists prior treatments and coping strategies. Of note is the 
large number of women who attempted different treatments 
during a span of many years. Patients had a mean of 4 ± 2.7 
failed treatments, with the most common being lubricants and 
dilator use (attempted by 74% and 73% of patients, respec-
tively). The many failed treatment attempts are consistent with 
the severity of vaginismus noted in this group of women with 
vaginismus. </p>

<p>Lamont grade 1: Patient is able to relax for pelvic exam </p>

<p>Lamont grade 2: Patient is unable to relax for pelvic exam </p>

<p>Lamont grade 3: Buttocks lift off table. Early retreat. Toes curl upward </p>

<p>Lamont grade 4: Generalized retreat: Buttocks lift up, thighs close, patient retreats </p>

<p>Pacik grade 5: Generalized retreat as in Lamont level 4 plus visceral reaction which 
may result in any one or more of the following: Palpitations, hyperventilation, sweating, 
severe trembling, uncontrollable shaking, screaming, hysteria, wanting to jump off the 
table, a feeling of going unconscious, nausea, vomiting and even a desire to attack the 
doctor. </p>

<p>Note: It is difficult to examine women who are Lamont Level 3 and 4 and Pacik Level 5. </p>

<p>From Lamont JA. Vaginismus. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1978;131:633-636. </p>

<p>Pacik PT. Vaginismus: review of current concepts and treatment using Botox injections, bupivacaine injections, and </p>

<p>progressive dilation with the patient under anesthesia. Aesthetic Plast Surg. 2011;35:1160-1164 </p>

<p>Pacik PT. Understanding and treating vaginismus: A multimodal approach. International Urogynecology Journal </p>

<p>2014; 25 (12), DOI: 10.1007/s00192-014-2421-y </p>

<p>Figure 2. Evaluation of patient response to pelvic examination (from Pacik Penetration Questionnaire). </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline patient demographic and condition </p>

<p>characteristics* </p>

<p>Characteristic 
N ¼ 241 </p>

<p>Finger penetration 
141 (58.5) 
Dilator 
134 (55.6) 
Gynecologic examination 
121 (50.2) 
Cotton swab 
100 (41.5) 
Tampon 
90 (37.3) 
Intercourse 
83 (34.4) 
Penetration history (before treatment) 
69 (28.6) 
Age 
30 ± 8.2 
Duration (y) 
7.8 ± 6.2 
Lamont-Pacik level of severity (1e5) 
3.9 ± 1.3 </p>

<p>*Data are presented as mean ± SD or number (percentage). </p>

<p>Table 2. Prior treatments and coping strategies* </p>

<p>Lubricants 
178 (73.9) 
Dilators 
175 (72.6) 
Kegel exercises 
121 (50.2) 
Topical anesthetics 
94 (39.0) 
Sex counseling 
74 (30.7) 
Psychotherapy 
69 (28.6) 
Excessive alcohol use 
69 (28.6) 
Physical therapy 
67 (27.8) 
Antianxiety medications 
64 (26.6) 
Muscle relaxants 
61 (25.3) 
Antidepressant medications 
57 (23.7) 
Hypnotherapy 
43 (17.8) 
Physical therapy with biofeedback 
35 (14.5) 
Biofeedback 
32 (13.3) 
Sedatives 
16 (6.6) 
Surgical hymenectomy (2 patients had 
hymenectomy þ episiotomy) </p>

<p>15 (6.2) </p>

<p>Surgical vestibulectomy 
7 (2.9) 
Hallucinogenic drugs 
5 (2.1) </p>

<p>*Data are presented as number (percentage). </p>

<p>Sex Med 2017;5:e114ee123 </p>

<p>Vaginismus Treatment 
e117 </p>

<p>MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES </p>

<p>Logs noted dilation progression, which included pain and 
anxiety with dilation, time to achieve intercourse, setbacks, and 
untoward effects. Post-treatment FSFI scores were compared 
with preprocedure scores. The lead author (Dr Pacik) personally 
entered all data prospectively into an extensive <rs id="software-0" type="software">Excel</rs> spreadsheet 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft</rs>, Redmond, WA, USA). This included re-evaluation 
of data at the time of consultation, treatment, and post-
treatment progress. </p>

<p>Evaluation of Data </p>

<p>The primary end point was the ability to achieve pain-free 
intercourse after treatment as reported in a daily log kept by 
the patient, ongoing communication with Dr Pacik, and FSFI 
reports. Adverse events (AEs) were monitored throughout the 
study and recorded. Treated patients were followed for a mini-
mum of 1 year (range ¼ 16 months to 9 years). All patients were 
treated in a certified outpatient surgicenter (OR) with a board-
certified anesthesiologist in attendance. The Student t-test was 
used for statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Multimodal Vaginismus Treatment Program: 
Technical Details </p>

<p>Physical examination (excluding pelvic examination) was done 
in the recovery area before treatment in the OR. Versed (mid-
azolam) 1 to 2 mg intravenously was administered as needed to 
help calm the patient in the recovery area and/or in the OR 
before cotton-tipped applicator testing. Additional sedation was 
done as needed with small titrated doses of propofol for women 
with more severe vaginismus (Lamont levels 3 and 4, Pacik level 
5). 
6,7,13 This was needed for patients with high anxiety to 
complete the cotton-tipped testing and examination. Some 
patients with severe vaginismus resisted all efforts at sedation and 
could not be placed into stirrups or examined. These women 
were given conscious sedation with versed and propofol, with no 
examination possible. Patients with less severe vaginismus 
(Lamont levels 1 and 2) can tolerate cotton-tipped testing 
without prior sedation much as any office pelvic examination. </p>

<p>Cotton-Tipped Testing 
When possible, cotton-tipped applicator testing ("Q-tip test") 
with as little sedation as possible was done to rule out vulvodynia 
and provoked vestibulodynia. 
14 Patients with severe vaginismus 
often demonstrate considerable anxiety to cotton-tipped testing 
and have difficulty distinguishing anxiety from pain, potentially 
resulting in a false positive test result for provoked 
vestibulodynia. </p>

<p>7   Digital Examination 
For patients who could tolerate digital examination, the vagina 
was examined for spasm. Spasm of the introitus was graded from 
0 (no spasm) to 4 (severe spasm). With severe spasm, it was 
difficult to insert the finger. In an unpublished correlation study, </p>

<p>the degree of spasm was found to be consistent with the 
predetermination of the severity of vaginismus. In general, spasm 
involves the introitus giving the appearance and digital sensation 
of a tightly closed fist (the "wall"). 
7,8 In a smaller number of 
women, some spasm also might be noted involving portions of 
the levator ani such as the pubococcygeus and puborectalis 
muscles, unilaterally or bilaterally. Too much sedation relaxes the 
introital spasm, making assessment inaccurate. </p>

<p>Injection Protocol 
Before bringing the patient into the OR, the nurse prepared 
the Botox. The Botox was kept on ice until ready for injection. 
One vial of frozen Botox 100 U was diluted with preservative-
free saline 2 mL, without foaming or shaking the vial, giving a 
concentration of 2.5 U/0.05 mL (Botox 50 U per 1-mL syringe). 
Using a pediatric speculum and bending the needle to 30  , 
Botox 50 U (20 injections ¼ 1 mL) was injected into the right 
bulbospongiosum and Botox 50 U (1 mL) was injected into the 
left side into the lateral submucosal areas of the introitus, marked 
by the residual hymenal fragments, at 7 to 9'clock on the pa-
tient's right and 3 to 5 o'clock on her left (Figure 3). A headlight 
is needed for the procedure. Injections are delivered above, into, 
and below the hymenal fragments on each side to include the full 
width of the bulbospongiosum. Intramuscular injections were 
found to be unnecessary and caused more bleeding. (Botox is 
known to diffuse approximately 1 cm from the injection site.) 
When other areas of spasm or tightness of the levator ani were 
identified, an additional 50 U was injected in similar divided 
doses submucosally into the affected muscles. </p>

<p>After the Botox injections, using 3-mL syringes, the patient 
received separate injections of 0.25% bupivacaine 18 mL with </p>

<p>Figure 3. Submucosal injections of Botox to the bulbospongio-</p>

<p>sum, on each side, using hymenal fragments as a landmark. The 
needle is bent 30 
at the hub for ease of injections. Bupivacaine 
injections are not shown. </p>

<p>Sex Med 2017;5:e114ee123 </p>

<p> 
Pacik and Geletta </p>

<p>1:400,000 epinephrine divided into 1-mL increments along the 
length of the right and left submucosal lateral vaginal walls (9 mL 
per side) from the level of the cervix to the introitus, to allow her 
to wake up pain free with a large dilator in place. No injections 
were delivered anteriorly or posteriorly to help avoid urinary and 
rectal incontinence. Conscious sedation was needed during 
vaginal injections and dilation, although, rarely, women with less 
severe vaginismus tolerated the procedure with no sedation. The 
patient was progressively dilated with the #4 dilator (3-inch 
circumference), the #5 dilator (4-inch circumference), and 
then, when possible, the #6 dilator (5-inch circumference) and 
reassessed with digital examination. Sometimes it was physically 
impossible to insert the #6 dilator. Approximately 10% to 15% 
of women required release of a constricting hymenal ring noted 
to be present around the circumference of the introitus (not to be 
confused with an intact hymen) with a small snip or the removal 
of a small triangular wedge on the left and right lateral sides of 
the ring. This procedure results in a small amount of bleeding 
that can be controlled with pressure. Hymenectomy was not 
needed in any of the patients. The procedure was concluded with 
bimanual examination and reinsertion of a #5 or #6 indwelling 
dilator, and the patient was awakened and transported to the 
recovery area (Figure 4). Operative time was approximately 
30 minutes. As a private certified OR, partners were allowed to 
observe the treatment if the patient gave consent. Partners were 
shown the degree of spasm and with a glove were able to palpate 
the spasm. During the procedure, they were instructed how to 
insert the dilators to help with postprocedure dilation (this 
helped the woman overcome some of her "control issues"). The 
breakthrough for many of these men observing the procedure 
was often profound and allowed them to understand, often for 
the first time, that vaginismus is a medical condition over which 
the woman had no control. </p>

<p>Recovery Room 
We have observed that waking up with a large dilator (#5 or 
#6) often "flips a switch" helping patients realize for the first time 
that penetration is possible, which allows for more rapid progress 
and intercourse. 
7,8 Patients frequently want to know if they had 
normal (vaginal) anatomy. Knowing this gives them a great deal 
of reassurance and can be profoundly comforting for them. </p>

<p>In the recovery room, the nursing staff worked with the 
patient and her partner for approximately 2 hours to help them 
get comfortable moving the dilator in and out and to review their 
postprocedure instructions. The bupivacaine anesthesia, which 
lasts approximately 6 to 8 hours, often made this a pain-free 
experience. Usually, three patients were treated during each 
session. This had the added benefit of allowing women and men 
to meet each other (with permission) and to understand that 
their condition was not unique. The patient was discharged with 
instructions to maintain and sleep with the #4 dilator inserted. 
Ibuprofen and sleeping aids such as Benadryl (diphenhydramine; 
Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer, Skillman, NJ, USA) were </p>

<p>recommended as needed for discomfort or inability to sleep once 
the local anesthesia was no longer effective. Patients returned to 
the clinic the following day with the #4 dilator in place. </p>

<p>Postprocedure Day 1: Advancement With Dilators and 
Counseling 
Patients returned to their respective cubicles to continue with 
supervised dilation to the larger dilators, although the Botox was 
not yet effective. It is likely this was possible as a result of the 
progressive dilation under anesthesia and the passive stretch 
during the night sleeping with the #4 dilator. Patients with severe 
vaginismus, who had never been able to use dilators, often made 
significant progress with the #5 and #6 dilators on the first day 
after the procedure. </p>

<p>Counseling 
On the day after treatment in the OR, postprocedure group 
counseling was done by Dr Pacik after permission was obtained. 
Group counseling was an effective way to engage women and 
their partners in an informal, open, and honest conversation 
about their vaginismus, although they were highly secretive 
before this. These group sessions often took approximately 
5 hours, which also allowed the participants to ask questions. 
Counseling included postprocedure instructions for dilator use, 
lubricants, and progression to coitus (Appendix 3). 
7,8 Rarely a 
patient requested private counseling, which was done in a 
separate part of the building. Women with vaginismus, especially 
those with severe vaginismus, usually are sexually inexperienced; 
their fears and heightened anxiety to penetration persist. Some 
women exchanged e-mails and phone numbers. This was helpful 
in maintaining a support system. Postdischarge dilation recom-
mendations are presented in Appendix 4. When applicable, 
patients were encouraged to continue seeing their clinicians such 
as psychologists, sex counselors, and physical therapists for 
ongoing care and support. </p>

<p># 3 Dilator = 2.5 inches or 63.5 mm (length = 3.5 inches) </p>

<p># 4 Dilator = 3.25 inches or 82.55 mm (length = 3.5 inches) </p>

<p># 5 Dilator = 4 inches or 101.6 mm (length = 3.5 inches) </p>

<p># 6 Dilator = 5 inches or 127 mm (length = 3.5 inches) </p>

<p># 7 Dilator = 5.5 inches or 139.7 mm (length = 3.5 inches) </p>

<p># 8 Dilator = 6.25 inches or 158.75 mm (length = 3.5 inches) </p>

<p>• 
• 
• 
• 
• 
• </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 4. Panel A shows Pacik borosilicate glass dilators sizes </p>

<p>3 to 8 (right to left). Panel B shows circumferences and lengths of 
Pacik borosilicate glass dilators. </p>

<p>Sex Med 2017;5:e114ee123 </p>

<p>Vaginismus Treatment 
e119 </p>

<p>Dilation, Dilators, and Home Care </p>

<p>Many protocols exist regarding dilation recommendations to 
overcome vaginismus. As presented in Table 1, more than 50% 
of women attempted the use of dilators and were unable to 
progress to comfortable penetration because, too often, not 
enough time was spent dilating. Regardless of the type of treat-
ment, dilation is an important part of the recovery process. 
Women have mentioned repeatedly that they hate to dilate and 
even patients who went through this rigorous program some-
times failed to dilate for long enough periods. The dilation 
instructions are summarized as follows. </p>

<p>First Month After Procedure 
Dilate 2 hours a day, 1 hour in the morning and 1 hour in the 
evening, or 2 hours at any one sitting. Advance to larger dilators 
as able until the #5 or #6 dilator becomes comfortable. </p>

<p>Second Month After Procedure 
Decrease dilation to 1 hour a day and advance to larger sizes. </p>

<p>Third Month After Procedure 
Dilate 15 to 30 minutes a day. </p>

<p>One Year After Procedure 
Women with severe vaginismus had a higher rate of recurrence 
if they stopped dilating by approximately 6 months. For this 
reason, even 10 to 15 minutes of dilation every day or two is of 
value. </p>

<p>It is helpful for the partner to assist with dilation to help 
transition to intercourse physically and psychologically. </p>

<p>Advancing to Intercourse 
Postprocedure counseling includes a discussion of the 
following items. Attempts at intercourse should be delayed 
until at least the #5 dilator can be inserted easily. It is helpful 
to dilate with the #5 or #6 dilator for approximately 1 hour 
before to attempting first-time intercourse. For partners who 
have larger penises, #7 (6-inch circumference) and #8 (7-inch 
circumference) dilators are available. During these first attempts 
at intercourse, patients and their partners are taught to pene-
trate with no more than the penile tip because women with 
severe vaginismus are fragile at this juncture and often have 
considerable fear. Men also are vulnerable in that erectile 
dysfunction might be noted including loss of erection and 
premature ejaculation. Everything possible is done to help 
remove the pressure of this moment. Once penile tip pene-
tration is achieved comfortably, the couple can advance to full 
penetration; however, thrusting is discouraged because this can 
be a setback for the woman. Women with severe vaginismus 
might note "leg lock," the involuntary closure of the thighs in 
anticipation of penetration. The "spooning position" with 
entry from behind has been found to be helpful in overcoming </p>

<p>leg lock. Women are encouraged to try different positions 
during their dilation and attempts at coitus to find their 
comfort zone. </p>

<p>Botox: Duration of Activity </p>

<p>Botox is effective for approximately 2 to 4 months, giving 
women ample time to become comfortable with dilation. 
Once women are dilating with a comfortable schedule, they 
should continue dilating beyond 4 months and often are un-
aware that the Botox is no longer active. Some patients dilated 
for at least 1 year before becoming comfortable with pro-
gression to intercourse. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>After treatment, 171 patients (71%) achieved pain-free 
intercourse, which was achieved at a mean of 5.1 weeks 
(median ¼ 2.5; Figure 5) as noted by personal communications 
and FSFI scores. This is especially noteworthy because most 
patients had severe vaginismus as noted by the Lamont and Pacik 
classifications, had an average of five failed treatments, and had 
the condition for a mean of 7 years. Six patients (2.5%) could 
not achieve intercourse within a 1-year period, despite the ability 
to use the #5 or #6 dilators. Of 197 patients with complete 
baseline FSFI data, the mean score was 16.0 ± 7.6 of a possible 
score of 36, indicating compromised sexual function. Ninety 
patients provided post-treatment FSFI ratings with a mean score 
of 24.8 ± 6.5 (Figure 6). The average change in FSFI scores from 
the baseline measurement to after treatment was statistically 
significant (t ¼ 8.8, df ¼ 88, P &lt; .001). Over time, changes in 
score were significant at 3 months (t ¼ 7.1, df ¼ 54, P &lt; .001), 
6 months (t ¼ 9.2, df ¼ 52, P &lt; .001), and 1 year (t ¼ 6.4, 
df ¼ 22, P &lt; .001). </p>

<p>Adverse Events </p>

<p>Minor AEs occurred in six patients: three patients developed 
mild temporary stress incontinence, two patients had mild 
temporary blurred vision that cleared within days to weeks, and 
one patient noted excessive vaginal dryness. All AEs cleared by 
4 months. There were no major or permanent AEs. One patient </p>

<p>Figure 5. Time to intercourse. </p>

<p>Sex Med 2017;5:e114ee123 </p>

<p> 
Pacik and Geletta </p>

<p>required retreatment 3 years after her original treatment and was 
able to achieve pain-free intercourse at 4.5 weeks after treatment. 
She is now 5 years after the procedure and has two children. </p>

<p>Miscellaneous </p>

<p>1. Forty-one patients had normal pregnancies; there were no 
congenital anomalies. Four women had miscarriages. Women 
who feared delivery sometimes opted for epidural anesthesia 
or caesarian section. 
2. One patient with an imperforate hymen masquerading as 
vaginismus completed her treatment in her home state. 
3. One patient was noted to have an intact hymen but did not 
require hymenectomy. 
4. Five patients (0.02%) were diagnosed with vestibulodynia 
before or after treatment. Two of these patients struggled with 
years of preprocedure severe vestibulodynia and vaginismus. 
One of these patients was able to achieve intercourse; how-
ever, the vestibulodynia remained too severe for continued 
coital efforts. More than 50% of women "tested positive" with 
cotton-tipped testing at the time of their treatment, indicating 
the importance of understanding false provoked vestibulody-
nia from anxiety when testing for vaginismus. None of the 
patients appeared to have vulvodynia before or after 
treatment. 
5. Postprocedure disgust issues requiring sex counseling was 
noted in two patients. 
6. Distraught women can struggle with suicidal ideation. One 
such patient was hospitalized twice for suicide attempts. 
7. The oldest patient (72 years) had secondary vaginismus for 
5 years ("hitting a wall," unable to tolerate finger penetration) 
and achieved comfortable intercourse at 3 weeks. </p>

<p>Frequently asked questions are listed in Appendix 5. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>There were several important outcomes of this study. 
(i) Although severe vaginismus can be difficult to treat and </p>

<p>treatment failures are common, this group of women had a rapid 
response to treatment. (ii) Stratifying the severity of vaginismus 
allowed us to properly support these women, many who had 
multiple prior failed treatments and had high levels of fear and 
anxiety. (iii) The multimodal nature of this program treated the 
psychologic fear and anxiety and the physical vaginal spasm. 
(iv) Giving these patients our personal contact information 
helped support them. (v) Some patients who showed no 
improvement after Botox injections elsewhere did not have 
counseling or support. Some had multiple attempts at Botox 
injections with continued failure. (vi) Vaginismus is not a sur-
gical problem. Hymenectomy and episiotomy are inappropriate 
treatments for this condition. (vii) The clinician needs to be 
aware of the many secondary challenges these women face and to 
be prepared for ongoing treatment or referrals. These include 
residual fear and anxiety for penetration, 
7,25,26 inability to 
progress to intercourse despite using dilators, 
7 low libido </p>

<p>26   (sometimes of both partners), heightened harm avoidance and 
pain catastrophizing, 
27 disgust issues, 
28 anorgasmia, partner so-
licitousness and hostility, 
29 infidelity, and erectile dysfunction. </p>

<p>7   We hypothesize that the insertion of dilators under conscious 
sedation at the time of Botox and bupivacaine injections, 
counseling, and post-treatment support provide the initial 
breakthrough that allows the patient to realize that pain-free 
penetration is possible and that her anatomy is normal. 
30 The 
chemodenervation of Botox injections takes effect approximately 
2 to 7 days after injection and lasts for approximately 4 months. </p>

<p>7   This gives these women adequate time to advance with their 
dilators and progress to intercourse. Women are not aware when 
the Botox is no longer active. Some women do not achieve 
intercourse for at least 1 year yet can be successful if they 
continue dilating. </p>

<p>Botox is a safe drug when used according to the manufac-
turer's recommendations. During the past 20 years, Dr Pacik has 
treated thousands of patients using Botox for dynamic facial 
wrinkles, excessive sweating, migraine headaches, and vagi-
nismus, with only rare minor untoward effects mostly the result 
of migration of Botox to nearby tissues. At the time of Dr Pacik's 
retirement, 391 women (of 555 inquiries) were treated using this 
program with few minor untoward events such as temporary 
mild stress incontinence. No permanent sequelae were noted. </p>

<p>This treatment program can be added to the armamentarium 
of a GYN practice. Treating these desperate women can be one 
of the highlights in a career dedicated to helping others 
(Appendix 6). </p>

<p>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS </p>

<p>Strengths </p>

<p>This study addressed the evaluation of women with 
vaginismus, a method to evaluate the severity of vaginismus, and 
treatment for this group of women. A large cohort of women 
with vaginismus participated in the study. This multimodal </p>

<p>Figure 6. FSFI measurements were available for 197 eligible </p>

<p>patients during baseline and 90 patients after treatment. 
FSFI ¼ Female Sexual Function Index. </p>

<p>Sex Med 2017;5:e114ee123 </p>

<p>Vaginismus Treatment 
e121 </p>

<p>treatment approach appears to treat the physical and psychologic 
manifestations of vaginismus, demonstrating a high rate of 
success and safety and a low recurrence rate, and has demon-
strated successful pain-free intercourse in patients who have had 
long-term failures with other types of treatment for vaginismus. 
There were no major complications and few minor untoward 
effects in this study. </p>

<p>Weaknesses </p>

<p>1. An important weakness in this study was the lack of 
comparison treatment. This multimodal vaginismus treat-
ment approach included injections of Botox and bupivacaine, 
dilation under anesthesia, the use of an indwelling dilator 
during recovery, and postprocedure counseling and support 
and suggests the need for a larger placebo-controlled clinical 
trial to better understand the role of each of the components. 
This was not possible in this cohort study because of the 
widespread geographic distribution of patients who could not 
be followed with office visits, resulting in incomplete post-
procedure data and patients lost to follow-up. 
2. As a cohort study, findings should be interpreted within the 
limits of this design. 
3. Although patients were encouraged to submit FSFIs with 
Dr Pacik at 3, 6, and 12 months, some data of successful 
advancement with dilators and progression to intercourse 
were delivered by e-mail logs, which could be prone to 
interview bias. 
4. The diverse geographic locations of patients obviated pre-and 
post-electromyographic studies, which could have been 
helpful in the assessment and follow-up. Women with severe 
vaginismus generally cannot participate with electromyo-
graphic studies as noted by the physical therapists who treated 
some of these patients. 
5. The references cited using onabotulinumtoxinA injections did 
not include limitations in their respective discussions. 
6. A "quality of life" survey would have been helpful in this study 
to compare pretreatment with post-treatment outcomes. 
7. The study was conducted in the setting of a private practice. A 
university setting would be helpful so that participants could 
be followed more closely. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The multimodal combination of onabotulinumtoxinA in-
jections with bupivacaine injections, progressive dilation under 
anesthesia, use of an indwelling dilator, and post-treatment 
counseling and support appears to be safe and effective in the 
treatment of vaginismus as noted by the improvement of FSFI 
scores, patient communications, and ability to progress to pain-
free intercourse. The lack of comparisons for this multimodal 
treatment approach suggests the need for additional studies and 
warrants additional investigation in larger placebo-controlled 
clinical trials. </p>

<p>Corresponding Author: Peter T. Pacik, MD, FACS, IF, 28 
Holiday Shore Drive, Dunbarton, NH 03046, USA. Tel: 603-
387-7735; E-mail: ptpacik@verizon.net </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest: The authors report no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Funding: None. </p>

<p>STATEMENT OF AUTHORSHIP </p>

<p>Category 1 </p>

<p>(a) Conception and Design 
Peter T. Pacik; Simon Geletta 
(b) Acquisition of Data 
Peter T. Pacik 
(c) Analysis and Interpretation of Data 
Peter T. Pacik; Simon Geletta </p>

<p>Category 2 </p>

<p>(a) Drafting the article 
Peter T. Pacik; Simon Geletta 
(b) Revising it for Intellectual Content 
Peter T. Pacik; Simon Geletta </p>

<p>Category 3 </p>

<p>(a) Final Approval of the Completed Article 
Peter T. Pacik; Simon Geletta </p>



<p>Sex Med 2017;5:e114ee123 </p>

<p> 
Pacik and Geletta </p>



<p>Sex Med 2017;5:e114ee123 </p>

<p>Vaginismus Treatment 
e123 </p>

</text></tei>