<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5210605" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">RNALocate</rs>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Increasing evidence has revealed that RNA subcellu-
lar localization is a very important feature for deeply 
understanding RNA's biological functions after be-
ing transported into intra-or extra-cellular regions. 
RNALocate is a web-accessible database that aims 
to provide a high-quality RNA subcellular localiza-
tion resource and facilitate future researches on RNA 
function or structure. The current version of RNALo-
cate documents more than 37 700 manually curated 
RNA subcellular localization entries with experimen-
tal evidence, involving more than 21 800 RNAs with 
42 subcellular localizations in 65 species, mainly in-
cluding Homo sapiens, Mus musculus and Saccha-
romyces cerevisiae etc. Besides, RNA homology, se-
quence and interaction data have also been inte-
grated into <rs type="software">RNALocate</rs>. Users can access these data 
through online search, browse, blast and visualiza-
tion tools. In conclusion, <rs type="software">RNALocate</rs> will be of help in 
elucidating the entirety of RNA subcellular localiza-
tion, and developing new prediction methods. The 
database is available at http://www.rna-society.org/ 
rnalocate/. </p>

<p>Biological functions of RNAs, including translation of ge-
netic information, cellular signal transduction and tran-
scriptional regulation etc., are determined by their location 
in cell (1,2). A cell is divided into different compartments 
that are related to different biological processes (3). For ex-
ample, the RNA localized in nuclear usually participates in </p>

<p>gene expression regulation or mitosis etc (4). Thus, the cel-
lular role of the RNA after synthesis could be inferred from 
its subcellular localization information. Based on this, sub-
cellular localization for RNAs plays an important role in 
studying biological function of RNAs. Therefore, it is ur-
gent to construct a database of RNA subcellular localiza-
tion to integrate, analyze and predict RNA subcellular lo-
calization for speeding up RNA structural and functional 
research. 
To complement with related research in RNA subcellu-
lar localization, we developed a web-accessible database 
(<rs id="software-12" type="software">RNALocate</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-12" type="url">http://www.rna-society.org/rnalocate/</rs>/), 
aimed to collect expanding catalog of diverse species' RNA 
subcellular localization in multiple biological processes 
by manually curating the literature. The first release of 
RNALocate has contained more than 37 700 manually 
curated RNA subcellular localization entries with exper-
imental evidence, involving 65 organisms (such as Homo 
sapiens, Musmusculus and Saccharomyces cerevisiae), 42 
subcellular localizations (such as Cytoplasm, Nucleus, 
Endoplasmic reticulum, Ribosome) and 9 RNA categories 
(such as mRNA, miRNA, lncRNA). Hence, <rs type="software">RNALocate</rs> 
provides a more specific subcellular localization resource 
in which to efficiently investigate, browse and analyze 
a particular RNA, and even provides insight into the 
functions of hypothetical or novel RNAs. The whole data 
set can be easily queried and downloaded through the 
webpage, and visualization tools for interactively browsing 
and analyzing the data set are provided. In addition, 
<rs type="software">RNALocate</rs> also allows researchers to submit new RNA 
subcellular localization. </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +86 451 86699584; Fax: +86 451 86699584; Email: wangdong@ems.hrbmu.edu.cn 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Hao Lin. Tel: +86 28 83202351; Fax: +86 28 83208238; Email: hlin@uestc.edu.cn 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Kongning Li. Tel: +86 451 86615922; Fax: +86 451 86615922; Email: kongningli@hotmail.com </p>

<p> † These authors contributed equally to the work as first authors. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>D136 Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, Database issue </p>

<p>Figure 1. The overview of the RNALocate database. </p>

<p>DATA SOURCES AND IMPLEMENTATION </p>

<p>In order to collect all available RNAs, <rs type="software">RNALocate</rs> inte-
grates all types of RNA symbols, mainly including mi-
croRNA symbols from the miRBase database (5), long non-
coding RNA (lncRNA) and mRNA symbols from NCBI 
Gene and <rs type="software">Ensemble genome database</rs> (6,7). Other ncRNA 
category names are also included, such as transfer RNA 
and small nuclear RNA from <rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">NCBI</rs> <rs id="software-4" type="software">Gene</rs> and Ensemble 
genome database (6,7). The list of subcellular localization 
names was collected according to the Gene Ontology (GO) 
(8). We have written a simple script to screen all abstracts 
and articles in the <rs type="software">PubMed database</rs> using the following 
keyword combinations: (each RNA symbol or RNA cate-
gory name) and/or (each subcellular localization). The rel-
evant hits were further inspected manually. Besides, we also 
retrieved several thousand subcellular localization entries 
from <rs type="software">lncRNAdb</rs> (9), <rs type="software">PomBase</rs> (10), <rs type="software">FlyBase</rs> (11), <rs type="software">TAIR</rs> 
(12) and <rs type="software">DOT</rs> (13) databases (Figure 1). 
The <rs type="software">RNALocate</rs> database is implemented using HTML 
and PHP languages with <rs type="software">MySQL server</rs>. The interface com-
ponent consists of web pages designed and implemented in 
HTML/CSS. It has been tested in the <rs type="software">Google Chrome</rs>, Fire-
fox and <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> web browsers. </p>

<p>DATABASE CONTENT </p>

<p>RNA subcellular localization information was manually 
obtained from articles published in the <rs type="software">PubMed</rs> database </p>

<p>before May 2016. In current version, <rs type="software">RNALocate</rs> docu-
ments 37 772 RNA subcellular localization entries with ex-
perimental evidence from 65 organisms, involving 42 sub-
cellular localizations (Figure 2) and 9 RNA categories 
(including csRNA, lncRNA, mRNA, miRNA, piRNA, 
snRNA, rRNA, snoRNA and tRNA) (Figure 3). Among 
these, more than 1400 entries were collected from lncR-
NAdb, <rs type="software">PomBase</rs>, <rs type="software">FlyBase</rs>, <rs type="software">TAIR</rs> and <rs type="software">DOT</rs> databases. Each 
subcellular localization entry contains detailed informa-
tion on RNA symbol, RNA category, alias, organism, se-
quence, homology, subcellular localization, tissue, valida-
tion method, PubMed ID, detailed description and net-
work. 
In 'Submit' page, RNALocate invites users to upload 
novel RNA subcellular localization data, and in 'Blast' 
page, sequence alignment can be done after parameter se-
lection. Except these, the whole data set could be down-
loaded through two approaches: 'Basic Download' and 
'API' (application programming interface). In 'Basic Down-
load' page, the whole data are saved in <rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-10" type="software">Excel</rs> and 
TXT formats, users can get them by clicking the download 
button. In 'API' page, users can access part of RNALo-
cate data by using script. RNALocate also provides three 
options in 'Help' page to supply instructions for using it, 
including 'Statistics' (detailed statistical tables), 'Tutorial' 
(procedure and illustrations of RNALocate) and 'Sister 
Databases'. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, Database issue D137 </p>

<p>Figure 2. The hierarchical organization and statistics of RNA subcellular localization. </p>

<p>Figure 3. The statistics of RNA category and organism. (A) The percentage of 9 RNA categories in RNALocate database (B) The entry number of 65 
organism in RNALocate database, only the organisms with ≥100 entries have been listed, respectively. </p>

<p>DATA QUERYING, SEARCHING AND BROWSING </p>

<p>RNALocate provides an interface for convenient retrieval 
of all RNA subcellular localizations. Users can query each 
entry through 'Keyword Search' in 'Search' page. In 'Key-
word Search', 5 paths and relevant examples have been pro-
vided, including 'RNA Symbol', 'RNA Category', 'Sub-
celllular localization', 'Organism' and 'Other ID (miRBase 
ID/Entrez ID)'. 
RNALocate provides brief details of search results as 
a table in the 'Search Result' page, while more detailed 
descriptions such as PubMed ID and description of the 
reference are displayed in 'Detail' page reached by select-
ing 'more'. When selecting the specific RNA symbol in 
'Search Result' page, the 'Detail' page presents more asso-</p>

<p>ciated information of the RNA, such as organism, subcel-
lular localization, alias, sequence, homology and validated 
method. More than 9200 RNAs with orthology/paralogy 
from miRBase and Homologene database have been pro-
vided in RNALocate for investigation on RNA subcellular 
localizations conservation. To further understand the in-
teraction information between different RNAs in various 
types of subcellular localizations online, a 'Network' option 
has also been provided to visualize RNA interaction net-
work with subcellular localization and organism (14,15). 
In 'Browse' page, users can access RNALocate in three 
different paths: 'By Localization', 'By RNA Category' and 
'By Organism'. A treeview and figure have been displayed 
in the three pages, respectively. Users could get browse re-
sults by clicking the node on the tree or the associated name </p>

<p>D138 Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, Database issue </p>

<p>in the figure. For convenience, the data in RNALocate are 
organized using a hierarchical structure of subcellular lo-
calization, according to the cellular component annotations 
documented in GO (8). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION AND FUTURE PROSPECTS </p>

<p>Several subcellular localization databases focused on pro-
teins have been previously constructed, such as DBSubLoc, 
Organelle DB, eSLDB, LOCATE, SUBA, LocDB and 
PSORTdb databases (3,16-21). They had led to a more 
comprehensive understanding of the biological functions in 
proteins. However, recent development has indicated that 
protein subcellular localization are perhaps only half of the 
story in cells, since an expanding catalog of diverse RNAs is 
actively involved in multiple biological processes in different 
subcellular localization. To complement with this absence, 
we developed the RNALocate database by organizing and 
presenting RNA subcellular localization data for 65 organ-
isms across 9 RNA categories. To our knowledge, this is the 
first database comprehensively focusing on RNA subcellu-
lar localization. We hope this resource will bridge the gap in 
RNAs and subcellular localization research, and stimulate 
further interesting elucidating the entirety of RNA subcel-
lular localization, and developing new prediction methods. 
In the future, we will continuously collate RNA subcellular 
localization reference data and update RNALocate. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Scientific Research Fund of Heilongjiang Provincial Edu-
cation Department [12541426]. 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



</text></tei>