<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5235341" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>BACKGROUND &amp; AIMS-Mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling in the exocrine 
pancreas has been extensively studied in the context of pancreatic cancer, where its potential as a 
therapeutic target is limited by acquired drug resistance. However, its role in pancreatitis is less 
understood. We investigated the role of mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase (MEK)-initiated 
MAPK signaling in pancreatitis to determine the potential for MEK inhibition in treating 
pancreatitis patients. </p>

<p>METHODS-To examine the role of MEK signaling in pancreatitis, we used both genetic and 
pharmacologic approaches to inhibit the MAPK signaling pathway in a murine model of cerulein-
induced pancreatitis. We generated mice harboring inducible short hairpins targeting the MEK 
isoforms Map2k1 and/or Map2k2 specifically in the pancreatic epithelium. We also used the MEK </p>

<p>inhibitor trametinib to determine the efficacy of systemic inhibition in mice with pancreatitis. </p>

<p>RESULTS-We demonstrated an essential role for MEK signaling in the initiation of pancreatitis. 
We showed that both systemic and parenchyma-specific MEK inhibition in established pancreatitis 
induces epithelial differentiation and stromal remodeling. However, systemic MEK inhibition also 
leads to a loss of the proliferative capacity of the pancreas, preventing the restoration of organ 
mass. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS-MEK activity is required for the initiation and maintenance of pancreatitis. 
MEK inhibition may be useful in the treatment of chronic pancreatitis to interrupt the vicious 
cycle of destruction and repair but at the expense of organ regeneration. </p>

<p>Keywords </p>

<p>Inflammation; Wound Healing; Tissue Regeneration; ADM </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
Reprint requests Address requests for reprints to: Howard Crawford, PhD, NCRC Building 520, Room 1347, 1600 Huron Parkway, 
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48109-1600. howcraw@umich.edu; fax: (734) 647-6977. 
Conflicts of interest The authors disclose no conflicts. </p>

<p>HHS Public Access </p>

<p>Author manuscript </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Published in final edited form as: 
Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2017 January ; 3(1): 99-118. doi:10.1016/j.jcmgh.2016.09.009. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Pancreatitis is the most frequent cause for hospitalization for a gastrointestinal disease. 1  Repeated bouts of acute pancreatitis cause a necrosis-fibrosis sequence leading to chronic 
pancreatitis (CP), which is characterized by progressive and potentially irreversible damage 
to the pancreas. 2 Although some acinar cells are lost during pancreatitis through necrosis, 3  other acinar cells undergo acinar-to-ductal metaplasia (ADM). 4 ADM are proliferative duct-
like structures theoretically capable of regenerating acinar cells lost in pancreatitis. 4-6 ADM 
induction has been linked to several mechanisms including ductal ectasia, 7 activation of 
nuclear factor kappa B (NF-κB), 8,9 Notch receptors, 10,11 and epidermal growth factor 
receptor (EGFR). Activation of EGFR by ectopic ligands has been demonstrated to drive 
ADM in ex vivo cultures 10,12 and in vivo. 12,13   High levels of RAS activity, established through transgenic overexpression of oncogenic 
Kras, are sufficient to drive CP and ADM. 14 This effect is mediated through RAS activation </p>

<p>of NF-κB signaling, which propagates a feed-forward signaling loop promoting chronic 
inflammation. 15 We and others have demonstrated that endogenously expressed mutant Kras </p>

<p>requires EGFR to achieve sufficient RAS activity to induce ADM and tumorigenesis. 16,17  We also observed that pharmacologic inhibition of mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase 
(MEK) is sufficient to block KRAS-driven ADM and subsequent tumor formation, 17  whereas MEK inhibition of established pancreatic intraepithelial neoplasia induces acinar 
cell redifferentiation. 18 Taken together, these data strongly support a key role for KRAS-
MEK signaling in the formation and maintenance of pancreatic preneoplasia. </p>

<p>In contrast to tumorigenesis, the role of mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling 
in the induction and persistence of pancreatitis in the absence of oncogenic Kras is less well-</p>

<p>elucidated. Pancreatitis is marked by an influx of macrophages that can release cytokines 
such as tumor necrosis factor-α and RANTES driving ADM by activation of NF-κB. 8 In 
addition, alternatively activated macrophages promote the activation of pancreatic stellate 
cells, further enhancing the fibroinflammatory response. 19 It has been postulated that 
stromally derived cytokines and growth factors are primarily responsible for driving acinar 
cell damage and ADM. 8 However, expression of EGFR ligands and EGFR activation is 
commonly observed in human CP, and in mice, parenchymal ablation of either EGFR or 
ADAM17, the primary EGFR ligand sheddase, prevents ADM and the stromal response in a 
cerulein model of pancreatitis. 17 These data collectively suggest that MEK signaling in 
epithelial cells, downstream of EGFR activation, is required for initiation of pancreatitis, 
including ADM and the fibroinflammatory response. The possibility that MEK activity is 
important for maintaining ADM suggests that MEK inhibitors may offer a treatment strategy 
for CP in human patients, for which there currently are no effective alternatives. 2   Here we have determined that inhibition of MAPK signaling in cerulein-induced pancreatitis 
by treatment with the MEK inhibitor trametinib blocked CP development. Furthermore, 
short-term trametinib treatment of established pancreatitis restored exocrine tissue and 
dramatically reduced inflammation and fibrosis. However, inhibition of MEK interfered with 
the restorative capacity of the organ by blocking cell proliferation. With longer-term 
trametinib treatment, loss of organ regeneration was even more pronounced. By using short 
hairpin (sh) RNA mouse models individually targeting both major MEK isoforms, we found 
that parenchyma-specific knockdown of MEK blocked pancreatitis-induced ADM and the </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 2 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>associated inflammation and fibrosis. Together, these data show that MEK signaling is a 
potent driver of the overall pancreatitis phenotype and is required for limited organ 
regeneration. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Blockade of Mitogen-activated Protein Kinase Signaling Prevents Chronic Pancreatitis </p>

<p>Previously we showed that parenchymal EGFR and its activation by ADAM17 are required 
for pancreatic tumorigenesis, 17 attributing this effect to a reduction in downstream MEK 
activation. We also found that parenchymal ablation of EGFR or ADAM17 blunted all 
aspects of experimental pancreatitis. 17 However, in each of these models, EGFR signaling 
was chronically inhibited before disease onset, preventing us from examining acute effects. 
Here we set out to explore the feasibility of acute MEK inhibition as a potential treatment 
for CP. First, we performed immunohistochemistry for phosphorylated extracellular signal-
regulated kinase (pERK) on a human pancreas tissue microarray that included normal and 
CP samples (Figure 1A) to determine whether MEK activity is potentially relevant to human 
CP. Ten of 12 CP samples showed pERK positivity in the epithelia and 12 of 12 in stromal 
cells. In contrast, 2 of 56 normal pancreas samples showed pERK positivity in the epithelia 
and 4 of 56 in the stroma. This ERK activity may be a result of being normal tissue in close 
proximity to cancer. </p>

<p>Pancreatitis can be induced in mice by administration of supramaximal doses of cerulein, a 
cholecystokinin ortholog, with the extent of damage determined by the amount and duration 
of treatment. Mild treatment regimens induce symptoms of acute pancreatitis, marked by 
acinar cell necrosis and an innate immune response. A more severe treatment protocol 
results in a phenotype more reminiscent of human CP, marked by ADM, fibrosis, and innate 
and adaptive immune responses. 17 However, unlike human CP, damage induced by chronic 
cerulein treatment resolves over time after cerulein withdrawal. </p>

<p>To investigate whether systemic inhibition of MEK blocked cerulein-induced pancreatitis in 
a manner similar to EGFR gene ablation, we pretreated mice with either the MEK inhibitor 
trametinib (T-CP) or vehicle (V-CP) and then continued this treatment with a cerulein 
treatment regimen that elicits a CP-like phenotype (Figure 1B) or saline as a vehicle control. 
The efficacy of trametinib treatment was verified by immunoblotting tissue lysates harvested 
from V-CP and T-CP groups, where ~60% lower pERK levels were observed (Figure 1C). </p>

<p>Histologic examination of pancreas tissue demonstrated that cerulein treatment strongly 
induced a dropout of acinar tissue and a gain of fibrotic stroma (Figure 1D). V-CP mice had 
~70% loss of acinar cell area, defined by area positive for amylase by 
immunohistochemistry (Figure 1E), compared with saline controls. Loss of acinar cells was 
accompanied by gain of a picrosirius-positive fibrotic stroma (Figure 1F), rich in 
inflammatory cells. Pancreata from T-CP animals had dramatically more amylase-positive 
acinar tissue compared with vehicle control, as well as significantly less fibrosis. The 
fibroinflammatory response and acinar dropout correlated to organ atrophy associated with 
CP, with V-CP pancreata losing 60% of their relative pancreatic mass compared with saline 
control (Figure 1G). In contrast, T-CP mice lost only 35% of relative pancreas mass </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 3 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>compared with saline control. There were no apparent differences in the tissue of mice 
treated with trametinib or vehicle in the absence of cerulein (Figure 1H). </p>

<p>To support the histologic findings, RNA was harvested from the tissue of V-CP and T-CP 
mice. Quantitative reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) was 
performed to assess the acinar vs ductal composition of the pancreas (Figure 1I). As 
expected, levels of amylase (Amy2b) were dramatically higher and levels of the ductal 
marker cytokeratin 19 (Krt19) were significantly lower in T-CP pancreata vs V-CP 
pancreata. Transcripts for the acinar-specific transcription factors Ptf1a and Mist1 confirmed 
higher levels of acinar differentiation in T-CP mice compared with V-CP mice. </p>

<p>Consistent with the epithelial response, examination of immune cell infiltration in the 
cerulein-treated tissue (Figure 1J and K) revealed that trametinib treatment strongly </p>

<p>attenuated F4/80 + macrophage, Ly6b.2 + neutrophil, and CD-3 + T-cell influx compared with 
vehicle treatment. Trametinib treatment also dramatically reduced the conversion of isolated 
acinar cell explants embedded in Matrigel (Corning, Corning, NY) to ductal cysts compared 
with vehicle control (Figure 1L and M), suggesting that the effects of MEK inhibition are at </p>

<p>least in part due to effects of the inhibitor on ADM, independent of inflammation. </p>

<p>Mitogen-activated Protein Kinase Kinase 1 and Mitogen-activated Protein Kinase Kinase 2 
Isoforms Are Redundant in Pancreatitis </p>

<p>The systemic use of trametinib cannot distinguish between the contributions of the 
individual MEK1 and MEK2 isoforms or between parenchymal and stromal activities. 
MEK1 and MEK2 have been shown in several other systems to have some non-redundant 
functions, 20-25 and we found prominent ERK activity in both the epithelial and stromal 
compartments in human CP (Figure 1A). To more precisely dissect the contributions of the 
MEK proteins, we generated mice in which we could conditionally and independently knock 
down expression MEK1 and MEK2 isoforms in vivo. Mice containing shRNAs targeting 
Map2k1 or Map2k2 (shMEK1, shMEK2) were cloned under the control of a Tet operator </p>

<p>and knocked in downstream of the Col1A1 locus. These mice were crossed with mice 
harboring a Cre-dependent tetracycline transactivator in a background with the pancreas-
specific Ptf1a Cre/+ . The shMEK1 and shMEK2 lines were also interbred to allow 
simultaneous knockdown of both MEK isoforms (Figure 2A). Doxycycline-induced 
expression of shRNAs resulted in an effective knockdown of the targeted isoform with no 
cross reactivity, whereas the shMEK1/2 mice demonstrated a loss of expression of both 
isoforms (Figure 2B). Potent knockdown of the target MEK isoform was observed with 72 
hours of doxycycline treatment, with the greatest level of knockdown achieved with 1 week 
of treatment (Figure 2C). The specificity of the shRNA expression was confirmed to be 
confined to the pancreas of mice harboring all the required transgenes by fluorescent 
imaging (Figure 2D). Importantly, there was no discernible effect on the normal pancreas 
from the knockdown of any of the genes or the expression of a control shRNA targeting 
Renilla luciferase (shRen713) (Figure 2E). </p>

<p>To test the requirement of MEK isoforms on the induction of CP, shRNA and Ptf1a +/Cre 
control mice were treated chronically with cerulein after activation of shRNA expression 
(Figures 3 and 4). Knockdown of either MEK1 or MEK2 alone was indistinguishable from </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 4 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>wild-type (WT) and non-target shRNA control mice, in which the tissue was heavily 
damaged after cerulein treatment (Figure 3B). However, the knockdown of both MEK1 and 
MEK2 together revealed potent inhibition of MAPK activation (Figure 4B) and led to a 
significant retention of acinar cell mass, as well as a marked decrease in the amount of 
fibrosis and significant reduction in immune infiltration (Figure 4C-E), similar to trametinib 
treatment. </p>

<p>In line with these histologic observations, knockdown of MEK1/2 led to dramatically higher 
transcript levels of acinar differentiation markers as well as decreased Krt19 levels (Figure 
4F) and was able to efficiently block the transdifferentiation of Matrigel-embedded acinar 
cells to ductal cysts (Figure 4G and H). Consistent with the results from trametinib </p>

<p>treatment, a significant difference was seen in the relative pancreatic mass between cerulein-
treated shMEK1/2 mice as compared with rttA controls (Figure 4I). </p>

<p>Mitogen-activated Protein Kinase Kinase Inhibition Does Not Block Acute Damage </p>

<p>We had previously observed that EGFR is required for CP induction but not for the acute 
cerulein response, 17 demonstrating that the blockade with chronic treatment was not due to 
trivial effects on cerulein signaling. It has also been suggested that MAPK inhibition 
mitigates the acute effects of cerulein-induced pancreatitis. 26 To test whether either 
trametinib treatment or knockdown might be affecting cerulein signaling itself, we examined 
the effect of MEK blockade on acute pancreatitis. Mice were pretreated with trametinib or 
vehicle as before and then concurrently with a cerulein regimen that would induce acute 
pancreatitis (Figure 5A). The acute cerulein treatment resulted in several hallmarks of acute 
pancreatitis including edema, necrosis, and an increase in serum amylase (Figure 5B and C) </p>

<p>regardless of inhibitor treatment. The shRNA mice and control mice were treated with 
doxycycline and subjected to the same acute pancreatitis protocol (Figure 5D). After similar 
trametinib treatment, cerulein-treated shMEK1/2 mice showed necrosis and edema and 
demonstrated no difference in serum amylase levels compared with cerulein-treated shRNA 
or control mice (Figure 5E and F). These data indicate the initial response of the acinar </p>

<p>compartment to cerulein is not blocked by MEK inhibition through either systemic or 
parenchymal-specific means. </p>

<p>Systemic Inhibition of Mitogen-activated Protein Kinase Kinase Ameliorates the 
Pancreatitis Phenotype but Disrupts Organ Regeneration </p>

<p>Having established that MEK inhibition concurrent with cerulein treatment blocks the onset 
of the pancreatitis phenotype, we set out to test whether MEK inhibition can reverse the 
pancreatitis phenotype. First, we induced CP in WT mice with cerulein and then continued 
cerulein treatment together with either trametinib or vehicle (Figure 6A) or withdrew them 
from cerulein treatment entirely to allow recovery (Figure 6B). Western blotting confirmed 
that MAPK activation was reduced in the trametinib-treated group compared with the 
vehicle-treated mice (Figure 6C). Trametinib treatment was sufficient to restore a significant 
amount of acinar tissue, with 80% of the amylase-positive area compared with the recovered 
cohort, whereas the vehicle-treated mice had less than 50% of the recovered control (Figure 
6D and E). Trametinib treatment also reduced fibrosis compared with vehicle-treated </p>

<p>controls and dramatically lowered the number of macrophages, neutrophils, and T cells </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 5 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>(Figure 6D and F). However, in trametinib-treated mice the relative mass of the pancreas did </p>

<p>not reach to the same size as the recovery group (Figure 6G), suggesting that MEK activity 
was required not just for maintenance of ADM but also for the tissue regenerative function 
of ADM. We confirmed that trametinib treatment induced acinar cell redifferentiation by 
using qRT-PCR analysis for acinar cell differentiation markers, compared with vehicle-
treated mice. However, transcript levels of the ductal marker Krt19 remained unchanged 
between the 2 groups. </p>

<p>Our data to this point were consistent with MEK inhibition driving the redifferentiation of 
acinar cells from ADM. However, ADM is known to be highly proliferative, 6 presumably 
contributing to the restoration of organ mass. Therefore, reversing the metaplastic state 
before sufficient proliferation or blocking epithelial proliferation globally regardless of 
differentiation status may prevent the pancreatic regeneration that would normally follow 
cessation of the damaging insult. To determine whether MEK inhibition blocks the 
proliferative capacity of the epithelium, we treated mice with cerulein for 1 week to 
establish a modest pancreatitis phenotype and then treated the mice with trametinib or 
vehicle for 48 hours to investigate the early effects of MEK inhibition. To track proliferation, 
bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) was administered 4 hours before death (Figure 7A). Inhibition 
of MAPK activation was verified by Western blot (Figure 7B), and BrdU incorporation was 
measured by immunohistochemistry (Figure 7C). Indeed, levels of BrdU incorporation were 
significantly higher in vehicle-treated animals compared with trametinib-treated mice 
(Figure 7D). In addition, RNA transcript levels of several acinar markers increased while the 
levels of Krt19 decreased in the trametinib-treated group (Figure 7E), which is consistent 
with the hypothesis that MEK activity is required for both proliferation and maintenance of 
the ADM differentiation state. Further analysis by using coimmunofluorescence for Ki67, as 
a marker of proliferation, the acinar cell marker carboxypeptidase A, and the ductal marker 
CK19 revealed that proliferative capacity of both the epithelial (positive for either) and the 
stromal/inflammatory compartments (negative for both) was reduced by MAPK inhibition 
(Figure 7F and G). The consequences of anti-proliferative effects of MEK inhibition were </p>

<p>more profound with longer-term cerulein treatment with MEK inhibition (7 days of cerulein 
followed by 14 days of combined cerulein and trametinib or vehicle), resulting in an even 
more severe loss of pancreatic mass (Figure 8). </p>

<p>Maintenance of Pancreatitis Requires Epithelial Mitogen-activated Protein Kinase Kinase 
Signaling </p>

<p>We next investigated whether knockdown of parenchymal MEK1 and MEK2 was sufficient 
to reverse the damage of established pancreatitis. Pancreatitis was established in shMEK1/2 
mice by cerulein treatment. Mice were then either removed from cerulein treatment and 
allowed to recover or continued on cerulein treatment with and without doxycycline-induced 
shRNA expression (Figure 9A-C). The shRNA expressing mice treated with cerulein 
demonstrated significant recovery of acinar mass and decreased levels of fibrosis compared 
with mice lacking shRNA expression (Figure 9D and E). This was also accompanied by a </p>

<p>loss of macrophage and neutrophil infiltration; however, there were more T cells in the mice 
expressing shRNA under cerulein treatment compared with the recovery group (Figure 9F-
H). Inhibition of MAPK activation in the doxycycline-treated mice was verified by Western </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 6 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>blot for pERK (Figure 9I), whereas the induction of expression of acinar markers and loss of 
Krt19 expression were verified by qRT-PCR (Figure 9J). No differences were seen in mice 
expressing a control short hairpin and in mice expressing single short hairpins targeting 
MEK1 or MEK2 alone. The relative pancreatic mass also did not differ between treatment 
groups (data not shown). </p>

<p>Cytokine Expression Is Modulated by Mitogen-activated Protein Kinase Signaling </p>

<p>The observation that blocking MEK signaling affected not just the epithelium but also the 
resulting fibroinflammatory response led us to examine cytokine production in mice treated 
with cerulein plus trametinib or vehicle. Whole tissue lysate was harvested from either 
untreated mice or mice treated with cerulein to establish pancreatitis, then concurrently 
treated with cerulein in combination with trametinib or vehicle (Figure 10A), and then 
examined by using a mouse cytokine array (Figure 10B). Among the cytokines detected in 
the array, the proinflammatory cytokines CXCL1, TNF-α, MCP1, ICAM1, IL1a, IL16, 
IL23, CXCL12, CSF1, as well as the canonically negative regulators TIMP1 and IL1-ra, 
were increased in CP and downregulated by trametinib treatment. With the cytokine array 
results as a guide, we used qRT-PCR analysis to confirm a significant reduction in 
expression of many proinflammatory cytokines in mice treated with trametinib after 
establishment of pancreatitis (Figure 10C) and in mice treated with trametinib before the 
induction of CP (Figure 11A). The RNA expression levels of many of these cytokines were 
also suppressed in doxycycline-treated shMEK1/2 mice after the establishment of 
pancreatitis (Figure 10D and E) or knockdown of MEK1 and MEK2 before cerulein </p>

<p>treatment compared with Ptf1a Cre/+ control mice (Figure 11B). Together, these data suggest 
that MEK inhibition, either systemically or in the parenchyma, prevents the establishment of 
the proinflammatory cytokine-rich microenvironment that exacerbates the fibroinflammatory 
response associated with CP (Figure 10F), disrupting ADM/inflammatory cell reciprocal 
communication in pancreatitis. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Pancreatitis is a serious health issue without any effective treatments. Our earlier studies on 
the importance of EGFR activity in pancreatic tumorigenesis strongly implicated EGFR/ 
KRAS/MEK/ERK signaling in the very earliest stages of tumor formation, 17 including those 
processes also associated with CP such as ADM. Here we show that MEK signaling is 
required not only for the initiation of the metaplastic process and the associated 
fibroinflammatory response but also for maintaining the transdifferentiated, metaplastic 
state. These observations closely mirror data implicating MAPK signaling in both the 
initiation and maintenance of metaplasia in the chief cells of the stomach epithelium, 27  illustrating a commonality in the role of MAPK signaling on the plasticity of Mist1 
expressing serous exocrine cells in different organs. 28 Genetic or pharmacologic inhibition 
of MEK activity consistently led to a larger population of amylase-positive acinar cells, 
decreased fibrosis, and an attenuated inflammatory response after the onset of pancreatitis. 
However, despite the amelioration of the common characteristics of pancreatitis pathology, 
chronic MEK inhibition also prevented the restoration of pancreatic mass that would be 
associated with legitimate healing. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 7 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>It has previously been demonstrated that the MAPK signaling pathway is upregulated in 
response to damage and required for adaptive pancreatic growth. 29,30 Our data further 
suggest that the MEK-ERK signaling axis is also an important part of the pancreatic wound 
healing process, similar to what has been observed in the regeneration of other 
gastrointestinal systems. Injury to the gastric mucosa results in activation of ERK in an 
EGFR-dependent manner, initiating the proliferation and migration necessary to begin the 
wound healing process. 31,32 Furthermore, the EGFR ligand HB-EGF has also been 
demonstrated to play an important role in intestinal restitution after ischemia in a manner 
requiring both the MEK-ERK and PI3-kinase pathways downstream of EGFR signaling. 33   The wound healing process can also be viewed in the context of tissue regeneration from a 
progenitor population. In Drosophilla EGFR-MAPK signaling is required for intestinal stem </p>

<p>cells to regenerate the midgut epithelium after bacterial infection. 34 EGFR and Notch 
pathways also cooperate to initiate proliferation and differentiation of gastric stem cells in 
response to injury. 35 However, unlike the intestine, the pancreas lacks a confirmed adult 
stem cell population. The proliferative nature of ADM compared with normal acinar or duct 
cells, together with the ultimate recovery of an acinar cell population after experimental 
pancreatitis, has led to the hypothesis that ADM is involved in the limited tissue 
regeneration observed on resolution of the damaging insult. 4,6 However, several studies 
suggest other sources of restored acinar cells after injury, including proliferation of other 
mature acinar cells, 5 proliferation and differentiation of centroacinar cells, 36  transdifferentiation of a duct cell subpopulation, 37,38 or expansion of a rare DCLK1-positive 
cell population. 39 Here we show that MEK inhibition after induction of pancreatitis blocks 
cell division, yet it increases the relative acinar cell population, suggesting that the 
precursors of these new acinar cells are preexisting rather than being derived from the 
proliferative expansion and differentiation of a small subpopulation of cells. The lack of 
regeneration seen in response to systemic MEK inhibition can also be, at least in part, a 
direct effect of MEK inhibition preventing macrophage recruitment and/or polarization, an 
important component of pancreatic regeneration. 40 None of these possibilities are mutually 
exclusive, but our data support a model where metaplastic ducts have the capacity to 
redifferentiate into acinar cells and that MEK activity is required for maintaining their 
metaplastic state. </p>

<p>The failure to regenerate organ mass clearly suggests a potentially deleterious consequence 
to MEK inhibition in treating pancreatitis. However, unlike experimental models of 
pancreatitis where the entire organ is simultaneously affected by the damaging agent, human 
CP usually manifests as a relatively localized region of sometimes severe damage and 
inflammation. Although MEK inhibition may prevent tissue regeneration in the afflicted 
region of the pancreas, we have found no adverse effects of short-term MEK inhibition on 
the normal pancreas. As such, the potential to resolve the pathology of the affected region, 
including the inflammation, without compromising the majority of the organ suggests some 
promise for MEK inhibition in the treatment of pancreatitis. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 8 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Mouse Strains </p>

<p>Ptf1a Cre/+ and shRen713 mice have been previously described. 41,42 The shMapk2k1 and 
shMap2k2 mice were generated by Mirimus Inc (Cold Spring Harbor, NY) on a mixed 
background and contained a ROSA26-CAG-LSL-rtTA 3 -IRES-mKate2 reverse tetracycline 
transactivator. 43 WT C57BL/6 mice were obtained from Jackson Labs (Bar Harbor, ME). 
Cerulein treatments were performed on animals between 6 and 12 weeks of age, with 
doxycycline treatments started up to 1 week before treating animals with cerulein. Animal 
experiments were conducted in accordance with the Office of Laboratory Animal Welfare 
and approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committees of Stony Brook 
University, Mayo Clinic, and the University of Michigan. </p>

<p>Cerulein-induced Pancreatitis, Doxycycline, and Inhibitor Treatments </p>

<p>Cerulein (American Peptide Company Inc, Sunnyvale, CA) was dissolved in sterile saline. 
For chronic pancreatitis, cerulein was administered to mice twice a day at a concentration of 
250 μg/kg body weight via intraperitoneal injection. For acute pancreatitis, mice were given 
hourly injections of cerulein for 7 hours at a concentration of 50 μg/kg body weight and then 
killed after an hour of recovery. An equal volume of sterile saline was injected as a control. 
Trametinib was injected intraperitoneally (Selleck Chemicals, Houston, TX) at 1 mg/kg and 
prepared as previously described. 44 BrdU (Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO) was prepared in 
saline and injected intraperitoneally at 50 mg/kg 4 hours before death of the animal. 
Doxycycline was administered via chow at 200 mg doxycycline per kg of diet (Bio-Serv, 
Flemington, NJ). </p>

<p>Histology </p>

<p>Mice were killed by CO 2 asphyxiation; then tissue was quickly harvested and fixed 
overnight at room temperature with Z-fix solution (Anatech LTD, Battle Creek, MI). Tissues 
were processed by using a Leica (Buffalo Grove, IL) ASP300S Tissue Processor, paraffin 
embedded, and cut into 5-μm sections. Immunohistochemistry was performed on a Dako 
Autostainer Plus (Dako North America, Inc, Carpinteria, CA) or Discovery Ultra XT 
autostainer (Ventana Medical Systems Inc, Tucson, AZ) and counterstaining with 
hematoxylin. Dual immunohistochemistry for CK19 and amylase was performed without 
counterstaining. Picrosirius red staining was performed per the manufacturer's instructions 
(Polysciences, Inc, Warrington, PA). Hematoxylin-eosin staining was performed by using 
Mayer's hematoxylin solution (Sigma-Aldrich) and Eosin Y (Fisher, Pittsburgh, PA). 
Immunofluorescence was performed as previously described. 45 Immunohistochemistry 
slides were scanned on a Pannoramic SCAN slide scanner (Perkin Elmer, WA), and then 
annotation regions encompassing greater than 1 mm of tissue were processed by using 
appropriate algorithms for each stain quantified by using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Halo</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Indica Labs</rs>, 
Corrales, NM). Immunofluorescence was quantified by manual counting of 5 fields per slide 
from images obtained on a Nikon A-1 confocal instrument at ×60 by using <rs id="software-1" type="software">NIS-Elements</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Nikon Instruments</rs>, Melville, NY). </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 9 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Antibodies </p>

<p>The antibodies used in this study are listed in Table 1. </p>

<p>RNA and Protein Harvest From Tissue </p>

<p>Mouse pancreas tissue lysate was obtained by quickly removing a piece of the pancreas from 
mice killed by CO 2 asphyxiation and snap freezing in liquid nitrogen. The frozen tissue was 
then homogenized in either RLT+ buffer for RNA or RIPA buffer supplemented with 
ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid-free protease inhibitor and PhosSTOP phosphatase 
inhibitor (Roche, South San Francisco, CA) by using a Pro 250 Homogenizer (Pro Scientific 
Inc, Oxford, CT). Lysate was then cleared by centrifugation and stored at −80°C. RNA was 
processed by using an RNEasy Plus kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA) following the manufacturer's 
protocol. </p>

<p>Western Blotting </p>

<p>Lysates were quantified by BCA assay (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc, Waltham, MA), and 
equal protein amounts were run onto sodium dodecylsulfate-polyacrylamide gel 
electrophoresis gels. Proteins were transferred from sodium dodecylsulfate-polyacrylamide 
gel electrophoresis gels to Immobilon-FL polyvinylidene difluoride membrane, blocked, and 
then incubated with primary antibodies. After washing, membranes were then incubated in 
secondary antibody, washed, and then exposed on autoradiography film (Bioexpress, 
Kaysville, UT) with West Pico ECL (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc) or scanned on an 
Odyssey CLx scanner (LI-COR, Lincoln, NE). Quantitation of Western blots was performed 
by using <rs id="software-2" type="software">ImageJ</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>, Bethesda, MD). </p>

<p>Serum Amylase Assay </p>

<p>Mice were killed by CO 2 asphyxiation, and blood was immediately harvested by cardiac 
puncture. Serum was separated by centrifugation in Microtainer vials containing a serum 
separation polymer (BD, Franklin Lakes, NJ). A kinetic amylase assay was then performed 
on a Synergy plate reader (BioTek, Winooski, VT) by using an amylase detection reagent 
according to the manufacturer's protocol (Pointe Scientific, Canton, MI). </p>

<p>Whole Animal Imaging </p>

<p>Fluorescence imaging was conducted by using an IVIS Spectrum (Perkin Elmer, Akron, 
OH) by using GFP filters. </p>

<p>Mouse Cytokine Array </p>

<p>Tissue lysate was prepared as above, and 100 μg protein from 2 mice of each treatment 
group was combined and analyzed by the mouse cytokine array panel as per the 
manufacturer's instructions (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN). </p>

<p>cDNA Synthesis and Quantitative Polymerase Chain Reaction </p>

<p>The cDNA was synthesized from isolated RNA with an iScript cDNA synthesis kit (BioRad, 
Hercules, CA). Quantitative PCR reactions were carried out with FastSyber master mix on a </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 10 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Viia7 thermocycler (Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY). Primer sets used for qPCR are 
listed in Table 2. </p>

<p>Three-dimensional Acinar Cell Explant Culture </p>

<p>The acinar cell isolation protocol has been previously described. 46 Briefly, the pancreas was 
harvested and minced with sterile scissors, digested with Collagenase P (Roche), passed 
through polypropylene mesh (Spectrum Laboratories, Rancho Dominguez, CA), and then 
pelleted through an fetal bovine serum gradient. The pelleted cells were embedded in growth 
factor reduced Matrigel, cultured with complete Waymouth's MB 752/1 medium (Sigma-
Aldrich), and maintained at 37°C in 5% CO 2 atmosphere. The shRNA and Ptf1a +/Cre explant 
cultures were treated with 10 μg/mL doxycycline hyclate (Sigma-Aldrich). WT acinar 
explants were treated with 100 nmol/L trametinib or dimethyl sulfoxide. After 3 days 
(Ptf1a +/Cre and shRNA mice) or 5 days (WT mice) of culture, the ratio of acinar to ductal 
conversion was counted by a blinded observer as an average of ten ×20 fields on a CKX41 
light microscope (Olympus, Waltham, MA). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Statistics were performed by using <rs id="software-3" type="software">Graph Pad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">6</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Graph Pad Software Inc</rs>, La Jolla, 
CA) by using an unpaired Student t test for comparison between 2 groups or a one-way </p>

<p>analysis of variance with Tukey multiple comparison test. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Devon F. Pendlebury for assistance with mouse experiments, Brandy Edenfield and Daniel Long 
for assistance with histology, and Megan T. Hoffman for helpful discussion and scientific insight relating to this 
project. The TROMA-III monoclonal antibody to CK19 developed by R. Kemler was obtained from the 
Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank developed under the auspices of the NICHD and maintained by the 
University of Iowa, Department of Biology, Iowa City, IA. </p>

<p>Funding Supported by National Institutes of Health grants R01 CA159222 to H.C.C. and R01 CA151588 to 
M.P.M. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used in this paper </p>

<p>ADM 
acinar-to-ductal metaplasia </p>

<p>BrdU 
bromodeoxyuridine </p>

<p>CP 
chronic pancreatitis </p>

<p>EGFR 
epidermal growth factor receptor </p>

<p>MAPK 
mitogen-activated protein kinase </p>

<p>MEK 
mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase </p>

<p>NF-κB 
nuclear factor kappa B </p>

<p>pERK 
phosphorylated extracellular signal-regulated kinase </p>

<p>qRT-PCR quantitative reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 11 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>sh </p>

<p>short hairpin </p>

<p>WT 
wild-type. </p>



<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 12 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 13 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 14 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 1. </p>

<p>MEK inhibition can block the onset of CP. (A) Immunohistochemistry for phosphorylated 
MAPK in human pancreatitis samples. (B) CP protocol with drug pretreatment. Black 
arrows indicate cerulein injection; green arrows indicate vehicle or trametinib treatment. (C) </p>

<p>Immunoblot for levels of phosphorylated MAPK, total MAPK, and the loading control 
HSP90. The ratio of the band intensities of phosphorylated/total MAPK is indicated under 
each lane. (D) Histologic characterization of tissue remodeling, hematoxylin-eosin staining 
(H&amp;E), dual immunohistochemistry with ductal marker CK19 (brown) and acinar marker 
amylase (blue), and picrosirius red stain, with respective quantitation (E and F) n ≥ 3 for all 
groups. White indicates saline treated; green indicates vehicle + cerulein; yellow indicates </p>

<p>trametinib + cerulein. (G) Relative pancreas mass, defined by percentage pancreas weight 
over body weight, n = 3 for saline and vehicle, n = 6 for trametinib. (H) Relative pancreas 
mass, defined by percentage pancreas weight over body weight, n = 4 for all groups. (I) qRT-
PCR analysis of acinar markers Amy2b, Ptf1a, and Mist1 and ductal marker Krt19. (J) 
Immunohistochemistry for mac rophages (F/480), neutrophils (Ly6B.2), and T-cells (CD3) 
with respective quantitation (K) n ≥ 3 for all groups. (L) Acinar cell explants embedded in 
Matrigel were imaged at Day 0 and Day 5. (M) Acinar to ductal cyst conversion on day 5 
was quantitated by a blinded observer, n = 3. Scale bars = 100 μm for all panels, 50 μm for 
insets. Error bars represent mean with standard deviation. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 15 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 2. </p>

<p>shRNA mouse characterization. (A) Representative genetic scheme of pancreas-specific 
inducible shRNA mice. (B) Western blot for MEK1, MEK2, and β-actin of protein lysate 
from pancreata harvested from doxycycline-treated mice. (C) Western blot for MEK2 
expression as a function of time from shMEK2 mouse on doxycycline. (D) Fluorescent 
imaging demonstrating shRNA expression specifically in the pancreas of shRNA mice. (E) 
Histologic representation of tissue from doxycycline-treated mice. Scale bars = 200 μm. 
GFP, green fluorescent protein; RFP, red fluorescent protein. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 16 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 3. </p>

<p>Knockdown of MEK1, MEK2, or non-target control has no effect on induction of CP. (A) 
Schematic representation of CP protocol after initiation of shRNA expression. (B) 
Histologic representation of tissue remodeling with respective quantitation. (C and D) n ≥ 3 </p>

<p>for all groups. (E) Immunohistochemistry for macrophage, neutrophil, and T-cell infiltration. 
(F-H) Quantitation of respective immunohistochemistry staining; error bars represent mean 
with standard deviation, n ≥ 3 in all groups. Scale bars = 100 μm for panels, 50 μm for 
insets. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 17 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 4. </p>

<p>Combined genetic knockdown of MEK1 and MEK2 can prevent onset of pancreatitis. (A) 
CP protocol after initiation of shRNA expression. (B) Immunoblot for levels of 
phosphorylated MAPK, total MAPK, and the loading control HSP90. The ratio of the band 
intensities of phosphorylated/total MAPK is indicated under each lane. (C) Representative 
histology of each genotype with quantitation for amylase and picrosirius positive tissue (D) 
and immune cell infiltration (E). Blue bars represent Ptf1a +/Cre control mice; red bars </p>

<p>indicate shMEK1/2 mice, n ≥ 3 for all comparisons. (F) qRT-PCR analysis of acinar markers 
Amy2b, Ptf1a, and Mist1 and ductal marker Krt19, n = 4. (G) Acinar cell explants 
embedded in Matrigel were imaged at Day 0 and Day 3. (H) Acinar to ductal cyst 
conversion on Day 3 as quantitated by a blinded observer, n = 3. (I) Relative pancreas mass, 
defined by percentage pancreas weight over body weight, n = 4 for all groups. Error bars 
represent mean with standard deviation. Scale bars = 100 μm for panels, 50 μm for insets. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 18 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 5. </p>

<p>MEK inhibition does not block induction of pancreatitis by cerulein. (A) Acute pancreatitis 
treatment protocol after pretreatment with either MEK inhibitor or vehicle. (B) 
Representative H&amp;E stains for each inhibitor treatment group. (C) Serum amylase levels for 
inhibitor treatments as detected by spectrophotometric activity assay. n = 3 for all groups. 
(D) Acute pancreatitis treatment protocol after activation of shRNA. (E) H&amp;E stains for each 
shRNA treatment group. (F) Serum amylase levels for shRNA mice as detected by 
spectrophotometric activity assay. n = 3 for all groups. Scale bars = 100 μm. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 19 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 6. </p>

<p>Trametinib treatment of established pancreatitis leads to reverse of tissue damage but not of 
tissue mass. CP protocol with inhibitor or vehicle treatment (A) or pancreatitis with recovery 
protocol (B). (C) Immunoblot for levels of phosphorylated MAPK, total MAPK, and the 
loading control β-actin. The ratio of the band intensities of phosphorylated/total MAPK is 
indicated under each lane. (D) Histologic representation of tissue remodeling and immune 
cell counts with quantitation (E and F, respectively), n ≥ 3 in all groups. White bars indicate 
the recovered cohort, green bars indicate cerulein + vehicle treated, and yellow bars indicate </p>

<p>the cerulein + trametinib treated group. (G) Relative pancreas mass, defined by percentage 
pancreas weight over body weight, of each treatment group, n = 4 in all groups. (H) qRT-
PCR analysis of acinar markers Amy2b, Ptf1a, and Mist1 and ductal marker Krt19, n = 3. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 20 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 7. </p>

<p>MEK inhibition inhibits acinar proliferation in response to tissue damage. (A) Abbreviated 
CP protocol with BrdU addition to assay proliferation. (B) Immunoblot for levels of 
phosphorylated MAPK, total MAPK, and the loading control β-actin. (C) Histologic 
representation of tissue by H&amp;E, immunohistochemistry for BrdU incorporation, and 
quantitation of BrdU staining (D), n = 4 for both groups. (E) qRT-PCR analysis of acinar 
markers Amy2b, Ptf1a, and Mist1 and ductal marker Krt19, n = 4. (F) Representative 
immunofluorescence images for DAPI (blue), Ki67 (green), CPA (red), and CK19 (white). 
(G) Ki67 quantitated by stromal (CPA − /CK19 − ) or epithelial (CPA + and/or CK19 + ) 
compartment. Error bars represent mean with standard deviation. Scale bars = 100 μm for 
panels, 50 μm for insets. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 21 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 8. </p>

<p>Long-term inhibition of MEK results in loss of ameliorative effect. Schematic representation 
of CP protocol with inhibitor or vehicle treatment (A) or pancreatitis with recovery protocol 
(B). (C) Relative pancreas mass of each treatment group, defined by percentage pancreas 
weight over body weight, n = 3 for recovery and vehicle and n = 4 for trametinib. (D-F) 
Quantitation of respective staining for each group; error bars represent mean with standard 
deviation, n ≥ 3 for all groups. Scale bars = 100 μm for panels, 50 μm for insets. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 22 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 9. </p>

<p>Combined knockdown of MEK1 and MEK2 can reverse cerulein-induced damage. 
Schematic and histologic representation of pancreatitis with recovery protocol (Recovery) 
(A), CP protocol (No Dox) (B), or shRNA activation during CP protocol (Dox) (C). (D-H) 
Quantitation of respective staining; error bars represent mean with standard deviation, n ≥ 3. 
(I) Immunoblot for levels of phosphorylated MAPK, total MAPK, and the loading control 
HSP90. (J) qRT-PCR analysis of acinar markers Amy2b, Ptf1a, and Mist1 and ductal marker 
Krt19; n = 3. Scale bars = 100 μm for panels, 50 μm for insets. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 23 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 10. </p>

<p>MEK inhibition diminishes levels of inflammatory cytokines during pancreatitis. (A) CP 
protocol with drug pretreatment. (B) Immunoblot array of cytokines present in pancreata or 
untreated mice or mice treated with cerulein and either vehicle or trametinib. (C) qRT-PCR 
analysis of inflammatory cytokines present in pancreata treated with cerulein and vehicle or 
trametinib. (D) CP protocol (No Dox) or shRNA activation during CP protocol (Dox). (E) 
qRT-PCR analysis of inflammatory cytokines present in cerulein with or without 
doxycycline-induced shMEK1/2. (F) Potential mechanism of amelioration of CP by MEK 
inhibition. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 24 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 11. </p>

<p>MEK inhibition prevents expression of inflammatory cytokines. (A) Schematic 
representation of CP protocol with inhibitor or vehicle treatment and qRT-PCR analysis of 
inflammatory cytokines from treated pancreata. (B) Schematic representation of CP protocol 
after initiation of shRNA expression in shMEK1/2 compared with Ptf1a +/Cre controls (Cre) 
and qRT-PCR analysis of cytokine expression in treated pancreata. Quantitation of 
respective staining for each group; error bars represent mean with standard deviation, n = 3 
for all groups. </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 25 </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Antibodies Used in This Study </p>

<p>Antibody 
Company 
Catalog no. Host species Application </p>

<p>Amylase 
Sigma-Aldrich 
A8273 
Rabbit 
IHC </p>

<p>Anti-RFP 
Life Technologies 
R10367 
Rabbit 
IHC </p>

<p>BrdU 
Abcam 
ab3626 
Rat 
IHC </p>

<p>CD3 
Abcam 
ab5690 
Rabbit 
IHC </p>

<p>CK19 
Develop. Studies Hybridoma Bank Troma-III 
Rat 
IHC, IF </p>

<p>CPA1 
R&amp;D Systems 
af2765 
Mouse 
IF </p>

<p>F4/80 
ABD Serotec 
MCA497G 
Rat 
IHC </p>

<p>HSP90 
Cell Signaling 
4874s 
Rabbit 
WB </p>

<p>Ki67 
Vector Labs 
VP-RM04 
Rabbit 
IF </p>

<p>Ly-6B.2 
ABD Serotec 
MCA771G 
Rat 
IHC </p>

<p>MEK1 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
SC219 
Rabbit 
WB </p>

<p>MEK2 (N-term) 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
sc524 
Rabbit 
WB </p>

<p>Turbo-GFP 
Thermo Fisher Scientific 
PA5-22688 
Rabbit 
IHC, WB </p>

<p>β-actin 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
sc-47778 
Mouse 
WB </p>

<p>p42/44 MAPK 
Cell Signalling 
9102 
Rabbit 
WB </p>

<p>p42/44 MAPK (T202/Y204) Cell Signaling 
4370P 
Rabbit 
WB </p>

<p>IF, immunofluorescence; IHC, immunohistochemistry; WB, Western Blot. </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Halbrook et al. 
Page 27 </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Sets of Primers Used in This Study </p>

<p>Gene 
Direction Primer </p>

<p>Hprt1 
5' 
TCAGTCAACGGGGGACATAAA </p>

<p>Hprt1 
3' 
GGGGCTGTACTGCTTAACCAG </p>

<p>Tbp 
5' 
CCCCACAACTCTTCCATTCT </p>

<p>Tbp 
3' 
GCAGGAGTGATAGGGGTCAT </p>

<p>Il1a 
5' 
CAAGATGGCCAAAGTTCCTGAC </p>

<p>Il1a 
3' 
GTCTCATGAAGTGAGCCATAGC </p>

<p>Cxcl12 
5' 
AGCCAACGTCAAGCATCTGA </p>

<p>Cxcl12 
3' 
CTTGCATCTCCCACGGATGT </p>

<p>Icam1 
5' 
TCCGCTGTGCTTTGAGAACT </p>

<p>Icam1 
3' 
GGCTCAGTATCTCCTCCCCA </p>

<p>Il-23 
5' 
TGGTTGTGACCCACAAGGAC </p>

<p>Il-23 
3' 
ATCCTCTGGCTGGAGGAGTT </p>

<p>Cxcl1 
5' 
CCGAAGTCATAGCCACACTCA </p>

<p>Cxcl1 
3' 
TTCACCAGACAGGTGCCATC </p>

<p>Ptf1a 
5' 
CATCGAGGCACCCGTTCAC </p>

<p>Ptf1a 
3' 
CAACCCGATGTGAGCTGTCT </p>

<p>Il16 
5' 
ACTTCCAGTGCATCTCAGGC </p>

<p>Il16 
3' 
CGGATGTCGGCTTACGATGA </p>

<p>Amy2b 
5' 
AGGAACATGGTTGCCTTCAG </p>

<p>Amy2b 
3' 
CTGACAAAGCCCAGTCATCA </p>

<p>Ck19 
5' 
CGCGGTGGAAGTTTTAGTGGG </p>

<p>Ck19 
3' 
AGGCGAGCATTGTCAATCTGTA </p>

<p>Mist1 
5' 
CTCGAATCCCCAGTTGGAAGG </p>

<p>Mist1 
3' 
CTCCGGAGACCCTTTGTCAG </p>

<p>Tnfa 
5' 
GACGTGGAACTGGCAGAAGAG </p>

<p>Tnfa 
3' 
TTGGTGGTTTGTGAGTGTGAG </p>

<p>Csf1 
5' 
GGTGGCTTTAGGGTACAGG </p>

<p>Csf1 
3' 
GACTTCATGCCAGATTGCC </p>

<p>Ccl2 
5' 
GGCTCAGCCAGATGCAGTTA </p>

<p>Ccl2 
3' 
GGACCCATTCCTTCTTGGGG </p>

<p>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2017 January 13. </p>

</text></tei>