<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5451875" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Soft tissue sarcoma is a rare neoplasm of mesen-
chymal origin, accounting for only ~1% of all adult cancers 
and consisting of 75 histological subtypes. In the present 
report, the unique case of a 14 year-old female with metastatic 
malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumor (formerly, malignant 
melanotic schwannoma) of the parotid gland, who experienced 
a durable response and sustained tumor control with Rexin-Malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumor (MPNST; formerly, 
melanotic schwannoma) is a rare neoplasm of Schwann cell 
origin capable of melanogenesis (1,2). Clinicopathologically, it 
is considered a distinct entity from conventional schwannoma 
due to genetic and clinical differences (3). Immunophenotypic 
indicators for schwannomas with melanotic differentiation 
include the presence of epitheloid cells with variably sized 
nuclei, and a marked accumulation of melanin (2), but differ-
ential diagnosis typically requires further analysis through 
ultrastructural and immunohistochemical testing. In terms 
of clinical management, it is of paramount importance to 
distinguish primary melanin-containing lesions from malig-
nant melanoma in order to plan an appropriate therapeutic 
approach. </p>

<p>Case report </p>

<p>A 14 year-old female initially presented with a non-painful 
swelling of the right posterior mandible with right facial 
weakness. A magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan of 
the face and neck revealed a 5.3 cm mass of the right parotid 
gland, and a chest computed tomography (CT) scan revealed 
several small, non-specific opacities in the upper right lobe. 
A histopathological examination performed by core needle 
biopsy revealed a malignant melanotic spindle cell neoplasm, 
with atypical spindle cell proliferation arranged in a fascicular 
pattern. The tumor was histologically and immunophenotypi-
cally consistent with MPNST. The patient underwent a right 
radical parotidectomy and a right modified radical neck 
dissection with reconstructive surgery. Note was made of 
the extension of the neoplasm into the soft tissues around the 
parotid gland with perineural invasion. Immunohistochemical 
analysis confirmed the diagnosis, with the involvement of 
three out of eight tumorous lymph nodes staining positive 
for laminin, homatropine methylbromide 45 (HMB-45), and 
tyrosinase, and negative for melanoma-associated antigen 
recognized by T cells (MART-1) and S-100 protein. In March 
2007, the patient started chemotherapy with temozolomide 
(75 mg/m 
2 given orally, daily for 45 days), and in April 2007, 
sorafenib (40 mg by mouth, twice daily), due to the increased 
sizes of nine lung lesions. In spite of these treatments, however, </p>

<p>Rexin-G </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, a tumor-targeted retrovector for malignant 
peripheral nerve sheath tumor: A case report </p>

<p>SETH KIM 
1 , NOAH FEDERMAN 
2 , ERLINDA M. GORDON 
1,3 , FREDERICK L. HALL 
3 and SANT P. CHAWLA </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 Sarcoma Oncology Center/Cancer Center of Southern California, Santa Monica, CA 90403; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Pediatric Hematology/Oncology, Mattel Children's Hospital at UCLA, 
Los Angeles, CA 90095; 
3 Counterpoint Biomedica LLC, Santa Monica, CA 90403, USA </p>

<p>Received December 8, 2016; Accepted March 29, 2017 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/mco.2017.1231 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Dr Erlinda M. Gordon, Sarcoma Oncology </p>

<p>Center/Cancer Center of Southern California, 2811 Wilshire 
Boulevard, Suite 414, Santa Monica, CA 90403, USA 
E-mail: erlinda.gordon@gmail.com </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CT, computed tomography; MRI, magnetic </p>

<p>resolution imaging; MPNST, malignant peripheral nerve sheath 
tumor; PNST, peripheral nerve sheath tumor; PET, positron emission 
tomography; GM-CSF, granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating 
factor; XC, exposed collagenous; TME, tumor microenvironment </p>

<p>Key words: targeted gene therapy vector, cell cycle control, </p>

<p>metastatic sarcoma </p>

<p>KIM et al: REXIN-G FOR MALIGNANT PERIPHERAL NERVE SHEATH TUMOR </p>



<p>a repeat positron emission tomography (PET)/CT scan in June 
2007 revealed diffuse progression in the lungs, thighs, and left 
flank. The patient was admitted for treatment with high-dose 
interleukin-2, but only received 7 of 14 doses due to unaccept-
able toxicity and disease progression. After three cycles of 
ifosfamide (1,800 mg/m 
2 /day for 5 days) as continuous infusion 
with mesna, and doxorubicin (37.5 mg/m 
2 /day intravenously 
for 2 days), a repeat PET/CT scan revealed further tumor 
progression; therefore, the chemotherapy was discontinued. 
In March 2008, the patient participated in a Phase 1/2 
clinical trial using intravenous Rexin-G 
® (developed at the 
USC Keck School of Medicine, Los Angeles, CA, USA) for 
advanced chemoresistant sarcoma (clinical trial protocol 
no. NCT00505713; see Table I). The patient received dose level 
3 of Rexin-G 
® [3x10e 
11 colony-forming units (cfu)] three times 
a week as an outpatient. Objective tumor responses were evalu-
ated by a number of parameters, including Response Evaluation 
Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) v1 (4), tumor volume, mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>(length x width 
2 x 0.52), tumor density in Hounsfeld units 
(HU) and the maximum standardized uptake value (SUV max ) 
by fluorodeoxyglucose (18-FDG) PET-CT (4,5). Based on the 
RECIST v1 and other radiological parameters, the patient 
experienced sustained disease control (Fig. 1). The patient's 
clinical course was complicated by an episode of nephrotic 
syndrome, which was attributed to the bi-weekly subcutaneous 
granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF) 
injections, and therefore these were discontinued. The patient 
received a total of 205 Rexin-G 
® vector infusions over a 2-year </p>

<p>period with minimal toxicity and no serious adverse events. 
Following the last infusion in June 2010, the patient underwent 
a PET/CT scan, comparing the results with those images taken 
prior to treatment. The radiology report stated that there was a 
marked overall improvement in the patient's pulmonary metas-
tases, with all but one nodule being either markedly improved 
in size, or resolved. It was also noted that the right pleural 
effusion and previous significant ascites had been resolved. 
Currently, nine years after commencing the Rexin-G 
® treat-
ment, the patient is alive and well, with no evidence of active 
neoplastic disease. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Peripheral nerve sheath tumor (PNST) is a rare subset 
of soft tissue sarcomas displaying an immunophenotype 
consistent with that of conventional schwannomas, along 
with cytoplasmic melanin deposition characteristic of mela-
nomas (3,6,7). These tumors occur most frequently at nerve 
roots, although other locations along the peripheral nervous 
system have been described (8). Tumors originating from the 
bone, soft tissues, heart, mouth, esophagus, bronchus, retro-
peritoneum, uterine cervix, orbit, parotid gland, as well as 
the spinal cord, acoustic nerve, cerebellum, and sympathetic 
chain, have been reported (1,9). Statistics have revealed a 1.1:1 
male: female ratio (9). The ages of those afflicted vary between 
10 and 84 years (7,9), although the peak incidence occurs with 
patients in their fourth decade (7). There have been fewer </p>

<p>Table I. USA-based clinical trials using tumor-targeted Rexin-G 
® for chemotherapy-resistant solid malignancies. </p>

<p>Clinical trial protocol 
number/dose level </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Clinical site(s)/Phase 
Clinical indication 
No. of patients 
Outcome </p>

<p>NCT00121745; dose 
Rochester, MN, USA: Phase 1 
Pancreas CA 
12 
0% 1-year OS 
level, minus 3-minus 1 </p>

<p>NCT00504998 
b ; 
Santa Monica, CA, 
Pancreas CA 
20 
26.7% 1-year OS 
dose level, 1-3 
USA/Manhattan, NY, USA/ 
13.3% 2-year OS 1 
(Duke) Durham, NC, USA: 
alive in sustained 
Phase 1/2 
remission, 9-year OS </p>

<p>NCT00505713 
b ; 
Santa Monica, CA, 
Bone and soft tissue 
36 
38.5% 1-year OS; 
dose level, 1-4 
USA: Phase 1/2 
sarcoma 
31% 2-year OS 1 
alive with no 
active disease, 
9-year OS </p>

<p>NCT00505271; 
Santa Monica, CA, USA/ 
Breast CA 
20 
60% 1-year OS 
dose level, 1-4 
Manhattan, NY, USA: Phase 1/2 </p>

<p>NCT00572130; dose 
Santa Monica, CA, 
Osteosarcoma 
22 
27.3% 1-year OS 
level, 1-2 
USA: Phase 2 
22.7% 2-year OS 1 
alive in sustained 
remission, 8 years </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Dose levels were calculated as follows: Dose level 1=1x10e 
11 cfu; dose level 2=2x10e 
11 cfu; dose level 3=3x10e 
11 cfu; and dose level 4=4x10e </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>cfu. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>A randomization test on the log-rank statistic using 20,000 random samples revealed a dose-response association between overall survival 
and the Rexin-G dosage (P=0.002 for sarcoma and 0.04 for pancreas cancer). Analysis was done using <rs id="software-0" type="software">NCSS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Number Cruncher Statistical Systems</rs>, Kaysville, UT, USA). Statistical analysis was performed by a biostatistician who was not otherwise involved in the study. 
CA, carcinoma; cfu colony forming units; OS, overall survival. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR AND CLINICAL ONCOLOGY 6: 861-865, 2017 </p>



<p>than 200 cases of PNST reported since it was first described 
in 1932 (10,11), with approximately 40 reported malignancies 
as of 2014 (12). To date, there have been no published cases 
of MPNST originating from the parotid gland. Therefore, 
this case is unique and worthy of report, particularly with 
respect to the patient's impressive response to an innovative 
tumor-targeted gene therapy vector, designated Rexin-G </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. 
To make a differential diagnosis between MPNST and 
spindle cell melanoma is very difficult, particularly in 
small biopsy specimens, due to the diverse range of tumor 
derivations from a Schwann cell lineage (13) and similar histo-
logical features, including cell pleomorphisms with prominent 
nucleoli (1). In the present case study, immunohistochemical 
staining and ultrastructural examinations proved to be useful 
in guiding the diagnostic process. All reported cases of 
MPNST, including the present patient's case, have revealed 
positive gene expression of HMB-45 and tyrosinase, indica-
tive of melanocytic differentiation, but negative expression of </p>

<p>MART-1 and S-100 protein, thereby eliminating a diagnosis of 
melanoma (14). Further studies for the expression of laminin, 
which was displayed intensely in two-thirds of the reported 
cases (15), concluded that the tumor represented a Schwannian 
differentiation, based on the biphasic pattern (i.e. individual 
cell and nested) in the external lamina. 
The prognosis for PNST is unpredictable at best, with 10% 
of all cases developing metastasis (8,10,14). Although gener-
ally considered benign, the tumor is prone to malignancy and 
recurrence, occurring in ~20% of patients (1,8,16). Surgery has 
been the primary treatment option (9), followed by radiation 
therapy or adjuvant chemotherapy. For the patient described in 
the present case report, a right parotidectomy was performed, 
and systemic chemotherapy was administered post-surgery to 
treat the metastatic lung lesions, albeit without success. 
Rexin-G 
® is the first tumor-targeted gene therapy vector 
that has been tested in the clinic (4). Injected intravenously, 
the targeted retroviral particles operate within the vascular </p>

<p>Figure 1. Various tumor parameters of the patient monitored over time. (A) Individual tumor volume measurements over time. Tumor volumes of individual 
target lesions (measured by CT imaging), in mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, were calculated using O'Reilly's formula (length x width 
2 x 0.52). (B) Individual tumor density measurements 
over time. Tumor densities of individual target lesions, in HU, were calculated by radiographic image analysis. (C) Individual FDG avidity measurements over 
time. Avidities of individual target lesions for 18-FDG (SUV max ) were measured in individual target lesions using a PET/CT scan. CT, computed tomography; 
PET, positron emission tomography; HU, Hounsfeld units; FDG, fluorodeoxyglucose; SUV max , maximum standardized uptake value. </p>

<p>KIM et al: REXIN-G FOR MALIGNANT PERIPHERAL NERVE SHEATH TUMOR </p>



<p>Figure 2. Illustration of the tumor microenvironment compared with normal tissues. (A) Normal tissue. (B) The XC-targeting motif enables the vector to seek 
out and accumulate in the tumor microenvironment by binding to abnormally exposed proteins found abundantly in tumors, e.g., as a result of tumor invasion, 
ECM remodeling and neoangiogenesis, but not in normal tissues. Xc, exposed collagenous; ECM, extracellular matrix. </p>

<p>Figure 3. An illustration of the mechanism of action of Rexin-G </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. The Rexin-G 
® nanoparticle displays an XC-targeting motif, derived from the coagulation 
factor, vWF, on its surface amphotropic gp70 envelope protein. When injected intravenously, Rexin-G 
® seeks out and accumulates in cancerous lesions by 
binding to exposed collagenous (XC) proteins. This chimeric retrovector has the innate property of binding to a tumor's natural viral/cell receptor, fusing, 
entering, uncoating, and integrating randomly into the chromosomes of only actively dividing cells (i.e., cancer cells). This selective property spares all termi-
nally differentiated and/or non-replicative cells of normal organs, including hepatocytes, neuronal cells and myocardial cells. Rexin-G 
® carries a cytocidal 
dominant negative cyclin G1 construct, which causes cell death via apoptosis. vWF, von Willebrand factor; XC, exposed collagenous. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR AND CLINICAL ONCOLOGY 6: 861-865, 2017 </p>



<p>system via a high-affinity collagen-binding motif derived from 
von Willebrand coagulation factor (17). Atypical amounts 
of exposed collagenous (XC) proteins are located in areas 
of tumor invasion, neoangiogenesis and stroma formation, 
possibly resulting from exposure to protease activity within the 
tumor microenvironment (TME; Fig. 2). Rexin-G 
® accumu-
lates in these metastatic deposits by seeking out the abnormal 
XC proteins, thereby increasing effective vector concentration 
in the TME in close association with the cancer cells. The 
function of the genetic payload (a dominant negative cyclin G1 
construct is encoded in Rexin-G </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>) is to halt the G1 phase of 
the cell cycle, thus inducing cell death via apoptosis-mediated 
pathways (Fig. 3) (17-20). 
Based on a critical evaluation of its safety and potential 
efficacy, as well as the unmet medical need, Rexin-G 
® was 
granted Orphan Drug status for soft tissue sarcoma and 
osteosarcoma by the US Food and Drug Administration 
(FDA) in 2008 (21); and in 2010, Phase 1 and Phase 2 clinical 
trials using Rexin-G 
® for chemotherapy-resistant soft tissue 
sarcoma and osteosarcoma, respectively, were successfully 
completed (5,21). The results of these studies demonstrated the 
overall safety and, in clinical trials for sarcoma and pancre-
atic cancer, the dose-dependent efficacy in controlling tumor 
growth and improving survival rates with the use of Rexin-G </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, 
particularly at the higher dose levels (Table I). Accordingly, 
long-term survival follow-up (up to 15 years post-treatment) 
is required by the US FDA for investigational gene therapy 
products; to date, there have been no reports of delayed or late 
adverse events associated with Rexin-G 
® treatment. 
In summary, in the present report, the unique case of 
a 14 year-old patient with widely metastatic MPNST of the 
parotid gland, who experienced a durable response and 
sustained tumor control (and minimal toxicity) with an inno-
vative therapy treatment of Rexin-G </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, an XC-/tumor-targeted 
retrovector bearing a cytocidal gene construct, is described. 
On the basis of these results, the continued development of 
Rexin-G 
® for this rare type of mesenchymal cancer, and poten-
tially other chemoresistant sarcomas, is highly recommended. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors are grateful to Heather C. Gordon (Art Consultant, 
Sarcoma Oncology Center, Santa Monica, CA, USA) for 
graphic illustrations and editorial assistance in the writing of 
this manuscript (see www.heathergordondrawings.com). </p>



</text></tei>