<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5095638" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT. The prevalence of Yersinia enterocolitica (Y. enterocolitica) and Yersinia pseudotuberculosis was examined in 151 pet animals in-
cluding 108 rodents, 39 rabbits and four sugar gliders from 13 pet stores in the Yamaguchi Prefecture, Japan. Y. enterocolitica serogroup O:3 
biotype 3 negative for the Voges-Proskauer reaction (O:3/3 variant VP-) was isolated from five Djungarian hamsters (Phodopus sungorus) 
raised at the same pet store. These pathogenic Y. enterocolitica isolates carried the virulence genes, yadA, ail and virF, and were shown to 
be clonal by pulsed-field gel electrophoresis with NotI digestion. This is a first report of pathogenic Y. enterocolitica O:3/3 variant VP-in 
pet Djungarian hamsters in Japan. 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">BioNumerics</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.1</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Applied Maths, Sint-Martens-Latem, Belgium</rs>M. KAMEYAMA ET AL. </p>

<p>
tion (O:3/3 variant VP-) and possessed the three virulence 
genes (yadA, ail and virF). PFGE analysis was conducted 
to determine the genetic relationship of the pathogenic 
Y. enterocolitica isolates; although a few differences were 
found between the banding patterns of the isolates, their 
similarities were &gt;93%, suggesting that the isolates could 
have originated from a common ancestor (data not shown). 
Y. enterocolitica includes several phenotypic variants 
(O serogroup/biotype) of which O:3/4, O:3/3 variant VP-, 
O:5, 27/2, O:8/1b and O:9/2 are those most associated with 
the occurrence of human yersiniosis worldwide [1, 9, 19]. 
Serogroup O:3 is considered the predominant variant in 
Japan, and the number of outbreaks and sporadic cases due 
to serogroup O:8 have been increasing since this variant was 
first isolated from humans in 1990 [12, 13, 15, 21]. Although 
the O:3/3 variant VP-has been previously isolated from sev-
eral animals (healthy pigs and dogs) and retail meat (pork 
imported from Taiwan and chicken from Thailand) in Japan 
[5-7, 15], to the best of our knowledge, this is the first report 
of the isolation of pathogenic Y. enterocolitica O:3/3 variant 
VP-from pet Djungarian hamsters in Japan. 
Store B investigated in this study is located in an urban 
area in the western part of Yamaguchi Prefecture. Sev-
eral mammals (dogs, cats, rodents and rabbits), birds and 
aquarium fish are sold at this store, all of which are bought 
from a number of breeders. In this study, we collected 15 
animal stool samples from 10 Djungarian hamsters, three 
Golden hamsters (Mesocricetus auratus), one Roborovski 
dwarf hamster (Phodopus roborovskii) and one domestic 
rabbit (Oryctolagus cuniculus) at store B (Table 1). Patho-</p>

<p>genic Y. enterocolitica was isolated from five Djungarian 
hamsters raised in individual cages (three in 2012 and two in 
2013). PFGE analysis suggested that these pathogens were 
clonal. All Djungarian hamsters at store B (both positive 
and negative for Y. enterocolitica) had been bought from 
the same breeder. The cages used for breeding the rodents 
were cleaned daily and are washed and disinfected after the 
animals were purchased. The Djungarian hamsters were 
provided with the same type of feed as the other rodents, and 
all animals were given tap water as drinking water. Thus, it 
is unlikely that the common source of the clonal pathogen 
contamination existed in the store between 2012 and 2013; 
although we did not examine the prevalence of pathogens in 
environmental samples, such as the feed, drinking water and 
cages. Therefore, it is unclear why the clonal pathogens were 
isolated solely from Djungarian hamsters. 
A number of studies using experimental animals have 
revealed that pathogenic Y. enterocolitica serogroups O:3 
and O:8 penetrate the intestinal mucosa in vivo [10, 16]. 
Although serogroup O:8 isolates have been shown to colo-
nize the intestinal tract of wild rodents, O:3 isolates do not 
colonize the intestinal tract of the large Japanese field mouse 
(Apodemus speciosus) [4, 11]. This suggested that the Djun-
garian hamsters from which Y. enterocolitica O:3/3 variant 
VP-was isolated in this study constitute transient carriers; 
further studies will be required to determine whether this 
pathogen can infect hamsters. 
Pet animals have long been suspected as a source of 
human yersiniosis, because of their close contact with hu-
mans, especially young children; however, pet to human </p>

<p>Table 1. Number of samples examined in this study </p>

<p>Animal 
No. of samples in pet stores </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D 
E 
F 
G 
H 
I 
J 
K 
L 
M Total </p>

<p>Pet rodents 
Chinchilla (Chinchilla lanigera) 
1 
1 
2 
2 
3 
2 
1 
2 
1 
15 
Chinese hamster (Cricetulus griseus) 
1 
1 
Degu (Octodon degus) 
1 
1 
1 
1 
3 
3 
4 
2 
1 
2 
19 
Djungarian hamster (Phodopus sungorus) 
10 a) 
4 
1 
1 
16 
Golden hamster (Mesocricetus auratus) 
1 
3 
1 
2 
1 
1 
2 
11 
Guinea pig (Cavia porcellus) 
1 
1 
1 
2 
2 
3 
3 
4 
1 
3 
2 
23 
Hamster (Subfamily Cricetinae) 
1 
1 
2 
4 
1 
9 
House mouse (Mus musculus) 
1 
1 
Japanese dwarf flying squirrel (Pteromys momonga) 
1 
1 
2 
Jerboa (Family Dipodidae) 
1 
1 
Lemming (Genus lemmus) 
3 
3 
Prairie dog (Genus cynomys) 
1 
1 
Richardson's ground squirrel (Urocitellus richardsonii) 
1 
1 
Roborovskii dwarf hamster (Phodopus roborovskii) 
1 
1 
Siberian chipmunk (Tamias sibiricus) 
1 
1 
2 
Squirrel (Family Sciuridae) 
1 
1 
2 
Pet rabbits 
Domestic rabbit (Oryctolagus cuniculus) 
1 
2 
4 
1 
6 
8 
3 
5 
1 
2 
4 
2 
39 
Other 
Sugar glider (Petaurus breviceps) 
1 
1 
1 
1 
4 </p>

<p>Total 
3 15 
2 15 
5 14 14 14 15 14 10 15 15 
151 </p>

<p>a) Of the ten Djungarian hamster samples, five were positive for Yersinia enterocolitica isolates. </p>

<p>YERSINIA ENTEROCOLITICA IN PET HAMSTERS </p>



<p>transmission has yet to be proven [3]. Fukushima et al. [8] 
have demonstrated the transmission of Y. pseudotuberculosis 
through environmental substances contaminated by feces 
from pathogen-infected cats. Since hamsters are popular 
pets worldwide, it is vital to alert pet owners and pet shops 
that pet hamsters could potentially carry pathogenic bacteria 
that might infect humans indirectly. This would enable the 
implementation of proper precautionary measures to prevent 
unwanted transmission. </p>



</text></tei>