<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5292639" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Aims The prognostic implications of QRS duration and morphology in heart failure patients treated with cardiac 
resynchronization therapy (CRT) remains debated. The present evaluation investigated the association between QRS duration 
(&lt;150 vs. ≥150 ms) and QRS morphology (left bundle brand block [LBBB] vs. non-LBBB) and long-term prognosis of a large 
cohort of unselected heart failure patients treated with CRT according to contemporary guidelines. </p>

<p>Methods and results Of 973 heart failure patients treated with CRT (mean age 66.1 AE 9.8 years, 76% male), 658 patients 
(68%) showed QRS duration ≥150 ms, and 772 patients (79%) had LBBB configuration. Compared with patients with QRS 
duration &lt;150 ms, patients with QRS duration ≥150 ms had less frequently ischaemic cardiomyopathy and atrial fibrillation 
and showed larger left ventricular volumes and lower left ventricular ejection fraction. Compared with patients with non-
LBBB configuration, patients with LBBB morphology were younger, less often males and less often had ischaemic cardiomyop-
athy and atrial fibrillation. On multivariable analysis, after correcting for relevant clinical and echocardiographic variables, LBBB 
morphology was significantly associated with better survival [hazard ratio (HR) 0.737; 95% confidence interval (CI) 0.584-
0.931; P = 0.010], whereas there was no statistically significant association between QRS duration ≥150 ms and survival (HR 
0.889; 95% CI 0.726-1.088; P = 0.252). </p>

<p>Conclusions In this large population of heart failure patients treated with CRT, QRS morphology was independently associ-
ated with long-term survival. The association between QRS duration and long-term survival was not statistically significant. </p>

<p>Cardiac resynchronization therapy (CRT) is an established ther-
apy for heart failure patients with reduced left ventricular 
ejection fraction (LVEF ≤35%) and prolonged QRS duration 
(≥120 ms) leading to important improvements in left ventricu-
lar (LV) function and prognosis. 
1-4 However, the individual 
prognostic benefit is not consistent, and selection of patients 
who will benefit from CRT remains challenging. Sub-analyses 
from randomized controlled trials and meta-analyses pointed 
out that QRS duration and morphology are relevant for prog-
nosis of patients treated with CRT. 
5-9 Patients with shorter </p>

<p>QRS duration and/or non-left bundle branch block (LBBB) 
morphology appear to benefit less than patients with longer 
QRS duration and/or LBBB morphology. 
5-9 However, the </p>

<p>patients included in randomized trials with non-LBBB configu-
ration represent a minority (5-30%), and approximately one 
third has a QRS duration between 120-150 ms. 
1-4 In addition, </p>

<p>the impact of QRS duration and morphology on CRT outcomes 
of selected patients included in randomized trials (frequently 
excluding patients with atrial fibrillation or associated comor-
bidities) may differ from unselected populations. A large 
registry has demonstrated that patients with QRS duration 
&gt;150 ms, and LBBB morphology had the most benefit from 
CRT, while the prognostic benefit of patients with shorter 
QRS duration or non-LBBB configuration remained controver-
sial. 
10 To provide further evidence in this important domain, </p>

<p>the current evaluation investigated the association between 
QRS duration (&lt;150 vs. ≥150 ms) and QRS morphology (LBBB 
vs. non-LBBB) and long-term prognosis of a large cohort of </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, 
provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. ESC Heart Failure published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the European Society of Cardiology. </p>

<p>ESC HEART FAILURE 
ESC Heart Failure 2017; 4: 23-30 
Published online 1 December 2016 in Wiley Online Library (wileyonlinelibrary.com) DOI: 10.1002/ehf2.12122 </p>

<p>unselected heart failure patients treated with CRT according to 
contemporary guidelines. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Patients and data collection </p>

<p>From an ongoing registry of heart failure recipients of a CRT 
with/without defibrillator function between 1999 and 2013, 
973 patients were included in this analysis. 
11 All patients </p>

<p>had drug-refractory heart failure symptoms, LVEF ≤35% and 
prolonged QRS duration (≥120 ms) according to recommen-
dations. 
12,13 Patients with right ventricular pacing who re-</p>

<p>ceived an upgrade of the device were excluded from this 
analysis. Twelve-lead electrocardiograms (ECGs), together 
with clinical and echocardiographic evaluation, were rou-
tinely performed before device implantation and after 6-
month follow-up. Patients were followed-up regularly at the 
heart failure outpatient clinic of the Leiden University Medi-
cal Center. All-cause mortality together with heart transplan-
tation and LV assist device (LVAD) implantation was the 
composite primary endpoint. Survival follow-up data were re-
trieved from municipality registries. Data of patients lost at 
follow-up were considered up to the last date of follow-up. 
The association between QRS duration and morphology and 
the primary endpoint was assessed. The Dutch Central Com-
mittee on Human-related Research (CCMO) allows the use of 
anonymous data without prior approval of an institutional 
review board provided that the data are acquired for routine 
patient care. All data used for this study were acquired for 
clinical purposes and handled anonymously. </p>

<p>QRS duration and morphology </p>

<p>Standard 12-lead ECGs were acquired with calibration at 
0.1 mV/mm at a paper speed of 25 mm/s. QRS duration 
was automatically detected and visually controlled. QRS mor-
phology was defined according to current definitions. 
14 QRS 
duration and morphology were both categorized into &lt;150 
vs. ≥150 ms and LBBB vs. non-LBBB, respectively. </p>

<p>Clinical and echocardiographic evaluation </p>

<p>Clinical evaluation included assessment of the New York 
Heart Association (NYHA) functional class, 6 min walk test </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>and quality of life according to the Minnesota Living with 
Heart Failure questionnaire. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Transthoracic echocardiography was performed with the 
patients in left lateral decubitus position. Commercially 
available equipment (Vingmed Vivid 7 or 9, General Electric 
Vingmed, Milwaukee, USA) was used for data acquisition. 
Standard parasternal and apical views were acquired to </p>

<p>assess LV dimensions and function. In addition, colour, 
continuous, and pulsed wave Doppler data were obtained 
to evaluate LV diastolic function, valvular heart disease, 
and to estimate pulmonary pressures. LV end-diastolic and 
end-systolic volumes were measured from the apical two 
and four-chamber views, and LVEF was calculated using 
the Simpson's method. 
17 Mitral regurgitation severity was 
graded semi-quantitatively using an integrative approach 
including vena contracta width and measurement of 
regurgitant volume and effective regurgitant orifice area 
with the proximal isovelocity surface method when 
possible. </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>Definition of response to cardiac resynchronization 
therapy </p>

<p>Response to CRT was defined as a reduction of ≥15% in LV 
end-systolic volume at 6 month follow-up. Patients who died 
or underwent heart transplantation or LV reconstructive sur-
gery within 6 months after CRT implantation were considered 
non-responders. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Device implantation </p>

<p>Through a subclavian or cephalic vein access, the right atrial 
and ventricular leads were positioned traditionally. The coro-
nary sinus was cannulized with the use of a guiding catheter, 
and a venogram was obtained. Afterwards, the LV lead was 
inserted in the coronary sinus and positioned in the lateral 
or posterolateral vein when possible. All leads were con-
nected to a dual chamber biventricular CRT device. Evalua-
tion of the device function was commonly combined with 
the regular controls at the heart failure outpatient clinic. 
The atrioventricular (AV) and inter-ventricular delays were 
set empirically at 120-140 and 0 ms, respectively, and CRT 
optimization was performed at follow-up at the discretion 
of the treating physician. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Continuous data are presented as mean AE standard deviation 
(if normally distributed) and dichotomous data are presented 
as frequencies and percentages. Comparisons of continuous 
and dichotomous data between patient groups were per-
formed using the Student's t-test and χ 
2 test, respectively. 
Two-sided P-values &lt;0.05 were considered significant. Cox 
proportional hazards model was used to identify the variables 
associated with the primary endpoint. Variables with a signif-
icant P-value on univariable analysis were entered in the mul-
tivariable model using the enter method. In addition, AV 
node ablation performed in patients with atrial fibrillation </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>M.J.H. Khidir et al. </p>

<p>ESC Heart Failure 2017; 4: 23-30 
DOI: 10.1002/ehf2.12122 </p>

<p>and low biventricular pacing rate was included as time-
dependent co-variate. The hazard ratios (HR) and 95% confi-
dence intervals (CI) are reported. All analyses were performed 
with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> for Windows, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 23.0</rs> (SPSS, Chicago, IL). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics </p>

<p>Table 1 summarizes the baseline characteristics. The mean 
age was 66.1 AE 9.8 years, the majority of the population 
was male (76%), and ischaemic cardiomyopathy was the un-
derlying cause of heart failure in 59% of the patients. NYHA 
functional class III or IV was reported by 697 patients (74%), 
and mean LVEF was 26 AE 8%. The majority of patients 
(n = 924; 95%) received a CRT device with defibrillator 
capabilities. </p>

<p>QRS duration and morphology </p>

<p>A total of 315 patients (32%) showed a QRS duration 
&lt;150 ms while the remaining 658 patients (68%) showed a </p>

<p>QRS duration ≥150 ms group. Patients in the latter group 
were less often affected by ischaemic cardiomyopathy and 
had less frequently atrial fibrillation as baseline rhythm com-
pared with patients with a QRS duration &lt;150 ms (Table 1). 
Furthermore, patients with a QRS duration ≥150 ms had 
larger LV volumes and lower LVEF than their counterparts. 
The distribution of CRT with defibrillator capabilities was sim-
ilar between the groups QRS duration &lt;150 vs. ≥150 ms (96 
vs. 94%, P = 0.292). 
Based on QRS morphology, 772 patients (79%) were cate-
gorized in the LBBB group and 201 (21%) patients in the 
non-LBBB group. The latter group comprised 114 patients 
with right bundle branch block and 87 with inter-ventricular 
conduction delay. Compared with patients in the non-LBBB 
group, patients with LBBB were younger, less often males, 
and less often had ischaemic cardiomyopathy. Additionally, 
atrial fibrillation was less frequent in patients with LBBB, 
the functional capacity was higher (as demonstrated by sig-
nificantly longer walked distances during the 6 min walk 
test), and the renal function was better compared with pa-
tients with non-LBBB. Finally, the mean QRS duration in pa-
tients with LBBB was significantly longer than the QRS 
duration in patients with non-LBBB. There were no differ-
ences in the distribution of CRT with defibrillator </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline characteristics </p>

<p>Overall population 
QRS duration 
QRS morphology </p>

<p>(n = 973) </p>

<p>&lt;150 ms 
(n = 315) </p>

<p>≥150 ms 
(n = 658) 
P-value </p>

<p>Non-LBBB 
(n = 201) </p>

<p>LBBB 
(n = 772) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age (year) 
66.1 AE 9.8 
65.2 AE 10.2 
66.5 AE 9.6 
0.054 
67.4 AE 9.7 
65.8 AE 9.8 
0.037 
Gender (male) 
738 (76%) 
251 (80%) 
487 (74%) 
0.064 
166 (83%) 
572 (74%) 
0.016 
Aetiology (ischaemic) 
570 (59%) 
207 (66%) 
363 (55%) 
0.002 
150 (75%) 
420 (54%) 
&lt;0.001 
NYHA III-IV 
697 (74%) 
223 (73%) 
474 (74%) 
0.816 
146 (76%) 
551 (73%) 
0.427 
Atrial fibrillation 
158 (16%) 
65 (21%) 
93 (14%) 
0.013 
50 (25%) 
108 (14%) 
&lt;0.001 
6MWT (m) 
319 AE 122 
317 AE 120 
320 AE 123 
0.724 
291 AE 120 
327 AE 122 
0.001 
QoL 
33 AE 19 
35 AE 20 
33 AE 18 
0.206 
36 AE 21 
33 AE 18 
0.097 
Body mass index 
26.4 AE 4.3 
26.6 AE 4.3 
26.3 AE 4.3 
0.491 
26.2 AE 3.7 
26.5 AE 4.4 
0.357 
Diabetes mellitus 
213 (22%) 
78 (25%) 
135 (21%) 
0.157 
53 (26%) 
160 (21%) 
0.104 
eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
6 5 AE 24 
66 AE 25 
64 AE 23 
0.217 
61 AE 23 
66 AE 24 
0.024 
Echocardiography 
LVEDV (mL) 
218 AE 79 
198 AE 70 
227 AE 81 
&lt;0.001 
208 AE 73 
220 AE 80 
0.058 
LVESV (mL) 
164 AE 70 
147 AE 59 
172 AE 73 
&lt;0.001 
154 AE 62 
167 AE 71 
0.018 
LVEF (%) 
26 AE 8 
2 7 AE 8 
2 5AE 8 
0.008 
27 AE 8 
2 6AE 8 
0.059 
Mitral regurgitation 
grade 3-4+ </p>

<p>156 (16%) 
43 (15%) 
113 (18%) 
0.213 
32 (17%) 
124 (17%) 
1.000 </p>

<p>Electrocardiogram 
QRS duration (ms) 
161 AE 23 
136 AE 8 
173 AE 16 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>158 AE 21 
162 AE 23 
0.019 
QRS morphology (LBBB) 
772 (79%) 
241 (77%) 
531 (81%) 
0.154 
0 (0%) 
772 (100%) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Medication 
Diuretic 
805 (83%) 
261 (83%) 
544 (83%) 
1.000 
175 (87%) 
630 (82%) 
0.086 
Spironolactone 
442 (45%) 
160 (51%) 
282 (43%) 
0.024 
94 (47%) 
348 (45%) 
0.727 
ACE-inhibitor 
857 (88%) 
272 (86%) 
585 (89%) 
0.296 
172 (86%) 
685 (89%) 
0.268 
β-blocker 
706 (73%) 
242 (77%) 
464 (71%) 
0.047 
132 (66%) 
574 (74%) 
0.018 
Anticoagulation/ 
Antiplatelet drugs </p>

<p>798 (82%) 
267 (85%) 
531 (81%) 
0.146 
175 (87%) 
623 (81%) 
0.047 </p>

<p>Statin 
570 (59%) 
196 (62%) 
374 (57%) 
0.127 
137 (68%) 
433 (56%) 
0.003 </p>

<p>6MWT, 6 min walk test; ACE, angiotensin converting enzyme; eGFR, estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate; LBBB, left bundle branch block; 
LVEDV, LV end-diastolic volume; LVESV, LV end-systolic volume; LVEF, LV ejection fraction; NYHA, New York Heart Association; QoL, qual-
ity of life according to the Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Significant difference expected by definition of dichotomization. </p>

<p>QRS duration vs. morphology and survival </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>ESC Heart Failure 2017; 4: 23-30 </p>

<p>
capabilities in the non-LBBB vs. LBBB group (94 vs. 95%, 
P = 0.389). </p>

<p>Response to cardiac resynchronization therapy </p>

<p>Echocardiographic response to CRT after 6 months was ob-
served in 498 patients (54%). LV reverse remodelling could 
not be evaluated in 54 patients because of missing follow-
up echocardiographic evaluation. The response rate differed 
significantly between patient groups based on QRS duration 
and morphology. LV reverse remodelling was less frequently 
observed among patients with a QRS duration &lt;150 ms 
compared with patients with a QRS duration ≥150 ms (44 
vs. 59%; P &lt; 0.001). Among patients with LBBB morphology, 
LV reverse remodelling was more frequently observed 
than in patients with non-LBBB morphology (56 vs. 46%; 
P = 0.011). </p>

<p>Long-term outcome </p>

<p>During a median follow-up of 59 (interquartile range 29-85) 
months, 423 patients reached the composite endpoint: 413 
patients died, 5 patients received heart transplantation, and 
5 patients underwent LVAD implantation. The survival curves 
for time to composite endpoint based on QRS duration and 
morphology accompanied by the corresponding log-rank test 
P-value are displayed in Figure 1. There were no differences 
in long-term survival when patients were dichotomized based 
on QRS duration. Despite the higher reverse remodelling rate 
in patients with a QRS duration ≥150 ms, the interaction be-
tween LV reverse remodelling and QRS duration did not 
reach statistical significance (HR 0.711; 95% CI 0.456-1.110; 
P = 0.133). However, when patients were dichotomized based 
on QRS morphology, patients with LBBB had better survival 
compared with patients with non-LBBB morphology. Patients 
with LBBB morphology and QRS duration ≥150 ms (reference 
group) and patients with LBBB morphology and QRS duration </p>

<p>&lt;150 ms had comparable survival rates (HR 1.128; 95% CI 
0.892-1.428; P = 0.315), whereas patients with non-LBBB con-
figuration and QRS duration &lt;150 ms (HR 1.590; 95% CI 
1.130-2.238; P = 0.008) and patients with non-LBBB morphol-
ogy and QRS duration ≥150 ms (HR 1.522; 95% CI 1.156-2.003; 
P = 0.003) had significantly worse survival compared to the ref-
erence group (Figure 2). Univariable and multivariable HR 
and 95% CI are displayed in Table 2. LBBB morphology was 
significantly associated with better survival (HR 0.737; 95% 
CI 0.584-0.931; P = 0.010), after correcting for age, gender, 
heart failure aetiology, NYHA III-IV, atrial fibrillation, AV 
node ablation, body mass index, diabetes mellitus, renal 
function, LV end-diastolic volume, LVEF, and mitral regurgita-
tion. In contrast, there was no significant association 
between QRS duration ≥150 ms and survival (HR 0.889; 
95% CI 0.726-1.088; P = 0.252). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present evaluation including a large cohort of unse-
lected heart failure patients treated with CRT according 
to current recommendations shows that QRS morphology 
but not duration is independently associated with long-
term survival. </p>

<p>Cardiac resynchronization therapy benefits in left 
bundle brand block versus non-left bundle brand 
block QRS morphology </p>

<p>Although a QRS duration ≥120 ms was an inclusion criterion for 
many randomized controlled trials on CRT, the distribution of 
different QRS morphologies was not balanced, and more than 
70% of the included patients had LBBB morphology. 
1-4,21 QRS 
morphology (LBBB vs. non-LBBB) has been consistently 
associated with better outcomes in patients treated with 
CRT. For example, in the Cardiac Resynchronization-Heart </p>

<p>Figure 1 Kaplan-Meier survival curve for patients dichotomized twice according to QRS duration (A) and morphology (B) including univariate hazard 
ratios (HR) for QRS ≥150 ms and left bundle brand block (LBBB) morphology, respectively. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>M.J.H. Khidir et al. </p>

<p>ESC Heart Failure 2017; 4: 23-30 </p>

<p>
Failure (CARE-HF) trial, which randomized 813 patients to CRT 
+ optimal medical therapy or optimal medical therapy alone, 
94% of patients had LBBB morphology while only 5% of pa-
tients had right bundle branch block QRS configuration. 
6 The 
presence of right bundle branch block morphology was inde-
pendently associated with the composite primary outcome 
of all-cause mortality and unplanned hospitalization for man-
agement of major cardiovascular events (HR 2.043, 95% CI 
1.332-3.157; P = 0.001). 
6 In addition, the sub-study of the </p>

<p>Multicenter Automatic Defibrillator Implantation Trial-Cardiac 
Resynchronization Therapy (MADIT-CRT) trial, including 1817 
patients with sinus rhythm at baseline ECG, showed that the 
presence of LBBB morphology was associated with a 53% re-
duction in the risk of heart failure events or all-cause mortality </p>

<p>of patients randomized to CRT with defibrillator compared 
with patients treated with implantable cardioverter defibrilla-
tor (ICD) alone whereas patients with non-LBBB QRS morphol-
ogy did not show clinical benefit from CRT. 
7 Subsequent 
meta-analysis pooling data from 5356 patients enrolled in 
four randomized trials showed that LBBB morphology was 
associated with significant reduction in the composite ad-
verse clinical events of patients treated with CRT (risk ratio 
0.64, 95% CI 0.52-0.77; P &lt; 0.0001) whereas patients with 
non-LBBB configuration failed to show clinical benefit. 
9 Re-
cently, the analysis of data from 31 892 heart failure patients 
treated with CRT (76% with LBBB QRS morphology) included 
in the National Cardiovascular Data Registry and the ICD 
registry showed that after a median follow-up of 3 years, </p>

<p>Figure 2 Kaplan-Meier survival curves for patients subdivided into four groups based on QRS morphology and duration. LBBB, left bundle brand block; 
HR, hazard ratios. </p>

<p>Table 2 Cox proportional hazards model </p>

<p>Univariable 
Multivariable 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age (year) 
1.036 (1.025-1.047) 
&lt;0.001 
1.020 (1.007-1.032) 
0.002 
Gender (male) 
1.593 (1.247-2.035) 
&lt;0.001 
1.310 (0.992-1.729) 
0.057 
Aetiology (ischaemic) 
1.867 (1.524-2.309) 
&lt;0.001 
1.461 (1.161-1.840) 
0.001 
NYHA III-IV 
1.976 (1.516-2.576) 
&lt;0.001 
1.501 (1.127-1.999) 
0.005 
6MWT (m) 
0.996 (0.995-0.997) 
&lt;0.001 
QoL 
1.016 (1.011-1.022) 
&lt;0.001 
Atrial fibrillation 
1.591 (1.243-2.036) 
&lt;0.001 
1.354 (1.014-1.808) 
0.040 
AV node ablation </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.045 (1.221-3.426 
0.007 
1.423 (0.773-2.619) 
0.257 
Body mass index (units) 
0.972 (0.949-0.995) 
0.017 
0.964 (0.938-0.991) 
0.009 
Diabetes mellitus 
1.643 (1.323-2.039) 
&lt;0.001 
1.576 (1.238-2.006) 
&lt;0.001 
eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.974 (0.970-0.979) 
&lt;0.001 
0.981 (0.976-0.987) 
&lt;0.001 
Echocardiography 
LVEDV (mL) 
1.002 (1.001-1.003) 
&lt;0.001 
1.002 (1.000-1.003) 
0.035 
LVESV (mL) 
1.003 (1.002-1.004) 
&lt;0.001 
LVEF (%) 
0.970 (0.958-0.983) 
&lt;0.001 
0.990 (0.976-1.005) 
0.195 
Mitral regurgitation grade 3-4+ 
1.789 (1.421-2.254) 
&lt;0.001 
1.324 (1.032-1.699) 
0.027 
ECG 
QRS duration (≥150 ms) 
0.889 (0.726-1.088) 
0.252 
QRS morphology (LBBB) 
0.672 (0.539-0.837) 
&lt;0.001 
0.737 (0.584-0.931) 
0.010 </p>

<p>CI, confidence interval; HR, hazard ratio; other abbreviations as in Table 1. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Time-dependent co-variate. </p>

<p>QRS duration vs. morphology and survival </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>ESC Heart Failure 2017; 4: 23-30 </p>

<p>
patients with LBBB morphology had 24% lower mortality risk 
than patients with non-LBBB morphology (HR 0.76, 95% CI 
0.72-0.80; P &lt; 0.001). 
22 Similarly, the present study, includ-
ing unselected heart failure patients treated with CRT dem-
onstrated that LBBB morphology was independently 
associated with superior survival. Therefore, LBBB morphol-
ogy is an important criterion to select patients who will likely 
benefit from CRT. </p>

<p>Cardiac resynchronization therapy benefits in QRS 
duration &lt;150 versus ≥150 ms </p>

<p>However, QRS duration has also been shown to be an impor-
tant determinant of the clinical benefits of CRT. In the COM-
PANION trial, a QRS duration &gt;148 ms was associated with 
significant reductions in all-cause mortality in patients treated 
with CRT. 
1 In addition, the results of the randomized trials on </p>

<p>CRT including patients with NYHA functional class II heart fail-
ure symptoms consistently showed that QRS duration ≥150 ms 
is associated with significantly reduced risk of all-cause mor-
tality and heart failure hospitalization and larger LV reverse 
remodelling compared with patients with QRS duration 
&lt;150 ms. 
3,4,21 In the MADIT-CRT trial, a QRS duration 
≥150 ms [present in 1175 (64%) patients] was associated 
with lower risk of all-cause mortality or non-fatal heart fail-
ure (HR 0.48, 95% CI 0.37-0.64) compared with QRS dura-
tion &lt;150 ms (HR 1.06, 95% CI 0.74-1.52; P = 0.001 for 
interaction). 
3 A recent meta-analysis, pooling data from 
5813 patients included in five randomized trials, showed 
that QRS duration ≥150 ms was associated with clinical ben-
efit from CRT (risk ratio 0.60, 95% CI 0.53-0.67; P &lt; 0.001) 
whereas patients with QRS duration between 120 and 
143 ms did not benefit from CRT (risk ratio 0.95, 95% CI 
0.82-1.10; P = 0.49). 
8 In contrast, the substudy of the 
CARE-HF trial demonstrated that QRS duration was not asso-
ciated with the composite primary outcome of all-cause 
mortality and unplanned hospitalization for management of 
major cardiovascular event. 
6 Of note, only 11% of patients </p>

<p>had a QRS duration &lt;150 ms, which may explain the lack 
of statistically significant association between QRS duration 
and outcome. Although the present study included a larger 
percentage of patients with a QRS duration &lt;150 ms 
(32%), the results are in agreement with those observed in 
the CARE-HF substudy 
6 and QRS duration was not associated </p>

<p>with long-term survival. </p>

<p>Integration of QRS morphology and duration 
versus outcome after cardiac resynchronization 
therapy </p>

<p>The aforementioned separate analyses showing that QRS du-
ration and morphology are important determinants of clinical </p>

<p>benefits of CRT have led to the investigation of the interac-
tion between QRS duration and morphology and its effects 
on CRT outcomes. 
5,10,23,24 The sub-analysis of the RAFT trial 
(after excluding patients with ventricular pacing and perma-
nent atrial fibrillation) showed that regardless the QRS dura-
tion, patients with LBBB morphology who were randomized to 
CRT with defibrillator function showed a reduction in the rates 
of the primary outcome (composite endpoint of all-cause 
mortality and heart failure hospitalization) (HR 0.640; 95% CI 
0.524-0.781; P &lt; 0.001). 
5 In addition, there was a continuous 
relationship between QRS duration and greater benefit from 
CRT is these patients. In contrast, patients with non-LBBB 
morphology allocated to the CRT arm showed a clinical bene-
fit only when the QRS duration was 160 ms or longer (HR 0.52, 
95% CI 0.29-0.96; P = 0.033). 
5 In addition, an individual pa-
tient meta-analysis on data from 3872 patients randomized 
in five clinical trials showed that patients with LBBB morphol-
ogy exhibited larger benefit from CRT than patients with non-
LBBB morphology, although the difference was not statisti-
cally significant. 
23 Importantly, QRS duration was significantly 
associated with reductions in all-cause mortality and the rates 
of the composite endpoint, particularly when QRS duration 
exceeded 140 ms. 
23 Based on this evidence, current guide-
lines have modified the recommendations and consider 
CRT a class I indication for heart failure patients with LBBB 
morphology (regardless the QRS duration) and class IIa for 
patients with non-LBBB and QRS duration ≥150 ms and IIb 
for non-LBBB and QRS duration between 120-150 ms. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>However, it is important to note that these observations of 
substudies and meta-analyses of randomized clinical trials 
include selected patients and may not represent the 'real-
world' patients being treated with CRT. 
Data from the National Cardiovascular Data Registry, which 
included 24 169 patients aged 65 years or more who 
underwent CRT implantation, showed that the adjusted risk 
of 3 year mortality was lowest for the patients with LBBB 
and ≥150 ms QRS duration (20.9%) and highest for the pa-
tients with non-LBBB and &lt;150 ms QRS (32.3%). 
10 There 
were no statistically significant differences in the adjusted risk 
of all-cause mortality between the groups of patients with 
LBBB configuration and QRS duration &lt;150 ms (26.5%) and 
the patients with non-LBBB configuration and QRS duration 
≥150 ms (30.7%). Therefore, it seems that patients with LBBB 
morphology and patients with wider QRS complex are more 
likely to benefit from CRT. These results are extended to a 
younger population in the present study, which demonstrates 
that QRS morphology but not duration is independently asso-
ciated with long-term survival. Probably, the smaller patient 
groups have precluded us from observing significant differ-
ences between subgroups based on QRS morphology and du-
ration. However, since these registries did not include a 
control group of patients who did not undergo CRT implanta-
tion, the efficacy of CRT could not be compared, and there-
fore, conclusions regarding the survival benefits of CRT in </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>M.J.H. Khidir et al. </p>

<p>ESC Heart Failure 2017; 4: 23-30 
DOI: 10.1002/ehf2.12122 </p>

<p>patients with non-LBBB morphology and QRS duration be-
tween 120 and 149 ms remain unclear. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>Some limitations should be acknowledged. The present anal-
ysis was retrospective and single centre introducing a bias. 
However, the present study extends the results to a younger 
unselected population compared with previous series. 
10 In 
addition, comparisons between patients undergoing CRT im-
plantation vs. patients who were medically treated or re-
ceived a conventional dual-chamber ICD were not possible. 
Furthermore, beyond QRS duration and morphology, previ-
ous study has demonstrated the relevance of other ECG pa-
rameters (PR interval, QRS axis, amplitude, and durations of 
each component of the QRS complex, QRS notching, QRS hi-
eroglyphs that suggest myocardial scar) in predicting CRT re-
sponse. 
25,26 These parameters were not considered in the 
present study. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In this large population of unselected heart failure patients 
treated with CRT according to contemporary guidelines, 
QRS morphology but not duration was independently associ-
ated with long-term survival. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>None. </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>V. Delgado received speaking fees from Abbott Vascular. The 
Department of Cardiology received unrestricted research 
grants from Biotronik, Boston Scientific, Edwards Lifesciences 
and Medtronic. </p>





<p>ESC Heart Failure 2017; 4: 23-30 </p>





<p>
M.J.H. Khidir et al. </p>

<p>ESC Heart Failure 2017; 4: 23-30 
DOI: 10.1002/ehf2.12122 </p>

</text></tei>