<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5009042" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>purpose: Total knee arthroplasty (TKA) accompanies the risk of bleeding and need for transfusion. There are several methods to reduce post-
operative blood loss and blood transfusion. One such method is using tranexamic acid during TKA. The purpose of this study was to confirm 
whether tranexamic acid reduces postoperative blood loss and blood transfusion after TKA. 
Materials and Methods: A total of 100 TKA patients were included in the study. The tranexamic acid group consisted of 50 patients who received an 
intravenous injection of tranexamic acid. The control included 50 patients who received a placebo injection. The amounts of drainage, postoperative 
hemoglobin, and transfusion were compared between the groups. 
results: The mean amount of drainage was lower in the tranexamic acid group (580.6±355.0 mL) than the control group (886.0±375.5 mL). There 
was a reduction in the transfusion rate in the tranexamic acid group (48%) compared with the control group (64%). The hemoglobin level was higher 
in the tranexamic acid group than in the control group at 24 hours postoperatively. The mean units of transfusion were smaller in the tranexamic acid 
group (0.76 units) than in the control group (1.28 units). 
conclusions: Our data suggest that intravenous injection of tranexamic acid decreases the total blood loss and transfusion after TKA. </p>

<p>Knee Surg Relat Res, Vol. 28, No. 3, Sep. 2016 189 </p>

<p>acid for patients undergoing TKA reduced the requirement of 
blood transfusion </p>

<p>19) </p>

<p>. In these studies, however, the blood loss was 
measured as the loss during surgery plus the drainage volume. 
Since there may also have been hidden losses as a result of hemo-
lysis and tissue extravasation, which would not have shown on 
drain output, the true effect of tranexamic acid on blood loss was 
not clear </p>

<p>20) </p>

<p>. A true estimate of total blood loss can be more appro-
priately made using a hemoglobin balance method </p>

<p>20,21) </p>

<p>. The cal-
culated blood loss based on hemoglobin drop and body volume 
takes into consideration both the hidden and evident losses. The 
purpose of this study was to assess the effect of tranexamic acid 
on total blood losses including hidden and evident losses through 
hemoglobin balance method </p>

<p>21) </p>

<p>. We hypothesized that tranexamic 
acid would decrease the total blood loss during TKA measured 
using a hemoglobin balance method </p>

<p>21) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>1. inclusion and exclusion criteria 
The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of 
the Chonnam National University Bitgoeul Hospital. This pro-
spective comparative study was conducted in a single institution 
based in two hospitals. All patients with primary end-stage knee 
osteoarthritis (Kellgren-Lawrence grades, 3-4) awaiting surgery 
were eligible for the study. We excluded patients with second-
ary osteoarthritis (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, posttraumatic 
osteoarthritis, gouty arthritis), a cardiovascular problem (e.g., 
myocardial infarction, atrial fibrillation, angina, heart failure), si-
multaneous bilateral TKA, a history of thromboembolic disease, 
bleeding disorder, known allergy to tranexamic acid, and lifelong 
warfarin therapy for thromboembolism prophylaxis. A total of 
100 patients were evaluated during the study period. Patients 
undergoing TKA were prospectively divided into one of the two 
study groups using sealed, opaque envelopes that were opened 
immediately before surgery. </p>

<p>2. Methods of tranexamic acid and outcome assessment 
In the tranexamic acid group, patients received tranexamic acid 
intravenously (10 mg/kg) 10 minutes before tourniquet deflation 
and again at 3 hours postoperatively </p>

<p>22,23) </p>

<p>. This regime was based 
on successful outcomes in literature and our own experience. In 
the control group, patients received a placebo 5 mL 0.9% normal 
saline at the similar timings of the tranexamic acid group. Pre-
operative data included age at the time of the operation, gender, 
and preoperative hemoglobin level. There were no differences 
between groups regarding the preoperative data (Table 1). Hemo-</p>

<p>globin levels were measured 2 weeks preoperatively and 6 hours, 
24 hours, 48 hours, and 5 days postoperatively. Total losses were 
calculated based on a 'hemoglobin balance method' described in 
literature </p>

<p>21) </p>

<p>. This method estimates the blood volume of a patient 
based on the postoperative hemoglobin drop. The lowest value of 
the postoperative hemoglobin level obtained until the 5th post-
operative day was used to calculate the hemoglobin drop. Trans-
fusions were performed in compliance with our hospital policy. 
Blood transfusions were planned for asymptomatic patients with 
a hemoglobin level of &lt;8.0 gm%. Transfusions were undertaken 
for patients with a level of &lt;10.0 gm% only if they had 1) symp-
toms that were not well tolerated, were related to anemia, and 
could not be attributed to another cause (myocardial ischemia or 
hypoxemia) or 2) ongoing blood loss </p>

<p>24) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>3. Surgical technique 
All operations were performed or supervised by two surgeons 
(EKS and JKS) using a midline skin incision and medial parapa-
tellar arthrotomy. A posterior-stabilized type implant was used 
and the patella was not resurfaced in all cases. All patients re-
ceived general or spinal anesthesia depending on the discretion 
of the anesthesiologist. A dose of 1 g cetrazole was given intra-
venously shortly before the operation. A tourniquet was applied 
around the upper thigh after elevation of the limb and exsangui-
nation with an Esmarch bandage and inflated to a pressure of 
280 mmHg before skin incision. An intramedullary alignment 
rod was used for femoral cutting and an extramedullary guide 
system was used for tibial cutting. Meticulous electric cauteriza-
tion of the soft tissue bleeding points was performed throughout 
the surgery. The tourniquet was not released until skin closure 
and application of a compressive dressing. Intraoperative blood 
loss was negligible in all patients because the tourniquet was not 
deflated until wound closure. In each knee, one intra-articular 
drain was applied and connected to a high-vacuum drain bottle. 
The patients were asked to utilize an intermittent sequential </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic Details of Patients in Both Groups </p>

<p>Variable 
Control group 
(n=50) </p>

<p>Tranexamic 
acid group 
(n=50) </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>Age (yr), mean (range) 
68.3 (52-83) 70.2 (55-86) 0.054 </p>

<p>Sex (M:F) 
2:48 
7:43 
0.089 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin (gm%), mean±SD 12.5±1.4 
12.3±1.6 
0.441 </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
24.8 
24.4 
0.861 </p>

<p>SD: standard deviation. </p>



<p>pneumatic compression device for deep vein thrombosis (DVT) 
prophylaxis as soon as possible. The compressive dressing and 
Foley catheter were removed on the first day after surgery. The 
drains were emptied every day and the amount of drained blood 
was measured. The drains were removed only when this amount 
was less than 100 mL for 24 hours. On average, drains were kept 
for 3 days (range, 2 to 5 days). This has been our institution's 
policy, as we have observed that removal of drains at one prese-
lected time may not work in all cases. Some cases have collection 
for longer periods and early removal in such cases may not only 
cause erroneous lower recordings of drained blood but also has 
a risk of hematoma formation. Both groups followed a standard 
postoperative rehabilitation protocol, including continuous pas-
sive motion of the knee and muscle strengthening exercises on 
the first day after surgery. All patients were asked to get out of 
bed with walker support on the afternoon of the first postop-
erative day to decrease the incidence of DVT, as described by 
Pearse et al. </p>

<p>25) </p>

<p>. Mechanical DVT prophylaxis using a pneumatic 
compression device was performed in all patients. Considering 
the low incidence of DVT in Asian populations </p>

<p>26) </p>

<p>, routine use of 
pharmacological prophylaxis was not prescribed according to our 
institutional policy. Routine screening for DVT was not done for 
asymptomatic patients. Symptomatic patients with excessive calf 
swelling and pain were screened for DVT using Doppler ultraso-
nography and computed tomography angiography. All patients at 
discharge were explained about warning symptoms of infection 
and DVT and were asked to report immediately to the emergen-
cy department in case of development of such symptoms. </p>

<p>4. data evaluation 
The total volume of drained blood and the decrease in hemo-
globin at 6 hours, 24 hours, 48 hours and 5 days postoperatively 
were recorded. Blood transfusions were recorded as the number 
of units of packed erythrocytes. All patients were discharged 
from the hospital after two weeks of surgery. All quantitative data 
were expressed as mean±standard deviation. Statistical signifi-
cance of differences in the mean values of continuous variables 
such as age, preoperative hemoglobin, total volume of drained 
blood, and postoperative decrease in hemoglobin level were 
determined using Student t-test. Chi-square test was used for cat-
egorical data including the need for blood transfusion. <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> ver. 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">14.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) was used for statistical analy-
ses. A p-value less than 0.05 was considered to indicate statistical 
significance. All aspects of the statistical analysis were reviewed 
by a statistician. </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>The mean postoperative total volume of drained blood was 
lower in the tranexamic acid group (580.6±355.0 mL) than in the 
control group (886.0±375.5 mL) (p=0.002). There was a reduc-
tion in the transfusion rate in the tranexamic acid group com-
pared with the control group (40% vs. 64%; p=0.016). The mean 
units of transfusion were smaller (p=0.007) in the tranexamic 
acid group than in the control group (0.76 units vs. 1.28 units). 
The hemoglobin level at 6 hours postoperatively was similar 
(p=0.801) in the two groups, but it was greater in the tranexamic 
acid group than in the control group at 24 hours, 48 hours, and 
5 days postoperatively at statistically significant levels (Table 2). 
The hemoglobin drop was calculated as the difference between 
the lowest postoperative hemoglobin level and the preoperative 
hemoglobin level. This drop was significantly high for the control 
group (2.8 gm/L) compared to the tranexamic acid group (1.7 
gm/dL) (p=0.000). The total amount of blood loss calculated us-
ing the hemoglobin balance method 
21) was significantly less in the </p>

<p>tranexamic acid group than in the control group (p=0.002) (Table 
2). There were no cases of symptomatic DVT or pulmonary em-
bolism (PE) in both groups during the 3 months of follow-up. 
Table 3 shows the amount of evident blood loss on each postop-
erative day measured based on the drain output and the number </p>

<p>Table 2. Postoperative Hemoglobin, Total Drain Output, and Blood 
Transfusion </p>

<p>Variable 
Control group 
(n=50) </p>

<p>Tranexamic 
acid group 
(n=50) </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Total volume of drained 
blood (mL) </p>

<p>886±375.5 580.6±355.0 0.002 </p>

<p>No. of patients receiving 
transfusion (%) </p>

<p>32 (64) 
20 (40) 
0.016 </p>

<p>Mean units of transfusion 
(unit) </p>

<p>1.28 
0.76 
0.007 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin (g/dL) 
postoperative </p>

<p>6 hr 
11.0±2.1 
11.1±2.3 
0.801 </p>

<p>24 hr 
10.2±1.7 
10.9±1.3 
0.042 </p>

<p>48 hr 
9.5±1.4 
10.5±1.6 
0.002 </p>

<p>5 day 
10.1±2.1 
10.8±2.2 
0.048 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin drop 
2.8±0.8 
1.7±0.5 
0.000 </p>

<p>Total loss (mL) 
1,404 
913 
0.002 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>p-values are for unpaired two-tailed Student t-test, except for blood 
transfusion which is for chi-square test. </p>

<p>Knee Surg Relat Res, Vol. 28, No. 3, Sep. 2016 191 </p>

<p>of patients still utilizing the drain. Postoperative day 1 losses were 
significantly different between the groups, but no difference was 
found on subsequent days. </p>

<p>discussion </p>

<p>The most important finding of the current study is that intra-
venous tranexamic acid decreased the perioperative blood loss, 
calculated total blood loss, hemoglobin drop, and need for trans-
fusion. Furthermore, this method did not cause an increase in 
the incidence of thromboembolic events. 
Surgical trauma after arthroplasty results in a hyperfibrinolytic 
state </p>

<p>27) </p>

<p>. Since early postoperative bleeding is the result of a shift 
in the hemostatic mechanism towards fibrinolysis, the anti-fibri-
nolytic drugs such as tranexamic acid are very effective to control 
bleeding. We agree with most reports in literature describing the 
reduction in blood loss as ranging 30%-50% </p>

<p>13-15) </p>

<p>. Most of these 
reports have evaluated blood losses in drains at 24-48 hours after 
surgery. Similar to these results, we also observed a reduction of 
40% in blood loss on postoperative day 1 (367 mL vs. 611 mL). 
The difference in drain output between two groups was ob-
served particularly on 1st postoperative day. This was primarily 
because tranexamic acid has a half-life of 3 hours and it remains 
in the extravascular tissue up to 17 hours </p>

<p>28) </p>

<p>, after which it has 
no effect on postoperative bleeding. Therefore, postoperative 
bleeding after 1st postoperative day showed no significant differ-
ence between two groups. Despite this, the overall blood loss in 
the tranexamic acid group was 35% less than that in the control 
group. This was because most bleeding after arthroplasty tends to 
occur during the first 24 hours </p>

<p>1-5) </p>

<p>. 
We found that tranexamic acid was effective in decreasing not 
only the evident blood loss but also the total blood loss based on 
the calculation using the hemoglobin balance method. It is diffi-
cult to compare total losses in most studies, as there is no uniform 
criterion for measurement. Most studies have not calculated total </p>

<p>losses </p>

<p>22,23) </p>

<p>. Few studies have used hematocrit drop 
29,30) while oth-</p>

<p>ers have used hemoglobin drop </p>

<p>24) </p>

<p>. Some studies have taken 2nd 
postoperative day hemoglobin values 
31) while others have used </p>

<p>4th postoperative day values 
21) for calculation. We believe that </p>

<p>hemoglobin usually decreases for initial 3-5 days after surgery 
and then begins to rise. The lowest value measured during this 
period best shows the true loss. Therefore, instead of a fixed day 
value, we used the lowest hemoglobin value for our calculation. 
We saw a reduction of 37% in total blood loss in the tranexamic 
acid group compared to the control group. Despite the utilization 
of different methods for calculation, most authors have shown 
tranexamic acid decreases total blood loss </p>

<p>21,29,30) </p>

<p>. 
We also observed a 24% decrease in the need for transfusion 
in the tranexamic acid group, and this reduction was statistically 
significant in consensus with data in literature. In addition, not 
only was the number of patients requiring transfusions less, the 
total number of transfusions required for each patient was sig-
nificantly less in the tranexamic acid group compared to the con-
trol group. The rate of transfusions in our study was a little high 
in both groups probably because of the female predominance; 
females tend to have lower preoperative hemoglobin levels com-
pared to those of males. In our study, the postoperative hemoglo-
bin was between 8-10 gm% at the time of transfusion in most of 
the patients who were transfused (16 in tranexamic acid group 
and 24 in control group) due to tachycardia not responding to 
fluid management; however, transfusion trigger has mostly been 
less than 8 gm% in literature </p>

<p>21,24) </p>

<p>. 
Tranexamic acid creates a prothrombotic state by inhibiting fi-
brinolysis. This raises the concern of DVT. However, we observed 
no adverse effects of tranexamic acid in terms of the develop-
ment of symptomatic DVT and PE. The safety of tranexamic acid 
has been well established in literature. Recent reviews and meta-
analyses have found no increased risk of thromboembolic events. 
They found that perioperative intravenous tranexamic acid ad-
ministration was not associated with increased risk of complica-
tions. 
We recognize limitations to our study. First, the sample size 
(100 patients) was too small to address some questions. Second, 
the study design was not double-blinded, randomized and can 
only be regarded as a prospective comparative trial. Third, the 
operations were performed by only two (EKS and JKS) of the 
total authors of this study. Fourth, the female to male ratio in our 
study was high because most TKA patients in our country are fe-
males. Female patients may have lower preoperative hemoglobin 
levels and greater blood transfusion rates after TKA than males; 
however, the ratios of females to males and the preoperative he-</p>

<p>Table 3. Postoperative Drain Output </p>

<p>Variable 
Control 
group (n=50) </p>

<p>Tranexamic acid 
group (n=50) 
p-value </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>POD 1 
611.6±227.1 (50) 
367.1±249.0 (50) 
0.009 </p>

<p>POD 2 
151.0±96.9 (41) 
146.6±68.3 (43) 
0.798 </p>

<p>POD 3 
133.1±58.0 (27) 
125.0±54.2 (21) 
0.634 </p>

<p>POD 4 
121.8±41.2 (15) 
98.2±28.6 (8) 
0.054 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation (number). 
POD: postoperative day. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>p-values are for unpaired two-tailed Student t-test. </p>

<p>192 Seol et al. Effect of Transexamic Acid on Blood Loss Reduction after TKA </p>

<p>moglobin levels were not different between the two groups in the 
study. Lastly, intraoperative anesthetic technique was determined 
based solely on the discretion of an anesthesiologist. This may 
have affected the total blood loss, and a study using a different 
anesthetic technique may be more appropriate. However, there 
was no statistically significant difference in the ratio of spinal to 
general anesthesia between the groups both groups, and thus we 
believe any effect the anesthetic technique could have on the re-
sults would have been the same in both groups. </p>

<p>conclusions </p>

<p>In conclusion, our prospective comparative study showed that 
the preoperative and postoperative single injection of tranexamic 
acid could be effective in reducing total blood loss and the need 
for blood transfusion after TKA for patients without any history 
of thromboembolic disease. </p>

<p>conflict of interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>

<p>references </p>



</text></tei>