<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5308490" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Introduction: One of the important input factors in the commissioning of the radiotherapy treatment planning 
systems is the phantom scatter factor (Sp) which requires the same collimator opening for all radiation fields. In 
this study, we have proposed an analytical method to overcome this issue. 
Methods: The measurements were performed using Siemens Primus Plus with photon energy 6 MV for field sizes 
from 5×5cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>to 40×40cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Phantom scatter factor was measured through the division of total scatter output factors 
(Scp), and collimator scatter factor (Sc). 
Results: The mean percent difference between the measured and calculated Sp was 1.00% and -3.11% for 5×5, 
40×40 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>field size respectively. 
Conclusion: This method is applicable especially for small fields used in IMRT which, measuring collimator 
scatter factor is not reliable due to the lateral electron disequilibrium. 
2 </p>

<p>) with a 
buildup cap of a size large enough to provide electronic equilibrium (2). To prevent contaminating electrons to the 
detector, the columnar mini phantom is used instead of buildup cap (3). The Sp is defined as the ratio of the absorbed 
dose at the depth of maximum dose (dmax) for a given field to that in the reference field at the same depth with the 
same collimator opening (4).The Sp becomes difficult to measure in practice (5); An indirect method of determining 
Sp, relates the total scatter factor (Scp) to the collimator scatter factor (Sc) (Figure 1, Eq.1); where Scp (r) is defined 
as the ratio of the absorbed dose at dmax in a water phantom for specific field to the absorbed dose in a reference field 
(6-10). Most treatment planning systems (TPS) need to enter Scp, Sc and Sp. Error in the measurement of Scp and Sc 
will cause problems to drive Sp (11).Therefore, it is necessary to calculate directly the phantom scatter factor using </p>

<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>

<p>Page 3524 </p>

<p>Monte Carlo simulation or analytical methods. According to the Sp definition, each measurement in the phantom has 
scattering effects from both phantom and collimator together. To eliminate the effect of collimator in this 
measurement, the field collimator should be tried to be constant during the measurement process. To solve this issue, 
Khan et al. produced the treatment field in phantom by collimator and then, without a change in collimator, they 
created the field references by lead blocks (12); Then, for the same condition, they defined the ratio of dosimeter 
readings for these two fields as Sp regardless of the block scattering involved in the measurement. An analytical model 
for calculating Sp is presented in this paper. We proposed a new setting to achieve the same collimator opening and 
all measuring done in phantom, therefore the lack of the lateral electron equilibrium for small field is not an issue. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Formula in the study </p>

<p>2. Material and Methods 
2.1. Theory 
According to the definition, the in-air output factor (Sc) can be written as Figure 1, Eq.2; which numerator and 
denominator are chamber readings (R) for the same number of monitor units (M) in the presence of a build-up cap for 
a field with dimensions L and L0 (as a reference field e.g. 10×10cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) at SSD=100cm and collimator opening CL, C0 
respectively. For the total scatter factor, measuring at the dmax in water phantom for a specific field (L) to that reference 
field (L0) for the same number of monitor units (M) (13), it would be written as Figure 1, Eq.3. To prevent electron 
contamination of the photon beam, it is recommended that all readings are performed at a depth of d=10 cm and then 
they are transmitted to the maximum depth using PDD (d) for that field size (14). So, the formula in Figure 1, Eq.4. 
According to Figure 2., L, L0 (field size), CL, and C0 (collimator opening) are shown as AB, EF, 
, and 
respectively. As can be seen in Figure 2, the total scatter factor is obtained by dividing the dosimeter reading which is 
caused by primary and secondary radiation (S') from two volume VABCD and reference volume VEFGH and then correct 
for depth d to dmax. The Sp is defined as the ratio of the absorbed dose at the dmax in phantom (water or solid water) </p>

<p>Electronic physician </p>

<p>Page 3525 </p>

<p>for a given field to that in the reference field with the same collimator opening (C0) to eliminate the collimator effect 
(4). Therefore, the formula in Figure 1, Eq.5. In this study, to maintain the collimator opening for all fields, the 
phantom surface can be pulled up (for L&lt;L0) or down (for L&gt;L0) (Figure 2). For example, for a field smaller than L0, 
L=AB, it is necessary to pull up phantom surface to J=(L/L0) ×SSD to achieve the same collimator opening. However, 
care must be which the dosimeter reading at J' needs to be corrected for SSD changes using Mayneord Factor. 
Therefore; we have to perform dosimetry in several SSDs and the main problem is phantom surface collision with 
Linac head for small fields. On the other hand, according to Eq. 3 and 5, the difference between the Sp and the total 
scatter factor is the amount of the collimator opening. Therefore, by considering a correction factor (for the effect of 
collimator) in the total scatter factor (Eq. 4), Sp can be achieved (Eq.5) as Figure 1, Eq.6. In Figure 2 with regards to 
the Pythagorean theorem, the trapezoid ABC"D" and A'B'C'D' are equal; therefore, the Sp is obtained by dividing the 
dosimeter readings at S' form two volume VA'B'C"D" and reference volume VEFGH. In this method, we propose to apply 
a factor (α) to correct scatter portion reached to the dosimeter (S') from VABCD to VABC"D". As mentioned in previous 
studies (15, 16), suppose that there is a parallel beam striking the surface of the phantom and consider a reference 
plane normal to the central axis, placed at depth d=10cm which the origin is on the central axis. Hence, each element 
(dx.dy) on this plane acts as a source of scattered radiation. The amount of scatter radiation reaching the central axis 
(dosimeter location, S') is inversely proportional to the square of the distance between surface elements and the origin. 
Therefore, with taking into account the photon attenuation µ, α is defined as Figure 1, Eq.7; Where µ is energy 
attenuation coefficient which depends on energy, field size and depth (17, 18). Therefore, the formula in Figure 1, 
Eq.8. α will be greater or lesser than 1 while phantom surface was pulled up or down respectively. Let us eliminate 
the small area at the origin of the coordinate with radius ε (refers to the ion chamber radius =3mm) to overcome 
singularity in nominator and denominator in Eq.7 and use polar system (Figure 3). Therefore, the scatter contribution 
to dosimeter location (S') for a rectangular field with dimensions (2Y × 2X) (Figure 3) is calculated as Figure 1, Eq.9. 
Finally, a general computer program using <rs id="software-0" type="software">MATLAB</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">7.12.0</rs> software was written to calculate α using the numerical 
method to solve Eq. 9. </p>

<p>Figure 2. (a) Diagram of under-radiation treatment volume in the standard mode of SSD=100 for reference field 
(VEFGH) and a small field (VABCD). In order to maintain collimator opening for smaller fields than the reference field, 
the phantom surface can be pulled up to the collimator location (A'B'). (b) DMCN, D"M"C"N" are the projection the 
field size L at distance OS', OJ'. </p>

<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>



<p>Figure 3. Polar system to calculate the scatter contribution to dosimeter location (S') for a rectangular field with 
dimensions (2Y × 2X). </p>

<p>2.2. Dosimetry and measurements 
The linear accelerator used in this study was a Siemens Primus Plus with photon energy 6 MV. A Scanditronix blue 
phantom (Wellhofer, Germany) (50 cm ×50 cm ×50 cm) and the Farmer ionization chamber 0.6cc were applied for 
measuring. Total scatter output factors, Scp, were measured at 10-cm depth water (S' in Figure 2) and source-surface 
distance (SSD) 100cm and for field sizes from 5×5cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>to 40×40cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. For Sc measurements, a polystyrene build-up 
cap was employed at maximum depth and source-surface distance (SSD) 100-cm. The Sp was measured indirectly 
using Eq. 1 as a routine method and then compared with Sp which was calculated by Eq.6, 7. </p>

<p>3. Results 
As has been shown in Table 1, the Sp for the photon beam was indirectly measured for all field sizes using measuring 
Scp and Sc according to Eq.1. The correction factor in Eq. 6 (α) was calculated using numerical calculation then by 
multiplying to Scp, Sp-cal was obtained. As can be seen, variations regarded to the energy attenuation coefficient (µ) 
changes Sp-cal results. While, elimination of the photon attenuation shows better results (fourth column). The 
measured and calculated phantom scatter were compared by percentage of difference which is mentioned the last three 
columns. According to Figure 4. for fields, which are far from the reference field (e. g. 5 and 40 cm), the differences 
between calculation and measurement are further than fields next to the reference field. This difference for fields 
larger than the reference field is becoming more evident. </p>

<p>Table 1. Phantom scatter factor (Sp) measured and calculated based on routine method (Sp-meas= Scp/Sc) and 
analytical method (Sp-cal= α.Scp). 
L (cm) 
(Field size) 
Sc 
Scp 
Sp-meas (Scp/Sc) Sp-cal=α.Scp 
Diff% (Spmeas-Spcal)/ Spmeas 
µ=0 
µ(r) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>µ(d,L) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>µ=0 
µ(r) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>µ(d,L) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>5×5 
0.957 0.948 0.990 
0.983 
0.980 
0.978 
0.72 
1.05 
1.23 
6×6 
0.971 0.963 0.992 
0.986 
0.983 
0.982 
0.62 
0.87 
1.01 
7×7 
0.982 0.976 0.994 
0.990 
0.988 
0.987 
0.39 
0.57 
0.67 
8×8 
0.991 0.993 1.002 
1.001 
1.000 
0.999 
0.10 
0.22 
0.28 
9×9 
0.998 0.999 1.001 
1.002 
1.002 
1.002 
-0.14 
-0.09 
-0.06 
10×10 
1.000 1.000 1.000 
1.000 
1.000 
1.000 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
12×12 
1.011 1.018 1.007 
1.013 
1.014 
1.015 
-0.62 
-0.72 
-0.77 
15×15 
1.021 1.038 1.017 
1.029 
1.031 
1.032 
-1.18 
-1.43 
-1.54 
20×20 
1.029 1.058 1.028 
1.045 
1.049 
1.051 
-1.61 
-2.07 
-2.24 
25×25 
1.035 1.081 1.044 
1.066 
1.072 
1.074 
-2.02 
-2.67 
-2.87 
30×30 
1.037 1.089 1.050 
1.072 
1.081 
1.083 
-2.13 
-2.94 
-3.14 
35×30 
1.040 1.091 1.049 
1.074 
1.084 
1.086 
-2.37 
-3.32 
-3.51 
40×40 
1.040 1.104 1.062 
1.086 
1.098 
1.100 
-2.33 
-3.42 
-3.59 
+ µ has been extracted from Bjangard's study; * µ has been extracted from Tahmasebi's study </p>

<p>Electronic physician </p>



<p>Figure 4. Phantom scatter factor (Sp) measured and calculated using various energy attenuation formula. </p>

<p>4. Discussion 
The phantom scatter correction factor (Sp) accounts for the contribution of the radiation scattered in the phantom 
material to the dose at the point at depth dref on the central axis that in the reference irradiation set-up. The amount of 
scattered radiation reaching to the dosimeter (S') depends on the volume of the phantom irradiated material, therefore, 
Sp is as a function of the field size at the surface of the phantom. There is little literature which has discussed analytical 
expression to calculate Sp. Blais and Karabrahimi in 2006 applied an equivalent field and Clarkson's method to 
calculate collimator scatter factor and Sp for kilovoltage x-ray radiation fields. They reported that the percentage 
difference between calculated and measured Sp was 6.3% and 3.5% for the equivalent field and Clarkson's method 
respectively(19). Chung et al. provided an analytical formalism to calculate phantom scatter factors for flattening filter 
free (FFF) mode photon beam by taking the product of the Sp in the presence of the flattening filter (FF) and the ratio 
of the off-axis ratio between the FFF mode and FF mode. They concluded that the percent difference between 
calculated and measured Sp ranged from -0.34% to 0.73% for Varian 6MV (20). This study has attempted to present 
an analytical approach to calculate the Sp using Scp values. It is most important to consider the percent difference 
range between the indirect measured and calculated Sp with 0.72%, 1.05% and 1.23% for 5×5 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>field size and -
2.33%, -3.42% and -3.59% for 40×40 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>field size for µ=0, µ(r), and µ(d, L) respectively. As can be seen in the last 
two columns Table.1, the Sp calculation shows approximately the same results for two expressions for µ. McKerracher 
showed indirect Sp values for fields &gt;4 cm width are independent of beam defining system and dependent only on 
measurement depth, beam quality and beam area irradiated, and Sp in fields &lt;4 cm width has also been shown to be 
independent of beam defining system and Linac design, and dependent only on measurement depth and beam area 
irradiated (6). One of the problems of indirect measurement method is measuring Sc for small fields due to the lack 
of the electron equilibrium. For small fields, this method is also insufficient due to the correction factor (α) will be 
close to 1, therefore, some other correction factors most be considered. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments: 
This study is taken from the Master's thesis therefore, the authors thank the office of Vice-Chancellor for Research of 
Jundishapur University of Medical Science, Ahvaz, Iran, for financial support with grant number (U-94039). </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: 
There is no conflict of interest to be declared. </p>

<p>Authors' contributions: 
All authors contributed to this project and article equally. All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>References: 
1) Miyashita H, Hatanaka S, Fujita Y, Hashimoto S, Myojyoyama A, Saitoh H. Quantitative analysis of in-air 
output ratio. J Radiat Res. 2013; 54(3): 553-60. doi: 10.1093/jrr/rrs118. PMID: 23292148, PMCID: 
PMC3650743. 
2) Khan FM, Gibbons JP. Khan's the physics of radiation therapy: Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins; 2014. </p>

<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>





</text></tei>