<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5013111" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Purpose To compare the measurements and failure 
rates obtained with a new swept source optical 
coherence tomography (OCT)-based biometry to 
IOLMaster 500. 
Setting Eye Clinic, Baskent University Faculty of 
Medicine, Ankara, Turkey. 
Design Observational cross-sectional study and 
evaluation of a new diagnostic technology. 
Methods 188 eyes of 101 subjects were included in 
the study. Measurements of axial length (AL), anterior 
chamber depth (ACD), corneal power (K1 and K2) and 
the measurement failure rate with the new Zeiss 
IOLMaster 700 were compared with those obtained with 
the IOLMaster 500. The results were evaluated using 
Bland-Altman analyses. The differences between both 
methods were assessed using the paired samples t test, 
and their correlation was evaluated by intraclass 
correlation coefficient (ICC). 
Results The mean age was 68.32±12.71 years and 
the male/female ratio was 29/72. The agreements 
between two devices were outstanding regarding AL 
(ICC=1.0), ACD (ICC=0.920), K1 (ICC=0.992) and K2 
(ICC=0.989) values. IOLMaster 700 was able to 
measure ACD AL, K1 and K2 in all eyes within high-
quality SD limits of the manufacturer. IOLMaster 500 
was able to measure ACD in 175 eyes, whereas 
measurements were not possible in the remaining 13 
eyes. AL measurements were not possible for 17 eyes 
with IOLMaster 500. Nine of these eyes had posterior 
subcapsular cataracts and eight had dense nuclear 
cataracts. 
Conclusions Although the agreement between the 
two devices was excellent, the IOLMaster 700 was more 
effective in obtaining biometric measurements in eyes 
with posterior subcapsular and dense nuclear cataracts. </p>

<p>The advancement of new technologies in intraocu-
lar lens (IOL) design and surgical techniques has 
increased the expectations of patients for excep-
tional postoperative vision without any refractive 
correction. The correct measurement of axial 
length (AL) and corneal power are crucial for the 
calculation of IOL power and achievement of the 
desired postoperative refraction. 
1 Modern optical 
biometry devices use either partial coherence inter-
ferometry (PCI) or optical low coherence reflect-
ometry (OLCR) to measure several variables 
including AL. In addition they can measure kerato-
metry (K), anterior chamber depth (ACD), lens 
thickness (LT) and horizontal white-to-white 
(WTW) corneal diameter using 
different 
approaches. 
2 Moreover, the built-in software in 
these devices provides more accurate IOL power </p>

<p>calculation and multiple choices of IOL formulas. </p>

<p>3   The IOLMaster (Carl Zeiss Meditec AG, Jena, 
Germany) is the gold standard of modern optical 
biometry devices. It uses the principle of PCI to 
obtain AL with high precision. 
4 5 Several reports 
have shown the accuracy of IOLMaster (IOLMaster 
or IOLMaster 500) for IOL calculation in routine 
and complicated cataract cases. 
6-9 However, mea-
surements can be difficult or unreliable with 
corneal opacities, macular diseases, advanced and 
posterior subcapsular (PSC) cataracts, vitrectomised 
eyes or poor fixation for PCI or OLCR based 
devices. </p>

<p>10 11   The IOLMaster 700 (Carl Zeiss Meditec AG, 
Jena, Germany), which is the first swept source 
optical coherence tomography (OCT) based biom-
etry, was introduced recently. It enables OCT 
imaging and visualisation across the entire length of 
the eye. It provides an image-based measurement, 
allowing the surgeon to view the complete longitu-
dinal section of the eye. Therefore, it may identify 
irregular eye geometries, such as lens tilt. 
Additionally, imaging of the fovea may alert the 
observer to insufficient fixation during measure-
ments. It also uses telecentric keratometry for 
corneal power measurements, similar to the 
IOLMaster 500. Briefly, it was introduced as an 
advantageous diagnostic device in an attempt to 
improve refractive results after cataract surgery. 
The purpose of this study was to compare the 
agreement between IOLMaster 500 and IOLMaster 
700 values for ACD, AL and keratometry. 
Measurement failure rates with both devices were 
also recorded and compared. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>This observational cross-sectional study comprising 
patients with cataract was performed at the Başkent 
University Faculty of Medicine, Department of 
Ophthalmology, Ankara, Turkey. The study was 
performed according to the Declaration of 
Helsinki. The University's ethics committee 
approved the study design and protocol. The 
patients were fully informed about the purpose of 
the study, after which they provided informed 
consent. 
Patients who were either diagnosed for the first 
time or who were under follow-up for cataract 
were included in the study. Patients were recruited 
during a 3-month period between April and June 
2015. All patients were examined by the same 
physician (AA) and in addition to routine ophthal-
mological examinations, cataract types were 
recorded as nuclear, cortical or PSC according to 
Lens Opacities Classification III scoring system 
(LOCS III). </p>

<p>12   Biometric measurements were </p>

<p>Akman A, et al. Br J Ophthalmol 2016;100:1201-1205. doi:10.1136/bjophthalmol-2015-307779 </p>

<p>
Clinical science </p>

<p>performed before pupillary dilatation in all patients. Patients 
who were unable to cooperate and fixate adequately during the 
measurements, with advanced macular problems like cystoid 
macular oedema or elevated scars, additionally whom had previ-
ous ocular surgery and irregular corneal surfaces were not 
included in the study. Corneal surface was investigated by 
Scheimpflug system (WaveLight Allegro Oculyzer; WaveLight 
AG, Erlangen, Germany). AL, ACD and corneal power (K1 
(flattest axis); K2 (steepest axis of corneal curvature 90°apart 
from flat axis)), and failure rates for both instruments were 
compared. </p>

<p>Instruments </p>

<p>IOLMaster 500 uses the PCI principle for AL measurements, a 
six-point telecentric technique for K readings and an image-
based slit lamp system for ACD measurements. It can also 
measure WTW distance. However, LT and central corneal thick-
ness (CCT) measurements are not available on IOLMaster 500. 
With this device, five consecutive measurements of AL and 
ACD, and three consecutive keratometry measurements were 
performed. A signal to noise ratio (SNR) value for AL readings 
is calculated. The manufacturer does not recommend the use of 
the measurements with SNR value less than two. Quality of ker-
atometry testing can be verified by visually checking the quality 
of the readings. 
IOLMaster 700 automatically takes swept source OCT scans 
and measures AL, along with CCT, ACD and LT. AL measure-
ments are the average values of three scans in each of six meri-
dians. For K readings, three average Ks, each of five single 
measurements are taken and the final average K readings are cal-
culated. On the IOLMaster 700, the operator can see the whole 
scan image and visually check the eye geometry and axis of the 
measurements; also the foveal scan checks the correct fixation 
by the patient. SD values of the ACD, LT and AL measurements 
are calculated and the device warns the operator of low-quality 
results if the SD for ACD &gt;0.021 mm, for LT &gt;0.038 mm and 
for AL &gt;0.027 mm. </p>

<p>Biometry measurement technique </p>

<p>Biometric measurements were performed using IOLMaster 500 
and IOLMaster 700 consecutively by the same technician for 
the first 100 eyes and the order was reversed for the remaining 
eyes. The quality control criteria for both devices were used in 
accordance with the above-mentioned manufacturer recommen-
dations. If measurements were not possible in accordance with 
limits, they were recorded as measurement failures for either 
device. The same examiner, who was trained according to the 
manufacturer's recommendations, performed all tests. 
All IOLMaster 700 scans were checked by the same surgeon 
(AA) for foveal scans to ensure the correct axis measurements 
and the scan was repeated if the patient was not fixating 
correctly. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The required sample size was calculated using the following 
formula: n=[(2×t f,0,95 ×SD)/CI] 
2 with t n-1;1-α/2 =1, 7 (quantile 
of t distribution for expected sample size n&gt;50 and α=0.05; 
SD; CI). 
2 The anticipated SDs were based on the results from 
preliminary study data for initial power analysis. </p>

<p>13   The results were evaluated using intraclass correlation coeffi-
cients (ICCs), Bland-Altman plots and paired samples t tests. 
Left and right eyes were included in the subsequent analysis, as 
most of the variation in the ocular variables considered in this 
study is found within rather than between the left and right eyes 
Table 1 The comparison of values between IOLMaster 500 and IOLMaster 700 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>Device </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>SD 
Paired samples </p>

<p>t test (p value) 
Range (minimum-maximum) </p>

<p>ICC </p>

<p>Differences </p>

<p>of the means </p>

<p>SD of difference 
of means </p>

<p>95% CI of 
differences of means </p>

<p>Paired samples </p>

<p>t test p value </p>

<p>Anterior Chamber depth (mm) </p>

<p>175 </p>

<p>IOLmaster 500 </p>

<p>3.31 </p>

<p>0.38 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>2.23-4.19 </p>

<p>0.920 </p>

<p>−0.08 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>−0.102 to </p>

<p>−0.063 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>IOLMaster 700 </p>

<p>3.23 </p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>2.33-4.14 </p>

<p>Axial length (mm) </p>

<p>171 </p>

<p>IOLMaster 500 </p>

<p>23.627 </p>

<p>1.25 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>20.92-28.33 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>−0.005 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>−0.008 to </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>0.830 </p>

<p>IOLMaster 700 </p>

<p>23.622 </p>

<p>1.32 </p>

<p>20.91-29.69 </p>

<p>Keratometry (flat, D) </p>

<p>188 </p>

<p>IOLMaster 500 </p>

<p>43.46 </p>

<p>1.77 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>48.35-37.17 </p>

<p>0.992 </p>

<p>−0.05 </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>−0.079 to </p>

<p>−0.014 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>IOLMaster 700 </p>

<p>43.41 </p>

<p>1.73 </p>

<p>37.25-48.21 </p>

<p>Keratometry (steep, D) </p>

<p>188 </p>

<p>IOLMaster 500 </p>

<p>44.50 </p>

<p>1.81 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>49.13-38.14 </p>

<p>0.989 </p>

<p>−0.08 </p>

<p>0.27 </p>

<p>−0.114 to </p>

<p>−0.036 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>IOLMaster 700 </p>

<p>44.42 </p>

<p>1.83 </p>

<p>38.05-49.07 </p>

<p>Difference of the means was computed by subtracting IOLMaster 500 values form IOLMaster 700 values. </p>

<p>ICC, intraclass correlation coefficient. </p>

<p> 
Akman A, et al. Br J Ophthalmol 2016;100:1201-1205. doi:10.1136/bjophthalmol-2015-307779 </p>

<p>Clinical science </p>

<p>(analysis of variance p values &gt;0.05 for AL, ACD, K1 and K2). 
Including both eyes in the study was also in accordance with 
similar previous studies. </p>

<p>2 14   Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> software (V.<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">22.0</rs> 
for Mac, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>, Chicago, Illinois, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Data from 188 eyes of 101 patients were included in the study 
(male/female: 29/72). The sample size proved statistically to be 
sufficient to determine and prove the data for ACD, AL, K1, K2 
with desired precision and probability. The mean age of the 
patients was 68.32±12.71 (range 24-81) years. One hundred 
and thirty-five eyes (71.8%) had nuclear cataracts, 18 eyes 
(9.5%) had cortical cataracts and 35 eyes (18.6%) had PSC cat-
aracts. Best corrected Snellen visual acuity ranged from finger 
counting to 0.9 (0.51±0.23). 
Table 1 summarises the ACD, AL, K1, K2 results for 
IOLMaster 500 and IOLMaster 700. Bland-Altman plots for 
comparisons between IOLMaster 500 and IOLMaster 700 are 
presented in figures 1-4. 
Although the agreements between the two devices were out-
standing regarding AL, ACD, K1 and K2 values, paired sample t 
tests showed statistically significant differences among ACD, K1 
and K2 measurements. These differences are quite small for 
clinical relevance and table 2 summarises the differences 
between two measurements for clinically acceptable values for 
ACD, AL, K1 and K2. 
IOLMaster 700 was able to measure ACD, AL, K1 and K2 in 
all eyes within high-quality SD limits of the manufacturer. 
IOLMaster 500 was able to measure ACD in 175 eyes, whereas 
measurements were not possible in the remaining 13 eyes. Nine 
of these 13 eyes had ACD values longer than 4.1 mm 
(IOLMaster 700 measurement data). AL measurements were not 
possible for 17 phakic eyes with IOLMaster 500. Nine of these 
eyes had PSC and eight had dense nuclear cataracts. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Satisfactory refractive results after IOL implantation depends on 
optimal biometry. Accurate AL, ACD and K readings are essen-
tial for all biometric formulas to calculate the IOL power 
required for the desired results. With the common usage of </p>

<p>toric and multifocal IOLs, accurate biometry has become more 
important than ever to reach the refractory goals that patients 
expect. The most common preventable sources of error are 
incorrect AL measurements and keratometry readings. </p>

<p>15   IOLMaster was the first optical biometer available for com-
mercial usage and its accuracy and repeatability made it the gold 
standard of biometry for many years. 
16 17 Other optical biom-
etry devices became available in the last few years. All these 
devices depend on patient fixation to a target. Poor fixation can 
be one of the reasons for AL measurement errors. Lens pro-
blems, dense vitreous opacities or foveal problems can also 
cause errors in optical biometry. In addition, with PSC and 
dense cataracts, the optical biometers available today can fail to 
take adequate measurements. </p>

<p>11 18   Swept source OCT based IOLMaster 700 provides an image-
based measurement, allowing the surgeon to view the complete 
longitudinal section of the eye. Therefore, it may identify 
irregular eye geometries, such as lens tilt, and imaging of the </p>

<p>Figure 1 Bland-Altman plot for anterior chamber depth (ACD) 
comparing IOLMaster 700 with IOLMaster 500. The 95% limits of 
agreement were −0.33 to 0.17 mm. Dotted lines, ±1.96 SD. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Bland-Altman plot for K1 value comparing IOLMaster 700 
with IOLMaster 500. The 95% limits of agreement were −0.48 to 
0.38 D. Dotted lines, ±1.96 SD. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Bland-Altman plot for axial length (AL) comparing 
IOLMaster 700 with IOLMaster 500. The 95% limits of agreement were 
−0.045 to 0.035 mm. Dotted lines, ±1.96 SD. </p>

<p>Akman A, et al. Br J Ophthalmol 2016;100:1201-1205. doi:10.1136/bjophthalmol-2015-307779 </p>

<p>
Clinical science </p>

<p>fovea may alert the observer to insufficient fixation during mea-
surements. This may allow for a more accurate performance of 
IOL power calculations and better refractive outcomes. 
Furthermore, the swept source OCT technology has the add-
itional advantage of extremely rapid data acquisition, including 
the ability to measure the AL along six different axes. 
In this study, we aimed to compare the performance of 
IOLMaster 700 with the gold standard IOLMaster 500. 
Regarding the AL measurements, IOLMaster 700 showed an 
incredible correlation with IOLMaster 500 with a ICC value of 
1. The mean measurement difference among the 188 eyes mea-
sured was 0.005 mm (SD=0.02). These results show that both 
devices measure the AL in nearly the same way. 
In eyes with PSC, IOLMaster 500 and other optical biometers 
have higher failure rates and immersion ultrasound (US) biom-
etry was the only option until today. 
11 18 Clinically, PSC cataracts 
are well known to cause more visual disability compared with 
other cataract types, even in low grades. As the opacities are 
located nearer to the nodal point of the lens, more light rays will 
be affected. This can be one of the reasons for measurement fail-
ures in PCI or OLCR based optical biometries. 
18 Using swept 
source OCT technology may overcome these problems and this 
could be the main reason for the higher acquisition rate for AL 
measurements with IOLMaster 700 in the presence of PSC or </p>

<p>dense cataracts. In our study, IOLMaster 700 was able to 
measure AL in all 188 phakic eyes, including the PSC and dense 
nuclear cataracts. However, IOLMaster 500 failed to acquire 
measurements in 9 of the 35 PSC cases and in 8 dense cataracts. 
Measurement failure rate of IOLMaster 500 can be reduced 
by using a higher number of measurements and selectively using 
the ones with better quality, a method described by Hill et al. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>But these methods are time consuming, require a higher number 
of measurements and the measurements need to be reviewed by 
an experienced and skilful operator. 
19 For routine clinical prac-
tice, these methods were not feasible in our clinical setting and 
we did not employ them. 
ACD measurements of IOLMaster 700 also correlated very 
highly with the IOLMaster 500. IOLMaster 500 does not 
measure ACD with PCI. The principal that IOLMaster 500 uses 
for ACD measurements is based on an optical section through 
the anterior chamber by means of a slit-illumination system with 
subsequent image assessment. It can be prone to operator errors 
and this method cannot measure the ACD in pseudophakic 
eyes. 
20 21 However, IOLMaster 700 uses swept source OCT 
images and is able to measure ACD, CCT and LT from the 
single OCT image that is aligned with the visual axis of the eye. 
Our results show that ACD measurements with IOLMaster 700 
are highly correlated with IOLMaster 500 (ICC=0.940). 
However, when we compared the mean differences of these 
groups, we saw that IOLMaster 700 measured ACD 0.08 mm 
shorter than IOLMaster 500. Although these values are very 
small for clinical significance, this finding is statistically signifi-
cant (p&lt;0.001). As only fourth-generation formulas like 
Holliday II and Olsen use ACD data, it will not affect the third-
generation formula results and this 0.08 mm difference will 
cause negligible IOL power difference for the fourth-generation 
formulas. Again, the ACD measurement failures were observed 
only with IOLMaster 500. For 13 eyes in which IOLMaster 500 
failed to obtain a measurement, nine eyes had ACD measured 
&gt;4.1 mm with the IOLMaster 700. In previous studies, ACD 
measurements obtained with IOLMaster 500 have been 
reported and compared with different US-based and optically 
based instruments, with variable results. 
22-24 ACD values were 
reported to be higher 
25 compared with ultrasonographic techni-
ques in some reports and lower 
26 in others. A number of 
reasons may be proposed for these differences. The IOLMaster 
500 may not measure the axial ACD because the slit source is 
projected from the temporal side. Measuring the anterior 
chamber off centre may result in an error. Another possible 
cause is the inclusion of keratometry in calculating the ACD. 
Both of the above-mentioned potential sources of error are </p>

<p>Table 2 The differences in measurements between IOLMaster 500 and IOLMaster 700; n (%) </p>

<p>Keratometry measurements (n=188) </p>

<p>Anterior chamber 
depth (n=175) 
Axial length (n=188) 
K1 
K2 </p>

<p>Depth (mm) 
n (%) 
Length (mm) 
n (%) </p>

<p>Keratometry 
measurements (D) 
n (%) </p>

<p>Keratometry 
measurements (D) 
n (%) </p>

<p>&lt;0.1 mm 
90 (52) 
No difference 
43 (24) 
&lt;0.5D 
181 (96) 
&lt;0.5D 
173 (92) 
&lt;0.2 mm 
154 (88) 
&lt;0.02 mm 
102 (56) 
&lt;1D 
188 (100) 
&lt;1D 
188 (100) 
&lt;0.3 mm 
175 (100) 
&lt;0.03 mm 
150 (82) 
&lt;0.05 mm 
165 (91) 
&lt;0.10 mm 
177 (96) 
&lt;0.15 mm 
188 (100) </p>

<p>Figure 4 Bland-Altman plot for K2 value comparing IOLMaster 700 
with IOLMaster 500. The 95% limits of agreement were −0.61 to 
0.45 D. Dotted lines, ±1.96 SD. </p>

<p> 
Akman A, et al. Br J Ophthalmol 2016;100:1201-1205. doi:10.1136/bjophthalmol-2015-307779 </p>

<p>Clinical science </p>

<p>eliminated in IOLMaster 700, since it uses swept source OCT 
images for the calculation of ACD. 
Keratometric measurements are the second important source 
of error for refractive outcomes. Both devices use a 
distance-independent telecentric keratometry system. In our 
study, nearly all of the keratometry measurements with both 
instruments were within 0.5 (D) for steep and flat meridians. 
Besides, the correlation coefficients for flat meridian 
(ICC=0.992) and steep meridian (ICC=0.989) show that both 
instruments measure corneal power with similar accuracy. 
Although very important for toric IOL calculations, axis mea-
surements are not used by most of the current biometric formu-
las for spheric IOL power calculations and so we did not 
include them in the current paper. 
With ICC close to 1, both devices are expected to give very 
similar IOL measurements in eyes with good fixation and no 
additional ocular problems, which is the case for most of the 
routine cataract cases we observe in developed countries. The 
main advantage of swept source OCT-based biometry like 
IOLMaster 700 becomes evident in patients with poor fixation, 
irregular eye geometries and denser cataracts. 
In this study we found that the IOL power for SRK/T, 
Holiday 1, Hoffer Q and Haigis derived by both devices were 
quite similar, and highly correlated. The mean difference was 
less than 0.10 D for all the formulas, less than the increment in 
the IOL power step (0.50 D). Although both devices did not 
have a clinically significant impact on IOL power, the chosen 
IOL formula should be considered. If the WTW measurement is 
required in a formula, such as in the Holladay 2, the result may 
be different. 
As a result, the agreement between the two devices was out-
standing regarding AL, ACD, K1 and K2 values. However, the 
IOLMaster 700 was more effective in obtaining biometric mea-
surements in eyes with PSC and dense nuclear cataracts com-
pared with IOLMaster 500. The ability of the new swept source 
OCT-based biometry to detect the fixation pattern, decentration 
or tilt of the lens and the tomographic visualisation of the com-
plete longitudinal section of the eye including the fovea helps to 
eliminate potential sources of error and, therefore, to optimise 
refractive outcomes in cataract surgery. </p>

<p>Contributors AA: substantial contributions to the conception or design of the 
work, or the acquisition, analysis or interpretation of data; drafting the work or 
revising it critically for important intellectual content; final approval of the version 
published. LA: substantial contributions to the conception or design of the work, or 
the acquisition, analysis or interpretation of data; drafting the work or revising it 
critically for important intellectual content. SGG: drafting the work or revising it 
critically for important intellectual content; final approval of the version published; 
agreement to be accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions 
related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately 
investigated and resolved. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Patient consent Obtained. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Baskent University. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which 
permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, 
and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is 
properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Akman A, et al. Br J Ophthalmol 2016;100:1201-1205. doi:10.1136/bjophthalmol-2015-307779 </p>

<p>
Clinical science </p>

</text></tei>