<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5293311" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: The demand for reconstructive breast procedures of various types 
has accelerated in recent years. Coupled with increased patient expectations, it has 
fostered the development of oncoplastic and reconstructive techniques in breast 
surgery. In the setting of postmastectomy reconstruction, patient satisfaction and 
quality of life are the most significant outcome variables when evaluating surgical 
success. The aim of this study was to evaluate the quality of life after implant breast 
reconstruction compared with autologous breast reconstruction. 
Materials and Methods: A cross-sectional study design was used. A total of 
65 women who had completed postmastectomy implant-based or autologous 
reconstruction in the participating center were asked to complete the <rs type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> 
(Reconstruction Module). 
Results: Data analysis demonstrated that women with autologous breast recon-
struction were significantly more satisfied with their breasts (P = 0.0003) and with 
the overall outcome (P = 0.0001) compared with women with implant breast re-
construction. All other <rs type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> parameters that were considered and observed 
were not significantly different between the 2 patient groups. 
Conclusions: Through statistical analysis, our results showed that patients who under-
went autologous tissue reconstruction had better satisfaction with the reconstructed 
breast and the outcome, while both techniques appear to equally improve psychoso-
cial well-being, sexual well-being, and chest satisfaction. Ortensia Pirro, MD* 
Ondrej Mestak, MD † 
Vincenzo Vindigni, MD* 
Andrej Sukop, MD ‡ 
Veronika Hromadkova, MD † 
Alena Nguyenova † 
Lenka Vitova, MD † 
Franco Bassetto, MD* </p>

<p>Comparison of Patient-reported Outcomes 
after Implant Versus Autologous Tissue Breast 
Reconstruction Using the <rs type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> </p>

<p>Disclosure: The authors have no financial interest to declare in 
relation to the content of this article. This study was supported by 
a research grant from Charles University in Prague, No. 97015. 
The Article Processing Charge was paid for by the authors. </p>

<p>Breast </p>

<p>ORIGINAL </p>

<p>PRS Global Open • 2017 </p>



<p>The aim of this cross-sectional study was to compare 
the quality of life in women who underwent breast re-
construction with implants with those who underwent 
free transverse rectus abdominis myocutaneous (TRAM) 
flap breast reconstruction, using <rs type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> 
11 to appraise 
patient-reported outcomes. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Sample </p>

<p>The study population consisted of women who had un-
dergone breast reconstruction after mastectomy for breast 
cancer. The patient sample was recruited at the Univer-
sity Hospital of Bulovka in Prague, Czech Republic. The 
choice of the reconstructive procedure for each patient 
is based on an evaluation of quality of tissue in area after 
mastectomy, body mass index, size of contralateral breast, 
and an excess of soft tissue in the lower abdomen. Patients 
with tight skin after radiotherapy and with higher body 
mass index are more prone to receive free TRAM flap 
breast reconstruction. The study population consisted of 
2 groups of women, the patients who underwent mastec-
tomy and delayed breast reconstruction with implants and 
patients who underwent mastectomy and delayed breast 
reconstruction with the free TRAM flap. 
The inclusion criteria included mastectomy patients 
who had undergone and completed breast reconstruction 
(unilateral or bilateral) between January 2012 and Janu-
ary 2015. The protocol was approved by the Ethical Re-
view Board of Bulovka Hospital in Prague, and all patients 
signed informed consent before participating in the study. </p>

<p>Procedure </p>

<p>A cross-sectional study design was used. Recruitment 
of patients was based on electronic medical records anal-
ysis. Afterward description of the study and a <rs type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> 
breast reconstruction postoperative questionnaire were 
sent to both groups of patients (50 letters for each group). 
The questionnaire booklet was mailed along with a self-
addressed, postage-paid return envelope according to the 
type of reconstruction. The questionnaires were marked 
with different colors to differentiate between implant breast 
reconstruction and autologous breast reconstruction. We 
received responses from 34 patients who underwent im-
plant breast reconstruction and 31 patients who underwent 
free TRAM flap reconstruction, giving a total of 65 patients. </p>

<p>BREAST-Q </p>

<p>The <rs id="software-6" type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center and the University of British Columbia</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-date">2006</rs>, all 
rights reserved) is a patient-reported outcome measure 
that was specifically designed to measure the quality of life 
and patient satisfaction among breast surgery patients. </p>

<p>11   The instrument was developed and validated with adher-
ence to guidelines set by the Scientific Advisory Commit-
tee of the Medical Outcomes Trust (2002) and the US 
Food and Drug Administration. 
12-15 The <rs type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> recon-
struction module was used as the primary outcome mea-
sure in this study. </p>

<p>The scales forming the <rs type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> reconstruction 
module are as follows: satisfaction with breasts, satisfaction 
with the overall outcome, psychosocial well-being, sexual 
well-being, physical well-being of the chest, satisfaction 
with nipple areola reconstruction, satisfaction with infor-
mation, satisfaction with the surgeon, satisfaction with the 
medical team, and satisfaction with the office staff. 
The patients' responses to each scale's items were 
analyzed through the Q Score that analyses data based 
on <rs id="software-9" type="software">RUMM</rs> <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">2020</rs>, a data-analyzing program developed by 
<rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">Rasch Unidimensional Measurement Models Laboratory</rs>. 
This software automatically transforms raw data into sum-
mary scores that range from 0 (very dissatisfied) to 100 
(very satisfied) for each scale. For all <rs type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> scales, a 
higher score indicates greater satisfaction or better qual-
ity of life. A mean change of 5 to 10 on a multi-item scale 
is perceived as "a little" change, 10 to 20 as "a moderate" 
change, and greater than 20 as "a maximal" change. 
Before commencing the study, the questionnaire had a 
Czech translation validated in accordance with the agree-
ment with the MAPI Trust (http:// www.mapi-trust.org/). 
The translated version was approved by <rs corresp="#software-11" type="creator">Andrea Pusic</rs>, the 
author of the <rs id="software-11" type="software">BREAST-Q</rs>. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The obtained data were reported in <rs id="software-12" type="software">Excel</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-12" type="creator">Microsoft Corp</rs>., Redmond, Wash.) and were analyzed using <rs id="software-13" type="software">SAS</rs> sta-
tistical software package version <rs corresp="#software-13" type="version-number">9.4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-13" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc</rs>., Cary, 
N.C.). Data are expressed as the mean and SD. Compari-
sons between breast reconstruction with implants and breast 
reconstruction with autologous tissues were made using a 
paired sample t test. Significance was considered at P &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>This cross-sectional study compared 2 cohorts in which 
34 (52.3%) women underwent mastectomy and successful 
breast reconstruction with implants and 31 (47.7%) wom-
en underwent mastectomy and successful breast recon-
struction with autologous tissue (free TRAM flap). Mean 
age of patients was 512 years in free TRAM group and 589 
years in implant group. Twenty-four (70.5%) patients from 
the free TRAM group and 12 (38.7%) patients from the 
implant group underwent radiotherapy. Three (8.8%) pa-
tients were smokers in free TRAM group compared with 
5 (16.1%) patients in the implant group. The time inter-
val between the operation and filling of the questionnaire 
was 12 to 48 months (average, 31 months). Data analysis 
demonstrated that women with autologous breast recon-
struction were significantly more satisfied with their breasts 
(P = 0.0003) and with the overall outcome (P = 0.0001) 
compared with women with implant breast reconstruction 
(Figs. 1, 2). Results of the analysis of the patient-measured 
outcomes within all 10 modules are presented in Figure 1. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The decision-making process of a patient undergo-
ing breast reconstructive surgery after mastectomy is very 
complex. In today's medical climate, patient satisfaction </p>

<p>Pirro et al. • Comparison of Patient-reported Outcomes </p>



<p>has become an important variable used to establish quality 
of care parameters. 
Through statistical analysis, our results showed that 
patients who underwent autologous tissue reconstruction 
appear to have better satisfaction with the reconstructed 
breast and the outcome, while both techniques appear 
to equally improve psychosocial well-being, sexual well-
being, and chest satisfaction. 
These data confirm previous reports in the literature, 
with a general consensus suggesting that patients whose 
breasts are reconstructed using autologous tissue are more 
satisfied. 
16,17 Autologous tissue reconstruction offers many 
advantages that prosthetic devices cannot offer, including </p>

<p>longevity, predictability, and success in complex cases such as 
prior radiation or device infection, as well as providing the 
added benefit of esthetic recontouring at the donor sites. 
Autologous reconstruction has the benefit of replacing like 
with like. Despite requiring lengthier procedures and a lon-
ger recovery, autologous tissue-based reconstruction has the 
potential to recreate a soft, naturally ptotic breast shape that 
is ideal for matching an unaffected contralateral breast. </p>

<p>18   The goal of reconstructive breast surgery is no longer 
to create a breast mound; instead, it aims to create a breast 
with a natural shape, volume, contour, and symmetry. The 
use of autologous tissues allows for reconstruction of a 
breast, which looks and feels more like a natural breast. 
Patient expectations after mastectomy and reconstruc-
tion have increased, and reconstructive plastic surgeons 
should continue to strive for excellence to satisfy them. 
In a previous study published by Hu et al, 
19 the authors 
stressed that both breast implant and autologous tissue re-
construction experience an "aging" process, resulting in 
different long-term complications that can variably influ-
ence the esthetic result. The authors noted that patients 
who underwent TRAM flap, compared with patients who 
underwent expander/implant reconstruction, showed 
greater long-term esthetic satisfaction. The satisfaction re-
duction in patients who underwent breast reconstruction 
using an expander/implant could be related to the high 
incidence of complications and reoperations required for 
this technique. 
20 Women who undergo reconstruction us-
ing silicone gel implants have up to a 28% 
21,22 risk of de-
veloping grade III or IV Baker capsular contracture and 
a 30% risk of having to remove or replace the prosthesis, 
resulting in an overall reoperation rate of 45% to 50%. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Means and SDs of the <rs type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> patient-reported scores (*statistically significant = P &lt; 0.01). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Mean distributions comparing <rs type="software">BREAST-Q</rs> patient-reported </p>

<p>scores from the implant and TRAM groups. </p>

<p>PRS Global Open • 2017 </p>



<p>Although implant-based breast reconstruction remains 
the most common method utilized to reconstruct a breast 
after mastectomy for cancer, autologous tissue reconstruc-
tion is generally regarded the gold standard in breast re-
construction. 
23 In any case, implant reconstruction has 
advanced through the years with better devices and im-
proved surgical techniques. This is why the spectrum of 
patients suitable for implant-based breast reconstruction 
goes beyond the traditional concept of slim to moderately 
built women with modest breast size and minimal ptosis. 
In addition, the development of acellular dermal matrices 
and fat transfer techniques will further evolve for patients 
suitable for implant-based techniques. 
Autologous breast reconstruction is an option for many 
women. The choice of breast reconstruction depends on 
multiple factors when selecting the best reconstruction 
option for a patient. One important consideration is the 
level of patient motivation and the willingness of the pa-
tient to undergo complex or extensive procedures. The 
magnitude of surgery, length of recovery, potential com-
plications, resultant scarring, and potential functional 
loss associated with some forms of autologous breast re-
construction may be valid reasons for patients to opt for 
implant-based surgery. 
Breast reconstruction should be tailored to meet the 
individual needs of the patients. The available options and 
decision-making process should be fully discussed in the 
setting of a balance of benefits and risks used in the final 
analysis of the patient's choice. Units that offer breast re-
construction should have access to the range of options in 
current practice for meeting these needs. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>Through statistical analysis, our results showed that 
patients who underwent autologous tissue reconstruction 
had better satisfaction with the reconstructed breast and 
the outcome, while both techniques appear to equally im-
prove psychosocial well-being, sexual well-being, and chest 
satisfaction. </p>

<p>Ondrej Mestak, MD, PhD 
Department of Plastic Surgery 
Bulovka Hospital 
1st Medical Faculty of Charles University in Prague 
Budinova 2, Prague 8, 14800, Czech Republic 
E-mail: mestak@gmail.com </p>



</text></tei>