<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5207597" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to examine changes in photoreceptor ellipsoid zone (EZ) and postreceptor retinal layer in retinitis 
pigmentosa (RP) patients by ganglion cell analysis (GCA) combined with optical coherence tomography (OCT) imaging to evaluate 
the structure-function relationships between retinal layer changes and best corrected visual acuity (BCVA). Sixty-eight eyes of 35 
patients with RP and 65 eyes of 35 normal controls were analyzed in the study. The average length of EZ was 911.1 ± 208.8 mm in RP 
patients, which was shortened with the progression of the disease on the OCT images. The average ganglion cell-inner plexiform 
layer thickness (GCIPLT) was 54.7 ± 18.9 mm in RP patients, while in normal controls it was 85.6 ± 6.8 mm. The GCIPLT in all quarters 
became significantly thinner along with outer retinal thinning. There was a significantly positive correlation between BCVA and EZ 
(r = À0.7622, P &lt; 0.001) and GCIPLT (r = À0.452, P &lt; 0.001). Therefore, we assess the retinal layer changes from a new perspective 
in RP patients, which suggests that EZ and GCIPLT obtained by GCA combined with OCT imaging are the direct and valid indicators 
to diagnosis and predict the pathological process of RP. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BCVA = best corrected visual acuity, EZ = ellipsoid zone, ERG = electroretinography, ELM = extend limiting 
membrane, GCIPLT = ganglion cell-inner plexiform layer thickness, GCA = ganglion cell analysis, GCL = ganglion cell layer, IPL = 
inner plexiform layer, OCT = optical coherence tomography, ORT = outer retinal thickness, RP = retinitis pigmentosa, RNFL = retinal 
nerve fiber layer, RPE = retinal pigment epithelium, RGC = retinal ganglion cell. </p>

<p>Retinitis pigmentosa (RP) is a hereditary degenerative disease of 
the retina. [1,2] As a cause of visual impairment, the prevalence of 
RP is about 1 in 4000, [3,4] which is characterized by slowly </p>

<p>progressive, concentric constriction of the visual field. [2,5] The 
earliest histopathological changes in all forms of RP involve 
shortening of the photoreceptor segments, so there are a number 
of studies about outer retinal changes, [5-9] while relatively fewer 
articles about inner retinal thickness. [10,11] In addition, the results 
showed that the inner retinal layers were preserved or even 
thickening compared to the outer retinal layers, which was 
associated with neuronal-glial remodeling, especially in early 
stage of RP patients. [12] In addition, the morphometry study 
showed that the ganglion cell number was not statistically 
different in the various stages of RP. [13] Therefore, currently 
proposed strategies to treat RP are based on the assumption that 
the inner retinal cells are intact. [2] However, there were also 
articles reported less ganglion cells in RP patients than in normal 
controls. [14,15] Besides, the inner retinal layers including the inner 
limiting membrane, retinal nerve fiber layer (RNFL), ganglion cell 
layer (GCL), inner plexiform layer (IPL), and inner nuclear layer 
measured by manual methods were widely different in previous 
studies, [11,12,15,16] and RNFL thickness is dramatically different 
in individuals. [17] So, the general conclusion that the inner retinal 
cells are intact need to be reassessed, especially by the modern 
devices. 
Ganglion cell IPL (GCIPL), which is topographically less 
variable among normal individuals, reflects both the retinal 
ganglion cell (RGC) bodies and the dendrites originating from the 
macular region. It has been confirmed to be valuable for 
diagnosing glaucoma obtained by ganglion cell analysis (GCA) 
incorporate into the new optical coherence tomography (OCT) 
device, which reflects localized RNFL defects better than </p>

<p>Editor: Stela Vujosevic. </p>

<p>GL and HL have contributed equally to the article. </p>

<p>Authorship: All authors involved in study design, data analysis, and revising of the 
manuscript, the authors agreed the submission of the article. </p>

<p>Funding/support: The work was supported by the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China grants (81271029 and 81300772), Specialized Research 
Fund Q2 for the Doctoral Program of Higher Education (20130072120053), and 
the Science and Technology Commission of Shanghai Q3 (11Jc1409900). </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>Supplemental Digital Content is available for this article. </p>

<p>Department of Ophthalmology, Shanghai Tenth People's Hospital Affiliated with 
Tongji University School of Medicine, Shanghai, PR China. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Correspondence: Fang Wang, Department of Ophthalmology, Shanghai Tenth 
People's Hospital Affiliated with Tongji University School of Medicine, 301 Middle 
Yan Chang Road, Shanghai 200072, PR China (e-mail: milwang_122@msn.com) </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-
ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is 
properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially 
without permission from the journal. </p>

<p>Medicine (2016) 95:52(e5785) </p>

<p>Received: 31 August 2016 / Received in final form: 30 November 2016 / 
Accepted: 1 December 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000005785 </p>

<p>Observational Study </p>

<p>Medicine ® </p>

<p>OPEN </p>



<p>papillary RNFL in advanced glaucoma. [18,19] However, there is 
no article to study about GCIPL changes in RP patients by GCA, 
and the thickness in the previous studies was measured from 2 or 
4 points by manual [20,21] ; therefore, it is necessary to reconfirm 
the condition of ganglion cells in RP. Visual function in RP cases 
was proved to be related with morphological changes of the 
photoreceptors in the macular area. [22-25] Unfortunately, the 
analysis of the relationship between GCIPL thickness (GCIPLT) 
and visual function has not been investigated. With the advent of 
higher resolution spectral domain (Cirrus high-definition 5000, 
Carl Zeiss Meditec, Inc.; Dublin, CA) OCT, combined with more 
precise segmentation of the retinal layers, GCIPLT measurement 
has become possible. [26] Therefore, it is necessary to use GCA to 
assess the morphological changes and thickness of GCIPL in RP 
patients. 
In the present study, we use the modern OCT with an axial 
resolution of 5 mm to evaluate the changes in receptor ellipsoid 
zone (EZ) and postreceptor retinal layer (GCIPL) in patients with 
RP. The relationship between best corrected visual acuity (BCVA) 
and EZ, and GCIPLT were investigated using a linear regression 
model. The factors affecting visual acuity were further analyzed 
by multiple linear regressions. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Materials </p>

<p>In this study, 70 eyes of 35 patients (11 female, 24 male; age range 
29-76 years; median age 51.5 years) with a clinical diagnosis of 
RP were examined, and the average diagnostic duration was 32 ± 
6.5 years. Sixty-five eyes of 35 patients (11 female, 24 male; age 
range 26-78 years; median age 51.8 years) without retinal disease 
served as normal controls. The study was conducted at Shanghai 
Tenth People's Hospital between December 2012 and April 
2015. The study was conducted in accordance with the tenets of 
the Declaration of Helsinki. Data collection and analysis were 
approved by the hospital ethics committee, and informed consent 
was obtained from all participants. RP patients were diagnosed 
based on clinical history, funduscopic appearance, visual field 
testing, and full-field electroretinogram records. All participants 
underwent a complete ophthalmologic examination, including 
measurement of BCVA, noncontact tonometry, slit-lamp bio-
microscopy, indirect ophthalmoscopy, color fundus photogra-
phy, full-field electroretinography (ERG), central visual field, and 
spectral-domain OCT. BCVA, expressed as the logarithm of the 
minimum angle of resolution (log MAR), finger count, hand 
movement, light perception, and no light perception were 
designated as 2, 3, 4, and 5, respectively. All participants followed 
the selection criteria: ERG was markedly reduced or had no rod 
response, and the area of central visual field was lost severely. 
Although some eyes were with good BCVA, the central visual field 
defect was severe (mean deviation &lt;À20 dB by Octopus Field 
Analyzer (Haag-Streit, Koeniz, Switzerland)), and the retinal 
atrophy of the eyes was severely shown by the fundus images. </p>

<p>2.2. Optical coherence tomography evaluation </p>

<p>High-definition (HD)-OCT (Cirrus high-definition 5000 OCT) 
with an axial resolution of 5 mm was performed on all 70 eyes 
with RP and 65 eyes of the normal controls. Cross-section images 
of 6 mm horizontal and vertical scans through the central fovea 
were obtained. A macular cube 512 Â 128 scan was obtained by 
Cirrus HD-OCT to obtain the central fovea thicknesses (CFT) 
and GCIPLT data. The macula thickness and the outer rings, </p>

<p>bounded by 3 and 6 mm concentric circles, were constructed 
using the automated software algorithm. Central subfield 
thickness was defined as the average thickness in the central 1 
mm subfield centered on the fovea. Average macular thickness, 
foveal thickness, outer macular (superior, nasal, inferior, and 
temporal) thicknesses, and macular volume were obtained for 
each eye. The GCA algorithm was incorporated into the newer 
<rs id="software-6" type="software">Cirrus OCT</rs> software version <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">6.5</rs> with the annulus of inner 
vertical and horizontal diameters of 1 and 1.2 mm, respectively, 
and outer vertical and horizontal diameters of 4 and 4.8 mm, 
respectively. As reported, [27] the outer ring size includes the area 
where the GCL is thickest in a healthy eye. The GCA algorithm 
identifies the outer boundaries of RNFL and IPL, between which 
is the GCIPL layer. GCIPLT will be analyzed according to 8 
parameters-average, minimum, and 6 sectors (superonasal, 
superior, superotemporal, inferotemporal, inferior, and infer-
onasal)-by the GCA algorithm embedded in Cirrus OCT. 
Grayscale images were used for a more precise identification and 
measurement of the EZ. Length was measured in the horizontal 
and vertical scans, and an average value was obtained. Outer 
retinal thickness (ORT) was defined as the region from the outer 
plexiform layer to the retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) layer/ 
Bruch complex, consisting of the outer plexiform layer, outer 
nuclear layer, extend limiting membrane (ELM), myoid zone, EZ, 
interdigitation zone, and RPE/Bruch complex. ORT was 
measured 1 mm from the fovea in the horizontal and vertical 
scans, and an average value was obtained. 
To measure RNFL thickness, 200 Â 200 axial scans were used 
in a 6 Â 6 mm 2 area around the optic disc cube. The software 
automatically detected the center of the optic disc and extracted a 
3.46-mm-diameter peripapillary circle to calculate RNFL 
thickness at each point of the circle. Four-quadrant thickness 
and global 360° average thickness provided by Cirrus OCT were 
used in the study, and the correlation between GCIPL and 
papillary RNFL thicknesses was analyzed. 
CFT and GCIPLT were classified into 3 grades according to the 
statistical percentile (33.3% and 66.6%). EZ appearance in the 
OCT images was graded from 1 to 3 as follows: Grade 1, 
shortened EZ (obtained from cross-section of 6 mm horizontal 
and vertical scans) more than 1 mm; Grade 2, shortened EZ less 
than 1 mm; and Grade 3, EZ not visible. </p>

<p>2.3. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed with the Statistical Package for 
the Social Sciences (<rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs>) for Windows (version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">20.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>.; 
Chicago, IL). Photographs were made using <rs id="software-5" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">20.0</rs> and <rs id="software-0" type="software">Graph 
Pad Prism5</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Graph Pad Software, Inc.</rs>., La Jolla, CA). 
Differences between the RP patients and the normal controls were 
tested with the Mann-Whitney U test and the Kruskal-Wallis test. 
Associations between the various OCT parameters and BCVA were 
examined using Spearman rank correlation. All factors affecting 
visual acuity were analyzed further by multiple linear regressions. 
Criterion significance was assessed at the P &lt; 0.05 level. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>Seventy eyes of 35 RP patients and 65 eyes without retinal 
diseases were enrolled in the study. One eye with unacceptable 
GCIPL OCT image and 1 eye with an unreliable papillary RNFL 
OCT image were excluded in RP group, so there were 68 eyes 
analyzed in the study. There were no statistically significant 
differences in age or gender between the RP patients and the 
normal controls. </p>

<p>Liu et al. Medicine (2016) 95:52 
Medicine </p>



<p>3.1. Characteristics of RP </p>

<p>As shown in Fig. 1, the typical fundus changes in RP patients 
include bone spicule-shaped pigment deposits, attenuation of the 
retinal vessels, waxy pallor of the optic disc, and various degrees 
of retinal atrophy. A disrupted EZ, concentric constriction of the 
visual field, and nonrecordable ERG responses are found in the 
late stage of RP. </p>

<p>3.2. Analysis of retinal thickness in macular area </p>

<p>The macular thickness analysis, including the central subfield, 
outer ring, area thickness, and posterior pole retinal volume are 
listed in Table 1. CFT and area macular thickness were 216.2 ± 
66.7 and 239.2 ± 32.4 mm in the RP patients, respectively, and in </p>

<p>the control group were 245.2 ± 22.4 and 283.0 ± 14.0 mm. 
Posterior pole retinal volume was 8.6 ± 1.2 mm 3 in the RP 
patients, while in control group was 10.2 ± 0.5 mm 3 . These values 
were significantly lower in RP patients (P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>3.3. Thickness map and macular retinal ganglion 
cell-inner plexiform layer thickness </p>

<p>As shown in Fig. 2, the images showed the retinal GCIPLT map, 
and the OCT parameter was measured in 6 sectors. Representa-
tive case of normal subject (left eye of 50-year-old male) (Fig. 2A). 
Representative case of RP patient (left eye of 54-year-old male) 
(Fig. 2B). The images showed that RP patients had thinner GCIPL 
thickness than normal controls in 6 sectors. The original data of </p>

<p>Figure 1. Characteristics of retinitis pigmentosa. (A) Fundus photograph with a black line (arrow) indicates the direction of the horizontal scan. (B) A shortened 
ellipsoid zone (white arrow) can be seen; the best corrected visual acuity was 0.5. (C) The extent of the visual field was less than 15°. (D) Electroretinography 
responses were almost nonrecordable. </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Comparison of macular thickness and volume between RP patients and normal controls. </p>

<p>RP group 
Control group </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>Mean ± standard 
deviation 
Range </p>

<p>95% Confidence 
interval </p>

<p>Mean ± standard 
deviation 
Range </p>

<p>95% Confidence 
interval 
t 
P </p>

<p>Macular thickness analysis, macular cube 
Central foveal thickness, mm 
216.2 ± 66.7 
89.0-434.0 
200.3-232.0 
245.2 ± 22.4 
199.0-295.0 
239.6-250.7 
À3.593 &lt;0.001 
Superior retinal thickness, mm 
241.4 ± 28.0 
168.0-303.0 
234.7-248.0 
285.0 ± 19.5 
179.0-319.0 
280.1-289.9 
À7.934 &lt;0.001 
Temporal retinal thickness, mm 
231.2 ± 33.2 
185.0-360.0 
223.3-239.1 
269.4 ± 15.1 
239.0-315.0 
265.7-273.2 
À7.984 &lt;0.001 
Inferior retinal thickness, mm 
239.4 ± 30.7 
178.0-307.0 
232.1-246.7 
273.1 ± 14.3 
246.0-320.0 
269.5-276.7 
À6.738 &lt;0.001 
Nasal retinal thickness, mm 
263.7 ± 37.5 
155.0-340.0 
254.7-272.6 
303.4 ± 17.8 
254.0-349.0 
298.9-307.8 
À6.729 &lt;0.001 
6 Â 6 square area retinal thickness, mm 
239.2 ± 32.4 
159.0-311.0 
231.4-246.9 
283.0 ± 14.0 
230.0-318.0 
279.5-286.4 
À7.734 &lt;0.001 
6 Â 6 square area retinal volume, mm 3 
8.6 ± 1.2 
5.7-11.2 
8.3-8.9 
10.2 ± 0.5 
8.3-11.5 
10.2-10.1 
À7.707 &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>RP = retinitis pigmentosa. </p>

<p>Liu et al. Medicine (2016) 95:52 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>GCIPLT in RP patients are shown in Supplementary material, 
http://links.lww.com/MD/B487. </p>

<p>3.4. Analysis of GCIPLT and ORT in macular area </p>

<p>GCIPLT was measured in 6 different locations: superior, 
superotemporal, inferotemporal, inferior, inferonasal, and super-
onasal (Fig. 3A). The mean GCIPLT was 54.7 ± 18.9 mm in the 
RP patients and 85.6 ± 6.8 mm in the normal controls (Table 2). </p>

<p>GCIPLT in all quadrants became thinner significantly (P &lt; 
0.001), especially in the temporal area (Fig. 3B). Detailed 
GCIPLT data in the different quadrants are presented in Table 2. 
The corresponding ORT was classified into 3 grades according to 
the statistical percentile (33.3% and 66.6%) of GCIPLT: 43.1, 
73.3, and 101.4 mm, respectively. The GCIPLT thinning was 
consistent with the ORT thinning (P &lt; 0.001). The correlation 
between GCIPLT and ORT was significant when evaluated with 
a linear regression model (r = 0.436, P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Thickness map and macular retinal ganglion cell-inner plexiform layer (GCIPL) thickness. The ganglion cell analysis algorithm identifies the outer 
boundaries of retinal nerve fiber layer and inner plexiform layer, between which is the GCIPL layer. (A) Representative case of normal subject (left eye of 50-year-old 
male). (B) Representative case of retinitis pigmentosa (RP) patient (left eye of 54-year-old male). The images showed that RP patients had thinner GCIPL thickness 
compared with normal controls in 6 sectors. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Ganglion cell-inner plexiform layer thickness (GCIPLT) and outer retinal thickness (ORT) measurements. (A) Representative optical coherence 
tomography image of a right eye in 6 sectors (superonasal, superior, superotemporal, inferotemporal, inferior, and inferonasal). (B) GCIPL thickness was measured 
using the Cirrus linear measurement tool at 6 locations. Compared with healthy eyes, the thickness of the ganglion cell-plexiform layer in various quadrants was 
significantly thinner in retinitis pigmentosa patients. ORT was defined as a region from the outer plexiform layer to the retinal pigment epithelium layer/Bruch 
complex. The thickness of the outer retina was classified into 3 grades according to the statistical percentile (33.3% and 66.6%) of GCIPLT. (C) The results showed 
that the thinning of GCIPLT was coincident with the thinning of ORT (P &lt; 0.001). (D) The correlation between GCIPLT and ORT was significant when evaluated by a 
linear regression model (r = 0.436, P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Liu et al. Medicine (2016) 95:52 
Medicine </p>



<p>3.5. Analysis of peripapillary RNFL thickness </p>

<p>The thickness of the peripapillary RNFL in the different 
quadrants is presented in Table 3. The mean thickness of the 
peripapillary RNFL was 102.1 ± 24.1 mm in the RP patients and 
101.1 ± 10.5 mm in the control group; the difference was not 
significant. The peripapillary RNFL thicknesses in the superior, 
inferior, nasal, and temporal quadrants were 113.6 ± 35.8, 117.2 
± 36.7, 83.0 ± 24.8, and 95.6 ± 21.8 mm, respectively, in the RP 
patients and 124.2 ± 21.0, 134.7 ± 18.8, 71.7 ± 11.0, and 73.7 ± 
10.7 mm, respectively, in the control group. Compared with the 
normal controls, RNFL thicknesses in the RP patients were 
significantly thicker in the temporal and nasal areas (P = 0.001) 
and thinner in the superior and inferior areas (P &lt; 0.05) (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>3.6. Length of EZ and ELM line in RP patients </p>

<p>In the RP patients, the EZ and ELM lines were present in varying 
lengths at the fovea and absent outside the macula. The lengths of 
the residual EZ and ELM lines depicted in the OCT images were 
measured (Fig. 5A), and the average lengths were 911.1 ± 208.8 
and 1621.2 ± 233.5 mm, respectively. The length of the ELM line 
was significantly longer than the average EZ length (P &lt; 0.005) 
(Fig. 5B). The correlation between ELM line length and EZ 
shortening was strong (r = 0.862, P &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 5C). The 
original data of EZ length in RP patients are shown in 
Supplementary material, http://links.lww.com/MD/B487. </p>

<p>3.7. Correlations between BCVA and CFT, GCIPLT, 
and EZ length </p>

<p>CFT and GCIPLT were classified into 3 grades according to the 
statistical percentile (33.3% and 66.6%). The length of the EZ in </p>

<p>the OCT images was graded from 1 to 3, as follows: Grade 1, 
average EZ greater than 1 mm, and the longest EZ was less than 3 
mm; Grade 2, abnormal EZ less than 1 mm; and Grade 3, EZ not 
visible. As shown in Fig. 6A1-C1, RP patients with a thicker 
CFT, GCIPLT and longer EZ had better BCVA (P &lt; 0.001). The 
results of an evaluation using a linear regression model showed 
that there was a significant positive correlation between BCVA 
and CFT (r = À0.5933, P &lt; 0.001), GCIPLT (r = À0.452, P &lt; 
0.001), and EZ length (r = À0.7622, P &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 6A2-C2); 
the EZ at the fovea demonstrated the strongest relationship with 
BCVA followed by GCIPLT and CFT. All of the factors affecting 
visual acuity were further analyzed by multiple linear regressions. 
Regression coefficients for significant factors are compared in 
Table 4. The results show that CFT (Beta [B] = À0.286; P = 
0.014), GCIPLT (Beta [B] = À0.217; P = 0.047), and EZ length 
(Beta [B] = À0.311; P = 0.013) were associated significantly with 
BCVA. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we aimed to investigate the changes in retinal 
photoreceptor EZ and postreceptor retinal layer in RP patients by 
GCA and analyze the relationship between the OCT parameters 
and BCVA. First, we examined CFT, and the results showed that 
the RP patients had significant thinning of CFT compared with 
the controls. The RP patients with thicker CFT had better BCVA, 
so there was a positive correlation between CFT and BCVA, 
which was consistent with the previous studies. [15,28] 
The earliest histopathological changes in all forms of RP 
involve shortening of the photoreceptor segments, but there are 
fewer articles about inner retinal thickness. The previous study 
reported that the inner nuclear, inner plexiform, and retinal </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Comparison of GCIPLT between RP patients and normal controls. </p>

<p>RP group 
Control group </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>Mean ± standard 
deviation 
Range </p>

<p>95% Confidence 
interval </p>

<p>Mean ± standard 
deviation 
Range </p>

<p>95% Confidence 
interval 
t 
P </p>

<p>GCIPL, mm 
Average 
54.7 ± 18.9 
18.0-110.0 
50.2-59.2 
85.6 ± 6.8 
70.0-103.0 
83.8-87.3 
À8.579 
&lt;0.001 
Minimum 
32.6 ± 21.2 
0.0-97.0 
27.5-37 
81.5 ± 9.3 
43.0-101.0 
79.2-83.9 
À8.923 
&lt;0.001 
Superior 
55.1 ± 19.1 
13.0-108.0 
50.6-59.7 
86.4 ± 7.8 
71.0-103.0 
84.4-88.4 
À8.476 
&lt;0.001 
Superotemporal 
47.8 ± 22.1 
7.0-107.0 
42.5-53.1 
85.0 ± 6.4 
74.0-101.0 
83.3-86.6 
À8.111 
&lt;0.001 
Inferotemporal 
48.6 ± 22.8 
0.0-102.0 
43.1-54.1 
85.8 ± 6.9 
71.0-105.0 
84.1-87.6 
À7.839 
&lt;0.001 
Inferior 
55.0 ± 20.6 
14.0-110.0 
50.0-60.0 
82.8 ± 7.4 
57.0-98.0 
81.0-84.7 
À7.757 
&lt;0.001 
Inferonasal 
60.1 ± 22.2 
11.0-111.0 
54.8-65.5 
86.0 ± 7.6 
69.0-105.0 
84.1-87.9 
À7.543 
&lt;0.001 
Superonasal 
60.1 ± 23.0 
8.0-126.0 
54.6-65.6 
87.9 ± 8.1 
70.0-107.0 
85.9-89.9 
À7.741 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>GCIPL = ganglion cell-inner plexiform layer, RP = retinitis pigmentosa. </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Comparison of RNFL thicknesses between RP patients and normal controls. </p>

<p>RP group 
Control group </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>Mean ± standard 
deviation 
Range </p>

<p>95% Confidence 
interval </p>

<p>Mean ± standard 
deviation 
Range </p>

<p>95% Confidence 
interval 
t 
P </p>

<p>RNFL thickness, mm 
Mean 
102.1 ± 24.1 
61.0-165.0 
96.3-107.9 
101.1 ± 10.5 
83.0-128.0 
98.4-103.8 
À0.148 
0.882 
Superior 
113.6 ± 35.8 
7.0-197.0 
105.1-122.1 
124.2 ± 21.0 
72.0-174.0 
118.9-129.5 
À2.091 
0.037 
Temporal 
95.6 ± 21.8 
53.0-158.0 
90.4-100.8 
73.7 ± 10.7 
52.0-99.0 
71.0-76.4 
À6.038 
&lt;0.001 
Inferior 
117.2 ± 36.7 
43.0-205.0 
108.5-126.0 
134.7 ± 18.8 
100.0-197.0 
130.0-139.5 
À3.340 
0.001 
Nasal 
83.0 ± 24.8 
40.0-217.0 
77.0-88.9 
71.7 ± 11.0 
48.0-94.0 
68.9-74.5 
À3.230 
0.001 </p>

<p>RNFL = retinal nerve fiber layer, RP = retinitis pigmentosa. </p>

<p>Liu et al. Medicine (2016) 95:52 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>GCLs were relatively intact. [11] In addition, the clinical and 
morphometry studies showed the similar results that inner retinal 
layers were preserved in the RP groups. [10,13] What is more, even 
inner retinal thickening was detected, which was related with 
neuronal-glial remodeling response to photoreceptor loss in RP 
patients, [29,30] but the patients in later stage with decreased inner 
retinal thickness was also proved. [12] In addition, the histopath-
ologic studies reported that RP had significantly fewer ganglion 
cells than those of the control group, [14] and the thickness of GCL 
combined IPL was significantly thinner in RP by OCT. [15] In 
addition, the new articles showed that ganglion cells decreased 
because of inherited photoreceptor degeneration in animal 
studies, [31,32] which was related with deficit of the retrograde 
axonal transport lead by inherited photoreceptor degenera-
tion. [33] Therefore, in the present study, we used GCA as a new </p>

<p>method for assessing the structural changes of GCIPL, which is 
related to the photoreceptor degeneration in RP patients. 
Compared with the measurement in previous studies, GCA 
assesses the thickness by a macular cube 512 Â 128 scan from 
more sites; as a result, we can obtain more detail and accurate 
GCIPLT data by the GCA combined with the modern OCT 
device with an axial resolution of 5 mm. Our results showed that 
GCIPLT in all quadrants exhibited significant thinning and that 
the thinning was greater in the superior and temporal quadrants 
than in the nasal and inferior quadrants, which indicated that the 
RP patients had decreased retinal thickness both in outer retina 
and inner retina in our study. 
While the thinning of ORT has been known, whether there is a 
relationship between GCIPLT and ORT has not been reported in 
RP patients. In the present study, we assessed the correlation </p>

<p>Figure 4. Peripapillary retinal nerve fiber layer (RNFL) thickness measurements. (A) Representative papillary optical coherence tomography image of a right eye in 
retinitis pigmentosa (RP) patient with RNFL thickness map and RNFL thickness values in different regions. (B)The results showed that peripapillary RNFL 
thicknesses did not differ significantly between the RP and control groups, but in the temporal and nasal quadrants, the RP group had a significantly thicker RNFL, 
while RNFL thinning was seen in the superior and inferior areas. However, total RNFL thickness was greater in the superior and inferior areas than in the temporal 
and nasal areas. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Ellipsoid zone (EZ) and extend limiting membrane (ELM) line. Grayscale images were used for the measurement of the EZ and ELM. Length was 
measured in the horizontal and vertical scans, and an average value was obtained. (A) The disrupted photoreceptor EZ ( </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>) and ELM ( # ) can be seen in the optical 
coherence tomography imagine. (B) Mean lengths of the EZ and ELM lines in 68 eyes with retinitis pigmentosa. ELM length was significantly greater than EZ length 
(P &lt; 0.005, t = À3.107). (C) There is a significant positive correlation between the lengths of the EZ and ELM lines (r = 0.862, P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Liu et al. Medicine (2016) 95:52 
Medicine </p>



<p>between GCIPLT and ORT, and the results showed that GCIPLT 
thinning was significantly related to the decreased ORT as well as 
the macular retinal thickness. We further assessed the correlation 
between GCIPLT and BCVA, RP patients with thicker GCIPLT 
had better BCVA, but the correlation was moderate. The reasons 
might be that some eyes with poor visual acuity still preserved the 
thickness of the RGC, and the present OCT could not distinguish 
the transition between the GCL and the IPL. So a larger study 
cohort and new OCT with a more precise segmentation of the 
retinal layers is needed in the future study. To summarize, the 
inner retina might be relative preserved in the early stage of RP; 
the thickness was decreased with the progression of the disease, 
especially in the late stage and advanced ones. 
RNFL is the axon originating from the ganglion cells, so we 
measured the thickness to see whether the papillary RNFL 
thinning occurred along with the degeneration of ganglion cell. 
In the previous studies, the changes in RNFL thickness are 
inconsistent, including thickening, thinning, or relative unifor-</p>

<p>mity, measured by time domain OCT or spectral domain 
OCT. [34-38] In addition, the relevant studies have indicated that 
RNFL thickening was most common in the temporal area, and 
RNFL thinning was found in the nasal and inferior regions. [35,37] 
However, results in our study showed that the average papillary 
RNFL thickness did not change significantly compared with the 
normal controls. But there existed a spatial preference of RNFL 
thickening in the temporal and nasal directions and RNFL 
thinning in the inferior and superior areas. These findings suggest 
that RNFL thickness changed in the RP eyes along with the 
degeneration of ganglion cell. But the reasons accounting for 
RNFL thickening or thinning in different areas need to be 
investigated in further researches. 
Although the mechanism of RNFL degeneration is different 
from glaucoma, the orders of RNFL thinning are similar in the 
sequence of RNFL thinning. [39] A recent study reported that 
compromised axonal transport would lead to RGC loss and 
decreased RNFL thickness during the developing process of RP, </p>

<p>Figure 6. Relationship between best corrected visual acuity (BCVA) and central fovea thicknesses (CFT), ganglion cell-inner plexiform layer thickness (GCIPLT), and 
ellipsoid zone (EZ). CFT and GCIPLT were graded from 1 to 3 according to statistical percentile (33.3% and 66.6%). The appearance of the EZ in the optical coherence 
tomography (OCT) images was graded from 1 to 3: Grade 1, shortened EZ greater than 1 mm; Grade 2, shortened EZ less than 1 mm; and Grade 3, EZ not visible. Mean 
visual acuity (log MAR units) as a function of the grade of the OCT parameters. (A1-C1) The difference among the 3 groups was statistically significant (P &lt; 0.005). Retinitis 
pigmentosa patients with thicker CFT and GCIPLT and longer EZ had better BCVA (P &lt; 0.001). (A2-C2) The correlations among BCVA and CFT, GCIPLT, and EZ were 
evaluated using a linear regression model. The results showed significant positive correlations among BCVA and CFT (r = À0.5933, P &lt; 0.001), GCIPLT (r = À0.452, P &lt; 
0.001), and EZ (r = À0.7622, P &lt; 0.001); EZ at the fovea demonstrated a stronger relationship with BCVA. </p>

<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>Multivariate logistic regression analysis of different factors significantly affecting BCVA. </p>

<p>Unstandardized coefficients 
Standardized coefficients </p>

<p>Model 
B 
SE 
Beta (B) 
t 
P </p>

<p>(Constant) 
3.679 
0.586 
6.275 
0.000 
CFT 
À006 
0.003 
À286 
À2.517 
0.014 
GCIPLT 
À017 
0.008 
À217 
À2.024 
0.047 
EZ band 
À001 
0.000 
À311 
À2.547 
0.013 </p>

<p>BCVA = best corrected visual acuity, CFT = central foveal thickness, EZ = ellipsoid zone, GCIPLT = ganglion cell-inner plexiform layer thickness. </p>

<p>Liu et al. Medicine (2016) 95:52 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>and the maximum transneuronal damage occurred mainly in 
the inferonasal quadrant, [35] which was consistent with the 
results in our study. Apart from RNFL thinning, the reasons for 
RNFL thickening have been studied, it has been reported that 
with the progress of RNFL degeneration, the proliferative 
glial cell displacing the atrophic nerve fiber and edematous 
changes of the residual RNFL were attributed to a thickened 
RNFL. [34] Hood et al [11] speculated that a purely mechanical 
factor compelling the thickening RNFL partially filled the 
quadrants where the receptors degenerated. As a result, RNFL 
thickening is found in the area where GCIPL thinning is greatest 
in RP patients. So while the regions of GCIPL thinning are 
corresponded to the areas of RNFL defects in glaucoma, [40] it is 
almost the opposite in RP patients. The results suggest that it 
should be prudent to make optimal use of RNFL thickness for 
predicting the status of RGC in patients with RP. Refer to the 
discrepancies among the different studies, it might stem from 
differences in OCT devices and the discordant stages of RP in the 
study populations. 
With the progression of RP, EZ disappeared from the 
peripheral part toward the fovea on the OCT images. Therefore, 
measuring the length of the residual EZ in RP patients is very 
useful for estimating residual central visual function. According 
to the length of the EZ, RP patients in our study were graded into 
3 groups: Grade 1, shortened EZ greater than 1 mm; Grade 2, 
shortened EZ less than 1 mm; and Grade 3, EZ not visible. The 
relationship between BCVA and EZ was significant, which is 
agreed with the results in the previous studies. [41,42] Thus, the 
average length of the EZ is an important OCT parameter for 
monitoring visual acuity in RP patients. 
With regard to the outer hyperreflected lines, the ELM line was 
found to be longer than the EZ. Pathological studies about RP 
confirmed that the earliest histopathological change is in the 
outer segments of photoreceptors, [9] where EZ is located. In 
addition, ELM consists of photoreceptor inner segment and 
Müller cell processes, [43] so EZ became disorganized earlier than 
ELM, but the shortened ELM lines were significantly related with 
EZ defect. 
Taken together, GCA is a new method to measure the GCIPLT, 
which helps to prove the real changes in the inner retinal layers of 
RP patients. Our further results showed that postreceptor retinal 
layer (GCIPLT) became significantly thinner along with the 
retinal photoreceptor EZ degeneration in all quarter, which was 
correlated with BCVA in RP patients. So, we assess retinal layer 
changes with the advent of the GCA software combined with the 
modern OCT devices from a new perspective and to quantify the 
changes both in outer and inner retinal layers, which are very 
useful for diagnosis, staging, and prognosis of RP. </p>









</text></tei>