<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5064647" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Mesenchymal stem cells are known to exert immunomodulatory effects in inflammatory 
diseases. Immuneregulatory cells lead to progressive joint destruction in rheumatoid 
arthritis (RA). Proinflammatory cytokines, such as tumour necrosis factor α (TNF-α) and 
interleukins (ILs) are the main players. Here, we studied progenitor cells from RA cartilage 
(RA-CPCs) that are positive for IL-17 receptors to determinate the effects of inflammation 
on their chondrogenic potenial. IL-17A/F reduced the chondrogenic potential of these 
cells via the upregulation of RUNX2 protein and enhanced IL-6 protein and MMP3 mRNA 
levels. Blocking antibodies against IL-17 positively influenced their repair potential. Fur-
thermore, treating the RA-CPCs with the anti-human IL-17 antibody secukinumab or 
the anti-TNF-α antibody adalimumab reduced the proinflammatory IL-6 protein level 
and positively influenced the secretion of anti-inflammatory IL-10 protein. Additionally, 
adalimumab and secukinumab in particular reduced RUNX2 protein to promote chon-
drogenesis. The amelioration of inflammation, particularly via IL-17 antagonism, might 
be a new therapeutic approach for enhancing intrinsic cartilage repair mechanisms in RA 
patients. </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 13.0</rs>C 2015 The Authors. European Journal of Immunology published by 
WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim. </p>

<p>www.eji-journal.eu </p>

<p>Eur. J. Immunol. 2016. 46: 440-445 </p>

<p>Immunomodulation </p>



<p>drafted the manuscript. B.M. performed the knee arthroplasties. 
B.S. and S.T. performed the data acquisition and analysis and 
revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final 
manuscript. This work was supported by a grant from the German 
Research Foundation in the Priority Programme "Osteoimmunol-
ogy -Immunobone" 1468, DFG, BL 1122/1-1. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest: The authors declare that they have no conflict 
of interest nor did they receive financial support other than from 
the German Research Foundation. </p>



<p>Received: 9/7/2015 
Revised: 8/10/2015 
Accepted: 6/11/2015 
Accepted article online: 12/11/2015 </p>

<p>C 2015 The Authors. European Journal of Immunology published by 
WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim. </p>

<p>www.eji-journal.eu </p>

</text></tei>