<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5081317" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Study Design: Descriptive cross-sectional study. 
Purpose: To determine the prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in patients with degenerative diseases of the spine about to undergo 
spinal surgery and the relations between such deficiency and potential risk factors. 
Overview of Literature: Vitamin D has a major role in musculoskeletal system health maintenance. Recently, studies on degenera-
tive diseases of the spine have shown a high prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in patients undergoing spine surgery. 
Methods: Serum levels of 25(OH)D were determined by an electrochemiluminescence detection assay. The other variables were de-
termined through relevant questionnaires, and the data was analyzed through analysis of variance, t-test, chi-square and multivariate 
logistic regression analysis. 
Results: A total of 110 patients were enrolled in the study. The mean serum level of 25(OH)D was 27.45±18.75 ng/mL, and 44.5% of 
patients showed vitamin D deficiency (25(OH)D&lt;20 ng/mL), with an additional 17.3% of patients having a serum level of 25(OH)D that 
was insufficient (20≤25(OH)D&lt;30 ng/mL). The prevalence of vitamin D deficiency was significantly higher in the younger age group 
compared to the older age group (p&lt;0.001) and the ones without a history of taking vitamin D supplements (p=0.013). Compared to 
men, women showed significantly higher levels of vitamin D (p=0.029). 
Conclusions: A high prevalence of vitamin D deficiency is seen in patients with degenerative diseases of the spine. On the other 
hand, the conventional risk factors such as old age or female sex alone did not seem to be sufficient in determining the likelihood of 
deficiency. Thus, it is recommended that vitamin D deficiency prevention strategies comprise a broader spectrum of the population 
through which such degenerative diseases and their consequences may be prevented or delayed. </p>

<p>Vitamin D is a fat-soluble steroid with the vast majority 
(80%-90%) of the vitamin D required by the body is pro-</p>

<p>vided by the conversion of precursors in the skin under 
the influence of UV light, usually from the sun; the rest 
(10%-20%) comes through food intake. It has been shown 
that vitamin D is involved in proliferation, differentiation, </p>

<p>Vitamin D deficiency and degenerative diseases of the spine </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>and maturation of chondrocytes [1], synthesis of proteo-
glycans-making up the matrix of intervertebral discs-
and also in regulation of plasma sulfate levels required for 
intracellular sulfation of proteoglycans [2]. For the health 
of intervertebral discs, active metabolites of vitamin D 
regulate proliferation, expression of matrix genes and 
production of certain proteins and cytokines in cells of 
annulus fibrosus and nucleus pulposus, the two macro-
structural components of the discs [3,4]. 
Spine diseases are relatively common among the mus-
culoskeletal diseases so that 50%-80% of adults experi-
ence at least one episode of low back pain (LBP) in their 
lifetime [5], and intervertebral disc degeneration is one of 
the primary causes considered for LBP [6]. 
Several studies have shown the epidemic hypovitamin-
osis D in today's society-both in developed and develop-
ing countries-and various studies have been conducted 
on the effects of vitamin D deficiency and its risk factors 
in various diseases including musculoskeletal diseases. 
However, according to our literature search, few studies 
have been devoted to degenerative diseases of the spine. 
Yet, some recent reports in this area have indicated a 
high prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in these patients 
[7-10]. 
Considering the issues resulting from vitamin D de-
ficiency in the musculoskeletal system as well as the 
medical need to address degenerative spinal lesions and 
the individual and societal costs involved-such as with 
reconstructive surgery-it seemed rational to conduct a 
study on evaluating the vitamin D levels in patients with 
degenerative disease of the spine. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>The research was an observational descriptive study in 
a cross-sectional format. It used convenience sampling 
to select the subjects. All the eligible patients had been 
referred to the neurosurgery unit in the Shariati Hospital 
in Isfahan, Iran, and were enrolled until a predetermined 
number of patients were reached. The sampling procedure 
began in late fall of 2013 and continued until late summer 
of 2014. </p>

<p>1. Inclusion criteria </p>

<p>Adult patients with degenerative spinal diseases such 
as intervertebral disc herniation, spinal canal stenosis </p>

<p>(based on magnetic resonance imaging, MRI) and spinal 
instability (defined as "functional instability," which re-
fers to a lack of neuromuscular control of the joint during 
activities) who had not responded to conservative and 
medical treatments, and thus were scheduled for a surgi-
cal procedure, were recruited after indicating their con-
sent. </p>

<p>2. Exclusion criteria </p>

<p>These included: (1) history of any fracture in the last 
month, (2) any infection or malignancy in the spine, 
(3) inflammatory spondyloarthropathy, (4) evidence of 
metabolic bone disease (such as hypo-and hyperpara-
thyroidism), (5) concomitant diseases influencing vita-
min D metabolism (including chronic liver and kidney 
disease, malabsorption, systemic infections and neo-
plasms), (6) psychiatric disorders and neurodegenerative 
disorders, and (7) patient withdrawal of participation in 
the project. </p>

<p>3. Data collection tools </p>

<p>For the study, blood samples were collected over a one-
week period before the surgery and then analyzed by an 
autoanalyzer device (Roche/Hitachi Diagnostic Elecsys 
2010 Immunoassay), and the 25(OH)D serum levels were 
determined. The test was via competitive protein binding 
with electrochemiluminescence detection. 
According to previous studies [11-13], patients were di-
vided into 3 groups based on the serum level of 25(OH)D: 
(1) Deficient group: defined by the serum level of 25(OH) 
D&lt;20 ng/mL. (2) Insufficient group: defined by the serum 
level of 20≤25(OH)D&lt;30 ng/mL. (3) Normal group: de-
fined by the serum level of 25(OH)D≥30 ng/mL. 
Patient body mass index (BMI) values were calculated 
from their height and weight, and they were classified 
into 4 BMI groups, based on the CDC classification [14]: 
(1) Underweight (BMI&lt;18.5 kg/m 
2 ), (2) Normal weight 
(18.5≤BMI&lt;25 kg/m 
2 ), (3) Overweight (25≤BMI&lt;30 kg/ 
m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>), (4) Obese (30≤BMI kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). 
Interviews and questionnaires were used to determine 
the status of other variables including age, sex, smoking 
status, whether taking vitamin D supplements and pain 
severity. Age values were categorized into three groups: 
(1) 20 to 39 years old (young), (2) 40 to 59 years (middle-
aged), and (3) ≥60 years (old). </p>

<p>Farid Zolfaghari et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2016;10(5):834-842 </p>

<p>Smoking was defined as habitual cigarette smoking 
during the last 6 months. The history of taking the vi-
tamin D supplements was defined as the consumption 
of any pharmaceutical products containing vitamin D 
(including oral and injection products) during the last 6 
months. 
For the severity of pain, Quadruple VAS (Visual Ana-
logue Scale) was used. 
The analysis of the collected data was with <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS statistics package</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA). It 
was used for the descriptive statistics including the means, 
ratios and their confidence intervals, and also the dia-
grams and tables. Statistical tests included the indepen-
dent t-test, one-way analysis of variance, chi-square, uni-
variate and multivariate binary logistic regression analysis. 
The significance level was set at 0.05 for all the statistical 
tests. 
The study was evaluated by Ethics Committee for Medi-
cal Research at Isfahan University of Medical Sciences 
(approval/ registration number 493054). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>A total of 110 patients entered the study. The lowest and 
the highest levels of 25(OH)D measured were 3 ng/mL and 
70 ng/mL, respectively. The mean serum level of 25(OH) 
D was 27.45±18.75 ng/mL. For the studied population, 
49 (44.5%), 19 (17.3%), and 42 (38.2%) of the subjects 
were in the deficient, insufficient, and normal groups, </p>

<p>respectively. </p>

<p>1. Supplement consumption and vitamin D serum levels </p>

<p>In total, 42 patients (38.5%) had a history of consumption 
of vitamin D supplements during the last 6 months. The 
groups with and without the history of the consumption 
of vitamin D supplement showed the mean serum level of 
25(OH)D as 37.33±20.31 and 21.06±14.78 ng/mL, respec-
tively (p&lt;0.001). Table 1 shows the supplement consump-
tion status in different groups according to age, sex and 
smoking. </p>

<p>2. Type of pathology and vitamin D serum levels </p>

<p>According to the type of pathology, five groups were de-
fined as follows: (1) lumbar disc herniation, (2) lumbar 
spine stenosis, (3) lumbar spine instability, (4) cervical 
disc herniation, and (5) cervical spine stenosis. 
However in some cases there was a combination of 
pathologies; in such cases, the predominant pathology 
was used for the classification. Frequency, vitamin D 
serum level and also supplement consumption status of 
these groups are shown in Table 2. There were 19 patients 
(17.3%) with cervical spine pathology of the studied 
population and 91 patients (82.7%) with the lumbosacral 
spine pathology. The mean serum level of 25(OH)D was 
14.87±10.86 and 30.07±19.02 ng/mL in these two groups, 
respectively (p&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>Table 1. Supplement consumption status in different groups of age, sex, smoking </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Vitamin D supplement 
p-value 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>Age group 
0.58 </p>

<p>Young 
18 (66.7) 
9 (33.3) </p>

<p>Middle age 
42 (61.8) 
26 (38.2) </p>

<p>Elderly 
7 (50.0) 
7 (50.0) </p>

<p>Sex 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Male 
43 (79.6) 
11 (20.4) </p>

<p>Female 
24 (43.6) 
31 (56.4) </p>

<p>Smoking </p>

<p>Yes 
13 (86.7) 
2 (13.3) 
0.032 </p>

<p>No 
53 (57.6) 
39 (42.4) </p>

<p>Total population 
67 (61.5) 
42 (38.5) 
-</p>

<p>Vitamin D deficiency and degenerative diseases of the spine </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>3. Age and vitamin D serum levels </p>

<p>The youngest and the oldest subjects were 22 and 78 years 
old. The mean age of the population was 47.06±11.94 
years. 
The mean serum level of 25(OH)D was 18.94±14.77 
ng/mL in the young group. It was 28.36±18.99 and 
39.36±17.88 ng/mL in the middle-aged and old groups, 
respectively (p=0.003). 
The relationship between the different age groups was 
studied using the additional test (Post Hoc) of LSD, and 
it was found out that in all cases the level of 25(OH)D 
was significantly higher in the older age group and the 
highest difference was observed between the young and 
old groups (p=0.001). There was no significant difference 
between different age groups in terms of the history of vi-
tamin D supplement use (p=0.58). </p>

<p>4. Sex and vitamin D serum levels </p>

<p>The studied population consisted of 54 male (49.1%) 
and 56 female (50.9%) patients. The mean serum level 
of 25(OH)D was 31.08±20.74 ng/mL in women and 
23.68±15.76 ng/mL in men (p=0.037). Also, vitamin D 
supplement consumption was significantly higher in 
women (p&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>5. Smoking and vitamin D serum levels </p>

<p>For the population, 15 (13.9%) and 93 (86.1%) sub-
jects were smokers and non-smokers, respectively. The 
mean serum level of 25(OH)D was 19.31±15.77 and 
28.69±19.12 ng/mL in smokers and non-smokers, respec-
tively (p=0.074). The consumption of vitamin D supple-
ments was significantly higher in non-smokers (p=0.032). </p>

<p>6. BMI and vitamin D serum levels </p>

<p>In the studied population, 3 (2.9%), 30 (28.6%), 44 
(41.9%), and 28 subjects (26.7%) were in the underweight, 
normal, overweight, and obese categories, respectively. 
The mean serum level of 25(OH)D was 12.33±9.2, 
24.05±17.23, 28.37±17.55, and 25.95±19.07 ng/mL in un-
derweight, normal, over weight and obese groups, respec-
tively (p=0.408). </p>

<p>7. VAS score and vitamin D serum levels </p>

<p>The mean VAS score in the three vitamin D groups was 
as follows: 73.12±12.50, 69.47±11.07, and 73.57±12.94 
in deficient, insufficient, and normal groups, respectively 
(p=0.467). </p>

<p>8. Season of the year for the testing and vitamin D serum 
levels </p>

<p>Sampling was performed from late in fall of 2013 to late in 
summer of 2014. From a total of 110 tests, 52 tests (47.3%) 
were performed in the spring, 12 tests (10.9%) in the sum-
mer, 4 tests (3.6%) in the autumn and 42 tests (38.2%) in 
the winter. 
The mean serum level of 25(OH)D was 27.51±19.74, 
23.38±14.85, 16.75±12.63, and 29.55±18.94 ng/mL in the 
spring, summer, fall, and winter, respectively (p=0.5). 
The univariate binary logistic regression analysis was 
used to assess each of the potential risk factors related to 
the vitamin D deficiency and to determine the odds ratio 
(OR). The relevant results are shown in Table 3. 
After the multivariate binary logistic regression analysis, 
only the age (adjusted OR, 0.17; 95% confidence interval 
[CI], 0.063-0.457; p&lt;0.001) and vitamin D supplement </p>

<p>Table 2. Distribution of all patients, supplement consumption and vitamin D serum level in different groups of pathologies </p>

<p>Type of pathology </p>

<p>All Subjects 
Supplement 
consumption 
Frequency (%) 
25(OH)D </p>

<p>Lumbar disc herniation 
34 (32.1) 
24.03±15.75 
7 (20.6) </p>

<p>Lumbar spine stenosis 
29 (27.4) 
34.99±21.73 
14 (48.3) </p>

<p>Lumbar spine instability 
24 (22.6) 
34.08±18.84 
13 (56.5) </p>

<p>Cervical disc herniation 
12 (11.3) 
11.80±7.50 
3 (25) </p>

<p>Cervical spine stenosis 
7 (6.6) 
20.14±14.13 
3 (42.9) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%) or mean±standard deviation. </p>

<p>Farid Zolfaghari et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2016;10(5):834-842 </p>

<p>consumption (adjusted OR, 2.874; 95% CI, 1.104-7.482; 
p=0.031) remained as predictors for deficiency. Factors 
entered in this analysis were age, sex, smoking status, 
supplement consumption, BMI and season of the year for 
the test. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Although, the degeneration of the vertebral discs is con-
sidered a part of a natural trend in aging, it can become 
accelerated, with the affected individual becoming symp-
tomatic at a younger age. This degeneration can most like-
ly be accounted for by mostly a genetic predisposition and 
partly by environmental factors. The environmental fac-
tors such as heavy physical activity can trigger a cascade 
of molecular events in disc degeneration, exacerbating the 
disorder in a vicious cycle. One of the factors playing a </p>

<p>role in these molecular processes is the vitamin D system. 
Of note, VDRs (vitamin D receptors) are expressed in os-
teoblasts, chondrocytes, and annulus fibrosus and nucleus 
pulposus cells of the discs [3,4]. In addition, vitamin D 
has been demonstrated to affect the proliferation and 
functional regulation of these cells and their production 
of certain proteins and cytokines in vitro. 
However, degenerative changes in bone and cartilage, 
either because of the natural aging or disease, can lead to 
fractures, spine instability and deformity, which can in 
turn result in chronic pain and neurological deficits. Also, 
a poor quality of bone affects the outcome of spine surger-
ies, especially instrumented ones, resulting in undesirable 
consequences. 
In a study of 360 patients with chronic LBP, the preva-
lence of severe vitamin D deficiency (&lt;9 ng/mL) was 
reported as 83% [15]. Stoker et al. [7] studied 313 patients </p>

<p>Table 3. Result from Univariate binary logistic regression analysis for potential risk factors of vitamin D deficiency </p>

<p>variable 
25(OH)D&lt;30 
frequency (%) </p>

<p>30≤25(OH)D 
frequency (%) 
Odds ratio 
95% Confidence 
interval 
p-value </p>

<p>Vitamin D supplement </p>

<p>Yes 
20 (47.6) 
22 (52.4) 
Reference 
-
-</p>

<p>No 
48 (71.6) 
19 (28.4) 
2.779 
1.242-6.219 
0.013 </p>

<p>Age group </p>

<p>Young 
25 (92.6) 
2 (7.4) 
45.833 
6.689-314.07 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Middle age 
40 (58.0) 
29 (42.0) 
5.057 
1.294-19.767 
0.02 </p>

<p>Elderly 
3 (21.4) 
11 (78.6) 
Reference 
-
-</p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Male 
39 (72.2) 
15 (27.8) 
2.421 
1.095-5.351 
0.029 </p>

<p>Female 
29 (51.8) 
27 (48.2) 
Reference 
-
-</p>

<p>Smoking </p>

<p>Yes 
12 (80.0) 
3 (20) 
2.764 
0.73-10.46 
0.134 </p>

<p>No 
55 (59.1) 
38 (40.9) 
Reference 
-
-</p>

<p>Body mass index </p>

<p>Underweight 
3 (100.0) 
0 
0 
0 
1 </p>

<p>Normal 
22 (73.3) 
8 (26.7) 
Reference 
-
-</p>

<p>Overweight 
25 (56.8) 
19 (43.2) 
0.478 
0.175-1.308 
0.151 </p>

<p>Obese 
18 (64.3) 
10 (35.7) 
0.655 
0.214-2.004 
0.458 </p>

<p>Season </p>

<p>Spring 
32 (61.5) 
20 (38.5) 
0.8 
0.213-3.006 
0.741 </p>

<p>Summer 
8 (66.7) 
4 (33.3) 
Reference 
-
-</p>

<p>Autumn 
3 (75.0) 
1 (25.0) 
1.5 
0.116-19.437 
0.756 </p>

<p>Winter 
25 (59.5) 
17 (40.5) 
0.735 
0.191-2.834 
0.655 </p>

<p>Vitamin D deficiency and degenerative diseases of the spine </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>undergoing surgical spinal fusion and reported that the 
prevalence of vitamin D deficiency (&lt;20 ng/mL) was 27% 
and the prevalence of insufficiency (&lt;30 ng/mL) was 57%. 
Also, in a study of the prevalence of vitamin D deficiency 
in patients with lumbar spinal stenosis (LSS) and its rela-
tion with pain, the prevalence of hypovitaminosis D was 
reported as 74.3% [10]. 
In the present study, we examined the vitamin D serum 
level status of the patients undergoing surgery for degen-
erative diseases of the spine and the relationship between 
the serum levels of vitamin D and the factors that can act 
as risk factors for vitamin D deficiency for these patients. 
A total of 110 patients were enrolled. Of these, 49 patients 
(44.5%) suffered from the vitamin D deficiency; also 19 
(17.3%) had insufficient levels of vitamin D; the remain-
ing 42 patients (38.2%) had normal serum levels. As such, 
61.8% suffered from hypovitaminosis D (25(OH)D&lt;30 
ng/mL), which is a considerable percentage of these pa-
tients. For the group with no history of the consumption 
of vitamin D supplement, the rate was 71.6%. Although 
the mean serum level of 25(OH)D was significantly high-
er in the group with a consumption history of vitamin D 
supplements (p=0.013), hypovitaminosis D prevalence 
was still 47.6%, indicating inadequate or incorrect levels 
of vitamin D supplementation. 
For patients undergoing cervical spine surgery, they 
made up only a small percentage of the patients in our 
study (19 subjects) and although their numbers may not 
be representative, 17 of 19 the patients (89.5%) suffered 
from hypovitaminosis D and only 2 patients (10.5%) 
showed normal vitamin D levels. On the contrary, patients 
undergoing lumbosacral spine surgery (91 subjects), only 
56.1% suffered from hypovitaminosis D. 
In terms of age of patients, older age has been tradition-
ally reported as a risk factor for vitamin D deficiency and 
various reports have stated the high prevalence of vitamin 
D deficiency in older people [16]. Also, the mechanisms 
such as the reduced capacity of intestinal absorption and 
the reduced skin synthesis of vitamin D are discussed in 
the context of aging [17]. However, clinical studies, partic-
ularly those for the spine, have shown that the age cannot 
be a good predictor of vitamin D deficiency. Moreover, 
studies conducted on patients with orthopedic surgery 
and spinal fusion have found a high prevalence of vitamin 
D deficiency in young adults [7,18]. Our study also re-
vealed a significant direct correlation (p&lt;0.001) between 
age and serum levels of 25(OH)D, which was independent </p>

<p>of the effect resulting from the consumption of vitamin 
D supplement. The highest rate of vitamin D deficiency 
was seen for the 20-39-year-old age group. Considering 
this, care should be taken that although the aging popula-
tion suffers from osteoporosis, osteomalacia, fractures 
and degenerative processes, young people should not be 
neglected. It may be that many of these pathological pro-
cesses start early at youth and controlling vitamin D levels 
at a young age might prevent degenerative spine diseases 
later in life. 
Females are regarded to be at risk for vitamin D defi-
ciency and many studies have confirmed this [19]. How-
ever, in a number of studies, there were no differences be-
tween female and male subjects for vitamin D deficiency 
[20] and even in some cases, it was shown a lower risk 
for hypovitaminosis D existed in females [18,21]. Also, in 
our study, the serum levels of 25(OH)D were significantly 
higher in women among the studied population (p=0.029). 
Moreover, vitamin D supplement consumption was con-
siderably and significantly higher in women (p&lt;0.001), 
and the higher vitamin D levels in this group may be due 
to the increased dietary supplementation and treatment in 
this group. 
Research and data about vitamin D status in the general 
adult population in our country is very limited. In these 
studies [22,23] prevalence of vitamin D deficiency has 
been reported to be from 30% to 80%, according to popu-
lation and regional differences. In the only study of adult 
population in our region (Isfahan, Iran) prevalence of 
hypovitaminosis D was reported to be about 70% [23] and 
the deficiency was more prevalent in women and youth. 
The main problem of this study was that about 80% of the 
studied population were female. 
Some assumptions have been suggested for smoking 
and its effects on the musculoskeletal system with indi-
cations of reduced intestinal absorption of calcium and 
increased rate of bone loss [24]. In this study, there was 
no significant difference in the serum levels of vitamin D 
between the smokers and non-smokers (p=0.134). The 
only noteworthy point was that the vitamin D supplement 
consumption was significantly higher in the non-smoker 
group (p=0.032). 
What should be stated about BMI as a risk factor for 
vitamin D deficiency is that in obese patients, an increase 
in adipose tissue leads to dispersion and distribution 
of this fat-soluble vitamin and thus a reduction in its 
bioavailability [7]. In this case, many studies suggest an </p>

<p>Farid Zolfaghari et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2016;10(5):834-842 </p>

<p>inverse relationship between BMI and the serum levels of 
vitamin D [18,25]. However, several clinical studies have 
also indicated a high prevalence of vitamin D deficiency 
in non-obese patients [26]. In our study, there was no sig-
nificant correlation between the serum levels of 25(OH) 
D and BMI (p=0.458); this was similar to the results of 
the study by Kim et al. [10] where they reported on 350 
patients with LSS. This was unlike the finding by Stoker et 
al. [7] in a study of 313 patients undergoing spinal fusion 
surgery where there was a high prevalence of vitamin D 
deficiency in obese individuals. 
In the case of presence of pain, there have been sev-
eral reports on the relationship between musculoskeletal 
pain and vitamin D deficiency [15,20,27], and it was 
demonstrated that treatment by vitamin D supplements 
could improve the symptoms [15,27]. In particular, in 
the case of the spine, both Stoker et al. [7] and Kim et 
al. [10] suggested an inverse correlation between the 
pain and the serum levels of vitamin D. Similar results 
have been reported for patients with chronic LBP and 
unsuccessful fusion surgery [15,28]. In spite of the above-
mentioned studies, we did not find any significant correla-
tion between the severity of pain and the serum levels of 
vitamin D (p=0.467). 
It is believed that individuals who live in more north-
ern latitude are at a higher risk of vitamin D deficiency in 
winter. This also includes individuals who in any way may 
have a limited exposure to sunlight [29]. However, several 
clinical studies [30] showed a high prevalence of vitamin 
D deficiency in lower latitudes and in summer, among 
them in our country (Iran) where there is a good deal of 
sunlight and there is still a high prevalence of vitamin 
D deficiency. In the present study, similar to what were 
stated in the studies by Stoker et al. [7] and Kim et al. [10], 
there was not a significant difference between the serum 
levels of vitamin D and the different seasons (p=0.655). 
For our study, however, the distribution of samples was 
not uniform in different seasons and most of samples 
(85.5%) were collected in spring and winter. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In summary, according to the results from the pres-
ent study and similar to other studies in this area, it can 
be stated that the vitamin D deficiency shows a high 
prevalence in patients with degenerative diseases of the 
spine, even in patients treated by vitamin D supplements. </p>

<p>Although vitamin D has attracted the attention of re-
searchers in recent decades and its role has been studied 
and confirmed in various diseases, with knowledge and 
awareness having increased among the public and medi-
cal professionals, it has not yet been enough. Although 
the elderly and women are traditionally at a higher risk 
of vitamin D deficiency with consequences such as osteo-
malacia, osteoporosis, etc., there is also no safety margin 
for vitamin D deficiency among youths and men and 
they should not be ignored. On the other hand, given the 
diversity and differences in research results for vitamin D 
deficiency risk factors, they are not enough for predicting 
or proposing vitamin D deficiency and it is recommended 
that vitamin D deficiency prevention strategies comprise 
a broader spectrum of the population in order to prevent 
or delay the onset of degenerative diseases and their con-
sequences. In addition, considering that vitamin D defi-
ciency existed even for patients treated with supplements, 
attention should be paid to the correct and complete dos-
ing after diagnosing the vitamin D deficiency. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors appreciate Dr. N. Almasi-the head of Shari-
ati hospital laboratory-and also staff of laboratory and 
neurosurgery ward of the hospital for cooperation during 
project implementation. </p>



<p>Vitamin D deficiency and degenerative diseases of the spine </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>





<p>Farid Zolfaghari et al. 
 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>