<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5220168" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>standardized log2 ratio at the Category level; Zp, standardized log2 ratio at the Peptide level; Zq, standardized log2 ratio at the Protein level </p>

<p>The mitochondrion harbors crucial cellular processes including 
ATP supply, metabolites generation for cytosolic processes, amino acid 
catabolism, ketogenesis and urea cycle, ion homeostasis, calcium 
cycling, oxygen sensing and other cell signaling pathways such as 
autophagy/mitophagy and apoptosis [1], and therefore it is considered 
a central integrator of the homeostatic signals in the organism [2]. 
Additionally, mitochondria enclose main cellular generators of reactive 
oxygen species (ROS), such as the components of the respiratory chain, 
a number of redox enzymes and potent anti-oxidative defense systems 
[1,3] which make this organelle a key player in cellular redox home-
ostasis. 
Obesity and obesity-associated pathologies have long been related 
to mitochondrial dysfunction [4]. Obesity is the most prevalent 
metabolic disease worldwide and is caused by an augmentation of 
the body fat due to a disproportion between energy uptake and 
expenditure [5]. White adipose tissue, the main adiposity regulator, 
is not merely a fat reservoir, but also a complex, essential endocrine 
organ [6]. Detrimental accumulation of the major intra-abdominal fat 
depot, the visceral adipose tissue (VAT), significantly increases the risk 
for metabolic comorbidities, like insulin resistance (IR) and type 2 
diabetes mellitus (T2DM) [7]. 
Obesity-driven IR clinical manifestations initiate when insulin 
target cells, such as adipocytes, inadequately respond to insulin, and 
over time T2DM pathology emerges [8]. Some of the key factors 
contributing to IR are: i) excessive nutrient supply to adipocytes, which 
leads to ROS production; ii) pro-inflammatory processes; iii) endo-
plasmic reticulum stress; iv) cell aging; and v) altered mitochondrial 
dynamics (such as fusion and fission events) [9-11]. Thus, mitochon-
drion is both the origin and target of multiple metabolic signals whose 
integration maintains insulin sensitivity. Importantly, it has been 
suggested that mitochondrial redox signaling has a key role in white 
adipose tissue, regulating different processes such as adipocyte differ-
entiation or adiponectin secretion through the modulation of redox-
sensitive transcriptional factors [12,13]. Not surprisingly, given that 
white adipose tissue is the greatest endocrine organ in the human body 
any alteration in adipocyte mitochondria could result in significant 
homeostatic disturbances. 
Although most mitochondrial functions are ubiquitous to all 
tissues, tissue-specific functions and tissue-specific control of mito-
chondrial capacity have been extensively reported [14]. Despite that 
adipose tissue in involved in regulating energy expenditure and insulin 
signaling [15], there is limited understanding of the relevance of 
mitochondria in this organ, mainly due to the scarcity of this organelle 
in white adipocytes [16]. 
We have linked obesity to the down-regulation of mitochondrial 
functions [17]. In this work we have extended our previous results, 
exploring the adipocyte mitochondrial proteome to further investigate, 
in obesity, the influence of a physiological process, aging, and a 
pathological process, T2DM. For that, we have relied on a high-
throughput multiplexed proteomic approach with isobaric labeling 
followed by liquid chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry 
(LC-MS) analysis, which allows the simultaneous identification and 
quantification of proteins. It is noteworthy that very few proteomic 
studies based on human mitochondria have been reported [18-21]. 
Using visceral adipocytes, Lindinger et al. [20] identified 62 mitochon-
drial proteins associated with obesity. Similarly to our study, the 
authors resorted to MS for protein identification, although the quanti-
fication relied on immunoblot analysis. </p>

<p>Since oxidation and reduction of thiol proteins are one of the major 
mechanisms by which reactive oxidants integrate into cellular signal 
pathways [22], a number of proteomic technologies have been recently 
developed for the enrichment, identification, and characterization of 
thiol-based redox modifications, what is known as redox proteomics 
[23,24]. Cys is considered the most important redox-responsive amino </p>

<p>acid due to its chemical properties and the range of its different 
oxidation states, together with its involvement in highly conserved 
functional positions in proteins. Additionally, due to their relevance 
and specificity, reversible Cys modifications have been suggested to 
play a main role in the regulation of protein activity and signal 
transduction [25,26]. In spite of their enormous potential, the function 
of oxidative modifications under physiological and pathophysiological 
conditions remains largely unknown. For these reasons, in this work we 
have further coupled our proteomic analysis with the study of dynamic 
alterations of oxidized Cys residues (oxCys) using a GELSILOX-based 
method [27]. 
Here, the application of state-of-the-art redox proteomics ap-
proaches to obese adipose tissue has uncovered a significant increase 
of Cys oxidation levels in oxidative phosphorylation (OXPHOS) sub-
units and, remarkably, an inverse correlation between Cys oxidation 
levels and protein abundance in both aging and T2DM conditions. Our 
results suggest impaired assembly of mitochondrial complexes together 
with defective import of nuclear-encoded proteins to the mitochon-
drion in diabetic patients. As far as we know, this work constitutes the 
most comprehensive depiction of the human mitochondrial proteome 
to date, as well as the first assessment of redox changes in adipocyte 
mitochondria. </p>

<p>2. Material and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Ethic statement </p>

<p>The study was conducted according to the recommendations of the 
Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Ethics Committees of 
Hospital Clínico San Carlos and Hospital Gregorio Marañón (Madrid, 
Spain). Signed informed consent was obtained from all subjects. </p>

<p>2.2. Biological samples </p>

<p>VAT samples were collected from 32 obese women (Body Mass 
Index, BMI≥40 kg/m 2 ) who underwent bariatric surgery. All the 
patients were of Caucasian origin. The surgeon aimed to obtain the 
samples at the beginning of the surgery and from the same anatomical 
location (omentum) in all patients. None of the non-diabetic patients 
suffered T2DM or other obesity-associated comorbidity (hypertension, 
dyslipidemia, obstructive sleep apnea syndrome or cardiovascular 
disease). Inclusion criterion for the diabetic group was suffering 
T2DM for at least two years. T2DM was defined by fasting plasma 
glucose &gt; 7 mmol/L and HbA1c &gt; 6.5%. All T2DM subjects were being 
treated with oral anti-diabetic drugs and in one case with insulin in 
order to control the comorbidities. Exclusion criteria encompassed: i) 
clinically significant hepatic, neurological, or other major systemic 
disease, including malignancy; ii) history of drug or alcohol abuse, 
defined as &gt; 80 g/day, or serum transaminase activity more than twice 
the upper normal range limit; iii) elevated serum creatinine concentra-
tions; iv) acute illnesses and current evidence of chronic inflammatory 
or infectious diseases; and v) mental illness rendering the subjects 
unable to understand the scope of the analysis. </p>

<p>2.3. Separation protocol </p>

<p>After sample collection, fresh VAT was suspended in Hank's 
Balanced Medium 199 (Cat. 22350, GIBCO®-Life Technologies) and 
immediately processed for adipocytes and stromal-vascular fraction 
(SVF) separation according to standard procedures. Briefly, 6g of 
adipose tissue were washed three times with PBS and minced until 
1-2 mm 3 pieces were obtained. Digestion was carried out in 0.2% 
Collagenase type I (M0A3689, Worthington Biochemical Corp.) solu-
tion in PBS for 60 min in water bath at 37 °C. The enzyme was 
inactivated with fetal bovine serum (FBS) and the suspension was 
centrifuged at 1,000 rpm for 10 min. Three different phases could be </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>recognized: the upper phase with the adipocytes; the middle phase with 
the digestion solution, and a red pellet which constitutes the SVF. 
Adipocytes were collected and suspended in PBS for filtering through a 
500 µm steel mesh. Three washing steps were performed for adipocytes 
at 800 rpm for 3 min to remove SVF particles. Different volumes of 
adipocytes (250 μL up to 1 mL) were separated and stored at −80 °C 
for subsequent analyses. </p>

<p>2.4. Preparation of mitochondrial protein extracts and tryptic 
digestion </p>

<p>For proteome profiling, mitochondrial enrichment was carried out 
with the Mitochondria Isolation Kit (Cat. 130-094-532, Miltenyi 
Biotec.) adapting the manufacturer's instructions to our sample. 
Frozen adipocytes (1 mL) were thawed and suspended in the Lysis 
Buffer provided by the kit, supplemented with a protease inhibitor 
cocktail (Halt Protease Inhibitor Cocktail, Thermo Scientific) and 
homogenized on ice for 15 min with a douncer homogenizer using 25 
strokes (pestle type B). After homogenization, the adipocyte sample 
was suspended in the Separation Buffer provided by the kit and 
magnetically labeled with human anti-TOM22 microbeads. After the 
application of a magnetic field, the retained mitochondria were eluted 
and centrifuged at 16,000 rpm during 2 min. The mitochondria-
enriched pellets were dried and frozen at −80 °C until protein extrac-
tion. Mitochondrial isolation was verified by electron microscopy 
(Supplementary Fig. 1). The mitochondrial pellets were treated with 
radioimmunoprecipitation assay buffer (RIPA) (25 mM Tris-HCl pH 
7.6, 150 mM NaCl, 1% NP-40, 1% sodium deoxycholate, 0.1% SDS) 
supplemented with 50 mM iodoacetamide (IAA). Sample pooling (n=4 
per group) was performed prior to digestion. Protein concentration was 
measured by the Pierce BCA Protein Assay (Life Technologies, Thermo 
Scientific). All samples were assayed in triplicate with less than 1% 
variation. For each pool, a total of 60 µg of proteins were digested with 
trypsin following a GELSILOX-based approach [27]. Experimental 
proteomic procedures are summarized in Supplementary Fig. 2. </p>

<p>2.5. iTRAQ labeling and peptide fractionation </p>

<p>For iTRAQ (isobaric Tags for Relative and Absolute Quantification) 
labeling, the dried peptides were taken up in 30 μL of 0.5 M triethy-
lammoniumbicarbonate (TEAB) buffer and labeled with the corre-
sponding iTRAQ reagent in 70% (v/v) ethanol for 1 h at room 
temperature. Then, 100 μL of 0.5% (v/v) trifluoroacetic acid (TFA) 
was added to stop the labeling reaction. The peptide samples were 
mixed, vacuum concentrated and diluted in 200 μL of 1% (v/v) TFA for 
desalting on Oasis HLB C18 cartridges (Waters). One-fourth of the 
tagged peptides were directly analyzed by LC-MS, and the remaining 
three-fourths were subject to mixed-mode cationic exchange (MCX) 
fractionation. The iTRAQ-labeled peptides were suspended in 5 mM 
ammonium formate with 25% (v/v) acetonitrile (ACN), pH 3.0, and 
separated into 5 fractions using MCX Oasis cartridges (Waters). The 
so-obtained peptide fractions were desalted using MicroSpin Columns 
C18 (The Next Group), vacuum-dried and kept at 4 °C for later LC-MS 
analysis. </p>

<p>2.6. LC-MS analyses and protein identification </p>

<p>High-resolution LC-MS analysis of iTRAQ-labeled peptides was 
carried out on an Easy nLC 1000 nano-HPLC apparatus (Thermo 
Scientific) coupled to an Orbitrap Fusion tribrid mass spectrometer 
(Thermo Scientific). Peptides were suspended in 0.1% formic acid and 
then loaded onto an PepMap100 C18 LC pre-column (75 µm I.D., 
2 cm, Thermo Scientific) and eluted on line onto an analytical 
NanoViper PepMap™ 100 C18 LC column (75 µm I.D., 50 cm, 
Thermo Scientific) with a continuous gradient consisting of 8-31% B 
in 240 min (B=90% ACN, 0.1% formic acid) at 200 nL/min. Peptides </p>

<p>were ionized using a Picotip emitter nanospray needle (New Objective). 
Each MS run consisted of enhanced FT-resolution spectra (120,000 
resolution) in the 390-1,200 m/z range followed by data-dependent 
MS/MS spectra of the 20 most intense parent ions acquired along the 
chromatographic run. The AGC target value for the survey scan was set 
to 10 6 . Fragmentation in the Orbitrap was performed at 33% normal-
ized collision energy with a target value of 10,000 ions. The full target 
was set to 30,000, with 1 microscan and 100 ms injection time, and the 
dynamic exclusion was set to 0.5 min. A total of 5 MS data sets, two 
from unfractionated material and three from the corresponding MCX 
fractions, were registered with 25 h total acquisition time. For peptide 
identification the MS/MS spectra were searched with the SEQUEST HT 
algorithm implemented in <rs id="software-26" type="software">Proteome Discoverer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-26" type="version-number">1.4.0.29</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-26" type="creator">Thermo Scientific</rs>). Database searching against human protein sequences from 
the UniProt database (September 2014, 147,615 entries) was per-
formed with the following parameters: trypsin digestion with 2 
maximum missed cleavage sites; precursor and fragment mass toler-
ances of 2 Da and 0.02 Da, respectively; carbamidomethyl and 
methylthio Cys and Met oxidation as dynamic modifications; and N-
terminal and Lys iTRAQ modifications as fixed modifications. The 
results were analyzed using the probability ratio method [28] and the 
FDR (False Discovery Rate) for peptide identification was calculated 
based on the search results against a decoy database using the refined 
method [29]. </p>

<p>2.7. Western-Blot analyses </p>

<p>A second cohort of patients (n=20) was independently considered 
for orthogonal validation analyses. Mitochondria were obtained from 
mature frozen adipocytes using the Mitochondria Isolation Kit (Cat. 
ab110171, Abcam), according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Concentration of mitochondrial suspension was determined by Pierce 
BCA Protein Assay. Ten μg of protein extracts were loaded, resolved on 
SDS-PAGE and transferred to Hybond ECL nitrocellulose membranes 
which were stained with 0.15% Ponceau red to ensure proper transfer 
and then blocked with 5% (w/v) BSA in TBS buffer with 0.1% Tween 
20. The primary antibodies used for protein validation were 1:2000 
rabbit anti-SOD2 (ADI-SOD-111, Enzo Life Sciences); 1:5000 rabbit 
anti-CS (C5498, Sigma-Aldrich); 1:2000 mouse anti-COX5B (sc-
374417, Santa Cruz Biotechnology); 1:2000 mouse anti-VDAC1 
(ab14734), 1:1000 rabbit anti-TFAM (ab47517), 1:1000 mouse anti-
NDUFA9 (ab14713), 1:1000 rabbit anti-SDHC (ab155999) and 1:1000 
mouse Total OXPHOS Human WB Antibody Cocktail (ab11041) 
including anti-UQCRC2 (ab14745), anti-MTCO2 (ab110258) and 
anti-ATP5A1 (ab14748) (Abcam). Blots were incubated with the 
appropriate IgG-HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies. The immunor-
eactive bands were visualized with Amersham ECL Western Blotting 
Detection Reagent (GE Healthcare). Blots were exposed for different 
times. Exposures in the linear range of signal were selected for 
densitometric evaluation with <rs type="software">Image J</rs> analysis software. 
Additionally, infrared-labeled secondary antibodies were also used 
(Li-Cor Biosciences). The bands were detected using the <rs type="software">Odyssey</rs> 
Infrared Imaging System (Li-Cor Biosciences), and the images were 
analyzed with Odyssey Application Software. </p>

<p>2.8. Mitochondrial activity assays </p>

<p>Mitochondria were obtained using the Mitochondria Isolation Kit 
(Abcam). Complex IV activity was measured using a microplate assay 
kit (Cat. ab109909, Abcam). Briefly, mitochondria were mildly digested 
and complex IV was immunocaptured within the wells. Bovine Heart 
Mitochondria (ab110338, Abcam) was used as a positive control. As 
negative control, the experiment was performed in the absence of 
substrate (reduced cytochrome C). All samples were assayed in 
triplicate. Activity was determined by measuring the changes in 
absorbance at 550 nm due to the oxidation of reduced cytochrome C. </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>Fig. 1. The human adipocyte mitochondrial proteome. (A) Representative images showing critical steps during sample preparation. Fresh VAT samples were obtained from 
obese patients (BMI ≥40) and processed to separate adipocyte and SVF components. Mitochondria-enriched pellets were obtained from mature adipocytes and proteins were extracted 
from each individual sample. (B) Selection of obese patients and comparative proteomic studies. Three clinical groups (n=4 each) were constituted as follows: diabetic women over 45 
years, non-diabetic women over 45, and non-diabetic women under 35 years. Proteins from each individual sample were pooled into their corresponding group and digested. The 
peptide pools were tagged with iTRAQ labels (indicated with different colors) and mixed accordingly to achieve two differential expression studies: T2DM differences in obese women 
(114 vs. 116) and age differences in non-diabetic obese women (116 vs. 117). (C) Protein identification refinement workflow. After matching the measured MS/MS spectra against the 
whole human UniProt database most of the proteins reliably identified were filtered out as no evidence for their mitochondrial origin was found. This led to the final set of 706 bona fide 
mitochondrial proteins finally considered for the quantitative proteomic analysis of mitochondria-enriched samples. (D) Relative distribution of bona fide mitochondrial proteins across 
major organelle compartments. </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>2.9. Blue native electrophoresis </p>

<p>To prepare native mitochondrial proteins, pellets were solubilized 
in 30-100 μL buffer containing 1.5 M aminocaproic acid, 50 mM Bis-
Tris, pH 7.0. Mitochondria were extracted with a digitonin:protein 
ratio of 4g/g. Solubilized samples were incubated on ice for 20 min and 
centrifuged for 30 min at 13,000 rpm at 4 °C . Then the supernatant 
was suspended in 750 mM aminocaproic acid, 50 mM Bis-Tris, 0.5 mM 
EDTA and 5% Serva Blue G-250 prior to loading. Thirty μg of protein 
were loaded in Native PAGE™ Novex® 3-12% Bis-Tris Protein Gels 
(Invitrogen). Duplicate gels were used for second-dimension (2D) 10% 
SDS-PAGE gels. Proteins were transferred at 1.3A constant for 10 min 
and probed with 1:1000 mouse anti-COX5A (ab110262), 1:1000 
mouse anti-NDUFA9 (ab14713) and 1:2000 mouse anti-VDAC1 
(ab14734) (Abcam). Blots were incubated with the appropriate IgG-
HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies. The immunoreactive bands 
were visualized with Cheluminate-HRP PicoDetect Kit for Western 
Blotting (Panreac AppliChem). </p>

<p>2.10. Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Descriptive results of continuous variables are expressed as mean ± 
standard deviation (SD). Statistical analyses were performed using the 
<rs id="software-22" type="software">Statistical Package for Social Science</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-22" type="version-number">v. 22</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-22" type="creator">SPSS, Inc</rs>). One-
way ANOVA (using Bonferroni's post hoc test) was used to compare the 
anthropometrical and clinical data from the patients. The relation 
between variables was evaluated by Pearson's Correlation Coefficient. 
Unpaired Student's t-test was used for direct comparisons between two 
groups of samples. Statistical significance was set at p &lt; 0.05 in all 
cases. A 1% peptide FDR threshold was considered. Peptide and 
protein abundance changes were assessed using the iTRAQ reporter 
ion intensities retrieved from MS/MS scans by <rs type="software">QuiXoT</rs> software 
[30,31] as inputs to the WSPP model [32]. This model circumvents 
the statistical issues reported for protein quantitation from iTRAQ-
labeled peptides [33] and, by decomposing the different variance 
components, takes into account variance non-homogeneity and the 
highly unbalanced structure of this kind of data [32]. The model also 
provides a robust framework for the full integration of quantitative and 
error information from a given level to a superior level (e.g. peptide to 
protein); thus, the standardized variable, Zq, is defined as the mean-
corrected log 2 ratio expressed in units of standard deviation at the 
protein level. For the quantitation of Cys oxidation, oxCys peptide 
abundance was evaluated by the corresponding standardized log 2 ratio, 
Zp, therefore avoiding biased calculations due to changes in the 
abundance of the proteins from which these peptides originated [27]. 
The threshold for differential protein and peptide abundance was set at 
|Zq|≥2 and |Zp|≥2, respectively. For the analysis of coordinated 
protein responses [34] a standardized log 2 ratio, Zc, was calculated 
for each functional protein category. Categories with at least 5 protein 
components and FDR &lt; 0.05 were considered significantly differential </p>

<p>and were subjected to cluster analysis. </p>

<p>2.11. Annotation databases and electronic resources </p>

<p>The database used for ontological protein classification contained 
ca. 2.3·10 6 functional categories with relevance to adipose tissue and 
obesity. These categories were retrieved from the <rs id="software-15" type="software">DAVID</rs> database 
(<rs corresp="#software-15" type="url">https://david.ncifcrf.gov/</rs>/) [35] including information from KEGG, 
PANTHER and GO_FAT annotations. Mitochondrial protein terms 
were obtained from both the GO Mitochondrion annotation 
(GO:0005739, http://www.geneontology.org/) and Human MitoCarta 
v2.0 [36]. Enrichment analyses were performed using <rs type="software">DAVID</rs> software 
[37]. </p>

<p>3. Results &amp; discussion </p>

<p>3.1. Mitochondrial proteome of human adipocytes </p>

<p>Our recent findings unveiled different patterns of mitochondrial 
remodeling in the aging and T2DM processes when studying whole 
adipose tissue in obese patients [38]. To further define the hallmarks of 
aging and T2DM in obese adipocyte mitochondria, we have resorted to 
a high-throughput proteomic procedure based on peptide iTRAQ 
labeling and LC-MS analysis (Supplementary Fig. 2). Mitochondrial 
samples were obtained from adipocytes previously isolated from VAT 
biopsies from 32 obese subjects (Fig. 1A). For proteome profiling, a 
subgroup of 12 obese women was selected according to the most 
homogeneous clinical features, and split in three different groups: 
diabetic over 45 years (n=4); non-diabetic over 45 years (n=4) and 
non-diabetic under 35 years (n=4) (Fig. 1B, Table 1). This facilitated 
two differential proteomic studies in a single experiment: diabetic vs. 
non-diabetic women over 45 years (T2DM differences), and older 
(mean age 50 years) vs. younger (mean age 32 years) non-diabetic 
women (age differences). For orthogonal validation analyses, a second 
cohort of patients (n=20) was independently considered. 
LC-MS analysis allowed the identification of 27,578 unique pep-
tides at 1% FDR, corresponding to 3,542 proteins codified by 3,306 
human genes (Supplementary Table 1). Of note, 841 out of 1,158 
proteins currently annotated in Human MitoCarta [36,39] were 
identified (Fig. 1C), covering 88% of the adipose tissue-specific proteins 
detected in mouse [36]. Co-isolated non-mitochondrial proteins were 
excluded from statistical analysis based on GO mitochondrion annota-
tion (GO:0005739) and the Human MitoCarta database. Furthermore, 
since protein functional categories often result from non-experimental 
annotations [40], several additional proteins were filtered out based on 
their canonical functions and other sources of evidence such as The 
Human Protein Atlas [41]. Thus, 706 bona fide mitochondrial proteins 
were finally subjected to quantitative statistical analysis. The distribu-
tion of protein content across the main organelle compartments 
revealed a consistent and reliable mitochondrial proteome, as expected </p>

<p>Table 1 
Clinical characteristics of obese patients considered for mitochondrial proteome profiling. Clinical variables are expressed as mean ± SD. One-way ANOVA was used to 
compare clinical variables. Significance was set at p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Non-diabetic women under 35 years (n=4) 
Non-diabetic women over 45 years (n=4) 
Diabetic women over 45 years (n=4) 
p </p>

<p>Age (years) 
32 ± 4 
51 ± 5 * 
50 ± 6 * 
0.00 
Body Mass Index, BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
43.65 ± 3.37 
44.75 ± 6.85 
46.63 ± 6.05 
0.76 
Waist circumference (cm) 
117.25 ± 8.77 
120.50 ± 8.23 
127.25 ± 2.99 
0.19 
Fasting glucose (mmol/L) 
5.29 ± 0.27 
5.64 ± 0.63 
8.78 ± 4.12 
0.13 
HbA1c (%) 
5.55 ± 0.24 
5.60 ± 0.14 
7.50 ± 2.00 
0.07 
Fasting triglycerides (mmol/L) 
1.31 ± 0.32 
1.65 ± 0.53 
2.08 ± 1.18 
0.40 
Total cholesterol (mmol/L) 
4.95 ± 0.67 
5.28 ± 0.52 
4.46 ± 1.46 
0.52 
cLDL (mmol/L) 
2.91 ± 0.30 
3.11 ± 0.43 
2.31 ± 1.01 
0.26 
cHDL (mmol/L) 
1.44 ± 0.38 
1.40 ± 0.15 
1.20 ± 0.14 
0.37 </p>

<p>* p &lt; 0.01, significant differences as compared to non-diabetic obese women under 35 years by Bonferroni's post hoc test. </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>[42] (Fig. 1D). Worth mentioning, 12 out of the 13 mitochondrial DNA 
(mtDNA)-encoded proteins were successfully detected (Supplementary 
Table 1). To our knowledge, our study has unveiled the largest number 
of mitochondrial proteins from a human sample, despite the stringent 
criteria applied to peptide identification (1% FDR), together with the 
carefully selected and manually curated functional database annota-
tions considered. </p>

<p>3.2. Quantitative proteomic analysis in aging and T2DM </p>

<p>LC-MS data obtained from the mitochondrial adipocyte samples 
were subjected to comprehensive statistical analysis using the WSPP 
model [32]. Proteins with |Zq|≥2 (corresponding to p &lt; 0.05) were 
considered differentially abundant proteins (DAPs) in each compar-
ison. Out of the 706 bona fide mitochondrial proteins considered, a 
total of 63 and 62 DAPs were identified in the age and T2DM 
assessments, respectively (Supplementary Table 2). The occurrence of 
shared features between aging and T2DM explains that 37% of DAPs 
were found common to the two comparisons. Thus, cytochrome c 
oxidase subunit 6B1 (COX6B1), a key player in cytochrome c oxidase 
activity [43,44], was found down-regulated in the age (Zq=−2.75) and 
T2DM (Zq=−5.06) comparisons. 
Since cellular processes are accomplished by proteins working 
together in complexes or functional pathways, we have also resorted 
to a systems biology model [45] to assess whether the protein </p>

<p>abundance changes took place in a coordinated manner, a biological 
event that is well-known [46]. These analyses revealed that global 
OXPHOS down-regulation is a key hallmark of age progression in 
adipocyte mitochondria (Fig. 2 A, Supplementary Table 3). These 
results were confirmed by Western Blot (WB) in an independent set 
of mitochondria samples using selected OXPHOS markers 
(Supplementary Fig. 3A). Additionally, the up-regulation of Vitamin 
D metabolism was also found associated with aging. In the T2DM 
comparison, protein-coordination analyses highlighted an up-regula-
tion of Response to oxygen levels process, among other protein 
functional categories (Fig. 2B, Supplementary Table 3). The Response 
to oxygen levels is illustrated by a significant increase of relevant 
components of the cellular antioxidant machinery like mitochondrial 
thioredoxin (TXN2) or mitochondrial superoxide dismutase (SOD2), 
which were found up-regulated in the T2DM assessment (Zq=4.02 and 
Zq=4.45, respectively). SOD2 is a key scavenging enzyme that converts 
superoxide to hydrogen peroxide and molecular oxygen in the mito-
chondrial matrix. SOD2 levels were also found increased in diabetic 
compared to non-diabetic patients by WB, using a second cohort of 
patients (Supplementary Fig. 3B), in agreement with earlier studies 
[47,48]. To further illustrate the above-described degree of coordinated 
behavior in aging and T2DM comparisons, the cumulative frequency 
distribution of protein changes (Zq) was plotted for the least redundant 
categories within the aging and T2DM clusters (Fig. 2C, D). Altogether, 
the coordinated responses highlight that the proteome alterations </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Coordinated protein responses in adipocyte mitochondria in aging and T2DM. (A-B) Protein functional categories differentially modulated in the age (A) and T2DM 
(B) comparisons. A color scale was used to represent the overlapping frequency of protein terms among categories that were up-(yellow) or down-regulated (purple). Category terms and 
clusters are fully described in Supplementary Table 3. (C-D) Coordinated protein regulation in the age (C) and T2DM (D) comparisons. The cumulative frequency of changes (Zq values) 
for the least redundant category in each of the clusters is represented together with the theoretical curve, showing a normal distribution of data, as well as the experimental curve, 
representing Zq for the whole set of proteins quantified in this study (n=706). An up-or down-wards shift from the theoretical curve means a coordinated up-or down-regulation, 
respectively. (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article). </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>follow well-differentiated patterns of adipocyte mitochondrial dysfunc-
tion in both conditions, supporting our previous studies based on 
whole VAT [38]. </p>

<p>3.3. Regulation of mitochondrial complexes </p>

<p>Mitochondrial ATP is produced by the OXPHOS machinery cou-
pling two set of reactions: first, the electron transfer of reducing 
equivalents to molecular oxygen through an exclusive assemblage of 
protein complexes, the electron transport chain (ETC); and second, the 
ADP phosphorylation through ATP synthase thanks to the proton-
motive force previously generated. OXPHOS subunits have dual genetic 
origin, nuclear and mitochondrial, with the exception of complex II 
subunits that are exclusively nuclear-encoded. Our study has success-</p>

<p>fully identified the majority of protein components of mitochondrial 
complexes (Figs. 3, 4): 49 structural and assembly factors for 
NADH:ubiquinone oxidoreductase (complex I); 3 for succinate oxidor-
eductase (complex II); 11 for ubiquinol-cytochrome c reductase (com-
plex III); 23 for cytochrome c oxidase (complex IV) and 20 ATP 
synthase subunits and related proteins (also referred as complex V). 
This work represents the largest number of OXPHOS proteins identi-
fied in human fat cells to date. This has enabled us to pinpoint </p>

<p>quantitative protein changes in each of the OXPHOS complexes in 
both the aging and T2DM assessments. 
Although, as described above, the proteins belonging to Oxidative 
phosphorylation function were coordinately down-regulated in the 
aging comparison (Fig. 2C), the individual analysis of each mitochon-
drial complex demonstrated that complex I, II, III and IV were indeed </p>

<p>Fig. 3. ETC mitochondrial complexes, OXPHOS subunits and related proteins in aging. (A) Heat-map representing protein abundance changes within the mitochondrial 
complexes. For each protein gene symbols are displayed together with the corresponding Zq (standardized log 2 ratio) values in a color scale (yellow means up-regulated and purple 
down-regulated). Color proportion resembles the global regulation tendency in the complex. Sigmoidal curves representing the cumulative frequency of changes for each mitochondrial 
complex are shown in Supplementary Fig. 4A. (B-C) Protein changes within mitochondrial complex I and IV naïve structures. (B) Schematic representation of mitochondrial complex I 
subunits along its structure modules: the membrane proton pumping arm (P module) and the matrix arm composed by the electron transferring element (Q module) and the NADH 
binding and oxidizing part (N module). (C) Schematic representation of monomeric cytochrome c oxidase (complex IV). Some cytochrome c oxidase subunits are not represented due to 
lack of information. Boxes are colored according to the relative protein abundance change in each comparison. Three-dimensional colored structures emphasize the global behavior of 
modules. Proteins containing oxCys residues are in red color. Assembly factors are not represented. Further information about specific Zq values can be found in Supplementary Table 2. 
(For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article). </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>significantly reduced, whilst ATP synthase was not regulated (Fig. 3A, 
Supplementary Fig. 4A). Protein changes in two of the most well-
known ETC complexes, I and IV, were studied in detail (Fig. 3B, C). 
Complex I is the largest enzyme complex of the respiratory chain 
encompassing 45 different subunits and requiring at least 13 specific 
assembly factors, and its activity facilitates the main entry of reducing 
power (through NADH) into the oxidative machinery [49,50]. Its L-
shaped structure is made up of a peripheral arm containing two 
functional blocks, the N (NADH binding) and the Q (ubiquinone 
binding) modules, and a membrane arm consisting of the P (proton 
pumping) element [51]. Complex IV is the terminal oxidase set of ETC 
enzymes, where the electrons are transported by four redox-active 
centers to molecular oxygen [52]. Complex IV relies on a dimeric 
structure where the three core components (MT-CO1, MT-CO2 and 
MT-CO3), translated within the organelle, must be assembled with the 
rest of nuclear-encoded components to reach an active form [53]. The </p>

<p>schematic representation of protein abundance along complex I and IV 
structures, according to up-to-date information [49,50,53,54], clearly 
evidenced the down-regulation of most of the protein components of 
these complexes as obese patients age (Fig. 3B, C). Interestingly, this 
effect is more pronounced in the N module of complex I, involved in 
NADH binding (Fig. 3B), as well as in the two core proteins (MT-CO1 
and MT-CO2) and two peripherally localized subunits (COX6B1 and 
COX6C) of complex IV (Fig. 3C). Since the decreased level of these 
proteins could contribute not only to the instability of both complex 
structures but also to their activity decline, our data could suggest an 
impairment of the electron flux within the mitochondrial ETC in the 
adipocytes from older compared to younger obese subjects. 
On the other hand, our results have shown a strong down-
regulation of mtDNA-encoded proteins associated with aging progres-
sion (Supplementary Fig. 5A). Notably, the mitochondrial transcription 
factor A (TFAM), the main player in the regulation of mtDNA copy </p>

<p>Fig. 4. ETC mitochondrial complexes, OXPHOS subunits and related proteins in T2DM. (A) Heat-map representing protein abundance changes within the mitochondrial 
complexes. For each protein gene symbols are displayed together with the corresponding Zq (standardized log 2 ratio) values in a color scale (yellow means up-regulated and purple 
down-regulated). Sigmoidal curves representing the cumulative frequency of changes for each mitochondrial complex are shown in Supplementary Fig. 4B. (B-C) Protein changes within 
mitochondrial complex I and IV naïve structures. (B) Schematic representation of mitochondrial complex I subunits along its structure modules as described in Fig. 3B. (C) Schematic 
representation of complex IV as described in Fig. 3C. Boxes are colored according to the relative protein abundance change in each comparison. Three-dimensional colored structures 
emphasize the global behavior of modules. Proteins containing oxCys residues are in red color. Assembly factors are not represented. Further information about specific Zq values can be 
found in Supplementary Table 2. (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article). </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>number [55], and involved in mtDNA stability, replication and 
transcription [56], was also found significantly diminished in older 
compared to younger obese patients (Zq=−3.05). These results were 
confirmed by WB analyses (Supplementary Fig. 3A). The involvement 
of TFAM in aging is tissue-specific [57] and has been mainly 
investigated in several rodent tissues. Remarkably, an aged-related 
decrease in TFAM amount in muscle and liver tissues of rats has been 
reported [57,58], further validating our results. Noteworthy, we pre-
viously described nuclear-encoded mitochondrial protein reduction in 
whole VAT biopsies with aging [38]. Altogether, our data support the 
decrease of ETC complexes with aging progression in adipocyte 
mitochondria. 
In the T2DM study, the detailed analysis of individual mitochon-
drial complexes revealed a normal distribution for complex I, whilst 
complex III, IV and V were slightly decreased (Fig. 4A, Supplementary 
Fig. 4B). Earlier studies in subcutaneous adipose tissue also reported 
the down-regulation of mitochondrial complex III, IV and V in obesity-
associated IR [59], in agreement with our results. Protein changes in 
the different complex I modules are illustrated in the schematic 
representation shown in Fig. 4B. Results highlighted a distinctive 
protein expression pattern depending on the complex modules. Thus, 
the P module was found up-regulated while the Q and N modules were 
mostly down-regulated. Moreover, a pronounced increase of succinate 
dehydrogenase cytochrome b560 protein (SDHC) was uncovered. 
SDHC is the membrane-anchoring subunit C of complex II in charge 
of transferring electrons from succinate to ubiquinone, and also 
participates in the tricarboxylic acid cycle (TCA). On the other hand, 
complex II is the minor site of entry of reducing equivalents into the 
ETC (from FADH 2 ). Our data suggest that complex II increase could be 
a compensatory response for the reduction of the oxidative capacity in 
diabetic compared to non-diabetic patients, due to the down-regulation 
of complex III, IV and V. In consonance with our results, complex II 
increased activity together with complex I, III and IV deficiencies, have 
been reported in the adipose tissue from a mouse model [60]. These 
authors also reported an enhancement of citrate synthase (CS) activity. 
Similarly, our results revealed that CS, a key enzyme of TCA, was up-
regulated in the T2DM comparison (Zq=3.28; Supplementary Fig. 3B, 
Supplementary Table 2), suggesting a metabolic shift favoring succi-
nate (complex II)-driven respiration in the adipose tissue of our 
diabetic patients. 
Noteworthy, and in contrast with the results found in the age 
comparison, the mtDNA-encoded proteins were mostly found up-
regulated in T2DM (Supplementary Fig. 5B). This may be accounted 
for by the alteration of mtDNA-encoded protein translation [61] and/ 
or underline the impairment of complex assembly owing to abnormal 
accumulation of specific modules. Our hypothesis about defective 
complex assembly is in agreement with the protein changes observed 
for complex I and IV structures, where clear differences between 
modules are observed in the relative abundance of nuclear vs. 
mtDNA-encoded proteins (Fig. 4B, C). Thus, the P module from 
complex I, which contains the highest number of mtDNA-encoded 
proteins, is up-regulated while the N module, which is exclusively made 
up of nuclear-encoded subunits, was found down-regulated (Fig. 4B). 
Likewise, in complex IV data revealed differences in the relative 
abundance between mtDNA (core module) and nuclear-encoded 
proteins (Fig. 4C). Of note, both the P module in complex I and the 
core module in complex IV are gathered in the first steps of the 
complex assembly process [49,53], strengthening our premise about 
defects in the accumulation of specific modules during complex 
assembly. This defective accumulation of mtDNA-encoded protein 
modules may be due, in part, to an impaired translocation of 
nuclear-encoded subunits to the mitochondrion in diabetic compared 
to non-diabetic subjects that would consequently lead to deficient 
complex assembly. Nuclear-encoded proteins are synthesized in the 
cytosol and transported to the mitochondrion mainly via chaperones 
like heat shock protein 70 (HSP70), and into the mitochondrion via </p>

<p>mitochondrial membrane transporters (mostly TOM and TIM com-
plexes) [62,63]. Interestingly, we have previously reported significantly 
lower levels of HSP70 in diabetic compared to non-diabetic patients 
[17], and in the present study we have found a down-regulation of 
several TOMM proteins, like TOMM70A (Zq=−3.31) and TOMM20 
(Zq=−2.07) (Supplementary Table 2), further supporting our hypoth-
esis. 
Previous studies addressing changes in mtDNA copy number have 
shown inverse correlation between mtDNA content and T2DM [64,65], 
in contrast with our results. Nevertheless, these studies were carried 
out in whole tissue samples and, therefore, could be affected by 
differences in the mitochondrial mass. It has to be noted that the 
current work is based on samples containing the same amount of 
mitochondria, thus avoiding such kind of differences. </p>

<p>3.4. Quantitation of cysteine oxidation in mitochondrial adipocytes </p>

<p>For several years, ROS production was considered unregulated and 
their targets were thought to be randomly distributed leading to the 
accumulation of damaged biological molecules, which were in turn 
pointed out as potential contributors to several pathologies [66]. 
Currently, there are clear evidences that ROS production has also 
favorable effects due to their implication in several signal transduction 
pathways involving reversible reduction and oxidation of specific 
amino acids [26]. 
To gain insight into mitochondrial redox signaling in obesity, we 
have carried out a large-scale identification and quantitation of 
reversible thiol oxidative modifications in adipocyte mitochondria </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Cys oxidation levels in OXPHOS proteins. Cumulative frequency of 
changes in oxCys peptides (Zp) and OXPHOS oxidized proteins (Zq) in the age (upper 
panel) and T2DM (lower panel) comparisons. Changes in oxCys peptides (red line) 
are represented together with their corresponding oxidized protein changes (dashed grey 
line). An up-or down-wards shift from the theoretical curve means a coordinated 
tendency to up-or down-regulation, respectively. (For interpretation of the references to 
color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article). </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>Table 2 
Differentially abundant oxCys peptides in the age and T2DM comparisons. Protein name, UniProt accession code and oxCys peptide sequences are shown. The position of the 
oxCys residues in each protein is specified together with the structural observations reported by UniProt. Zp corresponds to the standardized log 2 ratio at the peptide level; the red-blue 
scale means increased or decreased oxidation, respectively. FDRp refers to FDR at the peptide level. M#, Methionine oxidation; C*, Cysteine methylthio modification (referring to 
oxidation site); K^, Lysine iTRAQ 4-plex tag. The iTRAQ modified N-terminal residues are shown in lower case. </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>based on a proteomic procedure that enables to independently 
ascertain quantitative changes at both the protein and the oxCys 
abundance levels. Our aim has been to evaluate the dual role of ROS </p>

<p>as secondary messengers vs. stress molecules through the analysis of 
Cys oxidative modifications in aging (a physiological condition) and 
T2DM (a pathological or stressful condition), respectively. To our 
knowledge, this study constitutes the first description of reversible Cys 
oxidation in human adipose tissue, particularly in adipocyte mitochon-
dria. 
A total of 229 oxCys peptides were identified at 1% FDR, corre-
sponding to 244 oxCys sites within a set of 116 proteins 
(Supplementary Table 4). The oxCys proteins were mainly oxidoreduc-
tases involved in Antioxidant activity or Nucleotide binding functions 
representing key mitochondrial processes such as Oxidative phosphor-
ylation, Tricarboxylic acid cycle or β-oxidation among others 
(Supplementary Table 5). Of note, 44 of the oxCys peptides identified 
(about 20%) pertained to OXPHOS subunits. Some of these oxCys-
containing proteins belonged to complex I and IV, as shown in red 
color in Figs. 3B-C and 4B-C. It is noteworthy that no oxCys sites were 
identified in mtDNA-encoded proteins (intra-membrane subunits); 
only proteins located in the inter-membrane or the matrix spaces 
exhibited these modifications (Figs. 3B-C, 4B-C). The WSPP statistical 
model revealed 21 and 30 oxCys peptides differentially abundant in the 
aging and the T2DM comparisons, respectively (Table 2, 
Supplementary Table 4). Remarkably, a considerable number of the 
altered oxCys sites corresponded to known disulfide bonds or to C-X 9 -C 
type motifs (e.g. Cys 30 and Cys 65 of COX6B1 and Cys 36 of NADH 
dehydrogenase [ubiquinone] 1 alpha subcomplex subunit 8, NDUFA8) 
(Table 2). These C-X 9 -C domains are localized in nuclear-encoded 
proteins that are imported into the mitochondrion through the evolu-
tionary conserved redox-active MIA (Mitochondrial Intermembrane 
space Assembly) pathway [67]. This minor pathway depends on redox-
regulated folding events that stabilize, trap and finally import into the 
mitochondrion the C-X 9 -C domain-carrying proteins like NDUFA8, 
NDUFS5 and COX6B1. NDUFA8, NDUFS5 are important accessory 
molecules that take part in the last stages of complex I assembly [68], 
whereas COX6B1 is a key protein involved in the biogenesis [69] and 
the stabilization of complex IV subunits [43]. Noteworthy, our redox 
proteomics data revealed that in T2DM comparison Cys-peptides from 
the aforementioned C-X 9 -C domain-carrying proteins were signifi-
cantly oxidized; likewise, in the aging comparison several oxCys-
containing peptides from COX6B1 were significantly increased 
(Table 2). Altogether, these data suggest an inadequate import of 
nuclear-encoded proteins into the mitochondria through the MIA 
pathway, with consequent compromised complex assembly. Since 
aging has long been associated to IR progression [70,71], the alteration 
of MIA pathway emerges as a connecting link between the pathology 
(i.e. IR) and the physiological aging. To our knowledge, this is the first 
time that defective protein transport alongside the organelle is pointed 
out as a hallmark of mitochondrial dysfunction in aging and T2DM. </p>

<p>3.5. Linking Cys oxidation to protein function in adipocyte 
mitochondria </p>

<p>Taking advantage of the deep mitochondrial proteome coverage 
reached in this study we have further investigated the association 
between Cys oxidation levels (as measured by the corresponding Zp </p>

<p>Fig. 6. OxCys modifications in OXPHOS proteins. Heat maps representing oxCys 
peptide changes and oxidized protein abundance changes in the OXPHOS complexes 
regarding aging (A) and T2DM (B) differences. The yellow-purple columns represent 
protein abundance changes according to Zq scale. The red-blue scale represents the 
oxCys-peptide abundance changes (Zp values) and the position of the oxCys residues in 
each protein is specified. Note that yellow-purple scale means up-or down-regulation 
and red-blue scale means increased or decreased oxidation. Further information about 
Zp values of oxCys-peptides is shown in Supplementary Table 4. (For interpretation of 
the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of 
this article). </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>values) and protein abundance (assessed by Zq) in the aging and T2DM 
assessments. Correlation analyses revealed that the changes in abun-
dance of oxCys were inversely associated to protein abundance levels, 
both in the aging (R=−0.26, p &lt; 0.0001) and T2DM comparisons 
(R=−0.38, p &lt; 0.0001) (Supplementary Fig. 6 A). Noteworthy, this 
inverse correlation was more pronounced considering only OXPHOS 
proteins in aging (R=−0.35, p &lt; 0.05) and, particularly, in the T2DM 
assessment (R=−0.64, p &lt; 0.0001) (Supplementary Fig. 6B). In addi-
tion, the analysis of the cumulative frequency of changes in oxCys 
peptides and OXPHOS oxidized proteins in both assessments showed 
that most of the oxCys peptides identified in these proteins tended to be 
up-regulated, whereas the corresponding proteins showed the opposite 
trend (Fig. 5). 
Although the role of reversible Cys modifications in redox signaling 
has been well appreciated [72], to date little is known about the 
biological implications of these modifications. Our data have revealed 
that oxCys abundance follows distinctive patterns concerning OXPHOS 
complexes in the two comparisons. In aging, the oxidation was mainly 
localized in complex III and IV, which also comprised the most down-
regulated proteins (Fig. 6A). In T2DM, however, the oxidation was 
restricted to complex I and IV (Fig. 6B), where most oxidized proteins 
showed down-regulated and oxCys peptides were significantly more 
abundant. This outcome is particularly pronounced in COX6B1, where 
oxidative changes in the C-X 9 -C domains could lead to its defective 
import into the mitochondrion through the MIA pathway, as earlier 
pointed out. Accordingly, our data suggest that COX6B1 oxidation 
could contribute to complex IV dysfunction. To further investigate this 
issue, we examined complex IV activity in a different set of mitochon-
drial samples. Interestingly, our data showed a significant decrease of 
complex IV activity in diabetic compared to non-diabetic patients 
(Fig. 7A). Remarkably, previous studies had evidenced that resveratrol, 
an anti-oxidant metabolite, improves complex IV activity [43], thus 
strengthening our results. In addition, Blue Native (BN)-PAGE ana-
lyses of digitonin-solubilized adipocyte mitochondria revealed that 
complex IV was found significantly decreased in diabetic compared </p>

<p>to non-diabetic patients (Fig. 7B), potentially accounting for the 
reduction of complex IV activity in T2DM. Consequently this alteration 
may support the respiratory dysfunction postulated for T2DM, since 
complex IV is associated to complex I and III in the different super-
complexes (SCs) [73]. Thus, 2D BN-PAGE assays revealed a trend 
toward the down-regulation of these SCs in diabetic patients (Fig. 7C). 
In agreement with these observations, impaired SCs assembly has been 
reported in muscle mitochondria from diabetic subjects [74]. </p>

<p>4. Conclusions </p>

<p>In the current work we have used adipose tissue from obese 
patients to address two different events previously related to oxidative 
stress and mitochondrial dysfunction: aging, a physiological situation, 
and T2DM, a severe obesity-associated disorder. In these two compar-
isons Cys oxidation levels correlated negatively with protein abun-
dance, notably in T2DM, where a greater number of these proteins 
were OXPHOS subunits. In diabetic patients the proteomic signature of 
mitochondrial dysfunction comprises: i) a decrease of specific OXPHOS 
subunits together with reduced complexes and SCs; ii) an increase of 
the antioxidant response; iii) adjustment of mitochondrial-vs. nuclear-
encoded protein modules suggesting a dysfunctional protein transloca-
tion into the mitochondria; and iv) oxidative Cys modifications related 
to defects in protein import through the MIA pathway. We have 
demonstrated an impaired activity of complex IV, which brings 
together the most down-regulated and, at the same time, the most 
oxidized OXPHOS protein components. Oxidative damage and protein 
changes undergone by the OXPHOS system may compromise the 
metabolic status of the adipocyte due to an imbalance of NADH/ 
NAD + and/or ATP/ADP levels. In addition, the modifications of 
proteins related to mitochondrial transport could also impact intra-
and inter-organelle crosstalk, severely disrupting adipocyte home-
ostasis and therefore leading to aberrant insulin sensitivity. The 
hallmark of age progression on mitochondrial remodeling also includes 
down-regulation of OXPHOS components together with increased Cys 
oxidation levels, albeit to a lesser extent as compared with the T2DM 
condition. It is not surprising that ROS and oxidative modifications 
play a more relevant role in a pathological condition like T2DM as 
compared to a physiological event like aging. In this sense, Complex IV 
emerges as a common target connecting the oxidative hallmarks of 
T2DM and aging progression, potentially accounting for the progres-
sion of insulin resistance over time in obese individuals. 
Setting aside the analysis of individual proteins we have resorted to 
an innovative combination of redox proteomics and systems biology 
approaches. The unprecedented capacity of this methodology has 
generated a vast amount of biologically relevant information, produ-
cing a molecular picture of the complex interplay between mitochon-
drial dysfunction and aging, obesity and T2DM. Furthering our knowl-
edge about reversible oxidative modifications and their implications 
would help to develop advanced integrative models of proteome 
regulation and redox signaling pathways, providing a basis for im-
proved redox-based therapeutics in obese patients. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>All authors declare that they have no financial conflict or competing 
interests that might be construed to influence the results or interpreta-
tion of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by grant SAF2012-33014 from MINECO, 
Spain (B.P.) and partially financed with FEDER funds, FPI-UAM 
Program (M.G.S.), PI15/01199 from ISCIII, Spain (A.T.) and Pro 
CNIC Foundation (E.C., J.A.L. and J.V). All data and materials are 
available. </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Adipocyte mitochondrial function in T2DM. (A) Complex IV activity in 
T2DM. Results represent the distribution of average activities of adipocyte mitochondria 
from diabetic (n=5, grey box) and non-diabetic (n=7, white box) patients. All samples 
were assayed in triplicate. Statistical significance was set at * p &lt; 0.05. (B) Results 
represent adipocyte mitochondria from diabetic (n=4, black bars) and non-diabetic (n=3, 
white bars) patients analyzed by 1D BN-PAGE. Complex IV bands were revealed by 
COX5 A. Graph bars represent the optical density means ± SD from two independent 
experiments. Statistical significance was set at * p &lt; 0.05. (C) Representative 2D BN/ 
SDS-PAGE analysis from diabetic and non-diabetic mitochondrial samples. Membranes 
were incubated with antibodies against NDUFA9 and COX5 A to reveal supercomplexes 
(SCs) associations. Db, diabetic; Non-db, non-diabetic. </p>

<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors wish to thank all the patients for their collaboration. 
We thank Raquel Mesa (from CNIC), Pablo Talavera, Ester Martín, 
Esteban Martín and Carmen Hernández (from Hospital Clínico San 
Carlos); and Miguel Ángel Steiner, Laura Gómez-Lanz, Jose María 
Monturiol and Jorge de Tomás Palacios (from Hospital Gregorio 
Marañón) for their kind contributions. We also acknowledge Dr. G. 
Eisinhofer and Dr. M. Mittelbrunn for the SDHC and TFAM antibodies 
and Dr. C. Ugalde and Dr. R. Pérez-Pérez for the critical reading of this 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Appendix A. Supporting information </p>

<p>Supplementary data associated with this article can be found in the 
online version at doi:10.1016/j.redox.2016.12.013. </p>







<p>M. Gómez-Serrano et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 415-428 </p>



</text></tei>