<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5210341" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background--Cardiometabolic risk (CMR) factors including hypertension, overweight/obesity, diabetes mellitus, and hyperlipi-
demia are high among United States ethnic minorities, and the immigrant population continues to burgeon. </p>

<p>Methods and Results--Hypothesizing that acculturation (length of residence) would be associated with a higher prevalence of 
CMR factors, the authors analyzed data on 54, 984 US immigrants in the 2010-2014 National Health Interview Surveys. The main 
predictor was length of residence. The outcomes were hypertension, overweight/obesity, diabetes mellitus, and hyperlipidemia. 
The authors used multivariable logistic regression to examine the association between length of US residence and these CMR 
factors.The mean (SE) age of the patients was 43 (0.12) years and half were women. Participants residing in the United States for 
≥10 years were more likely to have health insurance than those with &lt;10 years of residence (70% versus 54%, P&lt;0.001). After 
adjusting for region of birth, poverty income ratio, age, and sex, immigrants residing in the United States for ≥10 years were more 
likely to be overweight/obese (odds ratio [OR], 1.19; 95% CI, 1.10-1.29), diabetic (OR, 1.43; 95% CI, 1.17-1.73), and hypertensive 
(OR, 1.18; 95% CI, 1.05-1.32) than those residing in the United States for &lt;10 years. </p>

<p>Conclusions--In an ethnically diverse sample of US immigrants, acculturation was associated with CMR factors. Culturally tailored 
public health strategies should be developed in US immigrant populations to reduce CMR. ( J Am Heart Assoc. 2016;5:e004059 
doi: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059) </p>

<p>Key Words: cardiovascular research • ethnicity • hypertension • migration • obesity </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>ardiometabolic risk (CMR), a construct that comprises a 
cluster of risk factors for cardiovascular disease and 
type 2 diabetes mellitus, poses one of the largest public 
health challenges in the United States (US). 
1,2 The prevalence </p>

<p>of CMR factors such as hypertension (33%), overweight/ 
obesity (69%), diabetes mellitus (9.3%), and hyperlipidemia 
(34%) remains high in US adults. 
2 Prevalence of and morbidity </p>

<p>associated with cardiovascular disease is projected to 
increase approximately 10% by 2030 and will affect nearly 
116 million US adults. 
3 The estimated total cost related to </p>

<p>CMR factors exceeds approximately $110 billion for over-
weight/obesity, 
4 $245 billion for diabetes mellitus, 
5 and $273 </p>

<p>billion for cardiovascular disease. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Although mortality attributable to CMR has been reduced 
in the general US population, 
2 disparities exist among specific </p>

<p>populations defined by race/ethnicity, socioeconomic status, 
health insurance status, geographic location, disability status, 
and sex. The CMR burden is particularly high among racial/ 
ethnic minorities in the US. 
2,6 African Americans have one of </p>

<p>the highest prevalence rates of hypertension in the world 
2 and </p>

<p>From the Department of Community and Public Health, Johns Hopkins School of Nursing, Baltimore, MD (Y.C.-M.); Counseling Psychology, Department of Psychology, 
University of Florida, Gainesville, FL (N.U.); Emory University Rollins School of Public Health, Atlanta, GA (O.O.); Department of Surgery, Johns Hopkins School of 
Medicine, Baltimore, MD (J.K.A.); Department of Public Health, Academic Medical Center, University of Amsterdam, the Netherlands (C.A.); Nell Hodgson Woodruff, 
School of Nursing Emory University, Atlanta, GA (C.M.R. S.D.); Department of Epidemiology &amp; Biostatistics, School of Public Health Georgia State University, Atlanta, GA 
(I.S.O.). </p>

<p>A moderated poster presentation of these findings was given at the American Heart Association's Epidemiology and Prevention (EPI) Lifestyle conference, March 
1-4, 2016, in Phoenix, AZ. </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Yvonne Commodore-Mensah, PhD, RN, Johns Hopkins School of Nursing, Department of Community &amp; Public Health, 525 North Wolfe Street, 
Room 419, Baltimore, MD 21205. E-mail: ycommod1@jhu.edu </p>

<p>Received June 14, 2016; accepted October 7, 2016. 
ª 2016 The Authors. Published on behalf of the American Heart Association, Inc., by Wiley Blackwell. This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is 
non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>are 30% more likely to die from cardiovascular disease than 
whites. 
7 Hispanics and individuals of Mexican, Caribbean, </p>

<p>Central American, South American, or other Spanish-speaking 
origins have higher rates of CMR factors, such as hyperten-
sion, high cholesterol, diabetes mellitus, and obesity, com-
pared with whites. </p>

<p>2   The percentage of racial/ethnic minorities in the US 
continues to rise and this diversification will, in part, be 
attributable to a rise in immigrant populations who will 
account for approximately 20% of the US population by 
2060. 
8 Immigrants are affected by unique factors that impact </p>

<p>their CMR and subsequent health outcomes. 
9 Post-migration </p>

<p>socioeconomic challenges, poor education, and lack of health 
insurance are among some of the most important factors that 
are associated with increased risk for cardiometabolic disease 
among immigrants. Generally, immigrants are significantly 
less likely to graduate from high school compared with 
nonimmigrants, have lower earnings than US-born resi-
dents, 
10,11 and are more likely not to have health insurance </p>

<p>compared with nonimmigrant whites. 
10,11 However, immi-</p>

<p>grants have been found to have high levels of social 
support. 
12,13 Some studies have shown that high social </p>

<p>support is associated with superior health outcomes among 
immigrants. 
14,15 Acculturation, a unique characteristic in </p>

<p>immigrants, to some extent is associated with social support 
and the assimilation of immigrants to the host's sociocultural 
environment. 
16 Acculturation is defined as "the dual process </p>

<p>of cultural and psychological change that takes place as a 
result of contact between two or more cultures and their 
individual members." 
16,17 Proxy measures of acculturation </p>

<p>such as length of US residence 
18 and languages spoken at </p>

<p>home are commonly used in lieu of lengthy scales in 
population-based studies to minimize participant burden. 
Acculturation has been associated with poorer health out-
comes among US immigrants. 
19 Prior studies have indicated </p>

<p>that acculturation is associated with increased prevalence of 
CMR factors among Asian, Hispanic, European, and black 
immigrants. 
20-24 Given the growing size of immigrants in the </p>

<p>US and the economic burden associated with CMR, examining 
the association between acculturation and CMR factors 
among immigrants in the US may provide further insight on 
how to frame public health interventions to reduce CMR and 
associated sequelae among immigrants in the US. 
In a prior study 
25 examining the relationship between </p>

<p>acculturation and cardiovascular disease risk factors among a 
relatively smaller but diverse pool of US immigrants based on 
the 2002 National Health Interview Survey (NHIS; N=5230), 
acculturation was found to be associated with increased odds of 
obesity, hyperlipidemia, and cigarette smoking. Building on 
findings of Koya and Egede, 
25 we re-examined the association </p>

<p>between acculturation and CMR factors among a contempo-
rary, diverse, and larger sample of US immigrants. This study </p>

<p>sought more specifically to examine (1) prevalence of CMR 
factors by length of residence (ie, acculturation) in the US of 
immigrants, and (2) differences in the association between CMR 
factors and acculturation among US immigrants stratified by 
sex. We hypothesize that increased length of stay of immigrants 
in the US would be associated with much greater odds of CMR 
factors than recently arrived immigrants to the US. We also 
theorize that the association between length of residence of 
immigrants in the US with CMR factors would vary by sex. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Data source </p>

<p>Data from the 2010-2014 US NHIS were utilized for this 
study. The NHIS is administered by the US Bureau of the 
Census for the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) </p>

<p>26   as an annual cross-sectional nationally representative survey 
of civilian noninstitutionalized US adults 18 years and older. 
Utilizing a multistage stratified cluster probability design with 
an oversampling of African Americans and Hispanic Ameri-
cans, the NHIS includes approximately 45 000 households 
and about 110 000 persons annually. 
27 The full methodology </p>

<p>of the NHIS is published elsewhere. 
27 Respondents provide </p>

<p>information on health indicators, healthcare utilization, and 
social and demographic characteristics. The NHIS uses one 
randomly selected adult per household to obtain in-depth 
information on healthcare services, health behavior, and 
health status. 
This study is restricted to 54 984 immigrants (defined as 
persons living in the US who reported being born outside the 
US). We pooled and merged data for the years 2010-2014 for 
use in this investigation, merging the sample adult file with 
the person-level file using established NCHS guidelines for 
combining NHIS data with the same sample design. 
26,27 The </p>

<p>year 2012 was considered the midpoint of the 2010-2014 
time frame included in the pooled data and so our estimates 
represent this time point. 
27 This study was exempt from </p>

<p>institutional review board review because deidentified data 
published by the NCHS were used in this study. </p>

<p>Study Population </p>

<p>All respondents self-reporting as foreign born were consid-
ered immigrants; this definition includes legal permanent 
residents, naturalized citizens, undocumented immigrants, 
and those with visas including students or temporary workers. 
Participants' place of birth data are provided in the NHIS 
based on the question, "Where were you born?" This variable 
categorizes respondents in the following 9 mutually exclusive 
regions of birth: Mexico, Central America, Caribbean Islands 
(hereafter Mexico); South America; Europe; Russia (and </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Acculturation and Cardiometabolic Risk in Immigrants 
Commodore-Mensah et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>former Soviet Union areas); Africa; the Middle East; Indian 
subcontinent; Central Asia; and Southeast Asia. Details on 
specific countries included in each of the regions are 
published elsewhere. </p>

<p>26   Outcomes </p>

<p>Overweight/obesity, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, and 
hyperlipidemia were the main outcomes. Body mass index 
(BMI) was calculated using NHIS participants' self-reported 
height and weight. BMI categories were defined as normal 
weight (18.5-24.9 kg/m 
2 ), overweight (25.0-29.9 kg/m 
2 ), </p>

<p>and obese (≥30 kg/m 
2 ). 
28 For this analysis, we dichotomized </p>

<p>BMI as either overweight/obese or normal weight. Hyperten-
sion, diabetes mellitus, and hyperlipidemia status were self-
reported. For instance, hypertension status was assessed 
with the question, "Have you ever been told by a medical 
doctor or health professional that you have hypertension, also 
called high blood pressure?" </p>

<p>Covariates </p>

<p>Using 10 years as a cutoff, we stratified the study population 
into two groups based on their acculturation (length of 
residence in the US). This is consistent with the definition of 
acculturation, in which lower acculturation was defined as 
residing in the US for &lt;10 years and higher acculturation as 
residing in the US for ≥10 years. 
17 Other variables included </p>

<p>age, sex, marital status, access to healthcare (health insur-
ance status), and socioeconomic status (income). We treated 
age in years as a categorical variable (&lt;25, 25-44, 45-64, 
65-74, ≥75) and sex as a dichotomous variable (male or 
female). Health insurance status was assessed from a 
detailed question about multiple sources of insurance and 
recoded as private, public, and noncoverage. The NCHS 
created and recoded a poverty income ratio (PIR; calculated 
as the ratio of the midpoint family income divided by the 
poverty level in dollars as defined by the Census Bureau for 
the corresponding survey year; &lt;1.00 [below federal poverty 
line], 1.00-1.99, 2.00-2.99, 3.00-4.99, and ≥5.00). We 
recoded this variable as poor/near poor (&lt;2.00) versus not 
poor/near poor (≥2). Education status was examined as a 
categorical variable (less than a high school education versus 
a high school education or higher). Marital status was 
examined with the following categories: currently married 
(living or not living with spouse or partner), previously married 
(divorced, separated, or widowed), and never married. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>All analyses were performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">2014</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp</rs>, 
College Station, TX). Sampling weights for the years 2010-</p>

<p>2014 were adjusted to account for pooling of the data. 
29 We </p>

<p>compared the two groups of immigrants (low and high 
acculturation) by sociodemographic characteristics and 
prevalence of hypertension, overweight/obesity, diabetes 
mellitus, and hyperlipidemia. We used chi-square test to 
assess differences in categorical variables and analysis of 
variance test for continuous variables. We estimated age-</p>

<p>Table 1. Sociodemographic Characteristics of US Immigrants 
by Length of Residence in the United States: 2010-2014 
National Health Interview Survey </p>

<p>Characteristic 
(Mean [SE], 
No. [%]) </p>

<p>Total 
N=54 984 </p>

<p>&lt;10 y 
n=12 317 </p>

<p>≥10 y 
n=42 667 
P Value </p>

<p>Age 
43.2 (0.2) 
35.1 (0.2) 45.5 (0.2) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Age categories, y, % </p>

<p>&lt;25 
13 
21 (0.8) 
10 (0.3) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>25 to 44 
44 
58 (0.9) 
40 (0.5) </p>

<p>45 to 64 
33 
17 (0.6) 
37 (0.4) </p>

<p>65 to 74 
7 
3 (0.2) 
8 (0.1) </p>

<p>≥75 
4 
1 (0.1) 
5 (0.2) </p>

<p>Female, % 
51 
50 (0.7) 
51 (0.3) 
0.557 </p>

<p>Poor/near poor 
40 
50 (1.1) 
38 (0.6) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>&lt;High school 
education </p>

<p>35 
37 (1.0) 
34 (0.6) 
0.001 </p>

<p>Employed 
63 
65 (1.0) 
62 (0.5) 
0.013 </p>

<p>Marital status, % </p>

<p>Married/living 
with partner </p>

<p>70 
69 (0.8) 
71 (0.4) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Previously 
married </p>

<p>10 
6 (0.3) 
11 (0.2) </p>

<p>Never 
married </p>

<p>20 
25 (0.8) 
18 (0.3) </p>

<p>Health insurance 
coverage, % </p>

<p>67 
54 (1.1) 
71 (0.6) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Region of birth </p>

<p>Europe 
4146 (8) 
514 (12) 
3632 (88) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>South 
America </p>

<p>3546 (6) 
829 (23) 
2717 (77) </p>

<p>Mexico 
30 146 (55) 5602 (19) 24 544 (81) </p>

<p>Russia 
739 (1) 
184 (25) 
555 (75) </p>

<p>Africa 
2019 (4) 
748 (37) 
1271 (63) </p>

<p>Middle East 
1029 (2) 
328 (32) 
701 (68) </p>

<p>Indian 
subcontinent </p>

<p>3417 (6) 
1575 (46) 1843 (54) </p>

<p>Central Asia 
3869 (7) 
1145 (30) 2724 (70) </p>

<p>Southeast 
Asia </p>

<p>6073 (11)  1393 (23) 4680 (77) </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Acculturation and Cardiometabolic Risk in Immigrants 
Commodore-Mensah et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>and sex-adjusted prevalence of overweight/obesity, hyper-
tension, diabetes mellitus, and hyperlipidemia by length of 
residence in the US. 
We tested for effect modification of sex on the relation-
ship between length of residence and CMR factors by 
including an interaction term (sex9length of residence). We 
used multivariable logistic regression analyses to determine 
the association between length of US residence and 
overweight/obesity, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, and 
hyperlipidemia, adjusting for known confounders. For each 
of the four outcomes (overweight/obesity, hypertension, 
diabetes mellitus, and hyperlipidemia), we fitted 3 multiple 
logistic regression models with length of US residence as 
the main predictor (reference group &lt;10 years) controlling 
for age, poverty status, health insurance, sex, and region of 
birth. In addition to these covariates, BMI was included as a 
covariate in the model with diabetes mellitus, hypertension, 
hyperlipidemia as the outcomes. These covariates were </p>

<p>included because of their clinical importance, our bivariate 
findings, and previous studies, which have shown that these 
variables confound the relationship between acculturation 
and CMR factors. 
25,30 A 2-tailed alpha with P&lt;0.05 was </p>

<p>considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Sociodemographic Characteristics </p>

<p>The basic sociodemographic characteristics of the study 
participants (n=54 984) stratified by length of residence in 
the US are presented in Table 1. There were statistically 
significant differences in age, rates of poverty, employment, 
and marital status in participants residing in the US for 
≥10 years compared with those with &lt;10 years of residence 
in the US (P&lt;0.01). Participants residing &lt;10 years in the US 
were younger, better educated, and more employed compared </p>

<p>Table 2. Prevalence of Cardiometabolic Risk Factors Among US Immigrants by Place of Birth: 2010-2014 National Health 
Interview Survey (N=54 984) </p>

<p>(%, 95% CI) </p>

<p>Europe 
n=4146 </p>

<p>South America 
n=3546 </p>

<p>Mexico 
n=30 146 </p>

<p>Russia 
n=739 </p>

<p>Africa 
n=2019 </p>

<p>Middle East 
n=1029 </p>

<p>Indian 
subcontinent 
n=3417 </p>

<p>Central Asia 
n=3869 </p>

<p>Southeast Asia 
n=6073 </p>

<p>Hypertension* 
20 (18-22) 17 (15-19) 
20 (20-22) 25 (2029) 
22 (17-23) 22 (17-26) 18 (16-20) 
18 (16-20) 23 (21-26) </p>

<p>Overweight/ 
obese* </p>

<p>59 (57-62) 58 (54-61) 
71 (70-72) 61 (51-70) 61 (57-65) 59 (54-64) 46 (54-64) 
32 (29-34) 41 (38-44) </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus 6 (5-7) 
6 (4-7) 
10 (9-10) 
6 (3-8) 
7 (5-9) 
9 (6-12) 
9 (7-11) 
6 (4-6) 
8 (7-10) </p>

<p>Hyperlipidemia 
10 (9-11) 
8 (7-10) 
8 (7-9) 
7 (4-9) 
5 (4-7) 
9 (6-12) 
9 (7-11) 
8 (7-10) 
10 (9-11) </p>

<p>CI indicates confidence interval. 
*P&lt;0.05 from chi-square test. </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>10% </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>30% </p>

<p>40% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>70% </p>

<p>Overweight/Obese 
Hypertension 
Diabetes Mellitus 
High Cholesterol </p>

<p>&lt;10y ≥10y </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 
P=0.092 </p>

<p>Figure. Age-and sex-adjusted prevalence of hypertension, overweight/obesity, diabetes mellitus, and </p>

<p>high cholesterol by length of US residence. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Acculturation and Cardiometabolic Risk in Immigrants 
Commodore-Mensah et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>with participants residing in the US for ≥10 years (P&lt;0.01). 
The rate of marriage/living with partners and health insurance 
coverage were higher among those residing in the US for 
≥10 years compared with those residing for &lt;10 years 
(P&lt;0.01). As shown in Table 1, more immigrants originated 
from Mexico (55%) compared with immigrants from Southeast 
Asia (11%), Europe (8%), Central Asia (7%), South America 
(7%), and Indian subcontinent (6%), Africa (4%), Middle East 
(2%), and Russia (1%). </p>

<p>Prevalence of CMR Factors by Region of Birth of 
Immigrants </p>

<p>There was notable heterogeneity in the age-and sex-adjusted 
prevalence of CMR factors by region of birth as illustrated in 
Table 2. The prevalence of hypertension and overweight/ 
obesity differed significantly by region of birth. As shown, the 
prevalence of hypertension was highest in Russian immigrants 
(25%) while the prevalence of overweight (71%) and diabetes 
mellitus (10%) were highest in Mexican immigrants. European 
and South Asian immigrants reported higher prevalence of 
hyperlipidemia (10%) than other immigrants, but this differ-
ence was not statistically significant. </p>

<p>Prevalence of CMR Factors by Length of 
Residence </p>

<p>As shown in Figure 1, the age-and sex-adjusted prevalence of 
CMR factors by length of residence suggests that the 
prevalence of hypertension, overweight/obesity, and diabetes 
mellitus were associated with increased length of US 
residence and indicated by the much higher prevalence in 
immigrants who have resided in the US for ≥10 years than 
immigrants with &lt;10 years of residence in the US. </p>

<p>Adjusted Odds of CMR Factors by Length of 
Residence </p>

<p>The results of the multivariable logistic regression analysis 
examining the relationship between the respective CMR 
factors and length of residence are presented in Tables 3 
through 6. In summary, after adjusting for age, sex, poverty 
status, health insurance, region of birth, and marital status, 
respondents residing in the US for ≥10 years were signifi-
cantly more likely to be overweight/obese (Table 3) and have 
diabetes mellitus (Table 4) and hypertension (Table 5), as 
compared with participants with &lt;10 years of residence. 
After fitting an interaction term between sex and length of 
residence, we observed that sex was an effect modifier for 
the outcomes of diabetes mellitus (P=0.019) and high 
cholesterol (P=0.002), hence stratified analyses are pre-
sented in Tables 4 and 6. Men who had resided in the US for 
≥10 years had a higher odds of diabetes mellitus than 
women who had resided in the US for ≥10 years (P=0.019). 
For the outcome of hyperlipidemia, women who had resided 
in the US for ≥10 years had a higher likelihood of diagnosis 
than those with &lt;10 years of residence. However, this 
relationship was not observed in men. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We sought to examine the contribution of acculturation, 
operationalized as length of US residence, on the prevalence 
of CMR factors in a contemporary and ethnically diverse 
sample of immigrants. Our findings support our hypothesis 
that increased years of US residence is associated with a 
higher prevalence of CMR factors, specifically hypertension, 
overweight/obesity, and diabetes mellitus. However, we did 
not observe an association between acculturation and 
hyperlipidemia in this study. 
Several lines of evidence have shown that acculturation to 
Western society is associated with hypertension. 
31-34 Accul-</p>

<p>turation is said to increase blood pressure (BP) through 
stressors associated with migration and cultural and behav-
ioral changes (in diet, physical activity, smoking) that occur 
after migration. Regarding the stress pathway, acculturation </p>

<p>Table 3. Multivariable Adjusted Odds of Overweight/Obesity 
Among US Immigrants: 2010-2014 National Health Interview 
Survey </p>

<p>AOR 
95% CI </p>

<p>Length of residence </p>

<p>&lt;10 y 
Ref 
Ref </p>

<p>≥10 y 
1.19* 
1.10 to 1.29* </p>

<p>Age 
1.01* 
1.00 to 1.01* </p>

<p>Not poor/near poor 
0.89* 
0.83 to 0.96* </p>

<p>Region of birth </p>

<p>Mexico 
Ref 
Ref </p>

<p>South America 
0.57* 
0.48 to 0.68* </p>

<p>Europe 
0.60* 
0.53 to 0.68* </p>

<p>Russia 
0.64* 
0.43 to 0.95* </p>

<p>Africa 
0.68* 
0.56 to 0.83* </p>

<p>Middle East 
0.61* 
0.48 to 0.76* </p>

<p>India 
0.36* 
0.31 to 0.42* </p>

<p>Central Asia 
0.19* 
0.16 to 0.22* </p>

<p>Southeast Asia 
0.29* 
0.25 to 0.33* </p>

<p>Sex 
0.78* 
0.75 to 0.83* </p>

<p>Health insurance 
0.96 
0.89 to 1.03 </p>

<p>Married (yes) 
1.36* 
1.26 to 1.47* </p>

<p>AOR indicates adjusted odds ratio; CI, confidence interval. 
*P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Acculturation and Cardiometabolic Risk in Immigrants 
Commodore-Mensah et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>to Western society is associated with a decrease in social 
support (a protective factor) and increased job demands, </p>

<p>35,36   which contribute to hypertension. While migration to the US 
creates an avenue for employment and economic well-being, 
the stress of adjusting to a new environment contributes to BP 
elevation. A meta-analysis by Steffen et al 
31 examining the </p>

<p>strength of the association between acculturation and BP 
observed that overall effect sizes associated with acculturation 
were 0.28 for systolic BP and 0.30 for diastolic BP, with 
increasing acculturation to Western society related to higher 
BP. Immigrants with higher levels of acculturation had an 
average of 4 mm Hg higher BP than those with lower levels of 
acculturation; this is similar to the effect sizes of traditional 
CMR factors including poor diet and physical inactivity. 
Migration results in changes in obesogenic behaviors and 
environments that contribute to overweight/obesity. Prior 
studies have found that immigrants from low-to medium-
income countries who have migrated to and reside in high-
income countries are more susceptible to overweight and 
obesity than their local counterparts. 
37,38 The unhealthy </p>

<p>weight gain is estimated to occur after 10 to 15 years of </p>

<p>residence in the host country, after which the overweight and 
obesity rates approach or exceed that of the host popula-
tion. 
39,40 Several studies have also shown positive correla-</p>

<p>tions between length of residence in high-income countries 
and weight gain. 
41,42 In our study, we observed that for both </p>

<p>sexes, even after adjusting for known sociodemographic 
variables, those residing in the US for more than a decade 
were more likely to be overweight/obese than newer 
residents. Two factors may account for this phenomenon. 
First, dietary acculturation-shifts from traditional diets of 
vegetables, meats, and whole grains to highly processed, 
high-fat, and high-sugar foods that are popular and readily 
available in the US 
43 -occurs when immigrants migrate to the </p>

<p>US. The limited availability of ethnic foods in the host country 
may compound this problem, with immigrants choosing 
readily available unhealthy foods, such as snacks and fast 
food, over their traditional diets. Second, physical activity 
levels may change upon migration to the US. Physical activity 
acculturation and the increased frequency of sedentary 
activities with increased years of US residence contribute to 
overweight/obesity. 
43 Prior studies of Asian and Hispanic </p>

<p>Table 4. Multivariable Adjusted Odds of Diabetes Mellitus Among US Immigrants: 2010-2014 National Health Interview Survey </p>

<p>Total 
N=54 984 </p>

<p>Men 
n=25 891 (47%) </p>

<p>Women 
n=29 093 (53%) </p>

<p>AOR 
95% CI 
AOR 
95% CI 
AOR 
95% CI </p>

<p>Length of residence </p>

<p>&lt;10 y 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref </p>

<p>≥10 y 
1.43* 
1.17 to 1.73* 
1.65* 
1.28 to 2.13* 
1.25* 
1.02 to 1.55* </p>

<p>Age 
1.05* 
1.05 to 1.06* 
1.05* 
1.05 to 1.06* 
1.05* 
1.04 to 1.05* </p>

<p>Not poor/near poor 
0.78* 
0.68 to 0.90* 
0.73* 
0.62 to 0.87* 
0.83* 
0.71 to 0.97* </p>

<p>Region of birth </p>

<p>Mexico 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref </p>

<p>South America 
0.58* 
0.43 to 0.79* 
0.58* 
0.40 to 0.84* 
0.59* 
0.42 to 0.82* </p>

<p>Europe 
0.54* 
0.44 to 0.66* 
0.54* 
0.42 to 0.69* 
0.53* 
0.41 to 0.69* </p>

<p>Russia 
0.51* 
0.28 to 0.91* 
0.52* 
0.28 to 0.97* 
0.49* 
0.24 to 0.99* </p>

<p>Africa 
0.80 
0.58 to 1.11 
1.02 
0.68 to 1.52 
0.59 
0.41 to 0.84 </p>

<p>Middle East 
0.93 
0.62 to 1.41 
0.85 
0.58 to 1.26 
1.01 
0.55 to 1.88 </p>

<p>India 
1.12 
0.86 to 1.45 
1.12 
0.86 to 1.45 
1.12 
0.79 to 1.59 </p>

<p>Central Asia 
0.56* 
0.44 to 0.71* 
0.58* 
0.43 to 0.80* 
0.54* 
0.40 to 0.73* </p>

<p>Southeast Asia 
0.92 
0.75 to 1.13 
0.92 
0.70 to 1.20 
0.92 
0.74 to 1.14 </p>

<p>Sex 
0.97* 
0.90 to 1.06* 
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>Health insurance 
1.09 
0.95 to 1.24 
1.07 
0.89 to 1.28 
1.11 
0.94 to 1.32 </p>

<p>Married (yes) 
0.89* 
0.80 to 0.98* 
1.17* 
1.07 to 1.29* 
1.10* 
1.00 to 1.20* </p>

<p>BMI 
1.01* 
1.01 to 1.02* 
1.01* 
1.01 to 1.02* 
1.01* 
1.01 to 1.02* </p>

<p>AOR indicates adjusted odds ratio; BMI, body mass index. 
*P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Acculturation and Cardiometabolic Risk in Immigrants 
Commodore-Mensah et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>immigrants suggest that higher acculturation may be associ-
ated with less physical activity. 
43,44 Since low-income and low </p>

<p>educational status are strongly associated with low leisure-
time physical activity, 
45 it is likely that socioeconomic </p>

<p>challenges that immigrants face may limit their ability to 
engage in leisure-time physical activity. Culturally tailored 
programs to improve physical activity levels in immigrants 
may improve CMR factors but also prevent diseases such as 
coronary heart disease, diabetes mellitus, and heart attacks. 
Behavioral changes that occur upon migration to the US 
may contribute to the development of diabetes mellitus in 
immigrants. Prior studies 
46,47 have observed mixed findings </p>

<p>on the association between acculturation and diabetes 
mellitus; this is not unusual because the health effects of 
acculturation vary by country of origin. Although our findings 
suggest that immigrants residing in the US for more than a 
decade have higher odds of reporting a diabetes mellitus 
diagnosis, it is possible that this relationship may not be 
consistent across all of the regions examined. The associ-
ation between acculturation and diabetes mellitus was 
stronger in male immigrants than female immigrants, a 
finding consistent with a previous study in Latinos where 
acculturation was assessed with length of residence, </p>

<p>language proficiency, current and desired environments, 
and ethnic identity. 
48 Using the NHIS 2007-2010, Brian </p>

<p>et al 
49 also observed that acculturation, measured with </p>

<p>nativity, language spoken at home, and length of US 
residence, was associated with a higher prevalence of 
diabetes mellitus in US Latino adults, a relationship only 
partly explained by BMI and weight-related behaviors such as 
total dietary calories and physical inactivity. Notably, most 
studies examining the relationship between acculturation and 
CMR factors in immigrants have focused primarily on 
Hispanic and Asian immigrants with very few addressing 
other immigrant population. 
In this study, we observed that female immigrants residing 
in the US for more than a decade were significantly more 
likely to report hyperlipidemia than newer residents. This 
finding conflicts with findings from Koya et al 
25 of higher odds </p>

<p>of hyperlipidemia with increasing years of US residence in 
men but not women. In the landmark Hispanic Community 
Health Study/Study of Latinos (HCHS/SOL), Rodriguez 
et al 
50 observed that longer US residence was associated </p>

<p>with higher odds of hyperlipidemia awareness, treatment, and 
control. Given the impact of hyperlipidemia on car-
diometabolic outcomes, it is important that additional studies 
be conducted in various immigrant groups to understand how 
the acculturation process may influence the development and 
treatment of hyperlipidemia. 
Our results showed a significant difference in health 
insurance coverage between long-term versus newer resi-
dents. While this may not be a direct measure of utilization of 
health screening services, it raises the possibility of bias and 
under-reporting of CMR factors as a result of underdiagnosis 
in newer immigrants even after adjusting for this as a possible 
confounder. It is possible that more acculturated immigrants 
report CMR/diseases because they are more likely than 
newer immigrants to have had adequate evaluation and 
diagnoses by healthcare providers. </p>

<p>Study Limitations </p>

<p>Several limitations to this study must be considered in the 
interpretation of our findings. First, CMR factors were 
obtained through self-report, as is all information in the NHIS; 
it is possible that the prevalence of hypertension, overweight/ 
obesity, diabetes mellitus, and hyperlipidemia may be over-
estimated or underestimated. The limitation is inherent in the 
NHIS as all information is obtained through self-report. It is 
also difficult to ascertain whether language barriers in the 
participants who were not native English speakers affected 
the accuracy of the self-reported data. Second, length of US 
residence is one of several proxy measures of acculturation 
and does not fully reflect the complex process of accultur-
ation like validated bidimensional acculturation measures. </p>

<p>Table 5. Multivariable Adjusted Odds of Hypertension Among 
US Immigrants: 2010-2014 National Health Interview Survey </p>

<p>AOR 
95% CI </p>

<p>Length of residence </p>

<p>&lt;10 y 
Ref 
Ref </p>

<p>≥10 y 
1.18* 
1.05 to 1.32* </p>

<p>Age 
1.06* 
1.05 to 1.06* </p>

<p>Not poor/near poor 
0.82* 
0.74 to 0.90* </p>

<p>Region of birth </p>

<p>Mexico 
Ref 
Ref </p>

<p>South America 
0.79* 
0.67 to 0.94* </p>

<p>Europe 
0.98 
0.85 to 1.13 </p>

<p>Russia 
1.33 
0.99 to 1.78 </p>

<p>Africa 
1.01 
0.79 to 1.30 </p>

<p>Middle East 
1.09 
0.80 to 1.49 </p>

<p>India 
0.93 
0.77 to 1.13 </p>

<p>Central Asia 
0.86 
0.72 to 1.02 </p>

<p>Southeast Asia 
1.26* 
1.08 to 1.48* </p>

<p>Sex 
1.00* 
0.94 to 1.07* </p>

<p>Health insurance 
1.20* 
1.09 to 1.32* </p>

<p>Married (yes) 
0.81* 
0.74 to 0.87* </p>

<p>BMI 
1.01* 
1.01 to 1.02* </p>

<p>AOR indicates adjusted odds ratio; BMI, body mass index. 
*P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Acculturation and Cardiometabolic Risk in Immigrants 
Commodore-Mensah et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Third, the cross-sectional nature of our study precludes us 
from making any causal inferences. Fourth, it is also possible 
that there may be residual confounding, which may account 
for the association between length of US residence and the 
prevalence of these CMR factors. Fifth, the sample represents 
only immigrants from broadly defined groups who participated 
in the NHIS, and our findings may not apply to the entire 
immigrant population in the US. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>We observed that in both sexes of an ethnically diverse 
sample of US immigrants, acculturation was associated with a 
higher prevalence of certain CMR factors. Immigrants residing 
in the US for ≥10 years were more likely to report a history of 
hypertension, overweight/obesity, and diabetes mellitus but 
not hyperlipidemia than those who had resided in the US for 
&lt;10 years. As the US continues to diversify, it is important to 
understand the evolution of CMR factors in new immigrants to 
prevent adverse health outcomes such as myocardial infarc-
tion, stroke, and kidney disease. Because different </p>

<p>acculturation experiences among immigrants in the US may 
contribute to their risk for CMR factors, it may be necessary 
to examine unique associations between CMR factors and 
acculturation separately among US immigrant subgroups. 
Future longitudinal studies of diverse immigrant groups may 
provide crucial information on which socioeconomic, behav-
ioral, environmental, and epigenetic factors contribute to CMR 
in immigrants to inform the development of culturally tailored 
interventions to mitigate CMR. Specifically, research examin-
ing the uptake of primary care and health screening services 
between newer versus long-term immigrants is needed. 
Targeted interventions to screen for CMR factors and educate 
immigrant populations are also needed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Dr Kenneth Hepburn for his editorial review of this 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>None. </p>

<p>Table 6. Multivariable Adjusted Odds of Hyperlipidemia Among US Immigrants: 2010-2014 National Health Interview Survey </p>

<p>Total 
N=54 984 </p>

<p>Men 
n=25 891 (47%) </p>

<p>Women 
n=29 093 (53%) </p>

<p>AOR 
95% CI 
AOR 
95% CI 
AOR 
95% CI </p>

<p>Length of residence </p>

<p>&lt;10 y 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref </p>

<p>≥10 y 
1.05 
0.90 to 1.24 
0.89 
0.71 to 1.10 
1.36* 
1.07 to 1.72* </p>

<p>Age 
1.04* 
1.04 to 1.05* 
1.03* 
1.03 to 1.04* 
1.05* 
1.04 to 1.05* </p>

<p>Not poor/near poor 
0.99* 
0.86 to 1.13* 
1.03 
0.84 to 1.26 
0.94* 
0.79 to 1.13* </p>

<p>Region of birth </p>

<p>Mexico 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref 
Ref </p>

<p>South America 
1.04* 
0.82 to 1.32* 
1.27 
0.93 to 1.74 
0.80* 
0.58 to 1.11* </p>

<p>Europe 
1.14 
0.95 to 1.37 
1.08 
0.85 to 1.38 
1.21 
0.92 to 1.58 </p>

<p>Russia 
0.72 
0.46 to 1.26 
0.79 
0.49 to 1.27 
0.66 
0.37 to 1.18 </p>

<p>Africa 
0.59* 
0.43 to 0.83* 
0.72 
0.46 to 1.13 
0.43* 
0.27 to 0.68* </p>

<p>Middle East 
1.02 
0.69 to 1.50 
0.91 
0.61 to 1.35 
1.19 
0.56 to 2.56 </p>

<p>India 
1.11 
0.82 to 1.51 
1.20 
0.82 to 1.74 
0.96 
0.55 to 1.67 </p>

<p>Central Asia 
0.93 
0.72 to 1.19 
0.99 
0.70 to 1.41 
0.87 
0.63 to 1.21 </p>

<p>Southeast Asia 
1.20* 
1.01 to 1.41* 
1.45* 
1.12 to 1.88* 
0.95 
0.74 to 1.24 </p>

<p>Sex 
0.72* 
0.64 to 0.82* 
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>Health insurance 
1.37* 
1.16 to 1.61* 
1.63* 
1.31 to 2.04* 
1.09* 
0.90 to 1.33* </p>

<p>Married (yes) 
1.08 
0.93 to 1.25 
0.82* 
0.69 to 0.98* 
0.99 
0.88 to 1.12 </p>

<p>BMI 
1.01 
1.00 to 1.01* 
1.00 
1.00 to 1.01 
1.01 
1.00 to 1.01 </p>

<p>AOR indicates adjusted odds ratio; BMI, body mass index. 
*P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Acculturation and Cardiometabolic Risk in Immigrants 
Commodore-Mensah et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>



<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Acculturation and Cardiometabolic Risk in Immigrants 
Commodore-Mensah et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>



<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.004059 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Acculturation and Cardiometabolic Risk in Immigrants 
Commodore-Mensah et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

</text></tei>