<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5128353" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>small proteins that are regarded as the hormones of the im-
mune system. 
8 Cytokines affect brain function by supporting 
neuronal integrity, neurogenesis, and synaptic remodeling. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Cytokines also have an effect on neurotransmitter systems 
and the neurocircuit, inducing behavioral alternations. </p>

<p>10-13 </p>

<p>Numerous studies have reported the increase of proinflam-
matory cytokines: IL-1, IL-6, tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-
alpha, and prostaglandin E2 (PGE2), in major depressive 
disorder. 
14-17 A study with a cerebrospinal fluid assay reported 
that IL-6 concentrations correlate with the severity of depres-
sion. 
18 A recent meta-analysis showed that the concentrations 
of cytokines (IL-1beta, IL-6, and TNF-alpha) are decreased 
after antidepressant treatment. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>A series of meta-analyses confirmed the correlation between 
pro-inflammatory cytokines (TNF-alpha and IL-6) and 
MDD; 
7,14,20 however, the role of other cytokines in MDD re-
mains unclear. In addition, ethnicity may play an important 
role in the relationship between the levels of cytokines and 
MDD, and relatively few studies have been conducted in the </p>

<p>ObjectiveaaCytokines have been reported to have key roles in major depressive disorder (MDD). However, much less is known about 
cytokines in MDD and antidepressant treatment due to the diversity of cytokines and the heterogeneity of depression. We investigated 
the levels of cytokines in patients with MDD compared with healthy subjects and their associations with antidepressant response. 
MethodsaaWe investigated the changes of several cytokines (eotaxin, sCD40L, IL-8, MCP-1alpha, TNF-alpha, INF-gamma and MIP-
1alpha) by Luminex assay in 66 patients with MDD and 22 healthy controls. The antidepressant response was assessed by 17-item Ham-
ilton Rating Scale for Depression. 
ResultsaaWe found the levels of sCD40L (p=0.001), IL-8 (p=0.004) and MCP-1 (p=0.03) of healthy controls were significantly higher 
than those of depressive patients. However, the level of eotaxin and TNF-alpha were not associated with MDD. In addition, we found 
the level of MCP-1 was significantly changed after antidepressant treatment (p=0.01). 
ConclusionaaThese findings suggest the roles of cytokines in MDD are complex, and could vary according to the individual character-
istics of each patient. Further studies regarding the relationship between cytokines and MDD will be required. </p>

<p>Psychiatry Investig 2016;13(6):644-651 </p>

<p>W Myung et al. </p>

<p>www.psychiatryinvestigation.org 645 </p>

<p>Asian population. 
7 In this study, we investigated cytokines that 
have been known to have a role in psychiatric disorder in Ko-
rean population with MDD. 
Our primary hypothesis is that the levels of cytokines would 
differ between the patients with MDD and healthy subjects. 
Secondary, we tested their associations with antidepressant re-
sponsiveness and the severity of depression. Additionally, we 
investigated their changes due to antidepressant medication. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>Sixty-six Korean patients with MDD were recruited from 
the clinical trials program of the Samsung Medical Center 
Geropsychiatry and Affective Disorder Clinics (Seoul, Korea). 
Patients fulfilled the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of 
Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition, Text Revision (DSM-IV-
TR), criteria for major depressive episode. 
21,22 Diagnoses were 
confirmed by a board certified psychiatrist on the basis of an 
initial clinical interview and a structured research interview. </p>

<p>23,24   A minimum baseline 17-item Hamilton Rating Scale for De-
pression (HAM-D) score of 15 was required. 
25 Exclusion crite-
ria were pregnancy, significant medical conditions, abnormal 
laboratory baseline values, unstable psychiatric features (e.g, 
suicide attempt), histories of alcohol or drug dependence, sei-
zure, neurological illnesses, including significant cognitive im-
pairment, or concomitant Axis I psychiatric disorders (schizo-
phrenia, bipolar affective disorder, primary diagnosis of 
adjustment disorder, or posttraumatic stress disorder). No pa-
tient met the DSM-IV criteria for the specifier 'Severe with 
Psychotic Features' , and none had received psychotropic medi-
cation with the current episode. In addition, no patients had 
received psychotropic medication within 4 weeks. Twenty-
two healthy volunteers without histories of psychiatric illness 
were recruited by advertisement. A psychiatrist screened the 
control group with an interview and then biochemical tests 
were administered. Volunteers with a family history of mood 
disorders or evidence of inflammatory illness (flu, allergic 
disease, or dermatitis) or immunopathies were not included. 
The protocol was approved by the ethics review board of Sam-
sung Medical Center, Seoul, Korea. </p>

<p>Procedures </p>

<p>Patients received an antidepressant monotherapy for 6 weeks. 
SSRIs [escitalopram (n=31), sertraline (n=2), paroxetine (n= 
11), fluoxetine (n=1)] and mirtazapine (n=21) were chosen 
by clinician based on the anticipated adverse effects and the 
symptomatic characteristics of patients. Dose titration was 
completed within two weeks to check compliance. The HAM-
D scores 
26 were obtained by a single trained rater every two </p>

<p>weeks. A response was defined as a decrease in HAM-D score 
of 50% or more at week 6. 
27 The rater and laboratory workers 
were blinded to the purpose of this study. In addition, cytokine 
data were not disclosed to the rater and the HAM-D scores 
were not exposed to the laboratory workers. </p>

<p>Determination of cytokine levels </p>

<p>Through a literature survey based on their likely importance 
for the psychiatric disorder, we initially selected 19 cytokines 
(exotaxin, sCD40L, IL-1a, IL-1b, IL-2, IL-4, IL-7, IL-8, IL-10, 
IL-12, FGF-2, MCP-1, TNF-alpha, alpha2-macroglobulin, 
Apoprotein AI, Apoprotein E, C3, INF-gamma and MIP-1al-
pha). We evaluated the analytical performance of the com-
mercially available assay kits, Human Cytokine/Chemokine 
Magnetic Bead Panel 1 and Human Neurodegenerative Dis-
ease Panel 1 (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA). Seven cytokines 
(eotaxin, sCD40L, IL-8, MCP-1, TNF-alpha, INF-gamma, and 
MIP-1alpha) were finally selected in the consideration of pre-
cision, calibration range and the limit of quantification of the 
assay method. These inflammatory markers have been shown 
to be relevant in psychiatric diseases. 
7,14,15,28,29 Venous blood 
was drawn at baseline and at week 6. After serum isolation by 
centrifugation, the samples were stored at -80°C. Inflamma-
tory markers were measured using 25 μL of serum with a 
Luminex 200 analyzer (Luminex Corporation, Austin, TX, 
USA) with the Human Cytokine/Chemokine Magnetic Bead 
Panel 1. 
Markers for which more than 10% of the samples had val-
ues below limit of quantitation (LOQ) at baseline were not 
included in the analysis. 
30 Two cytokines were excluded from 
the analysis because they frequently had values below the 
LOQ (53.4% for INF-gamma, and 67.0% for MIP-1alpha). 
Eotaxin (none), sCD40L (none), IL-8 (1.1%), MCP-1 (none), 
TNF-alpha (8.0%) were included in the analysis. For each 
marker retained for analysis, samples with undetectable val-
ues were given the value zero. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Continuous variables are presented as median and inter-
quartile range. The Wilcoxon rank-sum test was employed to 
compare these variables between healthy control subjects and 
patients or the responsive and non-responsive groups. Cate-
gorical variables were presented as frequencies and propor-
tions, and tested with Fisher's exact test. Median regression 
was employed to compare non-normally distributed continu-
ous variables adjusting for other variables. The Wilcoxon signed-
rank test was used to compare the cytokine values of pre-and 
post-antidepressant treatment. Relationships between two 
continuous variables were tested by Spearman's correlation 
analysis. p-values were corrected by Bonferroni's correction </p>



<p>Serum Cytokine Levels in Depression </p>

<p>for the multiple association tests of cytokines and noted as cor-
rected p. All differences were considered to be significant at 
p&lt;0.05. Statistical analysis was undertaken using <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA SE</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">10.0</rs> for Windows (College Station, TX, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinical and demographic characteristics </p>

<p>Clinical and demographic characteristics are shown in Table 
1. There were no notable differences between the control sub-</p>

<p>jects and patients with respect to age and sex. The rate of re-
sponse to antidepressants was 40 of 66 patients (60.6%). A fam-
ily history of depression was present in 15.2% of the patients. 
The median baseline HAM-D score was 19 (interquartile range: 
17-21), indicating moderate to severe depression. Age, sex, 
episode number, current episode duration, age at onset, and 
baseline HAM-D score were not associated with antidepres-
sant responsiveness. In addition, choice of drug had no effect 
on the rate of response (p&gt;0.05). The median HAM-D score 
gradually decreased from 19 to 9 (week 2: 15, 
12-18 week 4: 12, </p>

<p>9-17   Table 1. Clinical and demographic characteristics of subjects </p>

<p>Variable 
Control subjects 
(N=22) </p>

<p>Depressive patients (N=66) 
Statistics and p 
Drug responsive 
(N=40) </p>

<p>Drug non-responsive 
(N=26) </p>

<p>Female, no. (%)* 
16 (72.7%) 
50 (75.8%) 
p=0.78 </p>

<p>28 (70.0%) 
22 (84.6%) 
p=0.24 </p>

<p>Age, year  † 
66.5 (64, 69) 
68 (60, 73) 
Z=-0.34, p=0.73 </p>

<p>69.5 (61.5, 73) 
68 (55, 72) 
Z=-0.91, p=0.36 </p>

<p>Family history of depression (%) 
10 (15.2%) 
p=1 </p>

<p>5 (12.5%) 
5 (19.2%) </p>

<p>Episode, no  † 
2 (1, 3) 
Z=1.54, p=0.12 </p>

<p>2 (1, 2) 
2 (2, 3) </p>

<p>Current episode duration, months 
3 (2, 12) 
Z=0.70, p=0.48 </p>

<p>3.5 (2, 10.5) 
3 (2, 13) </p>

<p>Age at onset, year  † 
59 (48, 67) 
Z=-1.27, p=0.20 </p>

<p>60.5 (51, 67) 
55 (32, 62) </p>

<p>HAM-D baseline  ‡ 
19 (17, 21) 
Z=1.10, p=0.27 </p>

<p>18 (17, 21) 
20 (17, 22) </p>

<p>Data are given as median and interquartile range. *Fisher' s exact test was used, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Wilcoxon rank-sum test was used. HAM-D: Hamilton depres-
sion rating score </p>

<p>Table 2. Baseline serum concentrations of cytokines in major depressive patients (N=66) and healthy controls (N=22) </p>

<p>Variable 
(pg/mL) </p>

<p>Control subjects 
(N=22) </p>

<p>Depressive patients (N=66) 
Statistics 
(Z)* </p>

<p>Corrected 
p* </p>

<p>Corrected p after 
adjusting for covariates  † 
Drug responsive 
(N=40) </p>

<p>Drug non-responsive 
(N=26) </p>

<p>Eotaxin 
135 (113, 172) 
135 (104, 190) 
0.24 
1 
1 </p>

<p>136.5 (109.5, 198.5) 
133 (99, 174) 
-0.60 
1 
1 </p>

<p>sCD40L 
44950 (28800, 66700) 
19700 (5990, 40800) 
3.07 
0.01 
0.001 </p>

<p>15100 (4965, 41600) 
23450 (8460, 40800) 
0.74 
1 
1 </p>

<p>IL-8 
15.65 (10.7, 21.2) 
10.01 (7.2, 13.6) 
3.09 
0.01 
0.004 </p>

<p>10.25 (7.37, 13.8) 
9.87 (6.78, 13) 
0.16 
1 
1 </p>

<p>MCP-1 
462.5 (373, 584) 
342 (235, 407) 
3.58 
0.002 
0.03 </p>

<p>350.5 (228, 456) 
304 (260, 371) 
-0.93 
1 
1 </p>

<p>TNF-alpha 
5.46 (3.7, 7.64) 
5.02 (2.9, 7.18) 
0.61 
1 
1 </p>

<p>5.02 (2.9, 7.18) 
4.86 (2.72, 9.18) 
0.14 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Data are given as median and interquartile range. *Wilcoxon rank-sum test was used; with Bonferroni correction for five cytokines, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Median re-
gression analysis was used after adjusting for age and sex; with Bonferroni correction for five cytokines. sCD40L: soluble CD40-ligand, IL-8: 
interleukin 8, MCP-1: monocyte chemoattractant protein-1, TNF-alpha: tumor necrosis factor alpha </p>

<p>W Myung et al. </p>

<p>www.psychiatryinvestigation.org 647 </p>

<p>week 6: 9 </p>

<p>6-14   ). </p>

<p>Serum cytokine levels and diagnosis </p>

<p>Baseline plasma concentrations of cytokines in the partici-
pants are shown in Table 2 and Figure 1. The median value of 
sCD40L of healthy controls was higher than that of depres-
sive patients (44950 pg/mL, 2880-66700 pg/mL vs 19700, 
5990-40800 pg/mL, respectively; corrected p=0.01). This dif-
ference was maintained after adjusted for age and sex [ad-
justed p=0.001, 95% confidence interval (CI)=14036.24- 43266.99]. IL-8 (corrected p=0.01) and MCP-1 (corrected p= 
0.002) were significantly associated with a diagnosis of major 
depressive disorder. The levels of IL-8 and MCP-1 were high-
er in healthy controls when compared to depressive patients. 
These associations were robust after adjusted for age and sex 
(IL-8: adjusted p=0.004, 95% CI=3.09-10.73, MCP-1: adjust-
ed p=0.03, 95% CI=44.71-254.38). The levels of these cyto-
kines did not differ with sex, old age (&gt;60), late onset (&gt;60) 
and recurrence (number of episode ≥2). </p>

<p>Serum cytokine levels and antidepressant treatment </p>

<p>We found no association between baseline cytokine concen-
tration and antidepressant response (Table 2). In addition, 
changes of cytokine concentrations after 6 weeks of antide-</p>

<p>pressant treatment were not associated with responsiveness. 
We found the level of MCP-1 significantly increased after 
antidepressant treatment (corrected p=0.01) (Table 3). This 
association was observed in both the response (corrected p= 
0.04) and non-response (corrected p=0.04) groups. Moreover, 
the significance of difference in MCP-1 concentration between 
the healthy controls and depressive patients disappeared after 
antidepressant treatment (p=0.06, 95% CI=-2.34-168.80). </p>

<p>Serum cytokine levels and severity of depression </p>

<p>There was no significant correlation between HAM-D score 
and cytokine concentration at baseline and at week 6. The 
HAM-D score changes did not correlate with cytokine level 
changes after antidepressant treatment. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we investigated the association between de-
pression response to antidepressant medication, and several 
inflammatory cytokines. We identified the association between 
diagnosis of depression and three cytokines (sCD40L, IL-8 
and MCP-1), and we found that the level of MCP-1 was signif-
icantly increased after antidepressant treatment. 
CD40 ligand (CD40L) is a transmembrane glycoprotein struc-</p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Healthy controls </p>

<p>Healthy controls </p>

<p>Depressive patients </p>

<p>Depressive patients </p>

<p>p=0.004 </p>

<p>p=1 </p>

<p>IL-8 (pg/mL) </p>

<p>TNF-alpha (pg/mL) </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Figure 1. Box plot: baseline plasma concentrations of cytokine in major depressive patients and healthy controls. A: Eotaxin, B: sCD40L, C: 
IL-8, D: MCP-1, and E: TNF-alpha. p-values were calculated by median regression analysis after adjusted for age and sex; Bonferroni cor-
rection was used for the five cytokines. sCD40L: soluble CD40-ligand, IL-8: interleukin 8, MCP-1: monocyte chemoattractant protein-1, 
TNF-alpha: tumor necrosis factor alpha. </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Healthy controls Depressive patients </p>

<p>p=1 </p>

<p>Eotaxin (pg/mL) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>150000 </p>

<p>100000 </p>

<p>50000 </p>

<p>0 
Healthy controls Depressive patients </p>

<p>p=0.001 </p>

<p>sCD40L (pg/mL) </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>1250 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>750 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Healthy controls Depressive patients </p>

<p>p=0.03 </p>

<p>MCP-1 (pg/mL) </p>

<p>D </p>



<p>Serum Cytokine Levels in Depression </p>

<p>turally related to TNF-alpha. 
31 CD40 ligand exists in two 
forms, membrane-bound and soluble (sCD40L). The protein 
binds to the CD40 receptor and induces the production of cy-
tokines, connective tissue degrading enzymes, and upregu-
lates the inflammatory response. 
32 This interaction between 
CD40 and CD40L is known to be an important step in the 
priming of helper T-cells. 
33 Leo et al. 
28 reported that sCD40L 
levels increased in patients with MDD compared with controls 
and also found a correlation between the level of sCD40L 
and the severity of depression as assessed by the HAM-D 
(Table 4). In addition, they reported that mood improvement 
with SSRI treatment was associated with a reduction in 
sCD40L. 
28 Another study reported by Neubauer et al. 
34 showed 
a concordant result, that CD40L was elevated in patients with 
depression as compared to controls. However, our results 
showed a diametrical association; the level of sCD40L in 
healthy controls was higher than that of depressive patients. 
We can speculate several reasons for the discrepancy. The 
first is the difference of the illness duration. Previous studies 
were conducted during the first episode of depression; how-
ever, in our study, depressive patients (72.7%) were experienc-
ing their second or a later episode of MDD. It has been sug-
gested that cytokine-induced neurochemical alterations might 
vary with the number of depressive episodes. 
35 Griffiths et al. </p>

<p>36   suggested that the recurrence of depression might involve 
chronic cytokine activation. Further studies for CD40L in re-
current depression are needed. Another possible factor for 
such discrepancy is the proportion of old age patients. Previ-
ous studies that reported an elevated level of CD40L in de-
pressive patients included mostly middle-aged patients. </p>

<p>28,34   Our patients were mostly elderly (age &gt;60 years, 74.2%), and 
a large portion of them had late-onset illness (age of first on-
set &gt;60 years, 45.5%). Several studies have suggested that the 
age at onset can vary in different subtypes of depression, espe-
cially in terms of heritability. 
37,38 In addition, previous studies 
reported that proinflammatory cytokines increase in healthy 
elderly people, 
39-41 although, we could not find a significant 
relationship between age, age on onset and sCD40L in our 
study subjects. Another consideration is that our study was </p>

<p>conducted in Asian population. Further studies with clinically 
homogeneous samples in recurrent depression and in an el-
derly group or various ethnic groups will be required. 
Previous studies that investigated the association between 
IL-8 and depression reported inconsistent results (Table 4). 
Simon et al. found elevated level of IL-8 in depression, 
42 but 
three other studies found no significant association. 
19,43,44 In 
contrast, Lehto et al. reported a decreased level of IL-8 in de-
pression, which was in agreement with our results. 
45 IL-8 has 
been known as a neutrophil chemotatic factor; 
46 however, the 
detailed functions of this cytokine are complex. High circulat-
ing levels of IL-8 act to decreased the infiltration of neutro-
phils to the inflammatory site, performing pro-or anti-inflam-
matory roles, depending on the concentration. 
8 Therefore, 
there was a possibility that the association between IL-8 level 
and depression could be changed according to the study pop-
ulation. 
Relatively few studies have investigated the association be-
tween MCP-1 and depression. Lehto et al. 
45 and Grassi-Oli-
veria et al. 
47 found that depression was associated with lower 
MCP-1 concentrations compare to healthy controls, but oth-
ers reported contrary results (Table 4). 
42,48 Our results, finding 
lower levels of IL-8 and MCP-1, suggest a reduced level of 
chemokines in depression. The detailed mechanism for this 
association is unclear. The neuroprotective function of neu-
ronal chemokines, 
49,50 and their dopaminergic activity-en-
hancing effect in the central nervous system could be possi-
ble explanations. However, limitations to our interpretation 
should be noted because our results were obtained from pe-
ripheral blood. 
Sutcigil et al. 
48 reported that the level of MCP-1 decreased 
after sertraline treatment. However, we found an increase in 
MCP-1 levels following antidepressant treatment. The major 
difference between our result and the previous study is the 
number of episodes that patients experienced. Sutcigil et al. 
included only first episode patients in their study, but, as not-
ed above, most of our study patients were recurrent depres-
sion. Although, we could not find a significant relationship 
between episode number and the level of MCP-1 in our </p>

<p>Table 3. Serum concentrations of cytokines at baseline and at 6 weeks after the antidepressant treatment in major depressive patients 
(N=66)* </p>

<p>Cytokine (pg/mL) 
At baseline 
At 6 weeks 
Statistics (Z) 
Corrected p </p>

<p>Eotaxin 
135 (112.5, 178) 
147 (106, 189) 
-1.82 
0.34 </p>

<p>sCD40L 
24800 (8390, 47350) 
18900 (5010, 51700) 
0.17 
1 </p>

<p>IL-8 
11.3 (7.9, 15.2) 
11.15 (7.28, 14.8) 
-0.61 
1 </p>

<p>MCP-1 
368 (261.5, 469.5) 
375 (286, 518) 
-3.19 
0.01 </p>

<p>TNF-alpha 
5.33 (3.33, 7.24) 
5.09 (3.25, 7.72) 
-0.04 
1 </p>

<p>Data are given as median and interquartile range. *Wilcoxon signed-rank test was used; with Bonferroni correction for five cytokines. 
sCD40L: soluble CD40-ligand, IL-8: interleukin 8, MCP-1: monocyte chemoattractant protein-1, TNF-alpha: tumor necrosis factor alpha </p>

<p>W Myung et al. </p>

<p>www.psychiatryinvestigation.org 649 </p>

<p>study subjects, the difference in the antidepressants used may 
have also contributed to this discordance. Interestingly, the 
directions of change in both studies were toward those of the 
healthy controls. The study of Sutcigil et al. showed a higher 
level of MCP-1 in depressive patients compare to healthy con-
trols, and the difference decreased after treatment. We found 
a decreased level of MCP-1 in depressive patients, and it was 
normalized toward the level of healthy controls after antide-
pressant treatment. The antidepressant effect of COX-2 in-
hibitors that block production of prostaglandin E and proin-
flammatory cytokines were investigated in several clinical 
trials. 
51-53 In one study, combination therapy of COX-2 inhib-
itor (celecoxib) and sertraline reduced level of serum IL-6 
levels in patients with MDD, and reduction of the severity of 
depressive symptoms and reduction of the level of serum IL-6 
were significantly correlated. 
53 Further studies that investi-
gate the effect of the combination treatment with COX-2 in-
hibitor on the level of MCP-1 could be helpful. 
We found no association between the level of eotaxin or </p>

<p>TNF-alpha and depression. These negative results were in-
consistent with recent studies for eotaxin 
47,54 and a meta-anal-
ysis of TNF-alpha. 
7 However, our findings are in line with 
other reports conducted in elderly patients. 
55-57 Additional 
studies adjusted for age with larger sample sizes are required. 
Several limitations were present in our study. Our sample 
was relatively small. The cross-sectional design for associa-
tion between depression and cytokines precludes conclusions 
about causality. We could not consider potential variables, 
such as smoking, lifetime use of anti-inflammatory or analge-
sic drugs, minor medical illness, and body mass index. An-
other consideration is that because our patients were mostly 
elderly due to the clinical setting of patient enrollment, the gen-
eralizability of our results to other age groups may be limited. 
Overall, we found the associations between sCD40L, IL-8, 
MCP-1, and depression. In addition, we showed that the level 
of MCP-1 was significantly increased after antidepressant 
treatment. Our results imply that the characteristics of study 
population are important, and the roles of cytokines in de-</p>

<p>Table 4. Summary of previous studies that investigated the association between depression and the significant cytokines in our study </p>

<p>Study 
Results </p>

<p>Association with depression 
Association with antidepressant response </p>

<p>sCD40L </p>

<p>Our study 
sCD40L levels decreased in MDD patients 
compared with controls </p>

<p>No significant association </p>

<p>Leo et al. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>sCD40L levels increased in MDD patients 
compared with controls </p>

<p>Response with SSRI treatment was associated 
with a reduction in sCD40L </p>

<p>Neubauer et al. </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>sCD40L levels increased in MDD patients 
compared with controls </p>

<p>Not investigated </p>

<p>IL-8 </p>

<p>Our study 
IL-8 levels decreased in MDD patients compared 
with controls </p>

<p>No significant association </p>

<p>Simon et al. </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>IL-8 levels increased in MDD patients compared 
with controls </p>

<p>Not investigated </p>

<p>Eller et al. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>No significant association 
No significant association </p>

<p>Mikova et al. </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>No significant association 
No significant association </p>

<p>O'Brien et al. </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>No significant association 
Not investigated </p>

<p>Lehto et al. </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>IL-8 levels decreased in MDD patients compared 
with controls </p>

<p>Not investigated </p>

<p>MCP-1 </p>

<p>Our study 
MCP-1 levels decreased in MDD patients compared 
with controls </p>

<p>MCP-1 levels increased after antidepressant treatment </p>

<p>Lehto et al. </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>MCP-1 levels decreased in MDD patients compared 
with controls </p>

<p>Not investigated </p>

<p>Grassi-Oliveira 
et al. </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>MCP-1 levels decreased in MDD patients compared 
with controls </p>

<p>Not investigated </p>

<p>Sutcigil et al. </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>MCP-1 levels increased in MDD patients compared 
with controls </p>

<p>MCP-1 levels decreased after sertraline treatment. </p>

<p>sCD40L: soluble CD40-ligand, IL-8: interleukin 8, MCP-1: monocyte chemoattractant protein-1, TNF-alpha: tumor necrosis factor alpha </p>



<p>Serum Cytokine Levels in Depression </p>

<p>pression are sophisticated and nuanced. The relationship be-
tween cytokines and depression remains to be clarified. Fur-
ther studies concerning covariance with age and recurrence 
are required. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by a grant of the Korean Health Technology 
R&amp;D Project from the Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare, Republic of Korea 
(A110339, HI14C2071). These funding sources were not involved in the 
creation of the study protocol, data analysis, or in writing the manuscript. </p>



<p>W Myung et al. </p>

<p>www.psychiatryinvestigation.org 651 </p>



</text></tei>