<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5338961" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Sympathetic block in the upper limb has diagnostic, therapeutic and prognostic 
utility for disorders in the upper extremity that are associated with sympathetic disturbances. 
Increased skin temperature and decreased sweating are used to identify the adequacy of sym-
pathetic block in the upper limb after stellate ganglion block (SGB). Baroreflexes elicited by 
postural change induce a reduction in peripheral blood flow by causing sympathetic vasocon-
striction. We hypothesized that sympathetic block in the upper limb reduces the decrease in 
finger blood flow caused by baroreflexes stimulated by postural change from the supine to long 
sitting position. This study evaluated if sympathetic block of the upper limb affects the change 
in finger blood flow resulting from postural change. If change in finger blood flow would be 
kept against postural changes, it has a potential to be a new indicator of sympathetic blockade 
in the upper limb. 
Methods: Subjects were adult patients who had a check-up at the Department of Pain Man-
agement in our university hospital over 2 years and 9 months from May 2012. We executed 
a total of 91 SGBs in nine patients (N=9), which included those requiring treatment for pain 
associated with herpes zoster in seven of the patients, tinnitus in one patient and upper limb 
pain in one patient. We checked for the following four signs after performing SGB: Horner's 
sign, brachial nerve blockade, finger blood flow measured by a laser blood flow meter and 
skin temperature of the thumb measured by thermography, before and after SGB in the supine 
position and immediately after adopting the long sitting position. 
Results: We executed a total of 91 SGBs in nine patients. Two SGBs were excluded from 
the analysis due to the absence of Horner's sign. We divided 89 procedures into two groups 
according to elevation in skin temperature of the thumb: by over 1°C (sympathetic block 
group, n=62) and by &lt;1°C (nonsympathetic block group, n=27). Finger blood flow decreased 
significantly just after a change in posture from the supine to long sitting position after SGB in 
both groups. In the sympathetic block group, the ratio of finger blood flow in the long sitting 
position/supine position with a change in posture significantly increased after SGB compared 
with before SGB (before SGB: range 0.09-0.94, median 0.53; after SGB: range 0.33-1.2, 
median 0.89, p&lt;0.0001). 
Conclusion: Our study shows that with sympathetic block in the upper limb, the ratio of finger 
blood flow significantly increases despite baroreflexes stimulated by postural change from the 
supine to long sitting position. Retention of finger blood flow against postural changes may be 
an indicator of sympathetic block in the upper limb after SGB or brachial plexus block. 
In clinical pain management and in patients with peripheral 
circulatory disorders, sympathetic block in the upper limb 
is commonly used for diagnostic, therapeutic and prognostic 
purposes for disorders associated with sympathetic distur-
bances in the upper extremity. During stellate ganglion block 
(SGB), as well, it is important to assess whether the sym-
pathetic nerve is blocked or not. Increased skin temperature 
and decreased sweating are used to identify the adequacy 
of sympathetic block in the upper extremity. However, this 
requires a thermography device to precisely evaluate skin 
temperature, a diaphoremeter to measure sweating, and an 
equipment to assess the sympathetic skin response. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>In general, when changing from the supine to sitting 
position, baroreflexes elicited by the postural change induce 
a reduction in peripheral blood flow by increasing the sym-
pathetic tone of peripheral blood vessels. 
2 Sympathetically 
mediated cutaneous vasoconstriction directly reduces periph-
eral blood flow. This can be measured using a laser blood 
flow meter. However, peripheral blood flow measurements 
by laser flowmetry may be unstable under certain autonomic 
nervous conditions. We previously reported a preliminary 
study describing the potential of retention of finger blood 
flow against postural change to become a new indicator of 
sympathetic block in the upper limb. 
3 This novel method for 
assessing successful sympathetic block uses blood flowmetry 
in association with baroreflexes induced by postural changes. 
We hypothesized that sympathetic block in the upper limb 
reduces the decrease in finger blood flow caused by barore-
flexes associated with postural change from the supine to long 
sitting position (i.e. sitting with the lower limbs stretched out 
in front of the subject). This study evaluated whether or not 
sympathetic block in the upper limb affects the change in 
finger blood flow with postural change. If change in finger 
blood flow would be kept against postural changes, it has a 
potential to be a new indicator of sympathetic blockade in 
the upper limb. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>This study was approved by the ethics committee of Shimane 
University Faculty of Medicine. Subjects were adult patients 
who had a check-up at the Department of Pain Management 
in our university hospital over 2 years and 9 months from May 
2012. We received written informed consent from all patients 
for participation in the study. Nine patients, five males 
and four females, aged 44-80 years (mean age 62.3 years, 
standard deviation 13.3), required treatment by SGB. The 
diagnoses were herpes zoster pain in seven of the patients, 
tinnitus in one patient and upper limb pain in one patient. </p>

<p>The patients had no history of orthostatic intolerance, such 
as orthostatic hypotension and related diseases affecting the 
sympathetic nervous system, or disordered circulation in the 
upper limb, and were not on prescription vasoactive, cardiac 
or sweating-related medication. 
Each patient was positioned supine with the cervical 
spine in the neutral position, and SGB was performed by an 
anterior approach under ultrasound guidance. A microconvex 
transducer (S-Nerve; SonoSite Co. Ltd., Bothell, WA, USA) 
with a 5-8 MHz resolution was used to scan the C6 vertebral 
level. The local anesthetic, namely, 5 mL of 1% mepivacaine 
(AstraZeneca Co. Ltd., Osaka, Japan), was injected into the 
longus colli muscle under the prevertebral fascia using a 
25-gauge and 25 mm long needle with an in-plane approach 
in the sagittal plane. 
Thereafter, the following four parameters were assessed 
in all patients: </p>

<p>1. Horner's sign. After SGB, we checked for the presence 
of myosis, ptosis and enophthalmos. This was assessed to 
identify successful block of the cervical sympathetic trunk. 
2. Presence of brachial nerve block to exclude sympathetic 
block in the upper limb due to inadvertent brachial plexus 
block. In patients in whom it did occur, a significant 
increase in blood flow to the fingers of the blocked hand 
was observed throughout the period of brachial plexus 
anesthesia. 
4 We checked if brachial nerve block was pres-
ent or not. 
3. Skin temperature of the thumb on the blocked side by 
thermography before SGB and 20 min after SGB. An indi-
cator of sympathetic block in the upper limb is elevated 
skin temperature of over 1°C relative to before SGB. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4. Blood flow in the ball of the thumb on the SGB side. 
This was measured using a laser blood flow meter (Laser 
Doppler ALF 21D, ADVANCE Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) 
in the supine position and immediately after changing to 
the long sitting position (the lowest finger blood flow), 
before SGB and 20 min after SGB. </p>

<p>Laser Doppler flowmetry is an excellent noninvasive tech-
nique for the measurement of cutaneous microcirculation. </p>

<p>6,7 </p>

<p>For this, laser Doppler probes were attached to the ball of 
the thumb to measure cutaneous microcirculation. The ball 
of the thumb, which is considered to be the most peripheral 
region in the upper limb, has relatively thick subcutaneous 
tissue. The thickness of the subcutaneous tissue is well suited 
for the measurement of finger blood flow by laser Doppler as 
affected blood flow by vasoconstriction. Stable finger blood 
flow over 10 s was measured in the supine position. Finger 
blood flow just after changing to the long sitting position </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>477 </p>

<p>Retention of finger blood flow against postural change </p>

<p>was measured as the lowest blood flow within the first 15 s 
of the postural change. The results of blood flow measure-
ments, measured by laser flowmetry, were expressed as 
mL·min </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>·100 g tissue </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>. When changing from the supine to 
long sitting position, the upper limb was stretched out along 
the trunk, parallel to the torso and vertical to the bed. This 
meant that the hand position was not changed in both the 
supine and long sitting positions. 
Finger blood flows were compared between the supine 
and long sitting positions before SGB and 20 min after SGB. 
Next, we calculated the finger blood flow ratio as (the lowest 
finger blood flow in the long sitting position)/(finger blood 
flow in the supine position) both before and after SGB. We 
evaluated the difference in finger blood flow ratios before 
and after SGB. Statistical analysis of the data before and 
after SGB was performed using the Wilcoxon signed-rank 
test. <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stat view</rs> for Macintosh (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 5.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., 
Cary, NC, USA) was used for all statistical analyses. p-Values 
&lt;0.01 were considered to be significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>We executed a total of 91 SGBs in nine patients. Two SGBs 
were excluded from the analysis because of the absence of 
Horner's sign (Table 1). Bleeding as a complication during 
and after the procedure did not occur in any of the procedures. 
We divided 89 procedures into two groups based on whether </p>

<p>the skin temperature increased by more or less than 1°C. The 
group of 62 SGBs, in which the skin temperature increased by 
more than 1°C, was considered as the successful sympathetic 
block in the upper limb group. The group of 27 SGBs, in 
which the skin temperature increased by &lt;1°C, was consid-
ered the nonsympathetic block group. Figure 1 demonstrates 
a case with effective sympathetic block in the upper limb as 
measured by thermography. Immediately after a change in 
posture from the supine to long sitting position, absolute finger 
blood flow in both groups decreased significantly before and 
after SGB (Table 2). In the nonsympathetic block group, the 
ratio of (finger blood flow in the long sitting position)/(finger 
blood flow in the supine position) in the thumb on the SGB 
side did not increase significantly with a change in posture 
after the block compared with the ratio before SGB (Table 3; 
Figure 2A). However, in the sympathetic block group, the ratio 
after SGB increased significantly with a change in posture 
compared with the ratio before SGB (Table 3; Figure 2B). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Sympathetic blocks, such as SGB, are widely used for the 
treatment of pain and sympathetic disorders of the head, neck 
and upper extremities. Recently, ultrasound-guided techniques 
have allowed for a more effective and precise sympathetic 
blocking, and may improve the safety of the procedure by 
direct visualization of vascular and soft tissue structures. 
8 The </p>

<p>Table 1 Number of SGBs, patient exclusion criteria and grouping </p>

<p>Number of SGBs performed 
91 
Exclusion criteria 
Negative Horner's sign 
2 
Brachial plexus block 
0 
Number of SGBs in groups 
Sympathetic block group 
62 (male 24, female 38) 
Nonsympathetic block group 
27 (male 22, female 5) </p>

<p>Notes: Sympathetic block group: elevation of skin temperature over 1°C. 
Nonsympathetic block group: elevation of skin temperature under 1°C. 
Abbreviation: SGBs, stellate ganglion blocks. </p>

<p>Before Lt. SGB 
After Lt. SGB </p>

<p>Figure 1 Thermography showing elevation in skin temperature in the upper limb 
by over 1ºC following SGB 
Abbreviation: SGB, stellate ganglion block. </p>

<p>Table 2 Finger blood flow </p>

<p>Group 
Before SGB 
After SGB 
p-Value </p>

<p>Supine range 
Sitting range 
Supine range 
Sitting range </p>

<p>Sympathetic block group 
4.8-95.3* 
0.5-73.8* 
18.7-73.3* 
15.6-83.0* 
p&lt;0.0001 
Median 
Median 
Median 
Median 
28.25 
15.8 
40.7 
33.85 </p>

<p>Before SGB 
After SGB </p>

<p>Supine range 
Sitting range 
Supine range 
Sitting range </p>

<p>Nonsympathetic block 
group </p>

<p>16.2-78.2* 
2.5-53.4* 
23.9-74.6* 
4.4-56.8* 
p&lt;0.0001 
Median 
Median 
Median 
Median 
34.7 
14.3 
46.1 
21 </p>

<p>Notes: Unit of blood flow: mL·min </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>, 100 g tissue </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>. Comparison between supine and sitting by Wilcoxon signed-rank test. *p&lt;0.0001. 
Abbreviation: SGB, stellate ganglion block. </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>478 </p>

<p>Nakatani et al </p>

<p>anatomical basis of this technique is that the cervical sympa-
thetic trunk lies entirely subfascially. 
9 The stellate ganglion, 
formed by fusion of the inferior cervical and first thoracic 
ganglia, is located adjacent to the neck of the first rib, lateral to 
the longus colli muscle and posterior to the vertebral artery. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>In the method of ultrasound-guided SGB reported by Shibata 
et al, the tip of the needle penetrates the prevertebral fascia in 
the longus colli muscle and 8 mL of 1% lidocaine is injected. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>They demonstrated how ultrasound-guided C6-SGB is per-
formed beneath the prevertebral fascia in the longus colli 
muscle. Another study reported that a 2 mL dose is sufficient 
for a successful block when performing an ultrasound-guided 
SGB. 
12 Following the report of Narouze et al, 
13 we typically 
use 5 mL of the local anesthetic for ultrasound-guided SGB. 
Reliable methods of evaluation of the success of sym-
pathetic block after SGB are, therefore, essential. The signs 
of a successful SGB are Horner's triad of myosis, ptosis and 
enophthalmos, and lack of sweating on the face on the block 
side, due to blockade of the cervical sympathetic trunk. The </p>

<p>other signs are venodilatation and absence of sweating in the 
upper limb, and increase in skin temperature of the blocked 
limb by at least 1°C, since SGB also affects the upper limb 
region. 
5 The most commonly used method for assessing suc-
cessful sympathetic block of the upper limb is measurement 
of the temperature of the skin. Skin temperature assessment 
with an infrared thermometer is a reliable early indicator of 
a successful block after brachial plexus block. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Other techniques include measurement of skin resistance 
and the sweat test. Of the tests employed to assess sympathetic 
block, temperature measurement is probably the most widely 
used technique to assess sympathectomy of the affected site. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>However, since temperature measurement may be affected 
by the environment of the clinical room, ensuring that the 
room temperature remains stable is important for precise 
measurements, as compared with measuring blood flow by 
laser flowmetry. 
We previously reported that retention of finger blood 
flow against postural change has the potential to be a new 
indicator of sympathetic block in the upper limb. 
3 In that 
report, the number of procedures in which the ratio of (finger 
blood flow in the long sitting position/finger blood flow in 
the supine position) was &gt;90%, which was significantly 
higher on the SGB as compared to the non-SGB side. 
3 In 
this study, we divided SGBs into two groups depending on 
whether skin temperature increased by more or less than 
1°C after the block. Elevation of skin temperature by more 
than 1°C was assumed to indicate successful sympathetic 
block in the upper limb after SGB. In both the groups of 
this study, there was a significant difference in blood flow 
between the supine and long sitting positions both before 
and after SGB. However, the ratio of blood flow in (long </p>

<p>Blood flow 
ratio </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 
Before SGB </p>

<p>Nonsympathetic block group </p>

<p>p=0.648 </p>

<p>After SGB </p>

<p>Blood flow 
ratio 
1.2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 
Before SGB </p>

<p>Sympathetic block group </p>

<p>p&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>After SGB </p>

<p>Figure 2 (A) Box plots of the ratio of finger blood flow (sitting/supine position) before and after SGB in the nonsympathetic block group. The ratio of finger blood flow 
was the same before and after SGB. (B) Box plots of the ratio of finger blood flow (sitting/supine position) before and after SGB in the sympathetic block group. The ratio 
of finger blood flow significantly increased after SGB in the sympathetic block group. 
Abbreviation: SGB, stellate ganglion block. </p>

<p>Table 3 The ratio of finger blood flow </p>

<p>Group 
Before SGB 
After SGB 
p-Value </p>

<p>Sitting/supine Sitting/supine </p>

<p>Sympathetic block 
group </p>

<p>Range 
Range 
0.09-0.94* 
0.33-1.2* 
p&lt;0.0001 
Median 
Median 
0.53 
0.89 
Nonsympathetic block 
group </p>

<p>Range 
Range 
0.1-0.88 
0.15-0.79 
p=0.648 
Median 
Median 
0.51 
0.43 </p>

<p>Notes: Comparison of the ratio between before and after SGB by Wilcoxon 
signed-rank test. *p&lt;0.0001. 
Abbreviation: SGB, stellate ganglion block. </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: https://www.dovepress.com/journal-of-pain-research-journal </p>

<p>The Journal of Pain Research is an international, peer reviewed, open 
access, online journal that welcomes laboratory and clinical findings 
in the fields of pain research and the prevention and management 
of pain. Original research, reviews, symposium reports, hypoth-
esis formation and commentaries are all considered for publication. </p>

<p>The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Retention of finger blood flow against postural change </p>

<p>sitting position/supine position) significantly increased after 
SGB. Sympathetic nerve block in the upper limb induced 
by SGB prevents efferent nerve conduction to the periph-
eral nerves of vessels and, hence, postural change-induced 
vasoconstriction. It, thus, induces peripheral vasodilation 
in the upper extremity and maintains blood flow in the face 
of postural change. The fact that the ratio of finger blood 
flow increased after SGB indicates that sympathetic block 
in the upper limb cut off baroreflexes in the upper body 
and maintained peripheral blood flow in the thumb against 
postural changes. 
Tschakovsky and Hughson reported that venous empty-
ing serves as a stimulus for transient (within 10 s) vasodila-
tion in vivo and this vasodilation can substantially elevate 
arterial flow. 
16 They studied arm elevation above the heart 
level in the sitting position, which is different from the supine 
and long sitting positions assessed in our study. We assessed 
and compared finger blood flow before and after SGB under 
the same conditions. The results of Tschakovsky's report 
differ from the findings of our study, likely because we 
performed the study without employing a venous emptying 
procedure. 
Szili-Torok et al reported that determination of baroreflex-
induced microvascular responses might serve as a feasible 
method for monitoring the effectiveness of sympathetic block 
during axillary brachial plexus block. 
17 They opined that 
measurement of blood flow was more reliable for assessing 
reflex responses than for evaluating sympathetic block. In 
their method, cutaneous vascular resistance was calculated to 
evaluate sympathetic activity. With our method, it is possible 
to evaluate sympathetic block in the upper limb merely by 
using laser flowmetry to assess the change in finger blood 
flow following postural change. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Our study shows that when the sympathetic nerves in the upper 
limb are blocked, the ratio of finger blood flow in long sitting/ 
supine position increases significantly despite baroreflexes 
stimulated by postural change from the supine to long sit-
ting position. Retention of finger blood flow against postural </p>

<p>changes may serve as an indicator of sympathetic blockade 
in the upper limb after SGB or brachial plexus block. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>