<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5466216" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The retrospective study aimed to investigate the indication for hypertrophy posterior longitudinal ligament (HPLL) removal in anterior 
decompression for cervical spondylotic myelopathy (CSM). A total of 138 consecutive patients with CSM were divided into 2 groups 
with developmental cervical stenosis (DCS) (group S) and non-DCS (group N), according to the Pavlov ratio. These 2 groups were 
subdivided into 2 further subgroups, according to whether HPLL was removed or preserved: group SR (49 patients) and group SP 
(32 patients) in group S, group NR (21 patients) and group NP (36 patients) in group N. The modified Japanese Orthopedic 
Association score (mJOA), the modified recovery rate (mRR), quality of life (QoL), and relevant clinical data were used for clinical and 
radiological evaluation. The mJOA scores improved from 7.3 ± 2.2 to 15.0 ± 1.8 in the SR group and from 7.9 ± 2.3 to 14.2 ± 1.5 in 
the SP group (P = .036), with postoperative QoL significantly higher in the SR group than the SP group. A reduction in the diameter of 
enlarged spinal canals occurred at a significantly faster rate in the SP group compared with the SR group (P = .002). Multivariate 
regression analyses showed removal of HPLL correlated with mJOA scores (coefficient = 7.337, P = .002), mRR (%) (coefficient = 
9.117, P = .005), PCS (coefficient = 12.129, P &lt; .001), and MCS (coefficient = 14.31, P &lt; .001) in the S group at 24 months 
postoperatively, while removal of HPLL did not correlate with clinical outcomes in the N group. The HPLL should, therefore, be 
removed when mobility was reduced and the spinal cord remained compressed after anterior decompression procedures in the 
patients with DCS. However, in non-DCS patients, it remains unclear as to whether removal of HPLL provides any clinical benefit, 
thus, HPLL removal may not be necessary. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ACDF = anterior cervical discectomy and fusion, CSF = cerebrospinal fluid, CSM = cervical spondylotic 
myelopathy, DCS = developmental cervical stenosis, HPLL = hypertrophy posterior longitudinal ligament, MCS = mental component 
summary, mJOA = modified Japanese Orthopedic Association score, MRI = magnetic resonance imaging, mRR = modified 
recovery rate, PCS = physical component summary, QoL = quality of life. </p>

<p>Anterior cervical discectomy and fusion (ACDF), described by 
Cloward in 1958, 
[1] is the most commonly utilized technique for 
the treatment of compressive cervical myelo-radiculopathy. Since </p>

<p>the initial application of this procedure, ACDF has been 
increasingly applied for the treatment of cervical spinal disorders 
following improvements in surgical techniques and instrumenta-
tion. However, controversy still exists as to whether hypertrophy 
posterior longitudinal ligaments (HPLLs) should be removed or 
preserved in ACDF procedures. 
[2] This debate has primarily 
arisen due to differences in management and that posterior 
longitudinal ligaments (PLL) are associated with complications in 
some patients. Specifically, the specific clinical indications for 
HPLL removal are still unknown during ACDF procedures. To 
date, studies are limited regarding the indication for the removal 
of HPLL in ACDF procedures for cervical spondylotic myelopa-
thy (CSM) in patients with developmental cervical stenosis (DCS) 
or without DCS, which indicates congenital cervical vertebral 
canal stenosis. Therefore, in our retrospective study, the clinical 
and radiological outcomes of patients who underwent HPLL 
preservation were compared with patients with HPLL removal in 
order to elucidate the clinical indications for removal during 
ACDF procedures and to provide a standardized protocol based 
on HPLL mobility. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Participants </p>

<p>During the period between June 2009 and March 2013, a total of 
159 consecutive patients with confirmed HPLL (1-2 levels) who 
underwent ACDF for CSM were selected and included in our </p>

<p>Editor: Bernhard Schaller. </p>

<p>BW and YY contributed equally to this work and considered co-corresponding 
authors. </p>

<p>Ethics statement: The study protocol was approved by our institution's ethics 
committee, and written informed consent was obtained from all participating 
patients. </p>

<p>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>a Department of Orthopedics, Beijing Friendship Hospital Affiliated of Capital 
Medical University, Beijing, 
b Department of Orthopedics, Xiangya Hospital, 
Central South University, Changsha, China. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Correspondence: Yong Yang and Bingqiang Wang, Department of Orthopedics, 
Beijing Friendship Hospital Affiliated of Capital Medical University Beijing, 95 Yong 
an Rd, Beijing 100050, China (e-mails: spineyangyong@sina.com, 
finewangbq@sina.com [YY] and finewangbq@sina.com [BW]). </p>

<p>Copyright © 2017 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC), where it is 
permissible to download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided 
it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially without permission 
from the journal. </p>

<p>Medicine (2017) 96:23(e7043) </p>

<p>Received: 12 February 2017 / Received in final form: 5 May 2017 / Accepted: 8 
May 2017 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000007043 </p>

<p>Observational Study </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>OPEN </p>



<p>study. In our study, HPLL was defined as the abnormal 
thickening of PLL greater than 3.5 mm and less than 5 mm 
without any ossified or calcified fragments. The presence of 
thickened HPLL was confirmed by T2-weighted magnetic 
resonance imaging (MRI) scanning, demonstrating the presence 
of compressed segmental epidural bursa that is composed of dura 
mater, spinal cord, and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). The exclusion 
criteria were as follows: patients with spondylotic amyotrophy, 
tumors, rheumatoid arthritis, pyogenic spondylitis and comor-
bidities, central nerve system disorders, peripheral neuropathy, 
known psychiatric illnesses, ligamentum flavum hypertrophy or 
facet hypertrophy, ossification of posterior longitudinal ligament 
or calcification of posterior longitudinal ligament, and a history 
of previous cervical spine surgery or injury; patients with a spinal 
cord compressing rate greater than 30% measured by MRI 
according to the Takahashi classification system. </p>

<p>[3]   We set criteria for DCS patients, defined as a Pavlov ratio </p>

<p>[4,5]   &lt;0.75. The Pavlov ratio was defined as the ratio between the 
sagittal diameter of spinal canal and the diameter of the vertebral 
body in the same segment measured in T2-weighted MRI 
scanning. 
[5,6] According to the aforementioned criteria, the 
patients were divided into 2 groups accordingly: DCS (group S) 
and non-DCS (group N). In anterior decompression procedures 
based on the mobility of HPLL, the 2 groups of patients were 
subdivided into 2 further subgroups according to whether the 
HPLL was removed or retained, which was detected under 
the operating microscope and head lamp. By the judgment of the 
relative position between the HPLL and adjacent upper and lower 
vertebral posterior edge attachment line, we made a decision to 
remove or preserve the PLL: if the HPLL showed insufficient 
mobility and the spinal cord remained compressed by the HPLL 
after decompression procedures behind the adjacent upper and 
lower vertebral posterior edge attachment line, then the HPLL 
was removed. Otherwise, the HPLL was preserved, as shown in 
Fig. 1. A total of 21 patients (13.2%) were lost to follow-up 
(9 due to noncompliance, 7 due to relocation, and 5 due to 
unknown whereabouts). Follow-up information was available 
for 138 out of the 159 patients (86.8%). Consequently, patients 
included were divided into 4 groups: group SR (HPLL removal 
n = 49, 32 males, 17 females, 58.4 ± 9.5 years), group SP (HPLL 
preserved n = 32, 20 males, 12 females, 54.8 ± 8.2 years) 
(Table 1), group NR (HPLL removal n = 21, 13 males, 8 females, 
61.5 ± 11.8 years), and group NP (HPLL preserved n = 36, 
18 males, 18 females, 58.8 ± 11.0 years) (Table 1). The data of 
clinical demographics showed that there were no statistical 
differences (P &gt; .05) between group SR and group SP, and group 
NR and group NP (Table 1). 
The study protocol was approved by our institution's ethics 
committee, and written informed consent was obtained from all 
participating patients. </p>

<p>2.2. Surgical procedures </p>

<p>All operations were performed by the same senior orthopedic 
surgeon in our spinal surgery department. ACDF procedures for 
CSM was performed as described in previous studies. 
[7,8] In order 
to expose the involved HPLL, we approached the procedure from 
a standard right-side anterior approach and removed any 
pathological structures, including degenerated discs, herniated 
intervertebral nuclei, and proliferative osteophytes. In the 
removal group, the HPLL was separated from the dura mater 
and meticulously resected. In the preserved group, the HPLL was 
preserved without specific management. The spinal cord was free </p>

<p>of compression after the procedures in all patients. During the 
discectomy procedure, the cartilage endplates were removed with 
curettage, and avoiding any additional damage to the endplate. 
The Caspar distractor was placed between adjacent vertebral 
bodies to perform distraction approximately 2 to 3 mm. A trial 
spacer was used to determine the appropriate implant size and 
type; a suitable polyether-ether-ketone cage (Medtronic Sofamor 
Danek USA Inc., Memphis, TN) packed with autologous local 
bone pieces taken from the operation site was placed safely into 
the intervertebral space. After implantation of the cage, a Caspar 
distractor was released. A titanium Codman plate (Johnson &amp; 
Johnson) or zephir plate (Medtronic Sofamor Danek) or Orion 
plate (Medtronic Sofamor Danek) (Fig. 2) was fixed onto the 
adjacent vertebrae with screws. Postoperatively, the patients were 
allowed to mobilize with a soft neck collar after bed rest for 
several days. Collar supports were removed after 4 to 6 weeks in 
all patients. All patients were followed up at 1, 6, 12, 24 months 
postoperatively. </p>

<p>Figure 1. (A) Spinal cord, (B) adjacent upper and lower vertebral posterior 
edge attachment line. (C) If the hypertrophy posterior longitudinal ligament 
(HPLL) was still located behind the adjacent upper and lower vertebral posterior 
edge attachment line after decompression, and the spinal cord was still 
compressed by the HPLL, the ligament was removed. (D) If the ligament was 
sufficiently mobile to reach the front of the line, the spinal cord was free of 
compression, it was retained. </p>

<p>Bai et al. Medicine (2017) 96:23 
Medicine </p>



<p>2.3. Clinical and radiological evaluation </p>

<p>Neurological function was evaluated using the Modified Japanese 
Orthopedic Association Cervical Spine Myelopathy Functional 
Assessment Scale, as described by Benzel et al. 
[9,10] The modified 
recovery rate (mRR) was calculated using the same formula as that 
applied for the original Japanese Orthopedic Association (JOA), 
changing the cumulative score from 17 to 18. </p>

<p>[9,10]   mRRð%Þ ¼ 
postoperative mJOA score À preoperative mJOA score 
18 À preoperative mJOA score 
Â 100% </p>

<p>The Medical Outcomes Study 36-item short-form health 
survey with the score ranging from 0 to 100, including physical 
component summary (PCS) measure, mental component sum-
mary (MCS) measure, 
[11,12] was used for the assessment of the 
quality of life (QoL), with higher scores representing improved 
health. The Medical Outcomes Study 36-item short-form health 
survey is a health status questionnaire that was developed 2 
decades ago to assess functional status and well-being, 
[11] which 
has since been applied in a variety of clinical settings. 
[13-15] The 
mean operating time, blood loss, and any associated complica-
tions were also evaluated and compared between groups. 
Radiological examinations (MRI, CT, and X-rays) were 
performed preoperatively. X-rays were performed every 3 
months, and MRI and CT scans were performed every 12 
months postoperatively for all patients. To determine intra-and 
interobserver variability, radiological measurements were carried 
out by 2 senior radiologists, who performed radiological 
evaluations independently for each patient. The anteroposterior 
median sagittal diameter of the cervical spinal canal was 
measured at the most stenotic operating vertebral level (Fig. 3) 
on sagittal T2-weighted MRI. 
[16] Bone fusion was defined when 
the following criteria were satisfied: no movement between the 
spinous processes; absence of a radiolucent gap between the graft </p>

<p>and the endplate; and presence of continuous bridging bony 
trabeculae across the graft-endplate interface (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>2.4. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were expressed as means ± standard deviation (SD) for 
quantitative variables. Qualitative data are represented as relative 
percentages. The Student t test and chi-square test were used for 
comparison of clinical and radiological data. Multivariate 
regression was used to analyze the clinical outcome effects of 
any independent variables. Multivariate regression was adjusted 
for age, gender, spinal cord compressing rate, mean duration 
of symptoms, pre-and postoperative sagittal diameter, pre-and 
postoperative modified Japanese Orthopedic Association score 
(mJOA), pre-and postoperative PCS, pre-and postoperative 
MCS, and surgical method (HPLL removing = 1; HPLL retaining 
= 0). 
[17] A P-value less than 0.05 (P &lt; .05) was considered 
statistically significant. Statistical analysis was performed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> statistical software package <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">15.0</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., 
Chicago, IL). </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Clinical and radiological outcomes </p>

<p>The 138 patients were followed up for more than 24 months, and 
no deaths occurred in either group. The mJOA scores improved 
from 7.3 ± 2.2 to 15.0 ± 1.8 in the SR group and increased from 
7.9 ± 2.3 to 14.2 ± 1.5 in the SP group (P = .036). Furthermore, an 
increase from 6.8 ± 1.8 to 14.3 ± 2.0 was observed in the NR 
group, and an increase from 7.4 ± 2.1 to 13.5 ± 1.4 in the NP 
group (P = .104). The mRR (%) between groups was significantly 
different (71.7 ± 13.7 in SR vs 64.1 ± 12.9 in SP, P = .014) and 
(64.3 ± 13.3 in NR vs 58.6 ± 12.2 in NP, P = .110). QoL including 
MCS and PCS in SR group was significantly higher than that in </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>The demographics and operation data of group SR, SP, NR, and NP. </p>

<p>Variable 
Group SR (n = 49) 
Group SP (n = 32) 
P 
Group NR (n = 21) 
Group NP (n = 36) 
P </p>

<p>Age, y 
58.4 ± 9.5 
54.8 ± 8.2 
.069 
61.5 ± 11.8 
58.8 ± 11.0 
.385 
Gender (n, %) 
.797 
.384 
Male 
32 (65.3%) 
20 (62.5%) 
13 (61.9%) 
18 (50.0%) 
Female 
17 (34.7%) 
12 (37.5%) 
8 (38.1%) 
18 (50.0%) 
Mean CR, % 
23.6 ± 5.0 
21.7 ± 6.3 
.129 
15.9 ± 6.1 
18.2 ± 6.2 
.169 
Pavlov ratio 
0.68 ± 0.05 
0.67 ± 0.05 
.311 
0.85 ± 0.07 
0.86 ± 0.11 
.615 
Mean duration of symptoms, mo 
17.7 ± 13.8 
17.4 ± 11.8 
.917 
23.0 ± 13.1 
24.0 ± 13.9 
.784 
Operative segment (C4-C7) 
.627 
.890 
Single segment 
39 (79.6%) 
24 (75.0%) 
16 (76.2%) 
28 (77.8%) 
Double segment 
10 (20.4%) 
8 (25.0%) 
5 (23.8%) 
8 (22.2%) 
Symptoms of radiculopathy 
7 (14.3%) 
4 (12.5%) 
.974 
4 (19.0%) 
5 (13.9%) 
.806 
Symptoms of myelopathy 
30 (61.2%) 
20 (62.5%) 
13 (61.9%) 
22 (61.1%) 
Combined symptoms 
12 (24.5%) 
8 (25.0%) 
4 (19.0%) 
9 (25.0%) 
Plate type 
.697 
.804 
Codman plate 
23 (46.9%) 
18 (56.3%) 
11 (52.4%) 
22 (61.1%) 
Zephir plate 
12 (24.5%) 
7 (21.9%) 
4 (19.0%) 
6 (16.7%) 
Orion plate 
14 (28.6%) 
7 (21.9%) 
6 (28.6%) 
8 (22.2%) 
Mean operating time, min 
192.4 ± 27.2 
181.8 ± 24.3 
.073 
195.7 ± 15.5 
187.6 ± 25.8 
.195 
Mean bleeding, mL 
382.5 ± 73.9 
367.1 ± 84.8 
.405 
383.3 ± 98.9 
376.1 ± 77.3 
.760 
Bone union 
3 mo 
45 (91.8%) 
29 (90.6%) 
.850 
17 (81.0%) 
33 (91.7%) 
.234 
6 mo 
46 (93.9%) 
32 (100%) 
.154 
20 (95.2%) 
34 (94.4%) 
.897 
12 mo 
49 (100%) 
32 (100%) 
-
21 (100%) 
36 (100%) 
-</p>

<p>Group SR, HPLL removal group in developmental canal stenosis group; group SP, HPLL preservation group in developmental canal stenosis group; group NR, HPLL removal group in nondevelopmental canal 
stenosis group; group NP, HPLL preservation group in nondevelopmental canal stenosis group. Pavlov ratio, the sagittal diameter of the spinal canal/the sagittal diameter of the vetebral body on lateral X-rays. 
CR = the compressing rate of spinal cord, HPLL = hypertrophy posterior longitudinal ligament. </p>

<p>Bai et al. Medicine (2017) 96:23 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>the SP group, but no significant difference was found between the 
NR and NP groups (Table 2). 
Radiological examination showed that the sagittal median 
diameter of the cervical spinal canal in the SR group was 
significantly wider than that in the SP group (P = .002) and no 
significant difference was found between the NR and NP 
groups (P = .151). Reduction in the postoperative spinal canal 
diameter occurred at a significantly faster rate in the SP group 
when compared with the SR group (P = .002). No significant 
difference was found in postoperative canal size between the 
NR and NP groups (P = .157) (Table 2). There were no 
significant differences between groups in terms of operating 
time, bleeding, bone graft union, and complications (Tables 1 
and 2). 
In multivariable regression analyses, after multivariable 
adjustment for other covariates mentioned above in DCS 
patients, removal of HPLL also correlated with improvements 
in mJOA scores (coefficient = 7.337, P = .002), mRR (%) 
(coefficient = 9.117, P = .005), PCS (coefficient = 12.129, P 
&lt; .001), and MCS (coefficient = 14.31, P &lt; .001) (Tables 3-6) 
at 24 months postoperatively. However, removal of HPLL did 
not correlate with clinical outcomes at 24 months in non-DCS 
patients. </p>

<p>3.2. Intraoperative and postoperative complications </p>

<p>No spinal cord injuries occurred in either group. Hoarseness, 
dysphagia, wound infection, and epidural hematomas were 
found in 4 groups and were managed conservatively. Cervical 
instability and displacement of grafts and steel fixators were also 
present in some patients, which were treated conservatively with 
immobilization, neck collars, and orthoses. Seven cases in DCS 
patients and 5 cases in non-DCS patients demonstrated transient 
postoperative shoulder muscle weakness. No neurological 
deterioration developed in participants in our study and 3 
patients developed CSF leakage in the SR and NR groups. This 
was accounted for due to significant adherence between HPLL 
and dura mater, resulting in damage to the latter during surgery. 
CSF leakage was treated conservatively. No statistical signifi-
cance was found in the incidence of complications between 
groups (Table 2). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Although anterior decompression is a common and widely 
accepted surgical technique for cervical myelo-radiculopathy, it is 
still difficult to determine whether HPLL should be removed 
during ACDF procedures for CSM. 
[18] Some studies have </p>

<p>Figure 2. Three different titanium anterior cervical fixing system. (A) Codman plate, (B) Zephir plate, and (C) Orion plate. </p>

<p>Bai et al. Medicine (2017) 96:23 
Medicine </p>



<p>reported that the PLL is fundamental in protecting the spinal cord 
and stabilizing the cervical spine. 
[2,19] However, Loughenbury 
et al 
[20] and Chen et al 
[21] demonstrated that the PLL also 
prevents protrusion of disc tissue into the spinal canal. PLL 
removal may lead to instability of the cervical spine and increase 
the risk of damage to the anatomical components of the cervical 
canal including the dura mater, spinal cord, nerve roots, and 
epidural vascular plexus. 
[12] Nevertheless, a clinical study 
conducted by Bai et al 
[17] has described the benefit of degenerative 
PLL removal in ACDF procedures for CSM. However, no definite 
indication was identified. Therefore, our study sought to identify 
the clinical indication for HPLL removal and to provide 
standardized removal in advance, based on HPLL mobility 
detected in ACDF for CSM patients. 
The results of our study revealed that HPLL removal may not 
markedly influence cervical spine stability, bone graft union and 
the incidence of graft, and internal fixation displacement both in 
DCS and non-DCS patients (Table 2). However, postoperative 
reduction in spinal canal diameter in the group SP was 
significantly faster than that in the group SR in DCS patients, 
which may reduce the long-term beneficial therapeutic effects of 
anterior decompression. However, no significant difference was 
found between the NR and NP groups in non-DCS patients 
(Table 2). Similarly, our data from DCS patients demonstrated 
that postoperative mJOA scores and neurological mRR scores in 
the SR group were significantly higher than those found in the SP 
group. These findings were in accordance with previously 
published studies. 
[18,22] Sagittal T2-weighted MRI scans showed 
that the mean median sagittal diameter of the cervical spinal canal 
was significantly wider in the SR group compared with the SP 
group. These results indicated that decompression was more 
effective after removal of HPLL in DCS patients. Improved 
mJOA and mRR (Table 2) scores may have resulted from 
complete removal of HPLL. Compared with DCS patients, no 
significance was found in postoperative mJOA scores, neurologi-
cal mRR scores, and the mean median sagittal diameter of the </p>

<p>Figure 4. The postoperative X-ray image of internal fixing plate system. (A) Postoperative A/P X-ray image. (B) Postoperative lateral X-ray image. The presence of 
bridging bony trabeculae at the graft-endplate interface, the radiolucent gap between the graft and the endplate, and the motion between the spinous processes 
found in postoperative X-ray figure can be used to evaluate the bone fusion condition. </p>

<p>Figure 3. The definition and measurement of spinal cord compression. The 
compressing rate (CR) was defined as the thickness of the condensed spinal 
cord (N) divided by the anteroposterior diameter of the spinal cord (M) on the 
sagittal image on magnetic resonance imaging T2-weighted scanning 
preoperatively. CR = N/M Â 100%. The CR and anteroposterior sagittal 
diameter of the spinal canal was measured at the most stenotic part of the 
spinal cord (S) on magnetic resonance imaging T2-weighted scanning. </p>

<p>Bai et al. Medicine (2017) 96:23 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>cervical spinal canal between the NR and NP groups at 
postoperative 24-month follow-up in non-DCS patients. In 
conclusion, mJOA and mRR scores, as well as the cervical spinal 
canal, did not benefit from removal of the HPLL in non-DCS 
patients (Table 2). 
Postoperative recovery following ACDF procedures is affected 
by the presence of DCS. 
[23] In our study, diagnosis of DCS was 
based on the Pavlov ratio, which is a reliable determinant, instead 
of the true diameter of the cervical spinal canal. 
[24] A Pavlov ratio 
value less than 0.75 indicates cervical canal stenosis. 
[4,5] After 
multivariate adjustment for other covariates in DCS patients, 
removal of HPLL also correlated with higher mJOA scores, mRR 
and improved PCS and MCS (P &lt; .05) representing an improved 
QoL. These findings suggest that HPLL removal correlated 
with positive clinical outcomes in DCS patients (Tables 3-6) at 
24-month follow-up. However, removal of HPLL did not 
correlate with outcomes in non-DCS patients, which indicated 
that the removal of HPLL did not influence mJOA and mRR 
scores or PCS and MCS at 24-month follow-up. 
Although no significant differences in terms of blood loss and 
operating time were observed between groups, HPLL removing </p>

<p>procedures required more complicated techniques. Determining 
HPLL mobility after discectomy was important and required 
careful detection and surgical experience. The safety of removal 
procedures depends on low traumatic manipulation of the spinal 
cord and protection of the dura mater, nerve structures. and 
epidural vascular plexus. 
[18] The dura mater can adhere to the 
thickest portion of the HPLL in many patients, and the procedure 
to separate the HPLL from the dura mater should be performed 
carefully to avoid tearing of the dura. 
CSF leakage is a well-known complication after removal of 
PLL in spinal canal decompression, and incidence varies from 
4.5% to 32%. 
[18] This complication is often found in patients, 
together with the adhesion of PLL. Yamaura et al 
[25] reported 
that the use of the "floating method" for ossification of posterior 
longitudinal ligament removal could decrease the incidence of 
CSF leakage, but to date, no comparative studies between DCS 
and non-DCS patients have been carried out to investigate the 
clinical effects of spinal canal decompression. Some studies have 
reported the application of dura sac repair as a management 
alternative for the treatment of CSF leakage. 
[18,26] In the 3 cases 
of CSF leakage in the removal groups in our study, the dura sac </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>The imaging, mJOA, SF-36, and complications of group SR, SP, NR, and NP. </p>

<p>Variable 
Group SR (n = 49) 
Group SP (n = 32) 
P 
Group NR (n = 21) 
Group NP (n = 36) 
P </p>

<p>Sagittal diameter of the canal, mm 
Preoperative 
8.20 ± 1.44 
8.31 ± 1.39 
.729 
8.05 ± 1.34 
8.35 ± 1.11 
.382 
Postoperative 24th, mo 
12.15 ± 1.10 
11.32 ± 1.21 
.002 
11.85 ± 1.42 
11.31 ± 1.33 
.151 
Sagittal diameter decrease (%) than postoperative 12th, mo 
8.63 ± 4.18 
10.84 ± 3.98 
.002 
7.43 ± 2.58 
8.42 ± 2.47 
.157 
mJOA 
Preoperative 
7.3 ± 2.2 
7.9 ± 2.3 
.212 
6.8 ± 1.8 
7.4 ± 2.1 
.291 
Postoperative 24th, mo 
15.0 ± 1.8 
14.2 ± 1.5 
.036 
14.3 ± 2.0 
13.5 ± 1.4 
.104 
mRR 
71.7 ± 13.7 
64.1 ± 12.9 
.014 
64.3 ± 13.3 
58.6 ± 12.2 
.110 
SF-36 (PCS, MCS) 
PCS preoperative 
40.4 ± 3.2 
41.0 ± 2.9 
.376 
41.0 ± 4.1 
41.3 ± 3.2 
.751 
PCS postoperative 24th, mo 
70.3 ± 4.8 
64.8 ± 9.1 
.001 
66.5 ± 8.6 
69.7 ± 5.5 
.095 
MCS preoperative 
40.1 ± 3.0 
39.5 ± 3.2 
.425 
39.1 ± 1.6 
40.5 ± 3.3 
.072 
MCS postoperative 24th, mo 
68.6 ± 7.1 
64.5 ± 10.3 
.039 
72.6 ± 5.2 
70.1 ± 6.4 
.148 
Complications 
Dural tearing and CSF leakage 
2 (4.1%) 
0 (0%) 
.247 
1 (4.8%) 
0 (0%) 
.187 
Transient muscle weakness (C5palsy) 
4 (8.2%) 
3 (9.4%) 
.850 
2 (9.5%) 
3 (8.3%) 
.878 
Adjacent disc degeneration 
7 (14.3%) 
5 (15.6%) 
.868 
3 (14.3%) 
6 (16.7%) 
.812 
Cervical instability 
3 (6.1%) 
2 (6.3%) 
.981 
1 (4.8%) 
3 (8.3%) 
.611 
Graft and steel displacement 
2 (4.1%) 
3 (9.4%) 
.333 
1 (4.8%) 
0 (0%) 
.187 
Hoarseness 
3 (6.1%) 
2 (6.3%) 
.981 
2 (9.5%) 
2 (5.6%) 
.572 
Dysphagia 
3 (6.1%) 
1 (3.1%) 
.543 
1 (4.8%) 
2 (5.6%) 
.897 
Infection 
3 (6.1%) 
1 (3.1%) 
.543 
2 (9.5%) 
1 (2.8%) 
.271 
Epidural hematoma 
2 (4.1%) 
0 (0%) 
.247 
0 (0%) 
1 (2.8%) 
.441 </p>

<p>Group SR, HPLL removal group in developmental canal stenosis group; group SP, HPLL preservation group in developmental canal stenosis group; group NR, HPLL removal group in nondevelopmental canal 
stenosis group; group NP, HPLL preservation group in nondevelopmental canal stenosis group. HPLL = hypertrophy posterior longitudinal ligament, MCS = mental component summary, PCS = physical 
component summary, mJOA = modified Japanese Orthopedic Association score, mRR = the modified recovery rate, SF-36 = Medical Outcomes Study 36-item short-form health survey. </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Multivariate regression analysis for independents and MCS of 
postoperation 24th mo. </p>

<p>Variable 
Coefficient 
P </p>

<p>HPLL removing 
14.31 
&lt;.001 
Postoperative mJOA 
3.20 
.002 
Postoperative PCS 
0.251 
.03 </p>

<p>HPLL removing = 1, HPLL retaining = 0. HPLL = hypertrophy posterior longitudinal ligament, MCS = 
mental component summary, mJOA = modified Japanese Orthopedic Association score, PCS = 
physical component summary. </p>

<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>Multivariate regression analysis for independents and PCS of 
postoperation 24th mo. </p>

<p>Variable 
Coefficient 
P </p>

<p>HPLL removing 
12.129 
&lt;.001 
Postoperative mJOA 
3.383 
.002 
Postoperative MCS 
0.264 
.03 </p>

<p>HPLL removing = 1, HPLL retaining = 0. HPLL = hypertrophy posterior longitudinal ligament, MCS = 
mental component summary, mJOA = modified Japanese Orthopedic Association score, PCS = 
physical component summary. </p>

<p>Bai et al. Medicine (2017) 96:23 
Medicine </p>



<p>defect was repaired using the placement of a gelatin sponge. A 
small piece of muscle and fibrin glue, or the dura, was sutured 
directly onto the defect. Our study showed that removal of HPLL 
did not significantly increase the incidence of CSF leakage, with 
this procedure being safe, and effective for the management of 
CSF leakage. 
Iatrogenic neurological injury is a concern for spinal 
surgeons. Preoperative planning and proper surgical technique 
helps minimize potential injury. Seven cases in DCS patients 
and 5 cases in non-DCS patients were found to have transient 
postoperative muscle weakness. This may have arisen due to C5 
nerve root withdrawal, 
[27] which may not be caused by nerve 
injury and has no definite associations with HPLL removal. 
Fortunately, these symptoms resolved gradually over a few 
weeks, and no significant difference was observed between the 
removal and retaining groups, both in DCS and non-DCS 
group. Additionally, due to epidural vascular plexus injury, 
postoperative hematomas have been occasionally described, </p>

<p>[28]   and these were consistent with the findings in our study. 
Although no serious compressive spinal cord symptoms in our 
study were observed, attention should be paid in order to avoid 
epidural vascular plexus injury, as such complications are often 
serious. 
Some limitations should also be noted in the present study. 
First, this was a single center retrospective study. Unlike 
prospective studies, the indication for HPLL removal is 
miscellaneous in a retrospective one. Second, follow-up at 24 
months may not be a sufficient amount of time, meaning that the 
reliability of the conclusions drawn from our study may be 
questionable. Additionally, our study included only 138 patients 
without random allocation. Therefore, further multicenter 
prospective randomized controlled studies with longer follow-
up durations and larger sample sizes are urgently required to 
address these issues. 
Based on the present retrospective study, we were able to draw 
several conclusions from our findings. 
In DCS patients, if the HPLL had reduced mobility, and the 
spinal cord remained compressed after decompression, the HPLL 
should be removed. Accordingly, removal of HPLL in such 
procedures appeared, from our findings, to be beneficial and 
provided more complete spinal cord decompression and 
improved postoperative outcomes. Furthermore, patients who 
underwent HPLL removal had an improved QoL at 24-month 
follow-up. Although these procedures were more complicated 
and required a more skillful approach, they were generally safe 
and effective. 
However, in non-DCS patients, it remains unclear as to 
whether removal of HPLL provides any clinical benefit, thus, 
HPLL removal may not be necessary. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank the staff at the Department of Orthopedics 
and the Department of Research and Statistics, Beijing Friendship 
Hospital, Capital Medical University, and the Department of 
Orthopedics, Xiangya Hospital, Central South University, for 
their kind cooperation when conducting this study. The authors 
also thank the staff at Medjaden Bioscience Limited Company for 
their kindly writing assistance. </p>



<p>Table 5 </p>

<p>Multivariate regression analysis for independents and mJOA score 
of postoperation 24th mo. </p>

<p>Variable 
Coefficient 
P </p>

<p>HPLL removing 
7.337 
.002 
Age 
0.04 
.007 
Preoperative mJOA 
0.278 
&lt;.001 
Postoperative MCS 
0.04 
.002 
Postoperative PCS 
0.04 
.002 </p>

<p>HPLL removing = 1, HPLL retaining = 0. HPLL = hypertrophy posterior longitudinal ligament, MCS = 
mental component summary, mJOA = modified Japanese Orthopedic Association score, PCS = 
physical component summary. </p>

<p>Table 6 </p>

<p>Multivariate regression analysis for independents and mRR 
postoperation 24th mo. </p>

<p>Variable 
Coefficient 
P </p>

<p>HPLL removing 
9.117 
.005 
Postoperative mJOA 
2.872 
.024 </p>

<p>HPLL removing = 1, HPLL retaining = 0. HPLL = hypertrophy posterior longitudinal ligament, mJOA = 
modified Japanese Orthopedic Association score, mRR = the modified recovery rate. </p>

<p>Bai et al. Medicine (2017) 96:23 
www.md-journal.com </p>







</text></tei>