<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5329793" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Background. The aim of this study was to eval-
uate the neuroprotective effect of surgery combined with 
traditional Chinese medicine(TCM)in the treatment of 
glaucoma by meta-analysis based on clinical controlled 
trial. </p>

<p>Glaucoma is a term for a group of eye disorders which 
result in damage to the optic nerve [1]. Most of the damage 
to the optic nerve is related to elevated intraocular pres-
sure (IOP) [2]. Glaucoma is the most commonly diagnosed 
eye disease, considered as the leading cause of blindness 
world-wide [3]. The exact pathogenesis for glaucoma is 
still not clear. Epidemiological data indicates that glau-
coma may be associated with genetic susceptibility, mood 
swings, fatigue and other factors [4]. The goals of glau-
coma management are to avoid nerve damage and pre-
serve visual field and total quality of life for patients with 
minimal side effects. At present, laser surgery, conven-
tional surgery and medicine are used to treat glaucoma. 
Recently, several clinical studies reported that clinical 
efficacy can be improved by surgery combined with tra-
ditional Chinese medicine (TCM) in the treatment of glau-
coma [5, 6]. However, the effectiveness of the combined 
treatment varied considerably among the published 
studies with small sample sizes. Accordingly, we per-
formed a meta-analysis on the basis of published clinical 
trials in order to identify whether the combined treatment 
was superior to surgery alone. </p>

<p>compared to control group (SMD=0.26~95% CI:0.09~0.43, 
P=0.003). </p>

<p>Conclusion. Surgery combined with TCM can improve the 
vision recovery rate and the visual fieldin the treatment of 
glaucoma compared to surgery or western medicine alone. </p>

<p>Keywords: Glaucoma; surgery; traditional Chinese medi-
cine; clinical controlled trial; meta-analysis </p>



<p>Li Chao et al </p>

<p>2 Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1 Studies identification </p>

<p>Clinical controlled trials comparing surgery plus TCM vs. 
surgery or surgery plus western medicine for the treatment 
of glaucoma, published before January 2015, were iden-
tified through an electronic sensitive search of Medline, 
the Cochrane central register of controlled trials, EMBSE 
and CNKI databases. The searching term was glaucoma 
[MeSH]/glaucoma [text]; Chinese medical[MeSH]/Chinese 
medical[test]; Chinese medicine [MeSH]/Chinese medi-
cine[test]. And the corresponding free text words were also 
used as the searching term. The title and abstract of iden-
tified studies were firstly evaluated to assess whether it 
was appropriate to the inclusion criteria or not. Following 
this, all of the potentially relevant trials were evaluated in 
full-text paper and all references of included articles were 
further scanned for additional analysis. </p>

<p>2.2 Inclusion Criteria </p>

<p>The patient inclusion criteria, treatment methods and 
outcomes for each individual study were extracted and 
checked by (LC) as described by the Cochrane Handbook 
formeta-analysis of randomized controlled trials [7]. The 
inclusion for this meta-analysis was as follows: (1) The 
patients included in each individual study were diagnosed 
of glaucoma with no restriction of age and gender. (2) The 
treatment was surgery+TMC in the experiment group and 
surgery alone or surgery+western medicine in the control 
group. (3) The outcomes were vision recovery rate and 
visual field improvement. The study design was prospec-
tive clinical trials without restriction of randomization. </p>

<p>2.3 Data Extraction </p>

<p>All the data for each individual study was extracted by 
two reviewers independently. If disagreement was found, 
the third investigator was consulted for consensus. The 
general information (name of the first author, year of pub-
lication, number of patients, treatment methods), for each 
included study was extracted. The outcome data of vision 
recovery and visual field were recorded for each individ-
ual studies. </p>

<p>2.4 Statistical analysis </p>

<p><rs type="software">STATA/SE</rs> 11.0（Stata Corp LP, http://www.stata.com） 
was used to perform the statistical analysis. Dichotomous 
data is calculated as the risk ratio (RR) with a95% confi-
dence interval (CI). Measurement data was demonstrated 
by mean with its standard difference and pooled by stan-
dard mean difference (SMD). Statistical heterogeneity of 
the results across the included studies was evaluated by 
Chi-square (χ 2 ) test [8], and the inconsistency was calcu-
lated by I2 [9]. If heterogeneity was found (χ 2 , p&lt;0.05 or 
I2&gt;50%), the random-effect method (Dersimonian-Laird 
method) was used to pool the data. Otherwise, without 
significant heterogeneity, fixed-effect method was used. 
The Egger's tests were performed to evaluate publication 
bias as described by Egger [10]. </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>3.1 General characteristic of included 
studies </p>

<p>Through searching the electronic databases of Medline 
(1960~2015.1), CENTRAL (the Cochrane central register 
of controlled trials 1989~2015.1), EMBASE (1980~2015.1) 
and CNKI (1979~2015.1), a total of 113 articles were ini-
tially identified. Of these, 66 potential applicable studies, 
published from2004 and 2014, were reviewed in full-text 
paper. Finally, 11 clinical studies [5, 6, 11-19] with 457 cases 
in the surgery+TCM and 386 subjects in the control group 
were included in this meta-analysis (Figure 1). The general 
information for the included studies was demonstrated in 
Table 1. </p>

<p>3.2 Heterogeneity assess </p>

<p>Significant heterogeneity was not found in the effect size 
of RR (I 2 =0.00%，P=0.647) , which indicated the pooled 
RR was calculated by fixed effect model. For SMD, no 
statistical heterogeneity existed in this meta-analysis 
(I 2 =39.6%，P=0.142) which indicated the SMD was pooled 
by fixed effect model. </p>

<p>A meta-analysis of neuroprotective effect for traditional Chinese medicine in the treatment of glaucoma </p>



<p>3.3 Vision recovery </p>

<p>Nine studies reported the vision recovery rate. The pooled 
results indicated that the surgery combined with tradi-
tional Chinesemedicine treatment procedure can sig-
nificantly improve the vision recovery rate compared 
to control group (RR=1.22, 95% CI:1.06~1.40, P=0.005), 
Figure 2. </p>

<p>3.4 Visual field </p>

<p>Six papers reported the data of visual field improve-
ment. The pooled results indicated that the visual field in </p>

<p>combined group was significantly improved compared to 
control group (SMD=0.26，95% CI:0.09~0.43, P=0.003), 
Figure 3. </p>

<p>3.5 Publication bias evaluation </p>

<p>A Begg's funnel plot and Egger's test were used to evalu-
ate the publication bias [13].For the effect size of RR, the 
Begg's funnel plot showed a small amount of asymmetry 
at the bottom (Figure 4). But the Egger's test demonstrated 
no significant publication bias (t=0.78, P=0.44). For effects 
size of SMD, no significant publication bias was found by 
Egger's test (t=1.82,P=0.143). </p>

<p>4 Discussion </p>

<p>Glaucoma, the leading cause of blindness in the world-
wide for people more than forty years old, is generally 
clinically divided into open-angle glaucoma and closed 
angle glaucoma. Regardless of open-angle or closed angle 
glaucoma, the major pathophysiology is that the intraocu-
lar pressure was increased, which can finally damage the 
optic nerve even leading to loss of vision. 
In clinical management, the general treatment modal-
ity was to avoid or reduce nerve damage, and preserve 
visual field, with minimal side effects [20, 21]. At present, 
laser surgery, conventional surgery and medicine are com-
monlyused to treat glaucoma. The effectiveness of these 
therapies is either limited or associated with significant 
side effects. </p>

<p>Table 1: The general characteristics of included studies </p>

<p>First author 
Year 
Surgery+TCM 
Surgery 
Treatment 
(month) 
n 
Treatment 
n 
Treatment </p>

<p>Liu An 
2006 
33 
Surgery+TCM 
31 
Surgery+medicine 
3 </p>

<p>Tao Rongsan 
2010 
40 
Surgery+TCM 
38 
Surgery 
3 </p>

<p>Lin Xiaodong 
2005 
30 
Surgery+TCM 
30 
Surgery 
3 </p>

<p>Wang Yan 
2010 
53 
Surgery+TCM 
48 
Surgery 
3 </p>

<p>He Yuhong 
2008 
29 
Surgery+TCM 
23 
Surgery 
4 </p>

<p>LiXiang 
2010 
95 
Surgery+TCM 
100 
Surgery 
3 </p>

<p>Pang Youhui 
2009 
82 
Surgery+TCM 
28 
Surgery 
3 </p>

<p>Li Jinshan 
2009 
34 
Surgery+TCM 
28 
Surgery 
2 </p>

<p>Ye Changhua 
2003 
23 
Surgery+TCM 
22 
Surgery+Placebo 
6 </p>

<p>Liu Dongjing 
2004 
18 
Surgery+TCM 
18 
Surgery+Placebo 
6 </p>

<p>Xiang Minhong 2006 
20 
Surgery+TCM 
20 
Surgery+Placebo 
6 </p>

<p>Figure 1: The searching flow chart of this meta-analysis </p>



<p>Li Chao et al </p>

<p>Figure 2: The forest plot of vision recovery treated by surgery+TCM versus surgery or western medicine alone </p>

<p>Figure 3: The forest plot of vision field improvement treated by surgery+TCM versus surgery or western medicine alone </p>

<p>A meta-analysis of neuroprotective effect for traditional Chinese medicine in the treatment of glaucoma </p>



<p>Traditional Chinese medicine has a unique advan-
tage in the treatment of chronic diseases, such as nervous 
system diseases. TCM believes that "the wind for glau-
coma cataract" stasis caused by water, which caused the 
disease. The treatment should be based on supplement-
ing Qi and nourishing Yin [22]. Several clinical studies 
have reported that it was effective for surgery combined 
with traditional Chinese medicine in the treatment of 
glaucoma [11-14]. But the effectiveness of the combined 
treatment ranged a lot among the published studies with 
small sample size. Thus, we searched all the published 
clinical studies reporting the neuroprotective effects of 
surgery combined with traditional Chinese medicine 
(TCM) in the treatment of glaucoma. We thenpooled the 
data by meta-analysis method. The pooled results showed 
that surgery combined with traditional Chinese medicine </p>

<p>treatment procedure can significantly improve the vision 
recovery rate compared to control group (RR=1.33, 95% 
CI:1.09~1.62, p=0.005). This means that the combined 
treatment modality was superior to surgery alone for 
vision recovery. Meta-analysis also found that the visual 
field in combined group was significantly improved com-
pared to control group (SMD=0.26，95% CI:0.09~0.43, 
p=0.003).Therefore, the combined treatment had more 
advantages in the aspect of neuroprotective effect for 
patients with glaucoma. 
Althoughthis meta-analysis found that surgery com-
bined with traditional Chinese medicine can imporve 
the vision recovery rate and the visual field in the treat-
ment of glaucoma compared to surgery or western med-
icine alone, several limitations are found in this study. 
Firstly, all of the 11 included studies come from China with 
patient ethincity "Han", which could lead to patientselec-
tive bias. Secondly, the patient number for each included 
studies was relative small. Thirdly, the results were 
pooled by extracted data of the published paper not the 
individual patient data, which may lead to information 
bias. Fourth, the treatment period ranged from 2 months 
to 6 months which can lead to clinical heterogeneity. In 
view of the above facts,multi-center prospective random-
ized controlled trialsareneeded for further evaluation of 
the the neuroprotective effect of surgery combined with 
traditional chinese medicine (TCM) in the treatment of 
glaucoma. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement: Authors state no conflict 
of interest </p>







</text></tei>