<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5334298" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: The lung cancer mortality rate in Xuanwei city is among the high-
est in China and adenocarcinoma is the major histological type. Lung cancer has 
been associated with exposure to indoor smoky coal emissions that contain high 
levels of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons; however, the pathogenesis of lung 
cancer has not yet been fully elucidated. 
Methods: We performed whole genome sequencing with lung adenocarcinoma 
and corresponding non-tumor tissue to explore the genomic features of Xuanwei 
lung cancer. We used the <rs type="software">Molecule Annotation System</rs> to determine and plot 
alterations in genes and signaling pathways. 
Results: A total of 3 428 060 and 3 416 989 single nucleotide variants were 
detected in tumor and normal genomes, respectively. After comparison of these 
two genomes, 977 high-confidence somatic single nucleotide variants were identi-
fied. We observed a remarkably high proportion of CÁG-AÁT transversions. </p>

<p>HECTD4, RCBTB2, KLF15, and CACNA1C may be cancer-related genes. Nine 
copy number variations increased in chromosome 5 and one in chromosome 
7. The novel junctions were detected via clustered discordant paired ends and 
1955 structural variants were discovered. Among these, we found 44 novel chro-
mosome structural variations. In addition, EGFR and CACNA1C in the mitogen-
activated protein kinase signaling pathway were mutated or amplified in lung 
adenocarcinoma tumor tissue. 
Conclusion: We obtained a comprehensive view of somatic alterations of Xuan-
wei lung adenocarcinoma. These findings provide insight into the genomic land-
scape in order to further learn about the progress and development of Xuanwei 
lung adenocarcinoma. </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer-related death 
globally. Based on GLOBOCAN estimates, 14.1 million 
new cancer cases and 8.2 million deaths occurred in 2012 
worldwide, 1-3 more than 40% of which were lung adeno-
carcinomas. Despite improvement in molecular diagnosis 
and targeted therapies, most tumors are only discovered at 
advanced stage. The overall five-year survival rate is 
approximately 15% worldwide, mainly because of late-stage 
detection and a paucity of late-stage treatments. 4 In China, 
lung cancer is the fastest increasing cancer and the leading </p>

<p>cause of all cancer death since 2004. In some regions, such 
as Xuanwei, the incidence of lung cancer is among the 
highest in China and the world. 5 Recently, a retrospective 
sampling survey reported mortality rates of lung cancer in 
Xuanwei of 98.10/10 5 in men and 83.21/10 5 in women. 6 
Lung cancer in Xuanwei has four remarkable characteris-
tics: higher incidence, higher mortality, adenocarcinoma is 
the major histological type, and similar incidence rates 
between men and women. Lan et al. 7 found that the higher 
incidence was most likely a result of the use of smoky coal 
in unvented stoves in this area. Despite large-scale 
improvement in stoves, the lung cancer mortality rate </p>

<p>88 </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 88-96 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, 
provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer ISSN 1759-7706 </p>

<p>remains very high in Xuanwei (91/10 5 compared with 
China's average of 31/10 5 in 2004-2005). We believe that 
other factors may contribute to the mechanisms of lung 
cancer development and progress in this area. Thus, the 
molecular study of lung cancer, especially genetic mechan-
isms, is of great importance. 
The development of next generation sequencing technol-
ogy has greatly facilitated the detection and characteriza-
tion of genetic variations, including single nucleotide 
variations (SNVs), chromosome structural variations 
(SVs), and copy number variations (CNVs) in human gen-
omes, especially in the field of cancer research. 8 Recently, 
cancer sequencing efforts based on next generation sequen-
cing technologies have provided a genome-wide view of 
mutations in leukemia, melanoma, lung cancer, and 
others. 9-11 In addition, somatic mutation events can reveal 
specific and novel information about the fundamental 
genetic mechanisms that may be involved in the develop-
ment and progression of lung adenocarcinoma in Xuanwei. 
Studies have validated the various genomic aberrations that 
may act as therapeutic targets. In recent years, new molec-
ular targeted drugs in the pharmacological treatment of 
adenocarcinoma have been introduced, and their effective-
ness is closely dependent on the presence of specific 
genetic mutations in the tumor. 12 Somatic mutations in the 
tyrosine kinase domain of the epidermal growth factor 
receptor (EGFR) gene are one of the most relevant targets 
for lung cancer treatment. 13,14 To date, research of next 
generation sequencing has discovered most of the relevant 
mutations that contribute to the pathogenesis of adenocar-
cinoma; however, there is limited genomic data of lung 
adenocarcinoma in Xuanwei. Therefore, we believe that 
unbiased whole genome sequencing (WGS) is required to 
screen more mutations of lung adenocarcinoma in 
Xuanwei. 
Herein, we present a detailed analysis of paired tumor 
and normal tissues from Xuanwei by WGS. Our findings 
present insights into the frequent somatic alterations that 
may be associated with the adenocarcinoma pathogenesis. 
Our results show a significant advance toward a compre-
hensive annotation of somatic alterations of lung adenocar-
cinoma in Xuanwei, and demonstrate the need for 
unbiased whole genome approaches to discover all muta-
tions associated with cancer pathogenesis. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Sample description and preparation </p>

<p>Lung adenocarcinoma and corresponding non-tumor tis-
sues were collected from a 41-year-old, non-smoking male 
patient from Xuanwei County at the First Affiliated Hospi-
tal of Kunming Medical University, China. The patient had </p>

<p>been exposed to coal smoke for 10 years. Sections that 
underwent curative resection were stained with hematoxy-
lin and eosin and examined by a pathologist to verify the 
diagnosis and evaluate tumor stage. Lung adenocarcinoma 
and corresponding non-tumor tissues were stored in liquid 
nitrogen until genomic DNA extraction. The Committee 
on Ethics in Research on Humans of the First Affiliated 
Hospital of Kunming Medical University approved the 
study. Informed consent was obtained from the patient. </p>

<p>Genomic DNA isolation and qualification </p>

<p>An experienced pathologist examined the lung adenocarci-
noma and corresponding non-tumor tissues to confirm the 
presence (&gt;80%) or absence of cancer cells. Lung adenocar-
cinoma and non-tumor tissues (25 mg each) were placed 
in liquid nitrogen and grinded thoroughly using a mortar 
and pestle. Decanted tissue powder and liquid nitrogen 
were placed into a 1.5 mL microcentrifuge tube containing 
180 μL of buffer animal tissue lysis. Genomic DNA 
(gDNA) was extracted using the QIAamp DNA Blood 
Mini Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to the 
manufacturer's protocol. gDNA was quantified using a 
NanoDrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer (CapitalBio 
Nano Q, Beijing, China). The integrity of the gDNA was 
tested using 1.0% agarose gel. </p>

<p>Whole genome sequencing (WGS) </p>

<p>Whole genome sequencing was performed by unchained 
combinatorial probe anchor ligation (cPAL) and DNA 
Nanoball (DNB) arrays. Sequencing substrates were gener-
ated by means of gDNA fragmentation and recursive cut-
ting with type IIS restriction enzymes and directional 
adapter insertion. cPAL was based on unchained hybridi-
zation and ligation technology, using degenerate anchors 
to read up to 10 bases from each eight adapter sites. DNB 
production was conducted using Phi29 DNA polymerase 
and nanoarray. WGS was performed using the Complete 
Genomics sequencing platform (Mountain View, CA, 
USA), resulting in a total of 259 218 Gb mapped sequences 
(86× average coverage) for the lung adenocarcinoma and 
242 639 Gb (81× average coverage) for the corresponding 
non-tumor tissue samples (Table 1). Reads were aligned to 
the reference genome (NCBI Build 37) to reach a 97% 
matching rate. Somatic variations in lung adenocarcinoma 
tissue were identified by comparing variations with the 
corresponding non-tumor tissue. A Circos plot of somatic 
variation between the lung adenocarcinoma and non-
tumor tissue was created, containing information about 
SNP, CNV, and SV (Fig S1). </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 88-96 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>



<p>X. Wang et al. 
WSG of Xuanwei lung adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>Mapping reads and calling variations </p>

<p>Genomic reads were initially mapped to the reference 
genome using a fast algorithm. These initial mappings were 
both expanded and refined by a form of local de novo 
assembly in all regions of the genome that appeared to 
contain variations based on these initial mappings. The de 
novo assembly fully leverages mate-pair information, 
allowing reads to be recruited into variants with higher 
sensitivity than genome-wide mapping methods alone typi-
cally provide. Assemblies were diploid, and sequencing 
produced two separate result sequences for each locus in 
diploid regions. Variants were called by independently 
comparing each of the diploid assemblies to the reference. 
The original computational methods for small variant 
detection are available at: http://online.liebertpub.com/doi/ 
full/10.1089/cmb.2011.0201. These methods have evolved 
over the development of further <rs type="software">Analysis Pipeline</rs> versions. </p>

<p>Single nucleotide variant (SNV) analysis </p>

<p>The algorithmic details of the small variant caller used to 
identify and score small variants (SNVs, insertions, deletions, 
and block substitutions) is available on the Complete Geno-
mics website: www.completegenomics.com/customersupport/ 
documentation. All variants were annotated for their pres-
ence in dbSNP 137 and the 1000 Genomes Project dataset. 
We evaluated the potential impact on protein function for 
somatic missense mutations identified through WGS using 
SIFT, a computational method. SIFT scores, ranging from 
0 to 1, were obtained from the program output. The SIFT 
score represents the normalized probability that a particu-
lar amino acid substitution is tolerated, and a score below 
the cut-off value 0.05 is generally considered deleterious. </p>

<p>Copy number variation (CNV) region 
analysis </p>

<p>The processing steps and algorithmic details of the CNV 
pipeline used to identify and score regions of genomic copy 
number variation are available at: www.completegenomics. </p>

<p>com/customersupport/documentation. The determination 
of CNV calling for normal and tumor samples consisted of 
the following steps: (i) computation of sequence coverage; 
(ii) estimation and correction of bias in coverage (modeling 
of coverage bias, correction of modeled bias, and coverage 
smoothing); and (iii) normalization of coverage by com-
parison to a baseline sample or set of samples. 
Following normalization of coverage, both normal and 
tumor samples were segmented using Hidden Markov 
Models (HMM), but with a different model for each sam-
ple type: HMM segmentation, scoring, and output. Finally, 
normal samples were subjected to a "no-calling" process 
that identified suspect CNV calls. </p>

<p>Structural variation (SV) analysis </p>

<p>Structural variation is generally defined as deletions, inser-
tions, duplications, inversions, translocations, or CNV in 
large DNA segments (&gt;1 kb), represented by one or more 
junctions. The process of detailed description of how an 
SV event was deduced from junction data involved the 
generation of an undirected graph of related junctions. We 
annotated each event with biological information: (i) with 
the list of all potentially disrupted genes -the genes that 
overlapped at least one of the junction side positions for 
any of the junctions that were grouped into the event; 
(ii) any events that may indicate a copy number change of 
a stretch of sequence (e.g. deletion, tandem-duplication, 
and distal-duplication events), including all of the genes 
that were completely contained in the affected sequence; 
and (iii) when a junction appeared to connect two different 
genes in a strand consistent manner, it was considered a 
possible gene fusion. </p>

<p>Molecule annotation of variations </p>

<p>Predicted single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) were 
compared using National Center for Biotechnology Infor-
mation (NCBI) dbSNP version 137 to annotate known 
SNP information. Each SNP was mapped on the genomic 
features of the UCSC gene table, such as coding region, 
untranslational region, and intron. Non-synonymous SNP 
information was extracted by comparing UCSC reference 
gene information (http://genome.Ucsc.edu/). Information 
on cancer-related mutations was obtained from the cosmic 
cancer information database (http://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/ 
cancergenome/projects/cosmic/). The Ingenuity <rs id="software-2" type="software">Molecule 
Annotation System (MAS</rs>) (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://bioinfo.capitalbio.com/mas3/</rs>/) was used for functional interaction analysis of the 
genes affected. The MAS is a whole data-mining and func-
tion annotation solution used to extract and analyze bio-
logical molecule relationships from a public knowledge 
base of biological molecules and signification. </p>

<p>Table 1 Sequence coverage summary for normal and tumor genomes </p>

<p>Sequence coverage 
Normal 
Tumor </p>

<p>Gross mapping yield (Gb) 
307.288 
324.531 
Both mates mapped yield (Gb) 
242.639 
259.218 
Average haploid coverage 
81× 
86× 
Fully called genome fraction 
0.975 
0.976 
SNVs 
3 416 989 
3 428 060 
Substitution 
89 536 
90 455 </p>

<p>SNV, single nucleotide variant. Coverage percentage and variations are 
with respect to National Center for Biotechnology Information Build 
37 of the human genome reference assembly. </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 88-96 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>WSG of Xuanwei lung adenocarcinoma 
X. Wang et al. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Identification and distribution 
of somatic SNVs </p>

<p>Called single-nucleotide variations were filtered to obtain a 
list of candidate somatic mutations (Fig 1). A total of 
3 428 060 and 3 416 989 SNPs were called independently 
from lung adenocarcinoma and corresponding non-tumor 
tissue, respectively. After comparing the SNPs presented in 
the non-tumor tissue, 55 142 somatic SNVs were identified 
in the lung adenocarcinoma tissue, reaching 11.4 mutations 
per megabase throughout the genome. Among them, 
977 were high confident somatic SNVs and 964 were 
potentially novel somatic mutations, compared with lung 
adenocarcinoma tissue. Of these SNVs, about 32% 
(309 SNVs) were located in intronic regions, 65% 
(631 SNVs) in intergenic regions, 1% (6 SNVs) in 
upstream or downstream regions of a gene, and 1% 
(5 SNVs) were located in 3 0 or 5 0 untranslated regions 
(Fig 2). The transition (Ts, 2 383 204) and transversion 
(Tv, 1 154 590) ratio was 2.127, and the homozygosity 
(1383596) and heterozygosity (1890004) proportions were 
42% and 58%, respectively. </p>

<p>HECTD4, RCBTB2B, KLF15, and CACNA1C may 
be cancer-related genes </p>

<p>We obtained a list of candidate somatic mutations, of 
which 12 are identified in coding regions with 10 non-
synonymous and two stopgain SNVs (Table 2). We further </p>

<p>analyzed the SNVs in exonic regions by comparing them 
with the cancer-related genes in the Catalogue of Somatic 
Mutations in Cancer database. A SIFT score for amino acid 
substitutions below the cut-off value 0.05 is generally con-
sidered deleterious. Finally, our results showed that 
HECTD4, RCBTB2, KLF15, and CACNA1C may be cancer-
related genes, with SIFT scores of 0.00, 0.00, 0.01, and 0.05, 
respectively. </p>

<p>CÁG-AÁT transversion was a common 
mutation in lung adenocarcinoma tissue </p>

<p>The composition of somatic variations in this lung adeno-
carcinoma sample was distinct from the germline varia-
tions. Across the entire genome, somatic variations 
occurred predominantly at CÁG base pairs (75.31%), and 
the most prevalent change was CÁG-AÁT transversion 
(56.86%). Germline variations occurred predominantly also 
at CÁG base pairs (51.84%), whereas the most frequent 
transitions were AÁT-GÁC (33.50%) and CÁG-TÁA (34.80%). 
Interestingly, enrichment of the CÁG-AÁT transversion was 
found to be a genome-wide trend for somatic variations, a 
sharp contrast to the 8.31% occurrence of germline varia-
tions (Fig 3a). 
The distribution of somatic mutations in the genome is 
highly non-uniform, as protein-coding exons have a sub-
stantially lower rate. In our sample, there were lower rates 
of mutation in the transcribed strand compared with the 
non-transcribed strand (Fig 3b). The ratio of the overall 
non-synonymous substitution rate (Ka) to synonymous </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow chart describing the methodol-
ogy used in filtering single nucleotide variants 
(SNVs) to obtain candidate novel somatic 
mutations. </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 88-96 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>



<p>X. Wang et al. 
WSG of Xuanwei lung adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>substitution rate (Ks) in this sample was 0.95, suggesting 
that most mutations are "passengers." </p>

<p>Nine CNVs increased in chromosome 5 
and one in chromosome 7 </p>

<p>Copy number variation is caused by the rearrangement of 
the genome. A DNA segment of 1 Kb or larger presents 
genome large copies that are increased or decreased com-
pared with a reference genome. CNV of more than two 
was defined as a CNV increase, while less than two was 
defined as a CNV decrease. We found that 14 CNVs 
increased in chromosome 5 and one CNV increased in 
chromosome 7. When the exact loci of tumor suppressors 
and oncogenes were analyzed, we identified nine CNVs 
increased in chromosome 5 and one in chromosome </p>

<p>7 involving gene expression (Table 3). Interestingly, tumor 
oncogenes EGFR at chromosome 7 and TERT at chromo-
some 5 were highly increased on chromosomal regions. </p>

<p>Forty-four novel SVs were identified </p>

<p>We screened for SVs based on discordant paired end geno-
mic sequencing data. Normal SVs called from non-tumor 
tissue were used as a filter to remove somatic SVs and 
technical artifacts, resulting in a list of candidate SVs. The 
SV analysis resulted in 1955 junction counts. During SV 
detection, 44 were not present with the required coverage 
in the normal sample and were designated as somatic SVs: 
16 deletions, eight tandem-duplication, four distal-duplica-
tion, five inversions, and 11 complex (Table S1). The 
majority of rearrangements cannot be ascribed to classical </p>

<p>Table 2 Details of predicted non-synonymous single nucleotide variations </p>

<p>Chromosome 
Start 
End 
Reference 
Alt 
Gene symbol 
Gene function impaction 
SIFT </p>

<p>12 
112 673 325 
112 673 325 
G 
A 
HECTD4 
Nonsynonymous SNV 
0 
13 
49 075 918 
49 075 918 
C 
A 
RCBTB2 
Stopgain SNV 
0 
3 
126 071 687 
126 071 687 
C 
A 
KLF15 
Nonsynonymous SNV 
0.01 
12 
2 721 085 
2 721 085 
G 
T 
CACNA1C 
Nonsynonymous SNV 
0.05 
14 
92 482 047 
92 482 047 
T 
A 
TRIP11 
Nonsynonymous SNV 
0.11 
14 
105 405 385 
105 405 385 
T 
A 
AHNAK2 
Nonsynonymous SNV 
0.17 
22 
21 330 800 
21 330 800 
G 
T 
AIFM3 
Nonsynonymous SNV 
0.27 
5 
94 764 399 
94 764 399 
C 
T 
FAM81B 
Nonsynonymous SNV 
0.32 
9 
136 421 040 
136 421 040 
C 
A 
ADAMTSL2 
Nonsynonymous SNV 
0.34 
16 
309 499 
309 499 
G 
T 
ITFG3 
Nonsynonymous SNV 
0.39 
2 
189 904 214 
189 904 214 
T 
G 
COL5A2 
Nonsynonymous SNV 
0.69 
6 
47 847 014 
47 847 014 
G 
C 
PTCHD4 
Stopgain SNV 
1 </p>

<p>SNV, single nucleotide variant. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Distribution of the 964 novel somatic 
single nucleotide variants (SNVs) based on their 
genomic location. Of the 964 potentially novel 
somatic mutations, 32% were in an intronic 
region, 65% in an intergenic region, 1% in 
upstream or downstream regions of a gene, 
and an additional 1% were in an untranslated 
(UTR) 3 0 or 5 0 region. </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 88-96 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>WSG of Xuanwei lung adenocarcinoma 
X. Wang et al. </p>

<p>SV patterns, because of the considerably greater complexity 
of somatically acquired rearrangements compared to germ-
line events. </p>

<p>Molecule annotation of variations </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">MAS</rs> was used to determine and plot the alterations of 
genes and signaling pathways. Indeed, two genes in the 
mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling path-
way, EGFR and CACNA1C, were found either mutated or 
amplified in lung adenocarcinoma tissue (Fig S2) and other 
cancer-related pathways also harbored multiple mutations 
(Fig S3). Activation of the MAPK pathway can result in a </p>

<p>multitude of physiological effects, including apoptosis, cell 
proliferation, mitosis, and the transcription of several 
classes of genes. EGFR was found in telomerase, cellular 
aging, and immortality pathways and plays a role in nicoti-
nic acetylcholine receptors in the regulation of cellular 
apoptosis (Fig 4). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Research has shown that lung cancer is caused by the accu-
mulation of genomic alterations. Until recently, it has been 
difficult to interpret these various changes within a single 
tumor that may work together to fulfill the hallmark traits </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>Figure 3 (a) Somatic single nucleotide mutation trends. Somatic mutations were primarily CÁG-AÁT transversions. Distribution of specific nucleotide 
changes among germline and somatic variations in the lung adenocarcinoma genome. CÁG-AÁT transversions accounted for 56% of high confidence 
somatic mutations, whereas most germline variations were AÁT-GÁC and CÁG-TÁA transitions. (b) Somatic single-nucleotide mutations of all types 
occurred at a lower frequency on the transcribed strand (TS). TS represent single nucleotide somatic mutation rates, with different types of base sub-
stitutions on the coding regions. The non-transcribed strand (NTS) represents the same classes of mutations occurring on the NTS. </p>

<p>Table 3 Copy number variation increased in chromosomes 5 and 7 </p>

<p>Chromosome 
Start 
End 
Called score 
CNV type score 
Overlapping gene </p>

<p>chr5 
9 590 000 
9 632 000 
3 
32 
TAS2R1 </p>

<p>chr5 
1 156 000 
1 228 000 
3 
33 
SLC6A18; SLC6A19 </p>

<p>chr5 
1 478 000 
1 498 000 
3 
6 
LPCAT1 </p>

<p>chr5 
1 532 000 
2 582 000 
3 
50 
IRX4; LOC100506843;LOC100506858; 
LOC728613; MIR4277; 
MRPL36; NDUFS6; SDHAP3 </p>

<p>chr5 
15 934 000 
16 328 000 
3 
31 
FBXL7; LOC100505959;LOC401176; MARCH11; MIR887 </p>

<p>chr5 
15 122 000 
15 890 000 
3 
43 
FBXL7 </p>

<p>chr5 
1 248 000 
1 410 000 
3 
52 
CLPTM1L; LOC100506791;SLC6A3; TERT </p>

<p>chr5 
19 856 000 
20 046 000 
3 
22 
CDH18 </p>

<p>chr5 
2 720 000 
4 094 000 
3 
42 
C5orf38; IRX1; IRX2; LOC285577 </p>

<p>chr5 
2 582 000 
2 720 000 
4 
69 
chr5 
4 194 000 
4 382 000 
3 
26 
chr5 
4 412 000 
4 486 000 
3 
32 
chr5 
18 718 000 
18 852 000 
3 
19 
chr5 
19 256 000 
19 346 000 
3 
4 
chr7 
55 018 000 
55 776 000 
3 
54 
EGFR; FKBP9L; LANCL2;LOC100507500; VOPP1 </p>

<p>CNV, copy number variation. </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 88-96 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>



<p>X. Wang et al. 
WSG of Xuanwei lung adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>of the malignant phenotype. The development of parallel 
sequencing technologies has provided a powerful tool for 
the study of lung cancer genomes. In this paper, we con-
ducted high-depth coverage (~80×) and detailed analysis 
of the whole genome sequence to a case of lung adenocar-
cinoma in Xuanwei. The sequencing analysis proved that 
data quality was high (only 5% of the total sequence was 
filtered out) and the reads almost completely covered the </p>

<p>reference human genome. Our results showed that Xuan-
wei lung adenocarcinoma could have a large number of 
new mutations, ranging from the single nucleotide to chro-
mosome alterations. We also found that some of these 
mutation genes participated in several well-described path-
ways that were known to contribute to cancer pathogene-
sis; however, most genes were unknown in our current 
understanding of the development and progression of dis-
ease. Therefore, WGS facilitated the investigation of the 
biological and clinical implications of such variations. 
In this study, the SNVs exhibited a highly distinctive 
pattern, showing a high proportion of CÁG-AÁT transver-
sions and a low fraction of AÁT-CÁG transversions. Studies </p>

<p>have indicated that CÁG to AÁT transversions are the most 
common substitution in non-small cell lung cancer associ-
ated with smoking, and our experimental results were con-
sistent 
with 
tobacco 
exposure-related 
mutation 
signatures. 15,16 Non-small cell lung tumors from non-
smokers are dominated by CÁG-TÁA transitions compared 
with CÁG-AÁT transversions in lung tumors from smokers. 
Lui et al. identified that CÁG-TÁA transitions were 
decreased in a progressive manner with cumulative expo-
sure to tobacco. 17 Interestingly, our patient was a non-
smoker who had been exposed to coal smoke for 10 years, 
and the CÁG-TÁA transitions (12%) were of relatively lower 
frequency compared with CÁG-AÁT transversions (56%), 
which may be associated with the coal smoke. However, 
our hypothesis requires further study for confirmation. 
A previous study showed that compositions of germline 
and somatic variants were different in lung cancer gen-
omes, with enriched CÁG-AÁT transversions in the somatic 
mutation group. 18 A direct comparison between germline 
and somatic variations highlighted the strong influence of 
smoking-related DNA damage. 19 Furthermore, GÁC-CÁG </p>

<p>Telomeres, Telomerase, Cellular Aging, and 
Immortality </p>

<p>Neuroregulin receptor degredation protein-1 
Controls ErbB3 receptor recycling </p>

<p>Role of ERBB2 in Signal Transduction and 
Oncology </p>

<p>Erk1/Erk2 Mapk Signaling pathway </p>

<p>CBL mediated ligand-induced 
downregulation of EGF receptors </p>

<p>EGF Signaling Pathway </p>

<p>Keratinocyte Differentiation </p>

<p>Telomeres, Telomerase, Cellular Aging, 
and Immortality </p>

<p>The role of FYVE-finger proteins in 
vesicle transport </p>

<p>Agrin in Postsynaptic Differentiation </p>

<p>mCalpain and friends in Cell motility </p>

<p>EGFR </p>

<p>Agrin in Postsynaptic Differentiation </p>

<p>Sprouty regulation of tyrosine kinase signals </p>

<p>Role of EGF Receptor Transactivation 
by GPCRs in Cardiac Hypertrophy </p>

<p>Map Kinase Inactivation of SMRT Corepressor </p>

<p>Figure 4 Gene pathway network BioCarta analysis. EGFR was found to play an important role in telomerase, cellular aging, and immortality. </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 88-96 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>WSG of Xuanwei lung adenocarcinoma 
X. Wang et al. </p>

<p>somatic changes were strongly enriched at GpA/TpC dinu-
cleotides, which accounted for 52% of the nucleotide GÁC 
variations. Lower rates of mutation have been found in a 
transcribed strand compared with a non-transcribed strand 
in a small cell cancer cell line. 15 We observed a similar 
trend, with a pattern that would result from transcription-
coupled DNA repair processes. 
In addition to commonly mutated genes, we also identi-
fied distinct mutational signatures and signaling pathways </p>

<p>in Xuanwei lung adenocarcinoma. Some somatic SNVs 
and CNVs have been already reported as either oncogenes 
or tumor suppressors in the COSMIC database, including 
EGFR and CACNA1C. In addition, we identified 13 lung 
adenocarcinoma specific genes in our study. Twelve non-
synonymous somatic mutations and two mutations known 
to be associated with lung adenocarcinoma were identified, 
including two SNVs located in exon 18 and exon 20 of the 
EGFR gene. EGFR, a cell surface protein, binds to the epi-
dermal growth factor. Binding of the protein to a ligand-
induced receptor dimerization and tyrosine autophosphor-
ylation leads to cell proliferation. 14 Both of these mutations 
are common in lung cancers, and both were thought to 
contribute to progression and development of the disease. 
This cancer genome had few mutated genes in the lung 
adenocarcinoma pathway, but showed statistically mean-
ingful genetic changes in the MAPK signaling pathways. 
MAPK signaling pathways can contribute to carcinogenesis 
in lung adenocarcinoma. 
This comparative analysis provides a complex mutation 
landscape as a reference data set in understanding lung 
adenocarcinoma genome variation and was an initial step 
in exploring lung adenocarcinoma genomic features in 
Xuanwei. The observed mutation landscape was probably 
shaped by many different processes, including how to gen-
erate the original mutations, how to affect DNA repair 
mechanisms, and how to select during tumor evolution. 20 
Selection could act in two directions: by retaining muta-
tions that will benefit tumor growth, while also limiting 
mutations in key functional regions of the genome, such as 
promoters and expressed genes. 
As a tumor from only one case was sequenced, we could 
not determine whether these somatic variations were derived 
from driver or passenger mutations. Our hypotheses ideally 
need to be tested in an in vitro model. The mutated target 
genes and their cellular signaling mechanisms indicated 
aberrations in DNA repair mechanisms, which may be 
related to the lung adenocarcinoma progression in our 
patient. Our study and other studies of individual cancer 
genomes have shown a trend in mutations, but identification 
of the recurrent driver mutations will require many more 
samples to sequence. Nevertheless, we believe the data pro-
vides a cornerstone for such studies and enriches the analy-
sis of Xuanwei lung adenocarcinoma in genomic variation. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant number: 
81160292), the Health Science and Technology Project in 
Yunnan Province (2014NS152), and the leading talent 
project of the health system in Yunnan province (L-
201202) supported this study. We also wish to thank the 
study participant. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>No authors report any conflict of interest. </p>





<p>X. Wang et al. 
WSG of Xuanwei lung adenocarcinoma </p>



<p>Supporting Information </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online 
version of this article at the publisher's website: </p>

<p>Figure S1 The genomic landscape of somatic alterations. 
Figure S2 Mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling 
pathway analysis. 
Figure S3 Gene Pathway Network_KEGG analysis. </p>

<p>Table S1 Details of somatic structural variations. </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 88-96 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>WSG of Xuanwei lung adenocarcinoma 
X. Wang et al. </p>

</text></tei>