<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5220128" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Acute myeloid leukemia (AML) is a clonal hematologic malignant disease of developing myeloid cells that have acquired aberrant 
survival, uncontrolled proliferation and a block in normal hematopoietic cell differentiation. Standard chemotherapy often induces 
remissions in AML patients, but the disease frequently relapses due to incomplete targeting of leukemia-initiating cells (LICs), 
emphasizing the need for novel effective treatments. Exportin 1 (XPO1)-mediated nuclear export, which is inhibited by the drug 
selinexor, is an attractive new therapeutic target in AML. Selinexor has shown impressive activity in Phase I/II clinical trials for AML. 
Here we report the anti-leukemic efficacy and tolerability of KPT-8602, a second-generation XPO1 inhibitor. KPT-8602 demonstrates 
substantially reduced brain penetration compared to selinexor, with resultant attenuation of the central nervous system mediated 
side effects of anorexia and weight loss. Due to its improved tolerability profile, KPT-8602 can be given daily compared to the two 
or three times weekly regimen of selinexor, and exhibits greater anti-leukemic efficacy against both leukemic blasts and LICs in AML 
patient-derived xenograft models. Importantly, normal hematopoietic stem and progenitor cell (HSPC) frequency is not significantly 
reduced by KPT-8602, providing a therapeutic window for elimination of relapse-driving LICs while sparing normal HSPCs. These 
findings strongly endorse clinical testing of KPT-8602 in patients with relapsed and refractory AML. </p>

<p>Currently available combination chemotherapy for acute myeloid 
leukemia (AML) induces complete remission in about 75% of 
younger and 45% of older patients, but the majority of patients 
relapse. 1 This high relapse rate is likely due to the inability of the 
existing drugs to effectively target the self-renewing and disease-
sustaining leukemia-initiating cells (LICs). 2-5 Therefore, novel 
therapies that not only eliminate the AML blasts but also target 
the LICs are needed to prevent leukemic relapse. 
An emerging therapeutic strategy in AML is inhibition of the 
nuclear export protein, exportin 1 (XPO1). This strategy exploits the 
dependence of leukemic cells on the continuous nuclear export of 
a subset of proteins and RNAs, although the precise cargos that 
are oncorequisite for AML cell survival have not yet been defined. 
XPO1, a karyopherin β family member, is a major nuclear-
cytoplasmic exporter in eukaryotes and regulates transfer of ~ 220 
proteins that contain leucine-rich nuclear export signals, as well as 
nuclear export signal-containing protein adaptors that mediate 
transfer of RNAs. 6-9 XPO1 affinity for its cargo is mediated by 
binding of Ran-GTP in the nucleus, and its cargoes are released 
upon Ran-GTP hydrolysis by Ran-GAP 10-14 in the cytoplasm. XPO1 
protein cargoes include tumor suppressor proteins, apoptosis 
inducers and cell cycle regulators. 15-17 Based on in vivo studies 
of selinexor, several types of hematologic malignancies and solid 
tumors are dependent on XPO1-mediated nuclear export for their </p>

<p>survival. In contrast, selinexor is well tolerated by normal cells, 
including blood cells and gastrointestinal epithelia. 18-26 
In an effort to exploit this selective vulnerability of cancer cells 
to inhibition of nuclear export, novel small-molecule XPO1 
inhibitors, or Selective Inhibitor of Nuclear Export (SINE) 
molecules, were designed by in silico modeling strategies. 27 
SINE compounds covalently bind to cysteine 528 in the cargo-
binding groove of XPO1 to block the interaction of XPO1 with its 
cargo and hence inhibit nuclear export. The first-generation 
orally bioavailable clinical SINE compound, selinexor (KPT-330), is 
currently being evaluated in Phase 1 and 2 clinical trials in adult 
patients with AML (NCT01607892, NCT02088541, NCT02249091, 
NCT02403310, NCT02093403, NCT02485535, NCT02299518, 
NCT02416908, NCT02212561 and NCT01607892), in a Phase 1 
trial for relapsed childhood ALL and AML (NCT02091245), in Phase 
1/2 trials in children with leukemia or MDS (NCT02212561), and in 
many other types of human cancer (http://clinicaltrials.gov). The 
results of these trials are encouraging, as they have demonstrated 
that selinexor alone or in combination with conventional therapies 
is active in inducing remission in patients with relapsed or refractory 
AML. 22,28-31 
Studies by our group and others demonstrated the anti-
leukemic activity of selinexor in xenograft preclinical models of 
human hematologic malignancies, including AML, chronic lym-
phocytic leukemia, T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia, chronic 
lymphocytic leukemia, and multiple myeloma. 18,19,22,23,25,32-38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Pediatric Oncology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, MA, USA; 2 Division of Hematology/Oncology, Children's Hospital, Boston, MA, USA; 3 Department of 
Medical Oncology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA; 4 Karyopharm Therapeutics, Newton, MA, USA; 5 Princess Margaret Cancer Centre, 
University Health Network, Toronto, ON, Canada and 6 Department of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada. Correspondence: Professor Dr AT Look, Department 
of Pediatric Oncology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Mayer Building, Room 630, 450 Brookline Avenue, Boston, 02215 MA, USA. 
E-mail: thomas_look@dfci.harvard.edu 
Received 8 January 2016; revised 24 March 2016; accepted 25 April 2016; accepted article preview online 23 May 2016; advance online publication, 24 June 2016 </p>

<p>Leukemia (2017) 31, 143-150 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/leu </p>

<p>In our most recent published study, we tested the activity of 
selinexor in primary patient-derived xenografts, or PDX models, 
established from AML patient cell samples. 39-41 PDX models are 
the gold standard assay for assessing the self-renewing LIC 
population, and the properties of LICs that read out in these assays 
have been shown to be clinically relevant. 42,43 In PDX models 
established from high-risk AML patients, selinexor very potently 
inhibits human AML blasts and eliminates the self-renewing 
LICs. 40 
Recently, a second-generation SINE compound, KPT-8602, was 
discovered by drug metabolism and pharmacokinetics-directed 
drug design (Supplementary Figure 1). KPT-8602 is orally bioavail-
able and has similar pharmacokinetic properties to selinexor, 
but has markedly reduced (approximately 30-fold less) penetration 
across the blood − brain barrier, as demonstrated in Table 1 of 
the accompanying manuscript by Hing et al. In clinical trials, the 
dose-limiting side effects of selinexor are central nervous system 
(CNS)-mediated anorexia with weight loss and malaise, as well as 
thrombocytopenia, which limit the frequency of dosing to two or 
three times per week. Toxicology studies in rats and monkeys 
indicate that KPT-8602 has a substantially better tolerability profile, 
probably due to its inability to penetrate into the CNS, with reduced 
anorexia, malaise and weight loss compared to selinexor. This 
evidence prompted us to test the anti-leukemic activity of KPT-8602 
against LICs in AML, and to compare the efficacy and tolerability of 
KPT-8602 and selinexor in PDX models of high-risk AML. Our results 
demonstrate the superior anti-leukemic efficacy of KPT-8602 
compared to selinexor, with minimal toxicity to normal hemato-
poietic stem and progenitor cells. These findings indicate that 
KPT-8602 should be tested for efficacy and tolerability in clinical 
trials of patients with relapsed and refractory AML. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patient-derived xenograft models of AML </p>

<p>Primary patient cells were collected from bone marrow aspirates of AML 
patients according to approved protocols. We used low-passage human 
AML cells that have been expanded from patient AML cells by injection 
into NOD-SCID-IL2Rcγ null (NSG) mice (but never cultured in tissue culture) 
and cryopreserved in multiple vials for experiments. To establish murine 
models of patient AML, or patient-derived xenograft (PDX) model, primary 
leukemic cells from AML patients were injected via the tail vein into NSG 
mice (The Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, ME, USA). Mice received the 
same number of AML cells, ranging from 8 × 10 4 to 20 × 10 4 AML cells per 
mouse, for establishing each PDX model. Injected mice were monitored for 
human CD45-positive (hCD45+) leukemia cells in peripheral blood by flow 
cytometry every 2 weeks and treatment was initiated when more than 5% 
of the cells were hCD45+ AML cells, as described previously. 40 To 
determine the level of leukemia infiltration and to obtain absolute counts 
(hCD45+ cells per femur and tibia) prior to therapy, four mice were killed 
and the bone marrow cells were extracted from femurs, tibia or spine by 
crushing the bone or spleen in FBS-supplemented RPMI medium. To 
determine the drug efficacies, mice were dosed by oral gavage with vehicle 
(methylcellulose/tween 80), selinexor (20 mg/kg twice a week for PDX AML-
CN and three times a week for AML-CK and AML/MDS) or KPT-8602 (15 mg/kg 
daily) for 4 weeks. To determine the drug response of mice in all 
experimental groups, we measured the percent hCD45+ AML cell 
infiltration among the bone marrow leukocytes and absolute counts of 
hCD45+ cells per femur and tibia in the PDX models of each 
experimental group. </p>

<p>Secondary transplantation assays </p>

<p>After 4 weeks of treatment, we killed the PDX mice and isolated the femur 
and tibia bone marrow cells in 4 − 7 mice of each experimental group. The 
bone marrow hCD45+ AML blasts at doses from 10 6 to 10 2 hCD45+ cells 
were transplanted into new recipient mice. After 18 − 22 weeks, cohorts of 
mice transplanted with dilutions of hCD45+ cells were screened for hCD45+ 
infiltration into the bone marrow of mouse femurs (for details please 
see reference 33 in Etchin et al. 40 ). The fractions of leukemic mice per 
total number of mice in each dilution cohort were used to calculate the LIC </p>

<p>frequency by Extreme Limiting Dilution software (http://bioinf.wehi.edu.au/ 
software/elda/). Please see Schmidt et al. 33 in the main text for details. </p>

<p>Engraftment of normal hCD34+ cells into NSG mice </p>

<p>Human CD34+ (hCD34+) cells were isolated from the cord blood of 
consenting healthy mothers according to approved procedures. 10 5 hCD34+ 
cells per mouse were intravenously injected into sublethally (200 cGy) 
irradiated NSG mice and peripheral blood was analyzed for the appearance 
of hCD45+ cells by flow cytometric analysis every 2 − 4 weeks. Human 
grafts were treated with either vehicle, selinexor (20 mg/kg twice a week 
for PDX AML-CN and three times a week for AML-CK and AML/MDS) 
or KPT-8602 (15 mg/kg daily) for 4 weeks. After 4 weeks of treatment, 
mice were killed and bone marrow was isolated from the femurs and tibias 
of 5 − 7 animals from each experimental group. The drug response of mice 
in each experimental group was measured by the percent infiltration 
of hCD45+ cells among the bone marrow leukocytes and total hCD45+ 
cell per femur and tibia. To determine the toxicity of drugs against 
hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs), serial dilutions of hCD34+ cells isolated 
from the bone marrow of femurs and tibias of mice from each 
experimental group after 4 weeks of treatment were transplanted into 
new recipient animals. After 18 − 22 weeks, cohorts of mice transplanted 
with dilutions of hCD45+ cells were analyzed for the presence of hCD45+ 
in the mouse bone marrow, following the same procedures as described 
for secondary transplantation assays for the analysis of LIC frequencies. 
The fractions of mice that demonstrated hCD34+ engraftment per total 
number of animals in each dilution cohort were used to determine the HSC 
frequency by <rs type="software">Extreme Limiting Dilution</rs> software. The following antibodies 
were used for flow cytometric analysis: hCD45, hCD33 (Biolegend, San 
Diego, CA, USA), hCD34 and hCD38 (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Percent and total hCD45+ cells in the bone marrow are presented as 
means ± s.e.m. Differences between experimental groups were determined 
with an unpaired Student's t-test. LIC and HSC frequencies were estimated 
from results of the secondary transplantation assays using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Extreme 
Limiting Dilution</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://bioinf.wehi.edu.au/software/elda/</rs>/). 44 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>KPT-8602 demonstrates anti-leukemic activity in vitro 
We initiated our study of a second-generation XPO1 inhibitor, 
KPT-8602, by examining the effects of KPT-8602 on the viability 
of human AML cell lines in vitro. Dose − response measurements 
of 10 AML lines incubated with KPT-8602 yielded IC 50 values of 
20 − 211 nM after 3 days of exposure, as determined by Cell 
Titer Glo viability assay (Table 1). These data demonstrate that 
KPT-8602 is a potent inhibitor of AML cells in cell-based viability 
assays. For each cell line, the half-maximal inhibitory value (IC 50 ) 
is consistently 30 − 50% lower for KPT-8602 than for selinexor on 
a nanomolar basis, indicating that KPT-8602 is more active than 
the first-generation XPO1 inhibitor, selinexor (Table 1). </p>

<p>Table 1. Anti-leukemia activities of KPT-8602 and selinexor in vitro </p>

<p>AML cell lines 
KPT-8602-IC 50 (nM) 
at 72h </p>

<p>Selinexor-IC 50 (nM) 
at 72h </p>

<p>Ratio </p>

<p>OCI-AML2 
19 
40 
0.48 
MV411 
30 
50 
0.61 
MOLM13 
32 
47 
0.68 
KG1 
66 
151 
0.44 
SKM1 
84 
120 
0.70 
Kasumi-1 
113 
172 
0.65 
OCI-AML3 
127 
154 
0.82 
Mono-MacI 
167 
179 
0.93 
U937 
205 
327 
0.62 
NB4 
211 
304 
0.69 </p>

<p>Abbreviation: IC 50 , 50% inhibitory concentration </p>

<p>XPO1 nuclear export inhibitor, KPT-8602, in AML 
J Etchin et al </p>



<p>Leukemia (2017) 143 -150 </p>

<p>KPT-8602 is highly active against AML blast cells in PDX models 
To determine the activity of KPT-8602 in human AML, we 
employed PDX models in which patient leukemic blast cells were 
transplanted into immunodeficient NOD-SCID-IL2Rcγ null (NSG) 
mice. The three primary AMLs selected for this study were from 
high-risk AML groups: complex karyotype AML (AML-CK), normal 
cytogenetics AML (AML-CN) in which the blast cells harbored 
a FLT3 internal tandem duplication (FLT3-ITD) and MDS-derived 
AML (MDS/AML). 1,45 
For each PDX model of human patient AML, leukemic blast 
cells were injected intravenously into NSG mice and monitored 
for disease progression, as demonstrated by the appearance of 
human CD45+ (hCD45+) cells in peripheral blood. Analysis of the 
extent of hCD45+ cell infiltration in the femur and tibia bones 
extracted from four engrafted animals was used to confirm that 
they harbored a heavy disease burden prior to the start of therapy. 
Once disease burden was established, the mice were split into 
vehicle control, selinexor and KPT-8602 experimental groups, and 
one of the drugs or vehicle was administered by oral gavage 
(Figure 1). At the end of the treatment period, response of the bulk 
AML cells was measured by percent hCD45+ cell infiltration and 
total counts of hCD45+ cells per femur plus tibia in the mice of each 
experimental group (Figure 1). 
KPT-8602 is much better tolerated by mice than selinexor. 
Specifically, selinexor given at 20 mg/kg three times a week for 
4 weeks causes dose-limiting anorexia and weight loss. In contrast, 
KPT-8602 given at 15 mg/kg daily for 4 weeks did not cause 
any weight loss in mice and bacon flavoring was not needed 
to encourage the mice to eat. Analysis of the anti-leukemic activity 
of the drugs demonstrated that although both selinexor and 
KPT-8602 were cytotoxic to leukemic blasts in all PDX models 
tested, KPT-8602 exhibited substantially more profound anti-
leukemic activity in AML-CN and AML-CK PDX mice (Figure 2). 
Specifically, in the AML-CK PDX model, the control mice show 
hCD45+ cell infiltration levels of 91 ± 0.9% of bone marrow 
leukocytes, with total hCD45+ cell counts of 5.3x10 6 ± 0.2x10 6 
per femur and tibia (Figure 2a). Selinexor caused a reduction in 
hCD45+ cell infiltration to 49 ± 8.8% and a 3.5-fold decrease in 
total hCD45+ cell counts to 1.5x10 6 ± 0.4x10 6 . In KPT-8602-treated 
mice, there was a more remarkable decrease in AML blasts, with 
hCD45+ cells accounting for only 7.6 ± 1.0% of bone marrow 
leukocytes and 0.2x10 6 ± 0.05 × 10 6 hCD45+ cells per femur and 
tibia (~27-fold reduction in AML cell numbers; Figure 2a). In the 
AML-CN PDX model, both drugs promoted a leukemic blast </p>

<p>reduction; however, KPT-8602 demonstrated higher anti-leukemic 
activity than selinexor, with no leukemic cells detected in the bone 
marrow of two of the eight AML-CN PDX-treated mice (Figure 2b). 
Taken together, these data demonstrate that KPT-8602 exhibits 
superior anti-leukemic activity and better tolerability in the AML 
PDX models tested, with nearly complete elimination of human 
AML cells in the AML-CN model. </p>

<p>KPT-8602 effectively targets the LICs of PDX models of primary 
AML 
We next examined the effects of KPT-8602 on AML LIC in the three 
PDX models. To determine the frequency of LICs in the vehicle 
control, selinexor or KPT-8602, we used a limiting dilution 
transplantation assay (Experimental Scheme, Figure 3a). Briefly, 
the bone marrow cells from the femurs and tibias of PDX mice 
after the treatment period were analyzed for hCD45+, and the 
cells were retransplanted at serial dilutions by i.v. injection into 
new NSG mice that were then left untreated (Figure 3a). After 
18 − 22 weeks, or earlier if the mice became ill, the recipient 
animals were analyzed for measurable hCD45+ AML cells in the 
mouse bone marrow. The fraction of mice with any detectable 
hCD45+ cells in each transplantation group determined the LIC 
frequency for the vehicle, selinexor and KPT-8602 treatment 
groups for each of the three AML PDX models. 44 The results of the 
limiting dilution transplantation assays clearly show that although 
both selinexor and KPT-8602 effectively target AML LICs, KPT-8602 
is more potent in eliminating LICs, as evidenced by a more 
profound reduction of LIC frequency in the AML-CK and AML-CN 
PDX models (507-fold vs 0.9-fold reduction in AML-CK, P o0.0001; 
and 437-fold vs 111-fold reduction in AML-CN by KPT-8602 vs 
selinexor, P = 0.79) (Figure 3b). In the MDS/AML PDX model, the 
anti-leukemic efficacy against LICs was comparable for both drugs 
(Figure 3b). Thus, KPT-8602 effectively eliminates LICs from high-
risk AML patients. </p>

<p>Selinexor and KPT-8602 greatly extend the survival of PDX mice 
We next assessed if prolonged treatment with selinexor or 
KPT-8602 extends the survival of PDX mice. Briefly, mice engrafted 
with either AML-CK or MDS/AML were treated with vehicle, 
selinexor or KPT-8602 for 4 months or until they became ill. After 
the treatment phase, the mice were monitored for ruffled fur and 
reduced activity and eventually were assessed for hCD45+ 
infiltration in the bone marrow or spleen. AML-CK mice treated </p>

<p>Figure 1. Experimental outline for the analysis of the anti-leukemic activity of KPT-8602 against primary human AML cells. Patient-derived 
xenograft mouse models of human primary AML were used in therapeutic experiments to assess the efficacy of KPT-8602 against AML cells 
isolated from patients with AML-CN, AML-CK and AML/MDS. BM, bone marrow. </p>

<p>XPO1 nuclear export inhibitor, KPT-8602, in AML 
J Etchin et al </p>



<p>Leukemia (2017) 143 -150 </p>

<p>with vehicle succumbed to disease within 1 month of treatment 
(Figure 4a). In this PDX model, selinexor extended survival to 
50 − 60 days from the treatment start. Strikingly, mice treated with 
KPT-8602 were still alive at ~ 140 days after the start of treatment, 
when the experiment was terminated (Figure 4a). Upon post-
mortem analysis, residual hCD45+ cells were detected in the 
mouse spleens but not in the bone marrow. In the MDS/AML 
group, vehicle-treated mice became moribund ~ 40 − 90 days 
from the start treatment, and mice treated with either selinexor or 
KPT-8602 for 17 weeks were alive 29 weeks from the start of 
treatment, when the experiment was terminated. Upon </p>

<p>postmortem analysis, no AML cells were detected in the spleen 
or bone marrow of seven of seven mice treated with selinexor and 
four of seven mice treated with KPT-8602 (P = 0.19 indicating 
similar survival benefit between the selinexor and KPT-8602 
treatment groups). </p>

<p>KPT-8602 is minimally toxic to normal hematopoietic stem and 
progenitor cells 
To define the hematopoietic toxicity of KPT-8602, we engrafted 
NSG mice with human CD34+ (hCD34+) cord blood cells. 
Successful engraftment of human blood cells was documented </p>

<p>AML-CK </p>

<p>Before 
Treatment </p>

<p>Vehicle Selinexor KPT-8602 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Bone marrow infiltration 
(% human CD45+ cells) </p>

<p>Before 
Treatment </p>

<p>Vehicle Selinexor KPT-8602 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>human CD45+ cells (x10^6) 
per femur + tibia </p>

<p>*** 
**** 
** 
** 
**** 
**** </p>

<p>Before 
Treatment </p>

<p>Vehicle Selinexor KPT-8602 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Bone marrow infiltration 
(% human CD45+ cells) </p>

<p>Before 
Treatment </p>

<p>Vehicle Selinexor KPT-8602 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>human CD45+ cells (x10^6) 
per femur + tibia </p>

<p>**** 
**** 
** 
**** 
**** 
* </p>

<p>AML-CN </p>

<p>AML/MDS </p>

<p>Before 
Treatment </p>

<p>Vehicle Selinexor KPT-8602 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Bone marrow infiltration 
(% human CD45+ cells) </p>

<p>Before 
Treatment </p>

<p>Vehicle Selinexor KPT-8602 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>human CD45+ cells (x10^6) 
per femur + tibia </p>

<p>**** 
**** 
**** 
**** </p>

<p>Figure 2. KPT-8602 is highly active against primary AML-CN, AML-CK and AML/MDS cells transplanted into NSG mice. AML cells isolated from 
patients with normal karyotype AML (AML-CN), complex karyotype AML (AML-CK) and AML/MDS were engrafted into NSG mice for 
therapeutic experiments. On the left panel of the figure, percent infiltration of human patient AML (human CD45+) cells in the bone marrow 
of NSG mice before and after treatment with vehicle, selinexor or KPT-8602. On the right panel, counts of human CD45+ cells per femur and 
tibia in mice transplanted with AML cells before treatment and following treatment with vehicle, selinexor or KPT-8602. Each symbol denotes 
a single animal (n = 4 − 8 per group). Error bars represent mean ± s.e.m.; *P o0.05, **Po 0.01, ***Po0.001, ***P o0.0001 by unpaired t-test for 
comparisons between the indicated groups. </p>

<p>XPO1 nuclear export inhibitor, KPT-8602, in AML 
J Etchin et al </p>



<p>Leukemia (2017) 143 -150 </p>

<p>by the presence of 430% hCD45+ cells in the mouse peripheral 
blood. Engrafted mice were dosed orally with vehicle or KPT-8602 
(15 mg/kg) daily for 4 weeks. After treatment, the bone marrows 
of KPT-8602-treated mice had a six-fold reduction in hCD45+ cell 
numbers per femur and tibia compared to vehicle-treated mice 
(Figure 5a). The impact on normal human hematopoietic stem and 
progenitor cell fractions by CD34/CD38 flow analysis and re-
transplantation assays (performed by the same methodology as 
described for PDX models of AML) demonstrates that, in contrast 
to its profound effects against AML LIC, KPT-8602 does not 
preferentially kill normal hematopoietic stem and progenitor 
cells (Figures 5b and c). In future studies of this drug, it will 
be important to further fractionate hematopoietic stem and 
progenitor cells using newly developed markers that distinguish 
functional subsets of these cells. 46 In addition, murine neutrophil </p>

<p>(after 4 weeks of treatment) </p>

<p>Vehicle, Selinexor, or KPT-8602 
Experimental Group </p>

<p>Re-transplantation Assay </p>

<p>10^5 hCD45+ cells 
10^4 hCD45+ cells 
10^3 hCD45+ cells 
10^2 hCD45+ cells </p>

<p>Compare LIC frequencies between experimental groups </p>

<p>Fold Reduction 
in LIC 
Frequency* </p>

<p>LIC 
Frequency </p>

<p>LIC 
Frequency </p>

<p>Fold Reduction 
in LIC 
Frequency* </p>

<p>LIC 
Frequency </p>

<p>Fold Reduction 
in LIC 
Frequency* </p>

<p>Vehicle </p>

<p>1/1155 
1 
1/311 
1 
1/4092 
1 </p>

<p>1/128923 
111-fold 
1/280 
0.9-fold 
&lt;1/771218 </p>

<p>KPT-8602 </p>

<p>1/504215 
437-fold 
1/157733 
507-fold 
&lt;1/681463 
&gt;150-fold </p>

<p>&gt;150-fold </p>

<p>PDX model of AML-CN 
PDX model of AML-CK 
PDX model of MDS/AML </p>

<p>* Fold Reduction in LIC frequency indicates ratio of LIC frequency after drug treatment to LIC frequency after treatment with the vehicle control </p>

<p>Selinexor </p>

<p>Figure 3. KPT-8602 efficiently targets the LICs of three primary AML samples engrafted into NSG mice. (a) Scheme for the limiting dilution 
repopulation assay. After 4 weeks of treatment, bone marrow AML cells isolated from mice treated with either vehicle, selinexor or KPT-8602 
were re-transplanted at serial dilutions into new recipient animals. The number of leukemic mice per total number of animals injected with 
AML cells in secondary recipients was used to determine the LIC frequency in vehicle-and drug-treated AML cell populations. (b) The table 
shows the LIC frequencies in AML-CN, AML-CK and AML/MDS xenografts after treatment with vehicle, selinexor or KPT-8602. The fold 
reduction in LIC frequency in response to drug treatment compared to vehicle controls shows the extent of LIC elimination in response to 
drug therapy. </p>

<p>0 
25 50 75 100 125 150 175 200 225 250 275 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Time from the Injection of AML cells (Days) </p>

<p>Percent Survival </p>

<p>Vehicle </p>

<p>Selinexor </p>

<p>KPT-8602 </p>

<p>Treatment Period 
(4 months) </p>

<p>Leukemia 
Progression </p>

<p>0 
25 50 75 100 125 150 175 200 225 250 275 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Time from the Injection of AML cells (Days) </p>

<p>Percent survival </p>

<p>Vehicle 
Selinexor 
KPT-8602 </p>

<p>Treatment Period 
(4 months) </p>

<p>Leukemia 
Progression </p>

<p>AML-CK </p>

<p>AML/MDS </p>

<p>Figure 4. KPT-8602 greatly extends the survival of AML patient-
derived xenografts (PDXs). Kaplan − Meier curves of PDX models of 
MDS/AML (a) and AML-CK (b) following treatment with vehicle, 
selinexor or KPT-8602. The engrafted mice were allowed to become 
leukemic with circulating AML cells and then treated for 4 months. 
MDS/AML and AML-CK PDX mice were followed for additional 
1 − 3 months to see if regrowth of AML could be prevented or 
delayed by longer treatments. (a) In the AML-CK PDX model, mice 
treated with KPT-8602 were alive at day 253. In these mice, no 
leukemia cells were detected in the bone marrow. (b) In the PDX 
model of MDS/AML, both selinexor-and KPT-8602-treated mice 
were alive at day 252. No leukemia cells were detected in the bone 
marrows of seven out of seven mice treated with selinexor and four 
out of seven mice treated with KPT-8602 (P = 0.19; Fisher's 
exact test). </p>

<p>XPO1 nuclear export inhibitor, KPT-8602, in AML 
J Etchin et al </p>



<p>Leukemia (2017) 143 -150 </p>

<p>and platelet counts and hemoglobin levels were within the 
normal range, as demonstrated in the PDX model of AML/MDS 
(Supplementary Figure 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our study demonstrates the anti-leukemia activity and tolerability 
of KPT-8602, a second-generation drug of the SINE class of XPO1-
mediated nuclear export inhibitors, in PDX models of high-risk 
human AML. Compared to selinexor, the first-generation and 
current clinical lead SINE drug, KPT-8602, exhibits superior efficacy 
against both bulk leukemic blasts and disease-sustaining LICs. 
KPT-8602 is an oral drug suitable for daily administration, and 
thus can easily be incorporated into combination regimens with 
current cytotoxic agents, which do not effectively target LICs, 
or with newer agents. The improved survival of PDX mice after 
prolonged treatment with KPT-8602 demonstrates the curative 
potential of this drug with extended administration. Importantly, 
KPT-8602 had minimal effects on normal hematopoietic stem and 
progenitor cells, suggesting that, like selinexor, it will not induce 
significant hematopoietic toxicity in patients. The preferential 
activity of KPT-8602 against AML cells, including LICs, compared 
to normal hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells implies 
that the former are more dependent for survival on XPO1-
mediated nuclear export of one or more macromolecular cargos. 
XPO1-mediated nuclear export regulates a subset of protein 
and RNA molecules that function in apoptotic signaling and 
cell cycle regulation. The mechanisms that mediate apoptotic </p>

<p>signaling in neoplastic cells but not in normal cells due 
to inhibition of XPO1 activity by KPT-8602 remain to be 
elucidated. 
The improved tolerability of KPT-8602 is likely due to its exclusion 
from the CNS by the blood − brain barrier, and is consistent with 
a central origin of the anorexia and malaise induced by selinexor. 
Because the blood − brain penetration of KPT-8602 relative to 
plasma concentrations was even less in monkeys than in mice, 
we are optimistic that patients treated with this drug will experience 
little to no nausea, anorexia and malaise, adverse effects that 
have been troublesome to a subset of patients receiving selinexor. 
Unlike ALL, CNS infiltration is not a major problem for AML patients, 
and CNS prophylaxis is not routinely given to AML patients 
undergoing treatment. Thus we do not think that the lack of CNS 
penetration will present a problem in terms of the anti-leukemic 
efficacy for AML patients treated with KPT-8602. 
An IND for KPT-8602 was recently approved by the FDA (IND 
Number 126583) and KPT-8602 entered a Phase 1/2 Open-Label 
Study of the Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of the SINE Compound 
KPT-8602 in Patients with Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma in 
January 2016. Our preclinical results indicate that KPT-8602 should 
be tested in clinical trials to determine its toxicity and efficacy in 
patients with advanced relapsed or refractory AML, with the hope 
that it can eventually be integrated into upfront combination 
chemotherapy regimens. Resistance will develop to any single agent 
used to treat AML, but the completely novel mechanism of action of 
KPT-8602 in comparison with currently approved drugs suggests </p>

<p>Normal Human 
CD34+ Grafts </p>

<p>Secondary 
Transplant 
Normal HSC 
frequency </p>

<p>Ratio of HSC Frequency 
in Drug vs. Vehicle Groups </p>

<p>Vehicle 
1/7389 
1 </p>

<p>Selinexor 
1/20496 
2.77 </p>

<p>KPT-8602 
1/6264 
0.85 </p>

<p>Before 
Treatment </p>

<p>Vehicle 
KPT-8602 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>hCD45 cells (x10^6) 
per femur and tibia </p>

<p>Vehicle 
KPT-8602 
Vehicle 
KPT-8602 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>hCD34+ 
hCD34+/hCD38-</p>

<p>% Human Stem and 
Progenitor Cells in BM </p>

<p>*** 
** </p>

<p>**** </p>

<p>6.5X </p>

<p>Figure 5. KPT-8602 spares normal human hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells (HSPCs) engrafted into NSG mice. (a) Human CD45+ 
(hCD45+) cells per femur and tibia in normal human CD34+ grafts before and after treatment with vehicle or KPT-8602 for 4 weeks. 
(b) Percentage of hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells, hCD34+ and hCD34+/CD38 − cells, in the BM of established grafts treated with 
vehicle or KPT-8602. (c) Normal HSC frequencies in grafts treated with vehicle, selinexor or KPT-8602 were obtained from analysis after 
transplantation into untreated secondary recipients. Fold reduction in HSC frequencies of selinexor or KPT-8602-treated grafts compared to 
vehicle-treated grafts. n = 6 − 9 mice per group. Error bars represent mean ± s.e.m.; ***Po0.0001 by Student's t-test for comparison between 
the indicated groups. **Po0.001, ****Po 0.0001. </p>

<p>XPO1 nuclear export inhibitor, KPT-8602, in AML 
J Etchin et al </p>



<p>Leukemia (2017) 143 -150 </p>

<p>that it could be extremely active in combination, by helping to kill 
residual AML LICs that can drive relapse. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>EB, WS, YL, SS and MK are employees of Karyopharm Therapeutics Incorporated and 
receive compensation and hold equity in the company. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We would like to thank Paul Kirschmeier and Prafulla Gokhale of the Lurie Family 
Imaging Center for assistance with the in vivo studies. We would like to thank the 
flow cytometry team led by John Daley and Suzan Lazo for their help with cell analysis. </p>

<p>This research was supported by William Lawrence and Blanche Hughes Foundation 
(ATL), Leukemia and Lymphoma Society's Translational research grant (ATL), Alex's 
Lemonade Young Research Investigator grant (JE), Luck2Tuck Foundation (JE), Claudia 
Adams Barr Innovative Basic Science Research Grant (JE) and Wong Family Award in 
Translational Research (JE). </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>JE designed and performed the experiments, analyzed the data and wrote the 
manuscript. AB performed in vivo mouse studies and analyzed the data. ASC 
performed in vivo mouse experiments. SS designed the KPT-SINE compounds. 
EB designed second-generation SINE, KPT-8602 compound. EB, WS, YL, SS and 
MK provided toxicology results and plasma vs brain measurements in mice and 
monkeys, and participated in the design of in vivo mouse studies and data 
analysis. IAG and RMS provided AML patient samples for this study. JCYW 
provided guidance on limit dilution transplantation studies n PDX models, 
analyzed the results and edited the manuscript. ATL guided the research, 
analyzed the results and wrote the paper. </p>





<p>Leukemia (2017) 143 -150 </p>



<p>© The Author(s) 2017 </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on the Leukemia website (http://www.nature.com/leu) </p>

<p>XPO1 nuclear export inhibitor, KPT-8602, in AML 
J Etchin et al </p>



<p>Leukemia (2017) 143 -150 </p>

</text></tei>