<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5327171" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To investigate the relationships between tear osmolarity and other ocular surface parameters and to </p>

<p>determine the diagnostic value of tear osmolarity in primary Sjögren's syndrome (SS) using tear film break-up 
time, Schirmer I test, and cornea/conjunctiva staining. 
Methods: We included 310 eyes of 155 patients diagnosed with dry eye disease (39 primary SS and 116 non-</p>

<p>Sjögren dry eye disease) at Seoul St. Mary's Hospital from August 2010 to January 2015. All subjects complet-
ed the Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI) questionnaire and underwent ocular examinations including tear 
osmolarity (TearLab Osmolarity System), Schirmer I test, slit lamp examination for tear film break-up time, and 
corneal and conjunctival fluorescein staining. We used the mean value of both eyes for all parameters. Fluo-
rescein staining was assessed using the Sjögren's International Collaborative Clinical Alliance ocular staining 
score (OSS). 
Results: In primary SS patients (n = 39), the mean subject age was 52.5 ± 11.9 years, and 94.9% of the subjects </p>

<p>were women. Mean tear osmolarity in SS was 311.1 ± 16.4 mOsm/L, with 16 (41.0%) subjects having values 
≥316 mOsm/L. In SS, there was a positive correlation between mean tear osmolarity and OSDI score (ρ = 0.405, 
p = 0.011) and OSS (ρ = 0.592, p &lt; 0.001). There was a negative correlation between mean tear osmolarity 
and the Schirmer I test (ρ = -0.625, p &lt; 0.001). There was no significant correlation between mean tear osmo-
larity and tear film break-up time in SS (ρ = 0.110, p = 0.505). 
Conclusions: Tear osmolarity measurements using the TearLab Osmolarity System can reflect both symptom </p>

<p>severity (OSDI) and objective signs (Schirmer test and OSS) in SS. </p>



<p>Korean J Ophthalmol Vol.31, No.1, 2017 </p>

<p>mouth [3]. In addition, systemic features of a cutaneous, 
respiratory, renal, hepatic, neurologic, and vascular nature 
often occur [2,4,5]. Primary SS occurs alone, while sec-
ondary SS occurs in conjunction with another autoimmune 
disease [6,7]. Occasionally, ocular symptoms precede other 
features, but the diagnosis of SS is often delayed owing to 
its ambiguous symptoms. In one study [8], time from the 
first symptom to a diagnosis of SS was a mean of 7 years, 
with considerable psychological distress caused by unex-
plained symptoms during that time. Therefore, early 
non-invasive diagnosis is necessary for SS. 
Several tools are used to evaluate the severity of dry eye 
disease, including tear film break-up time, fluorescein or 
lissamine green staining of the cornea and conjunctiva, 
and the Schirmer test, but these tools are limited by their 
low specificity and interobserver variation [9]. Moreover, 
sometimes these tools have a low correlation with subjec-
tive symptoms. Much effort has been made to find an ideal 
diagnostic tool that is simple, specific, sensitive, objective, 
non-invasive, reproducible, and has a clear cut-off value. In 
recent years, tear osmolarity has been considered a reliable 
diagnostic marker of dry eye disease [10-13]. Further, tech-
nology has become available to measure tear osmolarity in 
the office setting with a microfluidic lab-on-a-chip device 
based on electrical impedance [14]. The TearLab Osmolari-
ty System (TearLab, San Diego, CA, USA) can collect a 
tear sample atraumatically and provides an absolute nu-
meric score. It provides results in a minute, and there is no 
interobserver variation. 
Data on the correlation between tear osmolarity and oth-
er dry eye severity markers is conflicting in the literature. 
Recent studies show that tear osmolarity has a correlation 
with the severity of dry eye in rheumatoid arthritis [15], 
ocular mucous membrane pemphigoid [16], and ocular 
graft-versus-host disease [17]. However, Amparo et al. [18] 
reported that changes in tear osmolarity did not contribute 
to prediction of dry eye symptoms or corneal staining after 
treatment. Further, other authors have reported that the ap-
plicability of TearLab is restricted by low reproducibility 
and wide variation in repeat measurements [12,19,20]. 
In this study, we focused on the correlations between 
tear osmolarity and other ocular surface parameters to fur-
ther analyze the diagnostic value of tear osmolarity in SS. 
Bunya et al. [21] have already investigated the relationship 
between tear osmolarity, the Schirmer I test, and dry eye 
symptoms in SS. However, their study did not include cur-</p>

<p>rently available tools, such as tear film break-up time and 
cornea/conjunctiva staining. Therefore, we included these 
parameters in our study. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This cross-sectional study comprised 310 eyes in 155 pa-
tients. We enrolled 39 patients diagnosed as having prima-
ry SS and 116 with non-Sjögren dry eye disease who were 
matched for age and sex. Inclusion criteria were age over 
20 years and a proven diagnosis of dry eye disease at Seoul 
St. Mary's Hospital from August 2010 to January 2015. SS 
was diagnosed according to the proposed international cri-
teria by American-European Consensus Group (2002) [22] 
and confirmed by both an ophthalmologist and a rheuma-
tologist. 
Exclusion criteria included active ocular inflammation 
or infection not associated with dry eye, drug toxicity, a 
history of ocular surgery or trauma, and wearing of con-
tact lenses. Subjects using systemic medications that could 
interfere with tear production such as diuretics, beta-block-
ers, benzodiazepines, and antihistamines were excluded, 
but patients taking systemic immunosuppressive agents for 
SS were included. Subjects who had used any eye drops in 
the 6 hours before the study were also excluded. 
The study design followed the standards for biomedical 
research laid down in the Declaration of Helsinki, and the 
protocols used were approved by the institutional review 
board of the Catholic University of Korea. 
Demographic information, current systemic or topical 
treatments, and other medical history were recorded. Ocu-
lar examinations including visual acuity, non-contact 
pneumatic tonometry, and anterior segment slit lamp ex-
amination were performed for all subjects. The tests for 
dry eye were performed in the following order: Ocular 
Surface Disease Index (OSDI) questionnaire, tear osmolar-
ity, Schirmer I test, slit lamp examination for tear film 
break-up time, and corneal and conjunctival fluorescein 
staining. We allowed a 5-minute interval between the tests. 
We assessed subjective symptoms using the OSDI ques-
tionnaire, which included 12 questions regarding dry eye 
symptoms during the past week; each symptom was grad-
ed from 0 to 4, for a final score of 0 (mild) to 100 (severe). 
A higher OSDI score represents greater disability. 
Tear osmolarity was evaluated using the TearLab Osmo-</p>



<p>M Kim, et al. Tear Osmolarity in Primary Sjögren's Syndrome </p>

<p>larity System. A 50-nL tear sample was collected from the 
inferior lateral meniscus of each eye, and the mean value 
of both eyes was used for the statistical analysis. Tear os-
molarity ≥316 mOsm/L has been reported to identify dry 
eye disease with high sensitivity, specificity, and predictive 
accuracy [11]. 
A 5-minute Schirmer I test (without anesthesia) was per-
formed before instillation of any eye drops. The standard-
ized Schirmer test strip (Eagle Vision, Memphis, TN, 
USA) was bent and placed at the inferior outer fornix. 
Each patient was instructed to keep his/her eyes closed 
during the test. The length of maximal wetting was mea-
sured after 5 minutes. A Schirmer test value ≤5 mm was 
considered abnormal. 
To measure tear film break-up time, we placed a fluores-
cein-impregnated strip in the lateral part of inferior fornix. 
Each patient was asked to blink, and the time before the 
corneal dry spot appeared in the stained tear film was re-
corded as the tear film break-up time. Tear film break-up 
time ≤5 seconds was considered abnormal. 
Corneal and conjunctival staining was evaluated after 
fluorescein staining under a yellow-barrier filter and cobalt 
blue illumination. Corneal and conjunctival staining was 
graded according to the Sjögren's International Collabora-
tive Clinical Alliance ocular staining score (OSS) [23]. 
All statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> for 
Windows <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 19.0</rs> (IBM Co., Armonk, NY, USA). We </p>

<p>used the mean value of both eyes for all parameters. The 
Mann-Whitney test was used to compare parameters be-
tween the two groups. The Spearman rank-order correla-
tion test was used to evaluate the relationships between 
variables in the patients with Sjögren dry eye disease. A 
p-value &lt;0.05 was considered to be statistically significant 
in all analyses. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Table 1 shows the clinical characteristics of the 155 study 
participants. Their mean age was 52.7 ± 12.0 years, and 148 
(95.5%) were female. Table 1 summarizes the mean (±stan-
dard deviation) values for the ocular surface parameters, 
i.e., OSDI score, tear film break-up time, Schirmer I test, 
tear osmolarity, and OSS. In the Sjögren dry eye group (n 
= 39), mean tear osmolarity in SS was 311.1 ± 16.4 mOsm/ 
L, and 16 measurements (41.0%) were over 316 mOsm/L. 
Mean tear film break-up time was 3.0 ± 2.1 seconds, and 35 
measures (89.7%) were ≤5 mm. The mean Schirmer I test 
value was 5.4 ± 6.9, and 24 measures (61.5%) were ≤5 mm, 
indicating significant dry eye. In the non-Sjögren dry eye 
group (n = 116), mean tear osmolarity was 297.7 ± 12.7 
mOsm/L, and 11 measures (9.5%) were over 316 mOsm/L. 
Mean tear film break-up time was 4.6 ± 1.9 seconds, and 
76 measures (65.5%) were ≤5 mm. The mean Schirmer I </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical characteristics of study participants </p>

<p>Variable 
Sjögren dry eye 
Non-Sjögren dry eye 
p-value 
Participant 
39 
116 
-
Sex 
-
Female 
37 
111 
Male 
2 
5 
Age (yr) 
-
20-30 
2 
4 
31-40 
3 
18 
41-50 
10 
22 
51-60 
13 
39 
&gt;60 
11 
33 
OSDI score 
23.4 ± 18.9 
21.7 ± 10.2 
0.620 
Tear film break-up time (s) 
3.0 ± 2.1 
4.6 ± 1.9 
&lt;0.001 
Schirmer I test (mm) 
5.4 ± 6.9 
6.7 ± 6.5 
0.052 
Tear osmolarity (mOsm/L) 
311.1 ± 16.4 
297.7 ± 12.7 
&lt;0.001 
OSS * 
3.4 ± 2.0 
4.0 ± 1.2 
0.047 </p>

<p>The Mann-Whitney test was used to compare parameters between the two groups. Values are presented as the mean ± standard deviation. 
OSDI = Ocular Surface Disease Index; OSS = ocular staining score. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>By Sjögren's International Collaborative Clinical Alliance [23]. </p>



<p>Korean J Ophthalmol Vol.31, No.1, 2017 </p>

<p>test value was 6.7 ± 6.5, and 61 measures (52.6%) were ≤5 
mm. Tear osmolarity value and OSS were higher in the 
Sjögren dry eye group. In contrast, the tear film break-up 
time value was higher in the non-Sjögren dry eye group. 
The scatter plots in Fig. 1 show correlations between tear 
osmolarity and other ocular surface parameters in the 
Sjögren dry eye group. There was a statistically significant 
positive correlation between mean tear osmolarity and 
OSDI score (ρ = 0.405, p = 0.011) and OSS (ρ = 0.592, p &lt; 
0.001). There was also a statistically significant negative 
correlation between mean tear osmolarity and the Schirm-
er I test (ρ = -0.625, p &lt; 0.001). However, there was no sig-
nificant correlation between mean tear osmolarity and tear 
film break-up time (ρ = 0.110, p = 0.505). 
In the non-Sjögren dry eye group, there were no signifi-</p>

<p>cant correlation between mean tear osmolarity and OSDI 
score (ρ = 0.101, p = 0.279), Schirmer I test (ρ = 0.119, p = 
0.205), tear film break-up time (ρ = 0.133, p = 0.165), or 
OSS (ρ = 0.145, p = 0.119). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The dry eye disease associated with SS is multifactorial 
in nature but is mainly aqueous deficient-type. In 2002, a 
revised international classification of SS was established 
by the American-European Consensus Group [22]. The 
criteria used include two objective measures of ocular in-
volvement, i.e., a Schirmer I test result ≤5 mm in 5 minutes 
and a Rose Bengal or other ocular dye score ≥4 according </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Scatter plot showing significant correlations between Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI) score and average tear film osmolarity (ρ 
= 0.405, p = 0.011), average Schirmer I test and average tear film osmolarity (ρ = -0.625, p &lt; 0.001), and average ocular staining score (OSS) 
and average tear film osmolarity (ρ = 0.592, p &lt; 0.001). The Spearman rank-order correlation test was used to evaluate the relationship 
between variables. OSS was by Sjögren's International Collaborative Clinical Alliance [23]. </p>

<p>Tear osmolarity (mOsm/L) 
280 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Schirmer I test (mm) </p>

<p>300 
320 
340 </p>

<p>rho = -0.625 
(p &lt; 0.001) </p>

<p>280 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Tear osmolarity (mOsm/L) </p>

<p>OSDI score </p>

<p>300 
320 
340 </p>

<p>rho = 0.405 
(p = 0.011) </p>

<p>280 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Tear osmolarity (mOsm/L) 
Tear film break-up time (s) </p>

<p>300 
320 
340 </p>

<p>rho = 0.110 
(p = 0.505) </p>

<p>280 </p>

<p>8.0 </p>

<p>6.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Tear osmolarity (mOsm/L) </p>

<p>OSS score </p>

<p>300 
320 
340 </p>

<p>rho = 0.592 
(p &lt; 0.001) </p>



<p>M Kim, et al. Tear Osmolarity in Primary Sjögren's Syndrome </p>

<p>to van Bijsterveld's scoring system. The Schirmer I test 
represents the tear production rate and remains the main-
stay of diagnosis. However, this test has some drawbacks 
with regard to interpretation of results in the event of re-
flex tearing, and the test strip induces irritation in patients 
with dry eye. Aside from the Schirmer I test, tear film os-
mometers are becoming popular for diagnosing dry eye. 
Until recently, quantification of inflammatory cytokines 
was limited to the research setting because of logistic 
problems such as the need for laboratory equipment and 
evaporation of tear samples in transit. In 2009, the TearLab 
Osmolarity System was approved by the U.S. Food and 
Drug Administration for assessment of dry eye. This sys-
tem has several strengths over other clinical tools. The 
purpose of our study was to identify correlations between 
tear osmolarity and other ocular surface parameters in SS. 
Comparing our Sjögren dry eye and non-Sjögren dry 
eye groups, tear film break-up time ( p &lt; 0.001) and 
Schirmer I test ( p = 0.052, no statistical significance) 
turned out to be worse in the Sjögren dry eye group. These 
results suggest that dry eye associated with SS is generally 
more severe than in non-Sjögren dry eye. 
In our patient population with SS, there was a positive 
correlation between tear osmolarity and OSDI score and 
OSS and a negative correlation between tear osmolarity 
and the results of the Schirmer I test. This finding is con-
sistent with the results reported by Utine et al. [24] who 
found a positive correlation between tear osmolarity and 
OSDI score and a negative correlation between tear osmo-
larity and the results of the Schirmer test with anesthesia. 
In contrast, Bunya et al. [21] found that a higher tear osmo-
larity was associated with lower scores on the OSDI ques-
tionnaire in SS patients. They hypothesized that the worse 
was the dry eye disease, the less sensitive was the cornea. 
In our patient population, the OSDI score was not signifi-
cantly affected (mean, 23.4 ± 18.9). These results suggest 
that the OSDI score is not necessarily proportional to the 
severity of dry eye disease [25,26]. 
Interestingly, we found no correlation between tear os-
molarity and tear film break-up time in SS patients. One 
possible explanation for this is the subjective nature of the 
tear film break-up time test. Another explanation is that 
tear film hyperosmolarity in SS can be mainly induced by 
increased release of inflammatory cytokines into the tear 
film instead of a decreased tear volume because osmolarity 
is defined as the amount of osmotically active solutes (os-</p>

<p>moles) present in 1 L of solution [27]. Further, an impact 
on this result is incidental because, as shown in the revised 
international classification for Sjögren's syndrome (2002), 
the Schirmer test and corneal staining score are more im-
portant than tear film break-up time when diagnosing SS. 
Tomlinson et al. [11] undertook a meta-analysis to deter-
mine the cut-off value for diagnosing dry eye disease; they 
proposed a cut-off of ≥316 mOsm/L (with a sensitivity of 
69% and specificity of 92%) for diagnosis of dry eye. In 
contrast, Szalai et al. [28] and Messmer et al. [29] have 
demonstrated that tear film osmolarity lacks the ability to 
distinguish between patients with and without dry eye. In 
our study population, mean tear osmolarity in the patients 
with SS was 311.1 ± 16.4 mOsm/L; in 16 patients (41%), this 
value was over 316 mOsm/L. To the best of our knowledge, 
there is no suggested cut-off value for SS-related dry eye 
disease. Tear osmolarity can be affected by a number of 
environmental factors, including air f low, humidity, the 
patient's general state of health, systemic medication, and 
seasonal or diurnal variation. Further, some authors have 
shown that a tear sample taken from the meniscus may 
underestimate tears over the surface of the eye, especially 
in patients with dry eye disease [30]. Further investigations 
should be conducted to establish a cut-off value in consid-
eration of the various factors affecting tear osmolarity. 
Our study has some limitations. First, the results may be 
confounded by a lack of data on relevant variables, such as 
systemic medications and the effects of environmental 
factors on measurements. Although the effect of systemic 
medication on tear film stability remains unclear, a previ-
ous study concluded that systemic anti-inf lammatory 
treatment did not significantly affect tear osmolarity or 
OSDI score in patients with SS [21]. Second, the current 
study did not evaluate repeat measurements in the partici-
pants. Bunya et al. [20] found a high degree of variability 
for tear osmolarity measured by the TearLab Osmolarity 
System; there was an error associated with repeat mea-
surements during one session in the patients with SS. 
Third, we found no correlation between tear osmolarity 
and other ocular surface parameters in non-Sjögren dry 
eye group. We suppose the reason is that non-Sjögren dry 
eye is multifactorial disease, although additional study is 
needed to answer this question. Finally, the present study 
was limited by the lack of inclusion of a control (non-dry 
eye disease) cohort, so it was not possible to evaluate nor-
mal variations. However, a major strength is that we evalu-</p>



<p>Korean J Ophthalmol Vol.31, No.1, 2017 </p>

<p>ated almost all of the conventional tests for dry eye dis-
ease. 
In summary, our study demonstrates that tear osmolari-
ty can reflect both symptom severity (OSDI score) and ob-
jective signs such as the Schirmer test and OSS. In clinical 
practice, tear osmolarity can have a central role in screen-
ing and diagnosing dry eye disease in patients with SS. 
Further large-scale investigations should be performed to 
evaluate whether tear osmolarity is of value in tracking the 
therapeutic response and for setting a cut-off value specific 
for SS-related dry eye disease. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>





<p>M Kim, et al. Tear Osmolarity in Primary Sjögren's Syndrome </p>



</text></tei>