<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5458115" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Adipose stromal cells (ASCs) have been identified as a mesen-
chymal cell population recruited from white adipose tissue 
(WAT) by tumors and supporting cancer progression. We 
have previously reported the existence of a non-glycanated 
decorin isoform (ngDCN) marking mouse ASCs. We identified 
a peptide CSWKYWFGEC that binds to ngDCN and hence 
can serve as a vehicle for ASC-directed therapy delivery. We 
used hunter-killer peptides composed of CSWKYWFGEC 
and a pro-apoptotic moiety to deplete ASCs and suppress 
growth of mouse tumors. Here, we report the discovery of 
the human non-glycanated decorin isoform. We show that 
CSWKYWFGEC can be used as a probe to identify ASCs in 
human WAT and tumors. We demonstrate that human 
ngDCN is expressed on ASC surface. Finally, we validate 
ngDCN as a molecular target for pharmacological depletion 
of human ASCs with hunter-killer peptides. We propose that 
ngDCN-targeting agents could be developed for obesity and 
cancer treatment. </p>

<p>There is an urgent need to identify novel anti-cancer druggable targets 
and therapies. Our previous studies have elucidated the role of tumor 
stromal cells derived from white adipose tissue (WAT), which con-
tains large numbers of adipose stromal cells (ASCs), the mesenchymal 
stromal cell (MSC) population expanded in obesity. 
1-5 We have 
shown that WAT contributes to the pool of tumor stromal cells </p>

<p>6,7 </p>

<p>in both mice 
5 and patients. 
8,9 There is accumulating evidence that </p>

<p>WAT surrounding the tumor is a key source of tumor stroma and 
that adenocarcinoma growth and progression is associated with infil-
tration of ASCs derived from WAT. Our recent study has identified 
ASCs recruitment by tumors as the mechanism through which 
WAT promotes cancer progression and link ASCs recruitment with 
poor patient survival. 
2 In animal studies, administered ASCs engraft 
tumors, which results in accelerated cancer progression. 
3-5 Our find-
ings confirmed by data from other groups 
10-14 demonstrate tumor 
recruitment of endogenous ASCs and indicate that ASCs promote 
survival and proliferation of neighboring malignant cells. The 
apparent contribution of ASCs to the tumor microenvironment has </p>

<p>raised a question regarding the safety of lipotransfer procedures in 
cancer patients. 
15-17 There is also emerging evidence that ASCs </p>

<p>contribute to therapy resistance of various cancers. </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>We and others have discovered that ASCs can be identified as cells pos-
itive for mesenchymal markers and CD34 while negative for endothe-
lial (CD31) and hematopoietic (CD45) markers. 
20,21 We had originally 
reported platelet-derived growth factor receptor-alpha (PDGFRa) and 
PDGFR-beta (PDGFRb), also known as CD140a and CD140b, as 
mesenchymal markers expressed on human ASCs. 
21 Subsequently, </p>

<p>PDGFRa and PDGFRb have been validated as adipocyte progenitors 
in mice by lineage tracing. 
22-24 We have shown that stromal cells ex-</p>

<p>pressing either PDGFRa or PDGFRb are recruited by tumors in mouse 
models. 
25 However, both PDGFRa and PDGFRb, as well as other </p>

<p>mesenchymal markers, are expressed on various cell populations in 
different organs. Therefore, they cannot serve as specific markers of 
ASCs, and the lack of molecules expressed on ASCs, but not on other 
MSCs, has impeded the progress in the field. We previously reported 
that DDCN, a truncated isoform of matricellular proteoglycan decorin 
(DCN), is expressed on the surface of mouse ASCs. 
26 This isoform lacks 
the N-terminal segment and is free of the glycosaminoglycan chain. A 
cyclic peptide with the sequence CSWKYWFGEC (termed WAT7) iso-
lated from a combinatorial peptide library based on its ASC homing 
was shown to bind DDCN. 
26 Whereas full-length DCN, expressed in </p>

<p>many organs, is exported extracellularly to crosslink collagen, the 
non-glycanated isoform, DDCN, is generated in WAT and is exposed 
on ASC surface. We showed that CSWKYWFGEC is specific for ASCs 
and does not recognize MSCs in other organs. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>Based on the ability of CSWKYWFGEC to undergo ASC internaliza-
tion, 
26 by analogy with our previous studies, 
27 we designed a 
bimodal peptide D-WAT composed of CSWKYWFGEC and of the </p>

<p>Received 27 January 2017; accepted 10 May 2017; 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.omto.2017.05.003. </p>

<p>Correspondence: Mikhail G. Kolonin, The Brown Foundation Institute of Mo-
lecular Medicine, University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston, 1825 
Pressler Street, Room 630-G, Houston, TX 77030, USA. 
E-mail: mikhail.g.kolonin@uth.tmc.edu </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 ª 2017 The Authors. 
1 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>KLAKLAKKLAKLAK domain linked via aminohexanoic acid. To 
circumvent the problem of short half-life of peptides in vivo due to 
proteolytic degradation, D-WAT is synthesized with all amino acids 
as D-enantiomers, which are not recognized by proteases and the im-
mune system. 
28 D-WAT has a dose-dependent and specific cytotox-
icity toward ASCs adherent in culture, whereas other cell types were 
not affected. 
25,29 In vivo, using flow cytometry and immunofluores-
cence (IF), we demonstrated depletion of ASCs, but not of MSCs, 
in other organs. In the mouse model, ASC depletion expectedly re-
sulted in WAT growth suppression and adipose tissue browning. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>Recently, we reported that targeting ASCs via DDCN also suppresses 
tumor growth. 
25 In that report, we demonstrated that D-WAT treat-</p>

<p>ment specifically depletes tumor stromal and perivascular cells 
without directly killing malignant cells or tumor-infiltrating leuko-
cytes. ASC cytoablation reduced tumor vascularity and cell prolifera-
tion, hence causing hemorrhaging, necrosis, and tumor growth 
suppression in several mouse carcinoma models. We also validated 
a D-WAT derivative with a pro-apoptotic domain KFAKFAK 2 that 
had higher cytoablative activity. </p>

<p>Whereas our previous studies have demonstrated that ASCs can serve 
as a drug target in mouse models, the clinical relevance of the discov-
ery of CSWKYWFGEC peptide and DDCN has been unclear. Because </p>

<p>DCN is evolutionary conserved, 
26 we investigated whether there is a </p>

<p>human isoform serving as an ASC marker. Here, we present data 
revealing the expression of non-glycanated (ngDCN) fragment of hu-
man DCN, an equivalent of DDCN, on both subcutaneous (s.c.) and 
intraperitoneal (i.p.) visceral ASCs. We show that CSWKYWFGEC 
can be used as a probe to identify ASCs not only in mouse but also 
in human WAT and tumors. Finally, we show that human ngDCN 
is also targeted by CSWKYWFGEC-directed hunter-killer peptides, 
thus enabling depletion of human PDGFRb 
+ ASCs. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Peptide CSWKYWFGEC as a Probe to Identify ASCs in Tissue 
Sections </p>

<p>To investigate whether a DCN isoform recognized by 
CSWKYWFGEC exists in humans, we tested whether this peptide 
can serve as a probe similar to an antibody. As a proof of principle, 
we tested this approach to identify ASCs in mouse paraffin tissue 
sections using CSWKYWFGEC peptide. Deparaffinized sections 
were incubated with biotinylated CSWKYWFGEC and subsequently 
with a streptavidin-fluorophore conjugate. As shown in Figure 1A, 
the peptide bound to PDGFRb-expressing cells in WAT, as expected. 
Importantly, by incubating the peptide with sections of RM1 adeno-
carcinoma tumors grown in mice, we demonstrated that it binds to a </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>PBS 
D-WAT </p>

<p>CSWKYWFGEC </p>

<p>pprobe+ cells, % </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Figure 1. CSWKYWFGEC Peptide Probe Identifies ASC in Mouse WAT and Tumors 
Prostate adenocarcinoma RM1 allografts grown in immunocompetent mice treated with PBS (A and C) or ASC-targeting peptide D-WAT (B and D). WAT (A and B) and tumor 
(C and D) sections were incubated with biotinylated ASC-binding peptide CSWKYWFGEC and then subjected to immunofluorescence with antibodies specific for mouse 
PDGFRb (red) to localize ASCs and with streptavidin (green) to localize the CSWKYWFGEC peptide. Note CSWKYWFGEC signal on PDGFRb-expressing ASCs in control 
WAT and tumors is shown (arrows). Nuclei are blue. The scale bar represents 50 mm. (E) Quantification of data from (A)-(D) shows that the frequency of CSWKYWFGEC-
bound cells in WAT and tumor capsule is reduced upon D-WAT peptide treatment. Plotted are mean ± SEM for multiple fields (n = 10). *p &lt; 0.01 (Student's t test). Ex-
periments were performed twice with similar results. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics </p>

<p> 
Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 </p>

<p>sub-population of cells in tumor stroma (Figure 1C). This indicates 
that some of the tumor-recruited ASCs may serve as a direct target 
of CSWKYWFGEC-directed hunter-killer peptides. To validate pep-
tide specificity, we incubated it with tissues from mice treated with an 
ASC-targeted hunter-killer peptide WAT7-KFAKFAK 2 (here termed 
D-CAN), which we reported previously. 
25 As expected, the frequency </p>

<p>of cells bound with CSWKYWFGEC and expressing PDGFRb 
was dramatically reduced after D-WAT treatment (Figures 1B-1E). 
This indicates that peptide CSWKYWFGEC specifically identifies 
DDCN-expressing cells in IF applications. </p>

<p>Human ASCs Express Non-glycanated DCN Recognized by 
CSWKYWFGEC </p>

<p>Comparison of mouse and human DCN amino termini revealed the 
high ortholog similarity. Specifically, the positions of cysteines form-
ing disulfide bonds downstream of the glycanation site and the site of 
mouse DCN cleavage resulting in DDCN showing disulfide bonds 
and the cleavage site in mouse DCN were conserved (Figure 2A). 
Based on that, we predicted that cleavage of human DCN may 
take place. To test this directly, we extracted proteins from ASCs 
derived from s.c. and i.p. WAT of three bariatric surgery patients. 
Membrane proteins were incubated with CSWKYWFGEC-conju-
gated beads or deactivated unloaded beads as a negative control. 
After washing, eluted proteins were subjected to immunoblotting 
with anti-human decorin antibodies. This revealed the presence of 
the core DCN band and a smaller band corresponding in size to 
DDCN specifically pulled down with CSWKYWFGEC (Figure 2B). 
Expression of the two DCN isoforms was confirmed for both s.c. 
and i.p. of different patients analyzed (Figure S1A). We also per-</p>

<p>formed immunoblotting with anti-human DCN antibodies directly 
on ASC extracts. Each of the two ngDCN forms was more abundant 
than glycanated DCN (Figure 2C). Human breast cancer cell line 
MDA-MB-231 used as a negative control was analyzed in parallel. 
There was no non-glycanated DCN bands observed in proteins 
extracted from MDA-MB-231 cells (Figure 2C). Non-glycanated 
DCN was also undetectable in other human cell lines, including 
PC3 and DU145 prostate adenocarcinoma, HepG2 liver adenocarci-
noma, and HEK293 embryonic kidney cells (Figures S1A and S1B). 
This indicates that, like in mice, human ngDCN is selectively ex-
pressed by ASCs. </p>

<p>CSWKYWFGEC Peptide as a Probe Binding Human ASCs </p>

<p>We then tested whether peptide CSWKYWFGEC can specifically 
identify mouse and human ngDCN in IF applications. First, we 
demonstrated peptide binding specificity by comparing wild-type 
(WT) and DCN-null mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs). 
30 Cells </p>

<p>growing in culture were incubated with biotinylated CSWKYWFGEC 
and then with streptavidin-Cy3 conjugate. Upon washing, notably 
higher binding of CSWKYWFGEC to WT MEFs was observed, 
whereas a control peptide CWLGEWLGC mimicking the b1 integ-
rin-interacting protein SPARC 
31 displayed no selectivity (Figure S1C). 
We then compared peptide binding to human ASCs and PC3 prostate 
adenocarcinoma cells used as a negative control. CSWKYWFGEC 
bound to the surface of ASC, whereas signal on PC3 cells was very 
low (Figure 3A). We preformed the same experiment with a scram-
bled peptide CWWGSFYEKC and an unrelated brown fat-homing 
peptide (BAT8) reported previously. 
32 The two biotinylated control </p>

<p>peptides did not bind to human ASCs (Figure 3A), confirming that </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Figure 2. Human ASCs Express Non-glycanated DCN that Binds to CSWKYWFGEC 
(A) A fragment of mouse and human DCN showing disulfide bonds and the cleavage site in mouse DCN. N-terminal and C-terminal sequences, as well as sequence 
downstream of GAG attachment site, are abbreviated (.). (B) Membrane proteins extracted from s.c. ASCs of a bariatric surgery patient 1 were incubated with 
CSWKYWFGEC-conjugated beads or control deactivated unconjugated beads. After washing, eluted proteins were subjected to immunoblotting with anti-human decorin 
antibodies. (C) Proteins extracted from s.c. ASCs of a bariatric surgery patient 2 and human breast adenocarcinoma cells (MDA-MB-231) were subjected to immunoblotting 
with anti-human decorin antibodies. Arrow points to the band doublet, where the upper band is the core decorin. ] indicates glycanated decorin. Experiments were performed 
for i.p. and s.c. WAT of three patients with similar results. </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 </p>

<p>
CSWKYWFGEC binding is specific. We also generated DCN-null 
human ASCs using the CRISPR/Cas9 approach to demonstrate 
that CSWKYWFGEC binding is contingent on DCN expression (Fig-
ure 3B). Indeed, biotinylated CSWKYWFGEC bound to unmodified 
ASCs, whereas the signal on DCN-knockout (KO) ASCs was dramat-
ically reduced (Figure 3C). Furthermore, we used CSWKYWFGEC 
peptide as a probe on paraffin sections of human tissues. An array 
of human organs was analyzed. Strikingly, CSWKYWFGEC showed 
binding to stromal cells in both s.c. WAT (Figure 4A) and peripro-
static i.p. WAT (Figure S2A), whereas the scrambled peptide (Fig-
ure 4B) or a control peptide BAT8 (Figure S2B) did not bind to cells 
of WAT. Importantly, CSWKYWFGEC displayed no binding to cells 
of lung (Figure 4C) or other control organs, including spleen, heart, 
skeletal muscle, pancreas, kidney, liver, and brain (Figure S2A). 
We also analyzed peptide binding to human breast cancer tissues. 
CSWKYWFGEC bound to stroma in WAT surrounding the tumor 
as well as to tumor stromal cells (Figure 4D). CSWKYWFGEC bind-
ing to tumor stromal cells was observed for different cancer subtypes 
and grades (Figure S3). </p>

<p>Human ASC Targeting with a Hunter-Killer Peptide </p>

<p>Next, we tested whether ngDCN-homing hunter killer peptides could 
be used for human ASC ablation. We incubated human ASCs and 
control cells with increasing concentrations of peptide D-CAN that 
has been shown to kill mouse ASCs. 
25 Trypan blue exclusion assay 
was used to assess cell death. At the concentration of 0.05 mM, pre-
viously reported effective for mouse ASC, 
25,29 D-CAN also killed 
$50% of human ASCs (Figure 5A). Importantly, control human 
cell lines were not killed by D-CAN at the concentration lethal for </p>

<p>Figure 3. CSWKYWFGEC Binds to ngDCN on Human 
ASC Surface 
(A) Live human ASCs from s.c. WAT of a bariatric surgery 
patient 1 and prostate adenocarcinoma cells (PC3) cells 
were incubated with 20 nM biotinylated CSWKYWFGEC, 
a scrambled peptide CWWGSFYEKC, or a control bio-
tinylated peptide (BAT8). After incubation in 10% FBS/ 
DMEM media for 2 hr, washing, and fixation, cells were 
incubated with streptavidin-Cy3 and stained with DAPI. 
Plotted are mean ± SEM for multiple fields (n = 10). *p &lt; 
0.01 (Student's t test). (B) Anti-DCN immunoblotting on 
protein extracts from human ASCs in which DCN was 
deleted (KO) and wild-type parental ASCs (WT) used as 
control. b-tubulin, loading control. (C) Live human DCN 
null and control ASCs were incubated with 20 nM bio-
tinylated CSWKYWFGEC. After incubation in 10% FBS/ 
DMEM media for 2 hr, washing, and fixation, cells were 
incubated with streptavidin-Cy3 and stained with DAPI. 
Nuclei are blue. The scale bar represents 50 mm. Plotted 
are mean ± SEM for multiple fields (n = 10). *p &lt; 0.01 
(Student's t test). Experiments were performed for i.p. and 
s.c. WAT of three patients with similar results. </p>

<p>ASCs (Figure 5A). Both subcutaneous and 
visceral ASCs from three different patients 
were confirmed to be sensitive to D-CAN treat-
ment (Figure S4A). Untargeted pro-apoptotic domain did not cause 
cell death at that concentration and killed cells only nonspecifically 
starting at 1 mM (Figure S4B). Importantly, by using human DCN-
null ASCs (Figure 3B), we showed that D-CAN kills only cells that ex-
press DCN (Figure 5B). Finally, we tested whether CSWKYWFGEC 
peptide kills a sub-population of human ASCs with a selectivity re-
ported in mice. 
25,29 By analyzing sections derived from bariatric sur-</p>

<p>gery patients, we discovered that human WAT contains PDGFRa </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>PDGFRb 
À ASCs in the stroma and PDGFRa 
À PDGFRb 
+ ASCs in </p>

<p>close association with the blood vessel lumen (Figure 6A). Thus, hu-
man WAT has two sub-populations of ASCs that we previously re-
ported in mice. 
29 Like in mice, D-WAT peptide killed some, but 
not all, human ASCs in cell culture, as revealed by trypan blue stain-
ing (Figure 6B). To identify the sensitive ASC sub-population, we 
performed IF with PDGFRa and PDGFRb antibodies while also 
immuno-detecting cleaved caspase 3 (a marker of apoptosis). Coloc-
alization studies clearly showed that D-WAT induced apoptosis of 
PDGFRb 
+ , but not of PDGFRa 
+ , ASCs. We conclude that, like in </p>

<p>mice, ngDCN is selectively expressed on PDGFRa 
À PDGFRb 
+ ASCs </p>

<p>that can be targeted with CSWKYWFGEC-directed hunter killer 
peptides. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>New molecular therapeutics are awaited to effectively suppress can-
cer aggressiveness and progression to metastatic stage. Inability of 
available drugs to overcome the resistance of cancer to treatment in-
dicates the existence of untargeted cell populations driving the dis-
ease. Growth and metastasis of solid tumors relies on the tumor 
stroma, the infiltrating non-malignant fibroblastoid cells. 
1,33 Disease </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics </p>

<p> 
Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 </p>

<p>progression is driven by these stromal cells 
1 that secrete trophic fac-</p>

<p>tors 
34-36 and mediate the desmoplastic deposition of extracellular 
matrix (ECM), tumor vascularization, and the epithelial-mesen-
chymal transition (EMT) enabling metastatic capacity. 
37 Tumor 
stroma also mutes anti-cancer immune response. 
38-42 Progression 
of many types of cancer is promoted by obesity, hallmark of which 
is WAT overgrowth and high BMI. 
2,16,43 The mechanisms underly-
ing increased risk of cancer mortality in obese patients remain 
unclear. Whereas diet 
44 and the metabolic syndrome 
45 appear to </p>

<p>underlie cancer initiation, different mechanisms account for the ef-
fect of obesity on cancer progression. A growing body of evidence 
indicates that the key determinant of cancer progression in obesity 
is WAT. 
43,46 Consistent with that observation, breast cancer survi-
vors that undergo WAT transplantation for breast augmentation 
have a higher chance of relapse, as we have reported. 
15-17 Factors 
secreted by ASCs, adipocytes, and infiltrating leukocytes, collectively 
called adipokines, have been considered as the mechanistic link 
between obesity and cancer. 
47 ASCs also secrete MCP-1 and 
other chemokines recruiting macrophages 
48 that accumulate in 
the crown-like structures associated with breast cancer risk and 
progression. </p>

<p>49,50 </p>

<p>At present, there are no therapies aimed at ASCs available due to the 
lack of validated molecular targets specific for these cells. Previously, 
we reported non-glycanated DDCN as the marker of ASC differenti-
ating into white adipocytes in mice. 
29 Here, we demonstrate that </p>

<p>human ASC express also non-glycanated DCN recognized by 
CSWKYWFGEC peptide. We show that this peptide can be used as 
an imaging probe or a vehicle directing cytotoxic therapeutics to 
ASCs and enabling their targeted depletion. We had previously 
reported that, in mice, ngDCN-homing hunter killer peptides 
D-WAT and D-CAN target PDGFRa-negative/PDGFRb-positive 
ASCs serving as progenitors of white adipocytes, whereas they spare 
the PDGFRa-positive/PDGFRb-negative brown/beige adipocyte pro-
genitors. 
25,29 Our data presented here indicate that both D-WAT and </p>

<p>D-CAN also target human ASCs with comparable selectivity. As we 
had demonstrated in animal studies, ASCs with higher PDGFRa/ 
lower PDGFRb signaling give rise to beige adipocytes, whereas 
ASCs with higher PDGFRb/lower PDGFRa signaling give rise to 
white adipocytes. It remains to be determined whether ngDCN spe-
cifically marks white adipocyte progenitor cells in humans. </p>

<p>Decorin is a ubiquitously expressed proteoglycan secreted into the 
extracellular matrix molecules. Its main function is modulation of fi-
brillogenesis through interaction with collagens and fibronectin. </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>Based on the DCN cleavage site resulting in DDCN, we have pre-
dicted that it is generated post-translationally. 
26 The protease gener-</p>

<p>ating DDCN remains to be identified. Our data showing that ngDCN 
added to cell culture medium binds to human ASCs (Figure S5) sug-
gest that proteolysis occurs extracellularly. The function of ngDCN 
remains to be determined. Both DCN and ngDCN have been re-
ported to suppress adipogenesis; 
26 however, the mechanism of their 
effects on specific pre-adipocyte lineages has not been analyzed. It 
has been shown that DCN suppresses PDGFR signaling by inter-
fering with PDGF activity. 
52 In mice, PDGFRa 
À PDGFRb 
+ ASCs 
are perivascular/mural cells, whereas the PDGFRa 
+ PDGFRb 
À cells </p>

<p>are localized deeper in the stroma. 
29 Our data demonstrate that, </p>

<p>in human WAT, the two corresponding stromal populations exist 
and have the same relative perivascular localization. It is possible 
that DCN and ngDCN regulate adipogenesis by suppressing 
signaling specifically through PDGFRa or PDGFRb. The function 
of DCN and ngDCN interactors, including PDGFs, transforming 
growth factor b (TGF-b), and resistin, which serves as a DDCN re-
ceptor in WAT, 
26,51 in modulating ASC fate remains to be tested. 
Studies in mouse models provide evidence that DCN suppresses 
PDGFRa signaling in liver cancer. 
52 Establishing how DCN and 
ngDCN modulates PDGFRa and PDGFRb signaling in the context 
of white and brown adipose tissue, tumors, and other fibrotic condi-
tions may delineate new approaches to disease prevention and 
treatment. </p>

<p>In summary, this study identifies a cell surface marker through which 
human ASCs can be identified and depleted. We propose that devel-
opment of drugs targeting human ASCs can lead to improved combi-
nation therapies complementing conventional cancer treatments in 
cancer patients. </p>

<p>Figure 4. CSWKYWFGEC as a Probe to Identify ASCs in Human WAT and 
Tumors 
Paraffin sections of indicated human tissues were incubated with biotinylated 
CSWKYWFGEC peptide or a scrambled peptide CWWGSFYEKC and subjected 
to IF with antibodies against CD31 (green) and streptavidin (red). Note that the 
scrambled peptide does not bind to WAT (B), whereas CSWKYWFGEC-bound cells 
are observed in s.c. WAT (A) and tumor stroma (D), but not in the lung (C). Nuclei are 
blue. The scale bar represents 50 mm. Experiments were performed for WAT of 
three patients with similar results. </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 </p>

<p>
MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Human Subjects </p>

<p>The clinical protocol was approved by the institutional review board 
(IRB) (protocol HSC-MS-14-0514). For ASC isolation, samples of 
subcutaneous and omental WAT from three de-identified patients 
undergoing bariatric surgery (coded as patients 1, 2, and 3) were 
used with similar results. Paraffin sections analyzed were from 
WAT of patients 1-3 and from 12 additional patients. Paraffin sec-
tions of eight control normal tissues were from human adult multi-
tissue panel-I T8234431 (BioChain). Paraffin sections were from 
the three breast cancer patients (invasive ductal carcinoma [IDC] 
grade 3 estrogen receptor [ER] 
+ progesterone receptor[PR] 
À stage 3 </p>

<p>breast cancer, ductal carcinoma in situ [DCIS] grade 3 ER 
À PR 
À stage </p>

<p>0 breast cancer, and IDC grade 2 ER 
+ PR 
+ stage 1 breast cancer) 
enrolled at MD Anderson Cancer Center and from periprostatic 
WAT specimens described previously. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Experimental Animals </p>

<p>Animal studies were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and 
Use Committee of UTHealth. C57BL/6 mice were from Jackson Lab-
oratory. For RM1 tumor cell grafting, 1 Â 10 
5 cells were injected with 
a 21-gauge needle s.c. onto lower back. </p>

<p>Peptides </p>

<p>Proteolysis-resistant WAT7-KLAKLAK 2 (D-WAT) and WAT7-
KFAKFAK 2 (D-CAN) were made as "all-D-amino acid" peptides 
with the targeting and apoptotic domains linked by aminohexanoic </p>

<p>Figure 5. Hunter-Killer Peptide Targeting Human 
ASCs Expressing DCN 
(A) Human subcutaneous ASCs from patient 1, breast 
adenocarcinoma (MDA-MB-231), and prostate adeno-
carcinoma (PC3 and DU145) cells were incubated with 
indicated concentrations of peptide D-CAN. Plotted are 
mean ± SEM for multiple fields (n = 10). *p &lt; 0.01 (Stu-
dent's t test). (B) Human unmodified ASCs and DCN-null 
ASCs (DCN-KO) were incubated with indicated concen-
trations of peptide D-CAN. After 4 hr treatment, cells were 
stained with trypan blue. Blue color shows selective killing 
of ASCs at 0.05 mM. The scale bar represents 50 mm. 
Plotted are mean ± SEM for multiple fields (n = 10). *p &lt; 
0.01 (Student's t test). Experiments were performed for 
i.p. and s.c. WAT of three patients with similar results. </p>

<p>acid linker NH-(CH 2 ) 5 -CO. Peptides were 
synthesized as acetate salt, cysteine cyclized, 
chromatographically purified to 99%, and qual-
ity controlled (mass spectroscopy). D-WAT, 
CSWKYWFGEC, and NH-(CH 2 ) 5 -KLAKLAK 2 
peptides were purchased from Celtek; D-CAN 
was purchased from Ambiopharm. Peptides 
were dissolved in PBS to 10 mM, and aliquots 
were stored frozen until dilution in PBS, filtration, 
and use. For peptide administration into mice, the 
metronomic s.c. injection protocol was used as 
described, 
29 starting the day after tumor grafting. Peptide biotinylation </p>

<p>was performed as described. 
26 Tissues and live cells were incubated with </p>

<p>biotinylated peptides at concentration 10 nM and 20 nM, respectively. </p>

<p>Affinity Chromatography </p>

<p>Protein pull-down assay was performed as described. 
26 Cells were 
disrupted in PBS containing protease inhibitors (PI) cocktail with 
a Dounce homogenizer; centrifugation (15,000 Â g for 30 min at 
4 
C) was performed to separate soluble proteins from membrane pel-
let. Membrane proteins were solubilized in PBS containing 1 mM 
CaCl 2 , 1 mM MgCl 2 , 50 mM n-octyl-beta-D-glucopyranoside, and 
PI cocktail (column buffer). Six milligrams of a cysteine-cyclized pep-
tide was coupled onto 250 mL of Affigel 10 (Bio-Rad), and the column 
was equilibrated with column buffer containing 1% Triton X-100. 
Peptide-coupled resin (10 mL) was incubated with 30 mg of membrane 
extract and washed with column buffer. Elution was performed with 
SDS-PAGE loading buffer. Protein preparations resolved on SDS-
PAGE were blotted onto Immobilon-FL membrane (Millipore), 
blocked with Odyssey blocking buffer (LI-COR Biosciences), and 
probed (in PBS/0.05% Triton X-100) with 1:1,000 goat anti-DCN 
(R&amp;D Systems). Signal was detected by Odyssey imaging system us-
ing anti-goat IRDye 800CW (LI-COR Biosciences). NS0-expressed 
murine DCN was from R&amp;D Systems. </p>

<p>Cell Lines and Primary Cell Culture </p>

<p>Cells were cultured in DMEM supplemented with 10% fetal 
bovine serum (FBS) and penicillin-streptomycin. Cell lines were </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics </p>

<p> 
Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 </p>

<p>purchased from the American Type Culture Collection. Pri-
mary cells were isolated and cultured as described. 
5,26 Freshly 
isolated ASCs were briefly cultured to remove non-adherent 
cells. Trypan blue exclusion assay was used to determine cell 
viability in peptide-treated ASCs and tumor cell lines as re-
ported previously. 
25,29 When cell density reached 80% con-
fluency, cells were treated with indicated concentrations of 
peptides in 0.5 mL culture medium for 2 hr. Cells were stained 
with 0.4% trypan blue solution (MP Biomedicals) for 10 min to 
visualize live and dead cells. DCN-null ASCs were generated 
from primary s.c. human ASCs of patient 1 using the CRISPR/ 
Cas9 method. 
53 To construct pLenti-CRISPR/Cas9 hDCN gRNA 
expression vectors, the 20-bp target sequence 5 
0 -GGCTCG 
AAGTCGCGGTCATCAGG-3 
0 containing the PAM sequence 
(underlined) was subcloned into lenti-CRISPR v2 plasmid (Addg-
ene no. 52961). </p>

<p>Figure 6. Selective Human PDGFRb 
+ ASC Depletion </p>

<p>with the Hunter-Killer Peptide 
(A) IF of human WAT identifies PDGFRa </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>PDGFRb </p>

<p>À </p>

<p>and PDGFRa </p>

<p>À </p>

<p>PDGFRb+ ASCs as distinct populations 
located around a blood vessel (*, green auto-
fluorescence). (B) Selective apoptosis of some, but not 
all, ASCs from human WAT treated with 0.01 mM control 
peptide or D-WAT is shown. Trypan blue staining (blue) 
reveals cell death. Plotted are mean ± SEM for multiple 
fields (n = 10). *p &lt; 0.01 (Student's t test). (C) IF on cells 
from (B) identifies apoptosis (cleaved caspase 3, green) 
of PDGFRb 
+ cells (yellow), but not of PDGFRa 
+ cells (red) </p>

<p>induced by 0.01 mM D-WAT. The scale bar represents 
50 mm. Plotted are mean ± SEM for multiple fields (n = 
10). *p &lt; 0.01 (Student's t test). Experiments were per-
formed for i.p. and s.c. WAT of three patients with similar 
results. </p>

<p>IF </p>

<p>Sections of formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded 
tissues were analyzed by IF as described. </p>

<p>5,26 </p>

<p>Antigen retrieval, washing with 0.2% Triton 
X-100, and blocking in Serum-Free Protein 
Block (Dako) was followed by incubation 
with primary antibodies (4 
C; 12 hr) and sec-
ondary antibodies (room temperature [RT]; 
1 hr) in PBS containing 0.05% Tween 20. 
Cells plated on 24-well plate were fixed 
with 4% paraformaldehyde, permeabilized 
with Triton X-100, blocked with Serum-Free 
Protein Block, and followed by incubation 
with primary and secondary antibodies, as 
above. Antibodies used were as follows: 
rabbit anti-mouse PDGFRb ab32570 (Abcam; 
1:100); rabbit anti-CD31 (Santa Cruz Biotech-
nology; 1:100); goat anti-human PDGFRa 
(R&amp;D; 1:100); rabbit anti-human PDGFRb 
(Abcam; 1:100); and rabbit anti-Asp175-
cleaved caspase3 from Cell Signaling Technology (1:100). 
Alexa-488-conjugated (1:150) and Cy3-conjugated (1:100) strepta-
vidin was from Invitrogen. Secondary antibodies were donkey 
Alexa-488-conjugated (1:150) immunoglobulin G (IgG) from 
Invitrogen and Cy3-conjugated (1:300) IgG from Jackson 
ImmunoResearch. Nuclei were visualized with DAPI. For quanti-
fications, at least ten random 10Â or 20Â magnification fields 
were blindly scored and/or measured using microscope grid. Tis-
sue IF images were acquired with Carl Zeiss upright Apotome 
Axio Imager Z1/ZEN2 Core Imaging software. Cells were imaged 
using a Leica microscope (Leica Microsystems; model: DM IL LED 
Fluo). </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p><rs type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> was used to graph data as mean ± SEM and to calcu-
late p values using homoscedastic Student's t test. </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 </p>

<p>
SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION </p>

<p>Supplemental Information includes five figures and can be found with 
this article online at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.omto.2017.05.003. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>M.G.K. designed the experiments, analyzed data, and wrote the 
manuscript; A.C.D. designed and conducted the experiments and 
analyzed data; A.D. conducted the experiments; and B.S., X.W., 
A.A.S., and N.T.U. provided materials, analyzed data, and edited 
the manuscript. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Zhanguo Gao and Angielyn Rivera for technical assistance. 
We thank Renato Iozzo and Jane Grande-Allen for sharing DCN-null 
MEFs. We thank Askar Kuchumov, Eugene Shevchenko, and Andrew 
Makarovskiy for many helpful discussions. This work was supported 
in part by CTSA award UL1 TR000371. </p>



<p>Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics </p>

<p> 
Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 </p>



<p>www.moleculartherapy.org </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy: Oncolytics Vol. 6 September 2017 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>