<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5094513" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Palmitoylethanolamide (PEA) has been suggested to have useful analgesic properties and to be devoid of unwanted effects. 
Here, we have examined critically this contention, and discussed available data concerning the pharmacokinetics of PEA and 
its formulation. Sixteen clinical trials, six case reports/pilot studies and a meta-analysis of PEA as an analgesic have been 
published in the literature. For treatment times up to 49 days, the current clinical data argue against serious adverse drug 
reactions (ADRs) at an incidence of 1/200 or greater. For treatment lasting more than 60 days, the number of patients is 
insufficient to rule out a frequency of ADRs of less than 1/100. The six published randomized clinical trials are of variable 
quality. Presentation of data without information on data spread and nonreporting of data at times other than the final 
measurement were among issues that were identified. Further, there are no head-to-head clinical comparisons of 
unmicronized vs. micronized formulations of PEA, and so evidence for superiority of one formulation over the other is 
currently lacking. Nevertheless, the available clinical data support the contention that PEA has analgesic actions and motivate 
further study of this compound, particularly with respect to head-to-head comparisons of unmicronized vs. micronized for-
mulations of PEA and comparisons with currently recommended treatments. </p>

<p>Palmitoylethanolamide (PEA, N-(2-hydroxyethyl) hexadecamide, 
palmidrol; structure shown in Figure 1) belongs to the family 
of N-acylethanolamines (NAEs), endogenous biologically 
active lipids including the endogenous cannabinoid receptor 
ligand anandamide and the satiety factor oleoylethano-
lamide. PEA was identified in the 1950s as being an active 
anti-inflammatory agent in chicken egg yolk [1, 2]. In mam-
mals, PEA is produced on demand from the lipid bilayer and 
is ubiquitous, with tissue concentrations in the mid to high 
pmol/g range being found in rodents [3]. Preclinical and 
clinical studies suggest PEA may potentially be useful in a wide 
range of therapeutic areas, including eczema, pain and neuro-
degeneration and at the same time to be essentially devoid of 
unwanted effects in humans (see e.g. [4-19] for examples, and 
[20] for a review of the clinical data accrued up to 2012 with 
respect to pain). PEA is currently marketed for veterinary use </p>

<p>(skin conditions, Redonyl 
™ , [Innovet]) and as a nutraceutical </p>

<p>in humans (Normast 
™ , Pelvilen 
™ [Epitech]), PeaPure 
™ [JP </p>

<p>Russel Science Ltd]) in some European countries (e.g. Italy, 
Spain; it is sold as a food supplement in other countries, such 
as the Netherlands). It also is a constituent of a cream 
(Physiogel AI 
™ , Stiefel) marketed for dry skin. </p>

<p>Most reviews on the subject of PEA and its clinical poten-
tial have presented it in a fairly cursory manner, with the ex-
ception of a very recent meta-analysis [21]. In addition, the 
pharmacokinetic properties of PEA have not been considered 
to any extent. In the present review, we have focused on 
these issues. </p>

<p>Preclinical pharmacology of PEA </p>

<p>The pharmacological properties of PEA with respect to pain, 
inflammation and mechanism(s) of action in preclinical </p>

<p>British Journal of Clinical 
Pharmacology </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol (2016) 82 932-942 932 </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd 
on behalf of The British Pharmacological Society. </p>

<p>DOI:10.1111/bcp.13020 </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in any me-
dium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>models have been well reviewed elsewhere [20, 22, 23] 
and will only be mentioned briefly here. PEA shows efficacy 
in a variety of pain models including carrageenan-and 
prostaglandin-induced hyperalgesia [6, 15, 18], the formalin 
test of persistent pain [8, 9], visceral hyperalgesia produced by 
instillation of nerve growth factor into the bladder [7, 12], and 
the sciatic nerve ligature model of neuropathic pain [14], 
whereas the acute thermal pain response is not affected [8]. 
The proposed mechanism(s) of action of PEA involve effects 
upon mast cells [6], CB 2 -like cannabinoid receptors [9, 12], 
ATP-sensitive K </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-channels [18], TRP channels [24], and NFkB 
[15], although the most robust evidence is for an action of PEA 
upon the nuclear receptor peroxisome proliferator-activated re-
ceptor α (PPARα) [13]. These are by no means the only actions 
of PEA: it can also, for example, interact as an agonist with 
GPR119, an orphan receptor involved in glucagon-like 
peptide-1 secretion [25, 26], and will, at least in theory, affect 
endocannabinoid signalling by acting as a competing sub-
strate for the endocannabinoid homologue anandamide 
(N-arachidonoylethanolamine). Some of these actions are 
shared by the endogenous NAEs N-oleoylethanolamine and 
N-stearoylethanolamine [13, 25, 27], but clinical data to our 
knowledge is lacking with respect to these compounds. </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetic considerations </p>

<p>There is very little data available in the open literature 
concerning the pharmacokinetic properties of PEA. To our 
knowledge, the bioavailability (F) and apparent volume of 
distribution (V d ) of PEA have not been reported. In view of 
this, we have attempted to provide some 'ball-park' estimates 
using data from a recent study investigating the plasma 
concentration of PEA following oral treatment of nine male 
Wistar rats (body weight 150-250 g) with 100 mg kg 
À1 of </p>

<p>PEA in a corn oil suspension [28]. The focus of that study 
was to find pro-drugs for PEA, and so the authors were con-
tent to report the area under the curve for the measurement 
period (AUC 0-8h ) and the approximate t max value. The plasma 
concentrations, in nM, reported in Table 2 of [28] are shown 
graphically in Figure 2. PEA is also relatively short-lived in 
human plasma: Petrosino et al. [29] reported in graphical 
form plasma PEA levels 0, 2, 4 and 6 h after oral administra-
tion of 300 mg micronized PEA to 10 healthy volunteers. 
There was a significant increase (from~10 to~23 pmol ml </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>plasma) at the 2 h time point, returning to baseline at the 
higher time points. </p>

<p>Assuming a simple one compartment model with first-order 
absorption and distribution, a plasma elimination half-time of 
12 min in the rat can be calculated using the time points be-
tween 15 min and 8 h of the data of [28], with an extrapolated 
(and very approximate) concentration at t = 0 ('C p(o) ') of 
910 nM (arrowed in Figure 2), corresponding to 0.27 mg l </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>. 
The AUC 1-8h of 6525 ± 1372 ng PEA min ml 
À1 reported in [28] </p>

<p>corresponds to a value of 37 ± 10 × 10 
À6 of given dose h </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>, as-
suming a total blood volume of 6.25 ml/100 g, of which 55% 
is plasma. Our interpretation of the data in [28] is that most of 
the PEA is outside of the blood following oral administration 
(for further analysis determining approximate V d values for a 
given bioavailability, see Appendix S1). 
The tissue distribution of PEA has also been studied: Grillo 
et al. [30] reported that in a small sample (n = 3-4 per group), 
administration of PEA (10 mg kg 
À1 ) emulsified in corn oil in-</p>

<p>creased levels of this lipid in the heart and brain of DBA/2 
mice 24 and/or 48 h after subcutaneous injections. 
Artamonov et al. [31] investigated the distribution of 
N-[9,10-
3 H] PEA in male 150-200 g Wistar rats 20 min after </p>

<p>oral administration (dose~100 mCi, 3.3 × 10 
À5 mol/100 g </p>

<p>of body weight, corresponding to approximately 
100 mg kg 
À1 ). They found that approximately 0.95% of the </p>

<p>administered PEA was found in the brain, with a very hetero-
geneous distribution: NAE levels of 10 400, 65, 110, 7.4 and 
2.2 pmol mg 
À1 of tissue were recovered in the hypothalamus, </p>

<p>white matter, brain stem, cerebellum and brain cortex, re-
spectively (means of three experiments). The corresponding 
values for pituitary gland and adrenal organs were 2050 and </p>

<p>Figure 1 </p>

<p>Structure of PEA. The compound is sometimes referred to as NAE 
16:0, where 16 and 0 refer to the number of carbon atoms and dou-
ble bonds, respectively, in the acyl side chain. The related com-
pounds anandamide and oleoylethanolamide are NAE 20:4 and 
NAE 18:1, respectively, using this nomenclature </p>

<p>Figure 2 </p>

<p>Plasma concentrations of PEA following oral dosing of 100 mg kg </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>to male Wistar rats (body weight 150-250 g). The data are taken 
from Table 2 of [28] and are shown as means ± SEM, n = 9. The time 
points from 0.25-8 h were fitted to a one-phase decay model using 
the least squares method (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">6.0</rs> h for the Macintosh). 
The model returns the extrapolated plasma concentration at t = 0 
(C p(o) , 913 ± 16 nM), the value to which the curve asymptotes 
(44 ± 1 nM, i.e. the data ≥2 h), the rate constant (3.4 ± 0.06 h 
À1 ) </p>

<p>and hence the t 1/2 value (0.21 h). Needless to say, the large data 
spread at the first time point renders the values approximate </p>

<p>Palmitoylethanolamide for the treatment of pain </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol (2016) 82 932-942 933 </p>

<p>85 pmol mg 
À1 of tissue, respectively. Very little of the total tri-</p>

<p>tium recovered in the hypothalamus was in lipids other than 
NAE (e.g. free fatty acids), whereas 28 and 34% of the label 
was metabolized in the pituitary and cerebellum, respectively 
[31]. The very heterogeneous distribution in the brain is sur-
prising for a lipophilic compound, and would suggest prefer-
ential retention by the hypothalamus. One explanation for 
such retention would be a selective expression of a PEA bind-
ing moiety in the hypothalamus. Interestingly, PPARα can be 
ruled out as such a target, because its expression in the hypo-
thalamus is low [32]. </p>

<p>Clinical studies with PEA </p>

<p>The clinical studies identified by our search (see Appendix S2 
for details) are summarized in Tables 1 and 2. We found 21 
clinical studies, of which 16 were clinical trials enrolling a 
range of 20 to 636 patients and five were case/pilot studies. 
In the clinical trials, PEA was used for periods ranging from 
14 days to 120 days, and the doses ranged from 300 mg to 
1200 mg daily. The administration form of PEA was in most 
cases oral tablets except some occasional use of sublingual for-
mulations (sachets), and the commonest form of evaluation 
was the visual analogue scale (VAS), where the patient makes 
a subjective assessment of her/his pain level on a 10 cm line 
where the left side represents no pain, and the right side repre-
sents the worst imaginable pain [33, 34]. With one exception 
([35], possibly a 'floor effect'), all available clinical trials re-
ported significantly reduced pain intensity and an almost 
complete absence of unwanted effects, the latter confirming 
early field studies of PEA in healthy individuals [4]. 
A meta-analysis into the clinical utility of micronized and 
ultra-micronized PEA on pain intensity in patients suffering 
from chronic and/or neuropathic pain has recently been pub-
lished [21]. The authors of [21], of whom two were employees 
of Epitech (the makers of Normast and other PEA prepara-
tions), obtained raw data from corresponding authors of 12 
studies (six published in journals, two published abstracts 
and four manuscripts either in preparation or submitted for 
publication) that met the inclusion criteria (including avail-
ability of raw data and comparable methods for assessing 
pain intensity). The authors concluded on the basis of their 
analyses that PEA was an effective treatment for pain with 
no registered serious adverse effects. Their analysis was based 
upon 12 studies that met their inclusion criteria (three 
placebo-controlled double blind studies, two open-label 
randomized vs. standard therapy and seven open-label 
studies without a comparator) in patients with a variety of 
aetiologies. Several outcomes were presented, of which a key 
finding was the difference in the number of patients achiev-
ing ≤3 in the NRS/VAS scores (55/263 [20.9%] for the con-
trols, 760/1138 [66.7% of the PEA treatment groups) [21]. 
The fact that approximately half of the included patients 
came from the open-label studies (703/30 PEA/control vs. 
266/485 PEA/control for the double blind studies) is perhaps 
a weakness of the study, although a Cox survival analysis 
(reduction in pain intensity to ≤3 on an NRS/VAS scale as 
endpoint) favoured both PEA over control and the double 
blind over the open-label studies (other factors with modest, </p>

<p>but significant effects in this analysis were gender and age 
(&lt;65 vs. ≥65); pain aetiology did not contribute significantly 
to the analysis). Whilst the strength of the article is that it 
has access to raw data, this is mitigated by a lack of discussion 
as to the quality of the key studies. Additionally, the authors 
did not discuss the issue of publication bias [36], whereby 
studies with less satisfactory outcomes would either not have 
been visible in their searches or alternatively might been ex-
cluded due to unavailability of the raw data. We cannot ad-
dress this issue here, but we have investigated the strengths 
and weaknesses of the key randomized controlled trials 
(RCTs), and further considered how to interpret the clearly 
promising data with respect to adverse effects. </p>

<p>Tolerability of PEA </p>

<p>As noted by other authors [20, 21], PEA appears to be well tol-
erated indeed. The only adverse event (not necessarily drug-
related) that has been reported was for a patient treated with 
300 mg Normast 
™ following impacted third molar extraction </p>

<p>[37]. The patient, who was not taking any other drugs, re-
ported palpitations lasting 2-3 h on the third day of 
Normast 
™ treatment. This occurred 1 h after Normast 
™ con-</p>

<p>sumption, and the patient did not continue with the trial af-
ter this event. This low rate of adverse events is remarkable 
indeed: after all, patients treated with placebo in double blind 
studies report adverse events. For example, in a recent 
multicentre, randomized double-blind study in patients with 
uncontrolled moderate to severe back pain, 35% of the 
placebo-treated patients reported treatment-emergent ad-
verse events (primarily nausea, constipation, vomiting, dizzi-
ness, headache and somnolence) [38]. As we do not have 
access to the study protocols, we cannot say whether the lack 
of adverse events found with PEA in the studies reflects a true 
low rate, or whether mild/moderate adverse events were not 
documented or reported. 
The likelihood of observing an adverse drug reaction 
(ADR) is dependent upon the number of patients observed, 
the frequency threshold of the ADR, and whether it occurs 
early on or after prolonged treatment. Frequencies of ADRs 
are divided into 'very common' (≥1/10), 'common' (≥1/100 
and &lt;1/10), 'uncommon' (≥1/1000 and &lt;1/100), 'rare' (≥1/ 
10 000 and &lt;1/1000), and 'very rare' (&lt;1/10 000). As a gen-
eral rule of thumb, the 95% likelihood of observing an ADR 
at a frequency threshold of 1/n in a study requires 3n patients 
[39]. In other words, at least 300 patients would be needed for 
a 95% likelihood of observing a single ADR at a frequency of 
occurrence of 1/100 [39]. For two and three ADRs to be ob-
served at this frequency, the number increases to 480 and 
650, respectively [39]. If we consider only the data in 
Table 1, and disregard for simplicity differences in dosaging, 
then a total of 1590 patients were treated with PEA. However, 
the number of patients drops off rapidly with increasing 
treatment time (shown visually in Figure 3; note that the y-
axis on the graph is logarithmic, not linear). For treatment 
times ≤49 days, the rule of thumb described above suggests 
that ADRs occurring this early on in treatment would be 
likely to have been seen for an incidence of 1/200 or greater. 
But remember, these numbers refer to a 95% likelihood of </p>

<p>L. Gabrielsson et al. </p>



<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Clinical trials investigating the effect of PEA in pain. Trials are listed in descending order with respect to the number of participants </p>

<p>Type of study </p>

<p>No. of 
patients 
Type of pain </p>

<p>PEA dosage </p>

<p>Formulation </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>length </p>

<p>Outcome (all </p>

<p>VAS scale unless 
marked with </p>

<p> ¶ or **) </p>

<p>Unwanted </p>

<p>effects </p>

<p>Conflict of 
interest </p>

<p>Sponsor </p>

<p>Ref </p>

<p>Double blind 
randomized 
controlled 
multi-centre, </p>

<p>placebo </p>

<p>636 (1/3 
placebo) 
Low back pain 
(lumbosciatica) </p>

<p>1 or 2 × 
300 mg daily </p>

<p>UM or M 
Normast </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>Epitech group </p>

<p>21 days </p>

<p>600 mg better 
than 300 mg, 
both doses 
significantly </p>

<p>better than 
placebo at </p>

<p>t = 21 days </p>

<p>None 
reported </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>[41] † </p>

<p>(Observational) </p>

<p>prospective </p>

<p>cohort </p>

<p>610 (564 
completions) 
Chronic pain </p>

<p>of different 
etiopathogenesis 
1200 mg daily 
for 3 weeks 
followed by </p>

<p>600 mg daily 
for 4 weeks </p>

<p>UM or M 
Normast </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>Epitech group </p>

<p>49 days </p>

<p>Significant decrease </p>

<p>in pain intensity in 
all patients 
(P = 0.0001) ¶ </p>

<p>None 
reported </p>

<p>Declare no 
conflict of 
interest </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>[49] </p>

<p>Non-randomized, 
non-controlled, </p>

<p>PEA as add-on 
compared </p>

<p>to only standard 
treatment* </p>

<p>118 (64 
received </p>

<p>PEA) </p>

<p>Low back pain 
(lumbosciatica) 
600 mg daily </p>

<p>Formulation 
unknown 
Manufacturer </p>

<p>unknown </p>

<p>30 days </p>

<p>Significant changes </p>

<p>for both groups, 
a slightly larger 
decrease in pain 
intensity with PEA 
compared to standard 
treatment.* No 
significant change </p>

<p>in ODI </p>

<p>None 
reported </p>

<p>Declare no 
conflict of 
interest </p>

<p>Angelini, 
Spain </p>

<p>[50] </p>

<p>Double blind, 
randomized, 
controlled, </p>

<p>placebo </p>

<p>111 (1/3 
placebo) </p>

<p>Lumbosciatic </p>

<p>pain </p>

<p>1 or 2 × 
300 mg daily </p>

<p>UM or M 
Normast </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>Epitech group </p>

<p>21 days </p>

<p>Significant reduction </p>

<p>of pain intensity with 
PEA regardless of 
simultaneous 
treatment with other </p>

<p>drugs compared to 
placebo at days 21 </p>

<p>None 
reported </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>[43] † </p>

<p>Observational </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>Fibromyalgia </p>

<p>Starting with </p>

<p>600 mg daily 
for 1 month 
following 300 mg </p>

<p>daily for month 2-3 </p>

<p>UM or M 
PEA-m </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, 
PEA-um </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, 
Epitech Group </p>

<p>6 months 
(PEA 3 months) </p>

<p>Addition of PEA to the 
treatment regimen 
significantly reduced </p>

<p>VAS pain scores further </p>

<p>None 
reported </p>

<p>Declare no 
conflict of 
interest </p>

<p>None </p>

<p>[51] </p>

<p>Randomized, 
double-blind, </p>

<p>Chronic pelvic </p>

<p>pain </p>

<p>M Manufacturer 
unknown </p>

<p>3 months </p>

<p>Significantly reduced </p>

<p>pain intensity with </p>

<p>None 
reported </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>[44] 
(continues) </p>

<p>Palmitoylethanolamide for the treatment of pain </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol (2016) 82 932-942 935 </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Type of study </p>

<p>No. of 
patients 
Type of pain </p>

<p>PEA dosage </p>

<p>Formulation </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>length </p>

<p>Outcome (all </p>

<p>VAS scale unless 
marked with </p>

<p> ¶ or **) </p>

<p>Unwanted </p>

<p>effects </p>

<p>Conflict of 
interest </p>

<p>Sponsor </p>

<p>Ref </p>

<p>3 parallel-group, 
placebo-
controlled </p>

<p>61 (1/3 
placebo, 1/3 
celecoxib) </p>

<p>800 mg daily 
(combined with 
transpolydatin) </p>

<p>PEA compared to 
placebo, although 
Celecoxib was more 
effective than PEA </p>

<p>Prospective </p>

<p>cohort </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>Endometriotic </p>

<p>pain </p>

<p>800 mg daily 
(combined with 
transpolydatin) 
M Tablets 
Manufacturer </p>

<p>unknown </p>

<p>90 days </p>

<p>Significant decrease in </p>

<p>pain intensity </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>[52] </p>

<p>Randomized, 
controlled </p>

<p>30 (1/2 
acupuncure) </p>

<p>Radiculopathy </p>

<p>600 mg daily </p>

<p>UM or M 
Normast </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>Epitech group </p>

<p>120 days </p>

<p>Significant decrease in 
chronic pain intensity 
with PEA compared to 
acupuncture treatment </p>

<p>only** </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>[53] ‡ </p>

<p>Open-label </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Diabetic or traumatic 
neuropathic pain </p>

<p>1200 mg daily </p>

<p>UM Sachets, 
Tablets 
Manufacturer </p>

<p>unknown </p>

<p>40 days </p>

<p>Significant reduction </p>

<p>of pain intensity. VAS, 
health questionnaire five 
dimensions for quality </p>

<p>of life (EQ-ED50) and 
NP Symptom Inventory 
(NPSI) used </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Declare no 
conflict of 
interest </p>

<p>Associazone 
Neuropatie 
Chroniche 
Piemonte 
ONLUS </p>

<p>[54] </p>

<p>Randomized, split </p>

<p>mouth, single 
blinded </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Postoperative pain </p>

<p>due to lower third 
molar surgery </p>

<p>600 mg daily </p>

<p>UM or M 
Normast </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>Epitech group </p>

<p>15 days </p>

<p>Significant decrease </p>

<p>in postoperative pain 
with PEA treatment </p>

<p>One case of 
drowsiness </p>

<p>and one case 
of palpitations </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>[37] </p>

<p>Open-label </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Neuropathic pain, </p>

<p>different types </p>

<p>600 mg daily 
(combined with 
pregabalin) </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>45 days </p>

<p>Significant reduction </p>

<p>of pain intensity </p>

<p>None 
reported </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>[55] ‡ </p>

<p>Open-label </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Peripheral diabetic 
neuropathy </p>

<p>600 mg daily </p>

<p>M Normast </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>Epitech group </p>

<p>60 days </p>

<p>Significant reduction </p>

<p>in pain intensity [Total 
Symptom Score TSS]** </p>

<p>None 
reported </p>

<p>Declare no 
conflict of 
interest </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>[56] </p>

<p>Controlled trial </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>Carpal tunnel 
syndrome </p>

<p>600 mg or 
1200 mg daily </p>

<p>UM or M 
Normast </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>Epitech group </p>

<p>30 days </p>

<p>Significant improvement </p>

<p>of CTS induced median 
nerve latency time. Also 
improvement of subjective 
discomfort, and Tinel's </p>

<p>sign** </p>

<p>None 
reported </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>[57] 
(continues) </p>

<p>L. Gabrielsson et al. </p>



<p>observing a single ADR [39], and of recognizing it as such. 
Nonetheless, the current clinical data argue against 'very 
common' or 'common' serious ADRs being found with PEA 
following these treatment times, whereas there is insufficient 
data to give information in the 'uncommon' or 'rare' 
categories. 
Treatment of chronic pain is not likely to be short term, 
and for ≥60 days of treatment, the number of patients is insuf-
ficient to rule out a frequency of ADRs of less than 1/100. That 
does not, of course, mean that such ADRs will occur, merely 
that there is insufficient data to judge whether or not they 
do occur. </p>

<p>Efficacy of PEA </p>

<p>The studies are summarized in Tables 1 and 2. The total num-
ber of participants is high in two trials (n ≈ 600) whilst the 
others are more modest in size, ranging from 20 to 118 partic-
ipants in all. Some of the trials compare PEA to placebo, 
others investigate PEA as an add-on to standard treatments. 
Many of the PEA clinical trials have limitations in terms of de-
sign: case reports (Table 2) have little value in terms of 
external validity, and open labelled trials (Table 1) do not take 
into account placebo effects, which are a major issue in pain 
studies [40]. The strongest indicator of efficacy is the RCT 
and we identified six blinded RCTs. 
The efficacy of PEA in the six blinded RCTs is summarized 
in more detail, together with our assessment of their 
strengths and weaknesses, in Table 3. The largest of the stud-
ies, investigating the effects of PEA on lumbosciatica [41] was 
included in the meta-analysis of [21]. The differences be-
tween days 0 and 21 for the VAS scores can be used to calcu-
late a treatment effect size, assuming that the VAS scores are 
normally distributed (this was not stated explicitly in the arti-
cle), and leaving aside the issue that VAS is an ordinal mea-
sure. From their data and using an online calculator (http:// 
www.psychometrica.de/effect_size.html; last accessed 14 
June 2016), we estimate Cohen's d values of 0.43 (95% CI 
0.23-0.62) and 1.35 (95% CI 1.14-1.56) for 300 and 2 × 
300 mg PEA, respectively. The latter value is a large effect size. 
In terms of the strengths/weaknesses of the studies, there 
are several issues that emerge, the small size of most of the 
other studies being the most obvious. Key issues are the 
nonreporting of time points other than the final time point 
[41], lack of (or surprisingly small values [42]), information 
as to the variation in VAS scores among the patients; data pre-
sented graphically rather than in tables [43, 44]; floor effects 
in the comparator group and possible post-hoc subgroup anal-
yses [35]; and evaluation time points that are difficult to com-
pare with current treatments [37]. Two of the studies had 
NSAID comparator groups; in one, the patients fared better 
with celecoxib than with PEA + transpolydatin [44], whilst 
in the other, the patients fared equally well with PEA and ibu-
profen over the first eight days, after which the effect of ibu-
profen plateaued out, whilst those patients treated with PEA 
continued to improve [42]. All in all, the data point to efficacy 
of PEA over placebo (assuming no publication bias), but more 
information is needed to be able to gauge this efficacy vs. cur-
rent treatment regimes. </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Type of study </p>

<p>No. of 
patients 
Type of pain </p>

<p>PEA dosage </p>

<p>Formulation </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>length </p>

<p>Outcome (all </p>

<p>VAS scale unless 
marked with </p>

<p> ¶ or **) </p>

<p>Unwanted </p>

<p>effects </p>

<p>Conflict of 
interest </p>

<p>Sponsor </p>

<p>Ref </p>

<p>Triple-blind, 
randomized, 
controlled </p>

<p>24 (1/2 
ibuprofen) </p>

<p>Temporomandibular </p>

<p>joint inflammatory 
pain </p>

<p>900 mg daily for 
7 days and then 
600 mg daily for 
7 days more </p>

<p>UM or M 
Normast®/ </p>

<p>Epitech group </p>

<p>14 days </p>

<p>Significantly larger 
reduction in pain 
intensity compared to 
ibuprofen treatment </p>

<p>on day 14 </p>

<p>None 
reported </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>None </p>

<p>[42] </p>

<p>Open-label </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Chemotherapy-</p>

<p>induced neuropathy </p>

<p>600 mg daily </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>60 days </p>

<p>Significant reduction in </p>

<p>pain intensity** </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>[58] </p>

<p>Double blind, 
randomized </p>

<p>and TENS §-alone 
controlled </p>

<p>20 (1/2 
TENS alone) </p>

<p>Vestibulodynia </p>

<p>800 mg daily 
(combined with 
transpolydatin </p>

<p>and TENS) </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>60 days </p>

<p>No significant 
improvement with </p>

<p>PEA treatment </p>

<p>Three cases </p>

<p>of mild transient 
gastrointestinal </p>

<p>symptoms </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>[35] </p>

<p>Abbreviations: M, Micronized; NM, Not micronized; NS, not stated in the article; NRS, Numerical rating scale; UM, Ultramicronized; VAS, Visual analogue scale. *NSAIDs, analgesics, muscle relaxants, 
corticosteroids; the exact treatment differed for patients / treatment centres.  †Article in Spanish.  ‡Article in Italian.  §Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation. The six blinded RCTs that we </p>

<p>identified are references [41], [43], [44], [37], [42] and [35].  ¶NRS used. **Other or unidentified evaluation method. ODI, Oswestry Disablity Index (measures quality of life in patients with low back pain). </p>

<p>Palmitoylethanolamide for the treatment of pain </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol (2016) 82 932-942 937 </p>

<p>Formulation of PEA </p>

<p>PEA is a poorly water-soluble substance and as such the dis-
solution rate is often the rate-limiting step for oral </p>

<p>absorption and bioavailability. Dissolution rate is influenced 
by, among other factors, particle size and therefore drug sub-
stances are usually micronized in order to achieve a more 
rapid dissolution. 
In the clinical trials discussed here, ultramicronized or 
micronized PEA was used except in three studies where 
the quality of PEA was unknown or not stated (Tables 1-3). 
Focus has been placed on the importance of micronization 
of PEA, in particular the advantages (or lack thereof) of mi-
cronized PEA over unmicronized PEA (see [45] for a flavour 
of this particular debate; note the conflict of interest state-
ment at the end of that article). In brief, the process of 
micronization results in smaller particles and hence a 
larger total surface area. This allows the gastrointestinal mi-
lieu more access to free surfaces on the drug particle and 
hence a faster dissolution can be achieved. This may lead 
to a better adsorption of the drug molecules [46]. There is 
a report in rodents that orally administered micronized 
and ultramicronized PEA are more efficacious than 
unmicronized PEA in the carrageenan model of inflamma-
tory pain [47]. However, in that study the formulations of 
PEA were dissolved in carboxymethylcellulose prior to oral 
or intraperitoneal administration, i.e. already in solution, 
which would be expected to bypass the contribution of 
the micronization. Head-to-head comparisons of the 
different formulations of PEA in humans are lacking, and 
thus there is no clinical data yet to support the use of 
one formulation over another, which is an unsatisfactory 
state of affairs. </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Case reports and pilot studies investigating PEA in patients with pain </p>

<p>Type of 
study </p>

<p>No. of 
cases 
Type of pain 
PEA dosage 
Formulation </p>

<p>Treatment 
length </p>

<p>Outcome (all 
VAS scale unless 
marked with 
* or  †) </p>

<p>Unwanted 
effects 
Ref </p>

<p>Pilot study, 
open-label </p>

<p>4 
Chronic pelvic pain 
associated with 
endometriosis </p>

<p>400 mg daily 
(combined with 
polydatin) </p>

<p>M 
90 days 
Reduction of pain 
intensity </p>

<p>None reported 
[59] </p>

<p>Case report 
collection </p>

<p>7 
Chronic idiopathic 
axonal neuropathy 
and pain </p>

<p>1200 mg daily to 
2000 mg </p>

<p>M 
Different amongst 
patients ranging 
from weeks to 
months </p>

<p>Reduction in pain 
intensity in all 
patients* </p>

<p>None reported 
[60] </p>

<p>Case report 
1 
Chronic regional 
pain syndrome 
type 1 </p>

<p>1200 mg daily 
(combined with 
topical ketamine 
cream) </p>

<p>M 
2 months 
Reduction of pain 
intensity † </p>

<p>None reported 
[61] </p>

<p>Case report 
1 
M u l t i p l es c l e r o s i s 
and central 
neuropathic pain </p>

<p>Up to 1200 mg 
daily (combined 
with acupuncture) </p>

<p>UM 
or M </p>

<p>9 months, 
intermittant </p>

<p>Reduction of pain 
intensity* </p>

<p>None identified ‡ [62] </p>

<p>Case report 
1 
Pudendal neuralgia 
Up to 900 mg 
daily </p>

<p>NS 
1 year 
'Improvement of 
neuralgia and 
associated 
symptoms' † </p>

<p>NS 
[63] </p>

<p>Abbreviations: M, Micronized; NS, not stated in the article; UM, Ultramicronized; VAS, Visual analogue scale. *NRS used.  †Other or unidentified 
evaluation method.  ‡Patient developed a cough early on in the study. The cough continued after PEA was stopped, and so the compound was 
reinstated. </p>

<p>Figure 3 </p>

<p>Number of patients treated with PEA in the studies summarized 
in Table 1 as a function of the length of treatment. The dotted 
lines represent the number of patients needed for a 95% likeli-
hood of observing a single ADR at the frequency of occurrence 
shown [39] </p>

<p>L. Gabrielsson et al. </p>



<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>As pointed out in the introduction, PEA has been the subject of a 
number of reviews in recent years (e.g. [20, 22, 23]), usually with a 
focus on the biochemistry of the endogenous compound, its </p>

<p>variation in physiological and pathological conditions, and the 
preclinical pharmacology of exogenously administered PEA. 
Pharmacokinetic data has largely been neglected, and the clinical 
data has been listed and described, rather than subjected to close 
scrutiny. We have attempted to rectify this in the present article. </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Efficacy and strengths/weaknesses of the six blinded RCT investigating the effects of PEA in pain </p>

<p>Efficacy 
Strengths (+) and Weaknesses (À) </p>

<p>Guida et al. [41] 
lumbosciatic algias with 300 or 600 mg Normast 
Significant reduction of VAS scores on day 21 from 6.6 ± 1.7 (means ± SD) 
to 4.6 ± 1.7 for placebo; 6.5 ± 1.9 → 3.6 ± 1.8 for 300 mg PEA and 7.1 ± 1.8 → 
2.1 ± 1.7 for 600 mg PEA. Similar result found for Roland-Morris disability 
questionnaire (measures back pain) 
Very few dropouts in the PEA groups </p>

<p>+ Well-powered study (636 patients) </p>

<p>+ Clear inclusion and exclusion criteria </p>

<p>+ Intention to treat analysis; repeat 
measurements of VAS scores and 
drug safety </p>

<p>À Efficacy data only reported for end 
of study data (Day 21). Authors did 
not report their findings on Days 7 
and 14 of treatment. </p>

<p>Canteri et al. [43] 
follow-up study to [41], significant reduction on day 21 for PEA groups 
compared to placebo </p>

<p>Smaller, confirmatory study (35-38 
patients per group) 
À Efficacy data reported graphically 
(without error bars) for end of study 
data alone (day 21) </p>

<p>Bacci et al. [37] 
Patients undertaking bilateral lower third molar extractions; randomized, 
split-mouth, single-blind study. Placebo or Normast 600 mg from 6 days 
before surgery to 9 days after surgery 
VAS scores on day 3 were 3.8 ± 3.1 cm vs 5.5 ± 2.4 cm; 
day 7: 1.0 ± 1.8 vs. 1.5 ± 2.2 cm (Normast vs. placebo) </p>

<p>Small study (30 patients, 26 completed 
protocol) 
À hard to assess its clinical relevance 
compared with, say, the standard NSAID 
treatment, where studies of pain relief 
have usually focussed on h after dosing 
[64] as opposed to days, as here </p>

<p>Cobellis et al. [44] 
women with pelvic pain, PEA (2 × 400 mg) + transpolydatin (40 × 2 mg/day) 
vs. placebo and vs. celecoxib (200 × 2 mg/kg/day × 7 days) 
reported VAS scores for dysmenorrhea, deep dyspareunia and non-menstrual 
chronic pelvic pain. Found efficacy of PEA + transpolydatin at 3 months (example 
for pelvic pain score): placebo reduced from~7.3 →~4.8 cm; PEA + transpolydatin 
reduced from~7.5 →~2.2 cm (celecoxib reduced from~7.8 →~1.4 cm). </p>

<p>+ Used non-parametric statistics for VAS 
scores since they were not normally 
distributed. </p>

<p>+ Long-term treatment </p>

<p>+ Comparator drug (celecoxib) </p>

<p>À Small study (20-21 patients/group) </p>

<p>À Data presented graphically rather than 
in a table </p>

<p>Marini et al. [42] 
patients with temporomandibular joint inflammatory pain, Normast (300 + 600 mg 
per day) vs. ibuprofen (600 mg ×3 per day) for two weeks. 
Similar reduction in VAS days 1-8. Thereafter ibuprofen plateaued out (at~3.7 cm) 
whereas PEA group continued down to 0.8 cm on day 14. </p>

<p>À Small study (24 patients) 
The patient population appears to be 
remarkably homogeneous in terms of 
their pain scores, with, for example, 
baseline and final VAS (in mm) of 70 ± 0.22 
and 7.7 ± 0.19 (means ± SE) for the PEA group. 
The variation of the VAS is usually an order of 
magnitude higher. </p>

<p>Murina et al. [35] 
60 days of treatment with PEA (2 × 400 mg per day) + polydatin (2 × 40 mg per day) vs. 
placebo in patients with vestibulodynia. All patients received transcutaneous electrical 
nerve stimulation (TENS). 
Large response in placebo (TENS) group (from 6.2 ± 1.1 → 2.3 ± 1.5 cm). Greater effect 
of TENS in patients with recent onset of the disorder who were given PEA + polydatin </p>

<p>+ Long treatment time </p>

<p>À Small study (20 patients) </p>

<p>À Large response in placebo (TENS) group 
(from 6.2 ± 1.1 → 2.3 ± 1.5 cm) per sig 
reduce chance of seeing additional PEA effect </p>

<p>À Unclear whether the significant finding 
was part of the original study design or a 
post-hoc subgroup analysis </p>

<p>None of the RCTs discussed above were flagged in our ClinicalTrials.gov search, so issues such as primary outcome changes and/or unmotivated 
subgroup analysis, issues which mar many RCTs [65, 66] have not been examined. However, it is reasonable to assume that reductions in VAS scores 
are a primary outcome. </p>

<p>Palmitoylethanolamide for the treatment of pain </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol (2016) 82 932-942 939 </p>

<p>Our analysis of the pharmacokinetic properties of PEA sug-
gests that the compound has a high volume of distribution. Per-
haps the most intriguing finding was the concentration of label 
in the hypothalamus after oral dosing of PEA tritiated in the acyl 
side chain [31]. It would clearly be of interest to confirm this 
finding and to identify potential novel PEA targets that are pref-
erentially expressed in the hypothalamus. 
With respect to the safety of PEA, our analysis suggests 
that too few patients have been treated for more than 60 days 
to argue that the compound lacks ADRs when given long 
term. This may well turn out to be the case, but further data 
is needed to allow a reasonable risk assessment. 
The clinical studies investigated in detail in the present 
review are of variable quality. In all cases, the authors have 
focused on the change in VAS scores, rather than the propor-
tion of subjects experiencing a reduction in pain to under a 
clinically meaningful cut-off point, although this issue was 
addressed in survival analyses undertaken in the meta-
analysis [21]. Further, comparative studies with current treat-
ments are rare, although in the case of endometriosis, PEA did 
not perform as well as celecoxib [44]. 
The clinical data are clearly promising, but more clinical 
trials are necessary, ideally with publicly available study pro-
tocols. Study size, treatment lengths and choice of scales for 
primary outcome measures are all important considerations 
[48], as well as head-to-head comparisons of unmicronized 
vs. micronized formulations of PEA (in order to determine 
whether or not one formulation is clinically superior to the 
other), and comparisons vs. standard treatments. Given the 
promising data so far accrued with this compound, it is to 
be hoped that these data will be forthcoming. 
After this article was accepted, Andresen et al. [67] have 
reported a well-conducted double-blind multicentre study 
comparing ultramicronised PEA (2 x 600 mg) and placebo as 
add-on treatments in 73 patients with neuropathic pain fol-
lowing spinal cord injury. Over the 12 week period, no supe-
riority over placebo was seen. </p>

<p>Competing Interests </p>

<p>All authors have completed the Unified Competing Interest 
form at www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf (available on re-
quest from the corresponding author) and declare no support 
from any organization for the submitted work, no financial 
relationships with any organizations that might have an 
interest in the submitted work in the previous 3 years and 
no other relationships or activities that could appear to have 
influenced the submitted work. 
The corresponding author thanks the Swedish Science Research 
council (Grant no. 12158) and the Research Funds of the Medical 
Faculty, Umeå University for research support. </p>



<p>L. Gabrielsson et al. </p>





<p>Palmitoylethanolamide for the treatment of pain </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol (2016) 82 932-942 941 </p>



<p>Appendix S1 Further pharmacokinetic analysis of pub-
lished data on PEA 
Appendix S2 Search methodology used in the present 
review </p>

<p>L. Gabrielsson et al. </p>



</text></tei>