<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5018359" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) is considered the leading cause of liver disease worldwide. Although many 
previous studies have evaluated the potential risk factors of NAFLD, few studies have determined the effect of residency or marriage 
status on NAFLD. </p>

<p>Objectives: We aim to evaluate whether residency and marriage status increased the risk factors for NAFLD. 
Materials and Methods: We utilized data from 5,052 participants, 18 years and older, from a cohort study conducted using 6,140 
participants in northern Iran. The population was divided into 16 subgroups according to sex and age; the age groups had an interval 
of 10 years. We randomly selected the subjects from each subgroup in proportion to the size of each subpopulation group. Logistic 
regression analyses were conducted on NAFLD as an outcome of marriage status, residency (rural vs. urban), and other potential 
risk factors. </p>

<p>Results: We found that NAFLD had an inverse association with rural living in men (OR = 0.513, 0.422 -0.622, P value &lt; 0.001) and 
women (OR = 0.431, 0.345 -0.539, P value &lt; 0.001). Furthermore, we determined that NAFLD had a direct association with marriage 
status for men (OR = 2.770, 2.004 -3.831, P value &lt; 0.001) and women (OR = 1.241, 1.033 -1.490, P value = 0.0209). </p>

<p>Conclusions: While rural living has a protective effect on NAFLD, marriage may be a potential risk factor for this condition. </p>

<p>Keywords: Rural Living, Marriage, NAFLD </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) is considered 
the leading cause of liver disease worldwide (1). NAFLD is 
comprised of a wide spectrum of liver pathologies, from 
simple steatosis to non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH). 
NAFLD can lead to liver cirrhosis and even hepatocellular 
carcinoma (HCC) (2). The prevalence of this condition has 
been estimated to be 20% -30% in western countries, and 
there is an increasing trend in low-and middle-income 
countries (1, 3). The increasing prevalence of NAFLD is at-
tributable to the increasing incidence of obesity, diabetes 
mellitus, metabolic syndrome (MetS), and other metabolic 
conditions (4, 5). Studies have been conducted to deter-
mine the prevalence and associated risk factors of NAFLD. 
Based on these studies, an association was established be-
tween NAFLD and age, obesity, blood pressure (BP), dyslipi-
demia, and insulin resistance (6, 7). However, to the knowl-
edge of the authors, only a few studies have evaluated the 
effect of residency and marriage status on NAFLD. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>The present study was conducted to evaluate the risk 
factors of NAFLD associated with residency and marriage. </p>

<p>3. Materials and Methods </p>

<p>3.1. Study Population </p>

<p>In the present study, we used data from 5,052 partici-
pants, who were 18 years and older, who were part of a co-
hort study of 6,140 participants in Amol, which is a popu-
lated city in Northern Iran. The cohort study involved in-
dividuals who were between the ages of 10 -90 years. The 
primary health care settings provided the sampling frame 
since each citizen had a health record. The participants 
were divided into 16 subgroups according to sex and age; 
each age group had an interval of 10 years. We randomly 
selected the subjects from each subgroup in proportion to 
the size of each subpopulation group. More details of the 
sampling strategy used in our cohort study were provided </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016, Kowsar Corp. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial usages, provided the original work is properly 
cited. </p>

<p>Motamed N et al. </p>

<p>in our previous study (8). Figure 1 shows a schematic dia-
gram of how the study population was chosen. </p>

<p>3.2. Data Collection </p>

<p>Trained healthcare providers measured the weight, 
height, waist circumference (WC), hip circumference (HC), 
and blood pressure (BP) of each participant. Weight and 
height measurements were taken once the participants 
had removed excess clothes and shoes. Height was mea-
sured when the participant was in an upright position, 
with the heels and buttocks in contact with the wall. WC 
was determined at the midpoint of the distance between 
the lowest costal ridge and the upper border of the iliac 
crest. The largest circumference between the waist and 
knee was measured for the HC. Following at least 5 min of 
rest, the BP was measured using a fitted cuff while the par-
ticipant was in a sitting position. Both the diastolic blood 
pressure (DBP) and the systolic blood pressure (SBP) were 
recorded. 
After 12 hours of fasting, levels of fasting blood sugar 
(FBS) and lipid profiles were evaluated for each participant. 
All laboratory tests, including FBS and lipid profiles, were 
assessed enzymatically based on a protocol using an auto-
matic BS-200 analyzer (Mindray, China). 
NAFLD was determined using evidence of hepatic 
steatosis shown in a sonogram where there was a lack of ev-
idence of other causes of acute or chronic hepatitis, such as 
significant alcohol consumption, use of steatogenic medi-
cation, or hereditary disorders. A single radiologist carried 
out all ultrasound examinations. Using the ultrasound 
method to detect NAFLD has some limitations since it is op-
erator and machine dependent; it is also limited in its use 
to detect steatosis in obese patients and in those patients 
with an excess of gas in the intestine (9). The homeostasis 
model assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) was cal-
culated according to the following equation (Equation 1): </p>

<p>HOMA − IR = 
(Insulin(mU/mL) × Glucose(mg/dL)) 
405 </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>3.3. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The logistic regression analyses were conducted sepa-
rately for men and women for NAFLD as an outcome. The 
potential predictors that were used in the analyses were: 
age, marriage (married vs. unmarried), residency (rural 
vs. urban), smoking (smoking vs. non-smoking), obesity 
(obese vs. non-obese), blood pressure (high BP vs. low), 
triglyceride (high TG vs. low), and high-density lipoprotein 
(low HDL vs. high). The obesity, high BP, high TG, and low 
HDL were defined based on a joint interim statement def-
inition of MetS (10). The Wald test, significant levels, and </p>

<p>odd ratios (OR) were reported. Univariate and multivariate 
analyses were performed for the logistic regressions. All 
statistical analyses were conducted using statistical soft-
ware (SPSS Inc., version 21, Chicago, IL and <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> software, 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 12</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp</rs>, Texas, US). The significant levels in all 
analyses were considered to be 0.05. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>Table 1 shows the basic characteristics of the study pop-
ulation based on residency. While the rural people had a 
higher WC, SBP, AST, FBS, HDL, and HOMA, the urban people 
had a higher DBP. 
Table 2 shows the basic characteristics of the study pop-
ulation based on marriage status. Based on our results, 
married people had a higher mean age, WC, DBP, GGT, ALT, 
FBS, and TG, but a lower HDL than unmarried people did. 
Table 3 shows the results of the univariate and multi-
variate binary logistic regressions. In these analyses, the 
NAFLD was considered to be the outcome variable. NAFLD 
had a direct association with marriage status in men (OR = 
2.770 (2.004 -3.831), P value &lt; 0.001) and women (OR = 1.241 
(1.033 -1.490), P value = 0.0209), and an inverse association 
with living in rural areas for men (OR = 0.513 (0.422 -0.622), 
P value &lt; 0.001) and women (OR = 0.431 (0.345 -0.539), P 
value &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>Our study revealed that rural living has a protective ef-
fect on NAFLD in men and women. This result was con-
firmed in both the univariate analyses and the multivari-
ate analyses. We showed that the prevalence of NAFLD is 
significantly lower in people who live in rural areas than 
in urban areas. One study in China showed that the preva-
lence of NAFLD was considerably lower in people who lived 
in rural areas (12.9%) compared with people in urban areas 
(23%) (11). Urbanization is related to unhealthy lifestyles, 
which likely played a critical role in the high prevalence 
of NAFLD in the urban areas. Previous studies showed that 
the levels of urbanization also played a critical role in the 
prevalence of NAFLD. Local economic status, social perfor-
mances, and cultural practices, such as the consumption 
of a healthy diet, regular exercise, and even living in areas 
with a healthy environment, can have an effect on health-
related practices (12). Other studies showed that living in 
an urban area of Iran is usually associated with a higher 
prevalence of psychological disorders (13). On the other 
hand, psychological disorders have a significant associa-
tion with NAFLD, although this association may be partly 
due to the consumption of anti-psychological medications </p>

<p> 
Hepat Mon. 2016; 16(7):e38357. </p>

<p>Motamed N et al. </p>



<p>in the Study </p>

<p>7104 Subjects Aged 10 -90 Years Were </p>

<p>Selected to Participate in the Cohort </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>6296 Subjects Agree 
153 Pregnant Women Were Excluded </p>

<p>6143 Subjects 10 -90 Years Were 
Included in the Cohort Study 
346 Subjects &lt;18 Were Excluded </p>

<p>5797 subjects of cohort study were </p>

<p>≥18 years </p>

<p>The Data of 259 Subjects Were Not </p>

<p>Appropriate to Analyze for the Present </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>5311 Subjects Were Included in the </p>

<p>Present Study </p>

<p>486 Subjects Were Excluded Due to a </p>

<p>History of Excess alcohol Consumption, a </p>

<p>Positive Test of HBsAg and Anti HCV Ab </p>

<p>and Regularly Consumption of Drugs </p>

<p>Associated with Fatty Liver Disease </p>

<p>Finally the Data of 5052 Subjects Were </p>

<p>Analyzed </p>

<p>Figure 1. A Schematic Diagram of the Study Participants and Exclusions </p>

<p>Table 1. The Basic Characteristics of the Study Population Based on Residency a </p>

<p>Residency 
P Value </p>

<p>Variables 
Urban (n = 2611) 
Rural (n = 2441) </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>44.26 ± 16.0 
44.25 ± 16.43 </p>

<p>0.674 </p>

<p>WC </p>

<p>90.50 ± 13.12 
91.76 ± 12.42 </p>

<p>0.0002 </p>

<p>DBP </p>

<p>78.07 ± 12.68 
74.34 ± 12.76 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>SBP </p>

<p>116.07 ± 16.31 
117.07 ± 16.92 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>GGT </p>

<p>27.93 ± 20.10 
28.28 ± 29.03 </p>

<p>0.6609 </p>

<p>ALT </p>

<p>23.31 ± 16.22 
23.66 ± 18.55 </p>

<p>0.4404 </p>

<p>AST </p>

<p>21.73 ± 11.98 
22.80 ± 11.24 </p>

<p>0.0005 </p>

<p>FBS </p>

<p>99.99 ± 35.66 
101.96 ± 35.05 </p>

<p>0.0348 </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>141.28 ± 96.71 
146.13 ± 97.86 </p>

<p>0.0668 </p>

<p>HDL </p>

<p>43.66 ± 11.40 
45.72 ± 12.17 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>HOMA </p>

<p>2.05 ± 2.06 
2.81 ± 2.22 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Prevalence and Percent </p>

<p>NAFLD </p>

<p>Men 
43.06 (40.58 -45.54) 
37.50 (35.23 -39.77) 
0.0012 </p>

<p>Women 
47.68 (45.12 -50.24) 
39.31 (36.35 -42.27) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Unmarried people 
20.07 (18.63 -21.50) 
15.82 (14.47 -17.17) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Smoking 
12.70 (11.50 -13.90) 
16.40 (15.03 -17.77) 
0.0001 </p>

<p>a Values are expressed as mean ± SD. </p>

<p>by psychiatric patients (14). Some studies have pointed 
out the role that vitamin D deficiency has on NAFLD (14). </p>

<p>Surveys in northern Iran have reported that there was a 
higher prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in an urban area </p>

<p>Hepat Mon. 2016; 16(7):e38357. </p>

<p>
Motamed N et al. </p>

<p>Table 2. The Basic Characteristics of the Study Population Based on Marriage Status a </p>

<p>Marriage Status 
P Value </p>

<p>Variables 
Unmarried (n = 910) 
Married (n = 4142) </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>29.38 ± 16.00 
47.62 ± 14.28 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>WC </p>

<p>83.24 ± 13.59 
92.836 ± 11.95 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>DBP </p>

<p>75.01 ± 13.43 </p>

<p>77.58± 13.81 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>SBP </p>

<p>111.91 ± 15.61 
115.25 ± 16.86 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>GGT </p>

<p>22.73 ± 13.74 
29.30 ± 27.86 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>ALT </p>

<p>21.97 ± 17.01 
23.81 ± 17.46 </p>

<p>0.0019 </p>

<p>AST </p>

<p>22.06 ± 11.06 
22.29 ± 11.77 </p>

<p>0.5637 </p>

<p>FBS </p>

<p>93.68 ± 25.42 </p>

<p>102.55 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>115.23 ± 64.31 
149.44 ± 101.79 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>HDL </p>

<p>45.90 ± 11.43 
44.41 ± 11.91 </p>

<p>0.0003 </p>

<p>HOMA </p>

<p>2.38 ± 1.99 
2.43 ± 2.21 </p>

<p>0.4875 </p>

<p>Prevalence and Percent </p>

<p>NAFLD </p>

<p>Men 
15.58 (12.75 -18.41) 
45.88 (43.98 -47.78) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Women 
25.84 (21.63 -30.06) 
47.83 (45.69 -49.96) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Smoking 
5.76 (4.34 -7.17) 
16.40 (15.34 -17.45) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>a Values are expressed as mean ± SD. </p>

<p>of northern Iran than in a rural area (15). These results sup-
port our findings about the protective effects of living in 
rural areas on NAFLD (15, 16). </p>

<p>We also showed that marriage has a high association 
with NAFLD in men. Thus, it can be considered to be 
a potential risk factor for NAFLD. However, there was a 
weak association between marriage and NAFLD detected in 
women. The association between marriage and NAFLD can 
be partly mediated by other risk factors for NAFLD, such as 
age, WC, BP, FBS, and TG. For example, the mean age, WC, 
SBP, DBP, FBS, and TG were significantly higher in married 
people than in unmarried people, although married peo-
ple had a lower HDL. However, this association was present 
in the multivariate analyses where we removed the effects 
of the other mediators, although the association was some-
what weaker than in the univariate analyses. </p>

<p>Although previous studies have found that marriage 
had a protective effect on all case mortality, other studies 
have reported inconsistent results about the role of mar-
riage on overall health (16-20). Some authors suggested 
that the beneficial effects that marriage has on health have 
been diluted because of industrialization and moderniza-
tion (20, 21). On the other hand, an overestimation of 
health by married people might help explain the previ-
ously reported positive effect that marriage has on health </p>

<p>(19). Overall, industrialization, urbanization, and mod-
ernization have negative effects on marital quality, family 
functioning, and spouse support, which can explain the di-
minishing protection that marriage has on health (19, 20). 
In developing countries, married people, particularly mar-
ried men, who have financial problems and household ex-
penses have less interests in engaging in healthy behav-
iors, including appropriate nutrition, regular exercise, and 
timely visits to physicians and other healthcare providers. 
Many married men may have two or even three jobs to earn 
their livelihood. They generally do not have enough time 
to exercise or perform other pleasurable activities. They 
may not eat an appropriate breakfast or eat other meals at 
an appropriate time. </p>

<p>In this study, we showed that rural living has a protec-
tive effect on NAFLD, while marriage can be a potential risk 
factor for NAFLD. Our results contrast with previous stud-
ies about the positive role that marriage plays in health. 
Although, the risk factors of NAFLD have been evaluated in 
previous studies, few studies have assessed the association 
between residency and marriage status with NAFLD. How-
ever, the present study had some limitations. We evaluated 
the associations in a cross-sectional study, which is not an 
optimal design for establishing cause-and-effect relation-
ships. However, we did evaluate the associations in a large </p>

<p> 
Hepat Mon. 2016; 16(7):e38357. </p>

<p>Motamed N et al. </p>

<p>Table 3. The Results of Univariate and Multivariate Logistic Regression Analyses </p>

<p>Methods 
Univariate 
Multivariate </p>

<p>Potential Predictors 
Wald 
OR (CI) 
P Value 
Wald 
OR (CI) 
P Value </p>

<p>Men (n = 1659) </p>

<p>Age 
110.69 
1.023 (1.019 -1.028) 
&lt; 0.0001 
1.97 
1.005 (0.998 -1.012) 
0.1599 </p>

<p>Marriage (married vs. unmarried) 
162.428 
4.273 (3.425 -5.347) 
&lt; 0.0001 
37.943 
2.770 (2.004 -3.831) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Residency (rural vs. urban) 
10.50 
0.793 (0.690 -0.913) 
0.0012 
45.47 
0.513 (0.422 -0.622) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Smoker vs. non-smoker 
1.87 
0.893 (0.759 -1.050) 
0.1711 
4.07 
0.805 (0.652 -0.994) 
0.0437 </p>

<p>WC (obese vs. non-obese) 
766.20 
13.912 (11.546 -16.763) 
&lt; 0.0001 
363.34 
7.859 (6.358 -9.715) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>BP (high vs. low) 
138.23 
2.451 (2.111 -2.847) 
&lt; 0.0001 
5.25 
1.257 (1.034 -1.528) 
0.0219 </p>

<p>TG (high vs. low) 
209.93 
3.139 (2.689 -3.665) 
&lt; 0.0001 
18.96 
1.580 (1.286 -1.942) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>HDL (low vs. high) 
133.04 
2.362 (2.041 -2.734) 
&lt; 0.0001 
2.40 
1.169 (0.959 -1.423) 
0.1215 </p>

<p>HOMA 
249.88 
1.537 (1.457 -1.621) 
&lt;0.0001 
91.33 
1.383 (1.294 -1.478) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Women (n = 1314) </p>

<p>Age 
353.44 
1.061 (1.055 -1.068) 
&lt;0.0001 
88.50 
1.038 (1.030 -1.047) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Marriage (married vs. unmarried) 
15.69 
1.346 (1.161 -1.558) 
&lt; 0.0001 
5.33 
1.241 (1.033 -1.490) 
0.0209 </p>

<p>Residency (rural vs. urban) 
17.30 
0.711 (0.605 -0.835) 
&lt; 0.0001 
54.26 
0.431 (0.345 -0.539) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Smoker vs. non-smoker 
0.22 
1.264 (0.473 -3.378) 
0.6407 
0.15 
0.756 (0.188 -3.063) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>WC (obese vs. non-obese) 
567.84 
11.802 (9.634 -14.458) 
&lt; 0.0001 
229.40 
6.233 (4.919 -7.899) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>BP (high vs. low) 
151.06 
3.009 (2.524 -3.587) 
&lt; 0.0001 
4.69 
1.288 (1.024 -1.619) 
0.0303 </p>

<p>TG (high vs. low) 
220.66 
4.034 (3.356 -4.848) 
&lt; 0.0001 
31.95 
1.954 (1.549 -2.464) 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>HDL (low vs. high) 
98.10 
2.407 (2.023 -2.864) 
&lt; 0.0001 
3.67 
1.253 (0.995 -1.577) 
0.0553 </p>

<p>HOMA 
161.23 
1.301 (1.242 -1.363) 
&lt; 0.0001 
43.29 
1.217 (1.148 -1.290) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>community based on a cohort study data, which can pro-
duce reliable results. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors would like to express their gratitude 
to: Iran University Medical Sciences for supporting this 
project; staff and management of Hefdah Shahrivar hospi-
tal, Amol, Iran, for their cooperation; and to the members 
of the Amol cohort study center. </p>

<p>Footnotes </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution: Nima Motamed: study con-
cept and design; analyses and interpretation of data; and 
prepared drafts of the manuscript; Mansooreh Maadi: 
acquisition of data; and administrative, technical, and 
material support; Masoudreza Sohrabi: acquisition of 
data; prepared drafts of the manuscript; and revised 
the manuscript; Hossein Keyvani: critical revision of the 
manuscript for important intellectual content; Hossein </p>

<p>Poustchi: critical revision of the manuscript for important 
intellectual content; Farhad Zamani: critical revision of 
the manuscript; study supervision manuscript; and study 
supervision. </p>

<p>Funding/Support: The study was supported by GILDRC. </p>



<p>Hepat Mon. 2016; 16(7):e38357. </p>

<p>
Motamed N et al. </p>



<p> 
Hepat Mon. 2016; 16(7):e38357. </p>

</text></tei>