<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5135399" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To compare patient's perception of consent quality, clinical and quality-of-life 
outcomes after laser vision correction (LVC) and refractive lens exchange (RLE) between 
patients who met their treating surgeon prior to the day of surgery (PDOS) or on the day of 
surgery (DOS). 
Design: Retrospective, comparative case series. 
Setting: Optical Express, Glasgow, UK. 
Methods: Patients treated between October 2015 and June 2016 (3972 LVC and 979 RLE 
patients) who attended 1-day and 1-month postoperative aftercare and answered a question-
naire were included in this study. All patients had a thorough preoperative discussion with an 
optometrist, watched a video consent, and were provided with written information. Patients then 
had a verbal discussion with their treating surgeon either PDOS or on the DOS, according to 
patient preference. Preoperative and 1-month postoperative visual acuity, refraction, preopera-
tive, 1-day and 1-month postoperative questionnaire were compared between DOS and PDOS 
patients. Multivariate regression model was developed to find factors associated with patient's 
perception of consent quality. 
Results: Preoperatively, 8.0% of LVC and 17.1% of RLE patients elected to meet their sur-
geon ahead of the surgery day. In the LVC group, 97.5% of DOS and 97.2% of PDOS patients 
indicated they were properly consented for surgery (P=0.77). In the RLE group, 97.0% of DOS 
and 97.0% of PDOS patients stated their consent process for surgery was adequate (P=0.98). 
There was no statistically significant difference between DOS and PDOS patients in most of 
the postoperative clinical or questionnaire outcomes. Factors predictive of patient's satisfaction 
with consent quality were postoperative satisfaction with vision (46.7% of explained variance), 
difficulties with night driving, close-up vision or outdoor/sports activities (25.4%), visual phe-
nomena (12.2%), dry eyes (7.5%), and patient's satisfaction with surgeon's care (8.2%). 
Conclusion: Perception of quality of consent was comparable between patients that elected 
to meet the surgeon PDOS, and those who did not. 
Prior to elective surgery, patients need to be adequately informed of the benefits and 
inherent risks of the proposed treatment, possible outcomes, as well as surgical and 
nonsurgical alternatives to the recommended procedure. 
1,2 As the number of procedures 
and their degree of technical complexity grow, delivering the correct information to the 
patient is becoming increasingly difficult. On one hand, patients should be informed in 
detail about their surgical procedure; on the other hand, overloading patients with too 
much technical/medical information may have unintended negative effects by confusing </p>

<p>Correspondence: steven C schallhorn 
gordon schanzlin new Vision institute, 
8910 University Center lane, suite 800, 
la Jolla, san Diego, Ca 92122, Usa 
Tel +1 858 455 6800 
email scschallhorn@yahoo.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Ophthalmology 
28 November 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2392 </p>

<p>schallhorn et al </p>

<p>patients, reducing their ability to retain information, and 
impairing their ability to provide an informed decision. </p>

<p>1-3   Inadequate consenting process (combined with poor out-
comes) is one of the most common reasons for malpractice 
litigation in ophthalmology. 
4-8 This problem is particularly 
hard to overcome, as many publications have shown that very 
little information presented during informed consent is actually 
retained by the patient. 
9-13 For this reason, numerous reports have 
studied the best way of communicating essential information to 
the patient. 
1-3 This includes verbal discussion, use of videotaped 
presentation, and use of leaflets and written consent forms, 
allowing patients to digest information at their own pace. </p>

<p>14-17   In elective refractive surgery, such as laser vision cor-
rection (LVC), refractive lens exchange (RLE), or private 
cataract surgery, one of the issues is the role of the treat-
ing surgeon in the consent process, and whether medical 
personnel other than the treating physician can assist in 
the delivery of a high-quality and meaningful preoperative 
consent process. The ability to discuss a surgical procedure 
with patients of different backgrounds and different cognitive 
abilities can vary significantly from surgeon to surgeon. </p>

<p>15-18   In some cases, the physician's inability to explain a proce-
dure in "plain language" results in poor understanding of the 
planned procedure, or an emotional barrier where patients 
might be reluctant or embarrassed to ask further questions. </p>

<p>16   Several clinical practices over the world have adopted a 
model where the preoperative discussion is performed by 
qualified clinical personnel, 
19,20 with the aid of other tools, 
such as a video consent, 
16,17 and/or plain-language written 
information, 
14,17 with the intent to provide a uniform and 
thorough consent process. In this model, consent is a multi-
step process culminating with the surgeon. 
The aim of the study was to investigate whether there 
was a difference in patient perception of their consent qual-
ity, clinical outcomes, and satisfaction after LVC and RLE 
between patients who met their treating surgeon on the day 
of surgery (DOS) and those who chose to have a discussion 
with the surgeon prior to the day of surgery (PDOS). </p>

<p>Patients and methods </p>

<p>This study was deemed exempt from full review by the 
Committee on Human Research at the University of California, 
San Francisco (CA, USA), because it used only retrospective, 
de-identified patient data. Informed consent to undergo laser 
in situ keratomileusis (LASIK), photorefractive keratectomy 
(PRK) or RLE procedure was obtained from all patients. All 
patients also provided consent to use their de-identified treat-
ment data for research purposes and statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Refractive and visual outcomes and postoperative patient 
questionnaire outcomes were extracted from electronic data-
base for patients who underwent LVC (3,972 patients) and 
RLE (979 patients) between October 2015 and June 2016. 
The inclusion criteria were corrected distance visual acuity 
20/25 or better in each eye, attended 1 day and 1 month 
postoperative aftercare, and completed a patient experience 
questionnaire at both visits. 
All patients underwent a preoperative consultation with an 
optometrist who was well instructed in the refractive surgery 
process. This consisted of a discussion as well as an examina-
tion and diagnostic testing. The discussion included assessing 
medical and ocular history, medications, employment, hob-
bies, lifestyle, refractive correction history, motivation for, 
and expectations of, refractive surgery. The examination con-
sisted of a manifest and cycloplegic refraction, uncorrected 
(UDVA) and corrected distance visual acuity (CDVA), exter-
nal ocular exam, ocular motility, confrontational visual fields, 
pupil diameter, detailed biomicroscopic exam (conjunctiva, 
tear film, cornea, anterior chamber, iris, crystalline lens), 
dilated fundoscopy (macula, optic nerve, and retinal periph-
ery), and diagnostic tests (corneal topography: Pentacam; 
Oculus Optikgeräte GmbH, Wetzlar, Germany; wavefront 
aberrometry: iDesign Advanced WaveScan System; Abbott 
Medical Optics Inc., Santa Ana, CA, USA; autorefraction 
and non-contact tonometry: Tonoref II, Nidek Co. Ltd., 
Gamagori, Japan). If there were any unresolved issues, the 
patients were either scheduled for a follow-up examination 
or an appointment with the treating surgeon. 
Based on the consultation, the optometrist determined 
whether the patient was a suitable candidate for refractive 
surgery and proposed a procedure (LVC or RLE) to best meet 
the patient's needs. This was followed by a discussion of the 
benefits, risks, side effects, healing process, and alternatives 
as well as addressing any patient questions or concerns. The 
patient was provided an information pack consisting of a copy 
of the informed consent document, written information about 
the procedure, preparation for the surgery day, and informa-
tion on what to expect on the day of surgery and after the 
procedure. All patients watched an educational video, which 
reiterated the benefits, risks, and possible side effects of the 
proposed surgery. Patients who were candidates for RLE 
were required to attend another consultation where further 
measurements (biometry for lens calculation: IOLMaster; 
Carl Zeiss Meditec AG, Jena, Germany; retinal optical coher-
ence tomography: Cirrus 4000 OCT, Carl Zeiss Meditec AG; 
and specular microscopy: SP 2000P specular microscope; 
Topcon, Co., Tokyo, Japan) were performed. These patients </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2393 </p>

<p>Consent process for elective refractive surgery </p>

<p>had another detailed discussion with the optometrist about 
the choice of multifocal lenses and optical side effects. 
All patients, if they desired to proceed with surgery, were 
encouraged to see their treating surgeon PDOS; this visit 
was made freely available to all who desired to schedule 
it and was without cost. Those who elected not to see their 
surgeon PDOS had a consultation with their surgeon prior 
to the procedure but on the DOS. In both cases, the surgeon 
confirmed the patient was suitable for the procedure and 
ensured they provided their informed consent. The consum-
mation of the consent process was the signing of the written 
consent document by the patient and surgeon. 
Postoperatively, patients were evaluated at 1 day, 
1 week, 1 month, and 3 months and thereafter, as neces-
sary. All patients were asked to complete a postoperative 
questionnaire. It was self-administered by the patient using 
a password-protected and secure computer terminal in an 
isolated area of the clinic and not accessible to any clinic </p>

<p>personnel. The results of this questionnaire were not made 
available to their treating physician, and patients were 
informed of this to ensure that they knew that they had 
total confidentiality in their responses. The questionnaire 
responses were stored in the secured central database, which 
is compliant with ISO 27001 for information security man-
agement systems. All response fields used a Likert scale 
to obtain the patient's preferences or degree of agreement. 
Questionnaires completed at postoperative day 1 and on 
1 month postoperative visit were used for analysis (Table 1). 
A total of 78% of LVC patients and 81.2% of RLE patients 
also completed a preoperative questionnaire where they rated 
degree of difficulties with visual phenomena and dry eye 
symptoms (Question 7 from Table 1) with spectacle/contact 
lens correction preoperatively. The mean difference between 
preoperative and postoperative scores was used for analysis. 
All questionnaire outcomes were compared between patients 
who met the surgeon PDOS and DOS. </p>

<p>Table 1 Patient experience questionnaire </p>

<p>Postoperative day 1 questionnaire </p>

<p>Question 1. Overall how satisfied are you with the care that was provided by the surgeon? 
(1= very satisfied, 2= satisfied, 3= neither, 4= dissatisfied, 5= very dissatisfied) 
Question 2. Overall how satisfied are you that the surgeon answered all of your questions? 
(1= very satisfied, 2= satisfied, 3= neither, 4= dissatisfied, 5= very dissatisfied) 
Question 3. Did you find the patient information folder that contained your consent form and other information useful and informative? 
(1= Yes, 2= No) 
One-month postoperative questionnaire 
Question 4. Do you feel you were properly consented for surgery? 
(1= Yes, 2= No) 
Question 5. Thinking about your vision during the last week, how satisfied are you with your vision? (without the use of glasses or contact 
lenses)? 
(1= very satisfied, 2= satisfied, 3= neither, 4= dissatisfied, 5= very dissatisfied) 
Question 6. Would you recommend vision correction surgery to your friends and relatives? 
(1= Yes, 2= No) 
Question 7. Think about your vision during the last week. Please rate the degree of difficulty you experienced with: 
• Starburst 
• glare 
• halos 
• Ghosting/double vision 
• Dry eyes 
(Measured on discrete scale from 1= no difficulty to 7= severe difficulty) 
Question 8. Because of your eyesight, how much difficulty do you have with driving at night? 
(1= no difficulty, 2= a little difficulty, 3= moderate difficulty, 4= a lot of difficulty, 5= never try to do this because of my vision, 6= never do this for 
other reasons) 
Question 9. Because of your eyesight, how much difficulty do you have doing work or hobbies that require you to see well up close, such as 
cooking, fixing things around the house, sewing, using hand tools, or working with a computer? 
(1= no difficulty, 2= a little difficulty, 3= moderate difficulty, 4= a lot of difficulty, 5= never try to do this because of my vision, 6= never do this for 
other reasons) 
Question 10. Because of your eyesight, how much difficulty do you have taking part in active sports or other outdoor activities that you enjoy (like 
hiking, swimming, aerobics, team sports, or jogging)? 
(1= no difficulty, 2= a little difficulty, 3= moderate difficulty, 4= a lot of difficulty, 5= never try to do this because of my vision, 6= never do this for 
other reasons) </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2394 </p>

<p>schallhorn et al </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data tabulation and statistical operations were performed with 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute, Inc</rs>., Cary, NC, USA) and <rs id="software-2" type="software">Microsoft Office Excel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">7.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Microsoft Corporation</rs>, Redmond, WA, 
USA) software. Unpaired t-test was used to compare clinical 
data and questionnaire outcomes between patients who had 
met their surgeon on DOS and PDOS. Chi-square test was 
used to compare percentages. 
Multivariate regression model was developed to find fac-
tors predictive of the outcomes of the Question 4 (Table 1): 
"Do you feel you were properly consented for surgery?" 
Stepwise generalized linear approach to the model creation 
was used, and patient's demographics, clinical parameters 
as well as other questionnaire responses were considered 
as independent variables in the regression model. Standard 
assumptions required for the use of a multivariate regression 
model approach were tested and satisfied. Although differ-
ent data transformations were explored, a linear relationship 
between the dependent and independent variables was deemed 
to be the most appropriate. Normality of all variables was 
tested and confirmed using Q-Q plots. A correlation matrix 
was used to conclude that there was little to no multicol-
linearity and independence was confirmed. An assumption of 
homoscedasticity was determined to be met using a White test 
to measure the homogeneity of variance of the residuals. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Eight percent (8.0%) of LVC patients and 17.1% of RLE 
patients elected to meet their surgeon PDOS. Tables 2 
(LVC) and 3 (RLE) compare preoperative and 1-month </p>

<p>postoperative clinical parameters between patients who have 
met their surgeon on the DOS and PDOS. There was no 
statistically significant difference in patient demographics or 
clinical parameters between DOS and PDOS patients, apart 
from a tiny (0.03 D), but statistically significant, difference 
in postoperative cylinder between DOS and PDOS patients 
in LVC group (Table 2). </p>

<p>Postoperative day 1 questionnaire </p>

<p>On the first postoperative day, an equal proportion of DOS 
and PDOS LVC patients (99.4%) stated they were satisfied 
or very satisfied with the care provided by their surgeon 
(Question 1 from Table 1). For the same question, 99.4% of 
RLE DOS and 98.8% of RLE PDOS patients (P=0.42) were 
satisfied/very satisfied with surgeon's care. 
The vast majority of patients in the LVC group (98.8% 
DOS patients vs 99.4% PDOS; P=0.37) and RLE group 
(99.1% DOS and 98.8% PDOS; P=0.68) were satisfied or 
very satisfied with their surgeon answering all their questions 
(Question 2). Additionally, 98.0% DOS and 98.7% PDOS 
LVC patients (P=0.36) and 97.5% DOS and 98.8% PDOS 
RLE patients (P=0.32) felt the preoperative written informa-
tion, including consent form, was useful and informative 
(Question 3). </p>

<p>One-month postoperative questionnaire </p>

<p>In the LVC group, 97.5% of DOS patients and 97.2% of 
PDOS patients indicated they were properly consented 
for surgery (Question 4; P=0.77). Similar outcomes were 
achieved in RLE group: 97.0% of DOS and 97.0% of PDOS </p>

<p>Table 2 Preoperative and 1-month postoperative clinical outcomes of laser vision correction patients </p>

<p>Surgeon-patient consent 
discussion on the DOS </p>

<p>Surgeon-patient consent 
discussion PDOS </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Number of patients (eyes) 
3,653 (7,004) 
319 (611) 
-
Male/female ratio 
53.0%/47.0% 
50.2%/49.8% 
0.32 
age, mean ± SD (range) 
35.2±11.0 (18-68) 
35.9±11.7 (18-76) 
0.15 
Preoperative data 
Sphere (D), mean ± SD (range) 
-2.27±2.40 (-11.0 to +5.00) 
-2.32±2.53 (-10.50 to 3.75) 
0.57 
Cylinder (D), mean ± SD (range) 
-0.79±0.75 (-5.75 to 0.00) 
-0.81±0.80 (-5.00 to 0.00) 
0.46 
MSE (D), mean ± SD (range) 
-2.66±2.41 (-11.13 to +4.88) 
-2.73±2.53 (-5.00 to 0.00) 
0.50 
CDVa [logMar], mean ± SD (range) 
-0.07±0.05 (-0.18 to 0.10) 
-0.07±0.05 (-0.18 to 0.10) 
0.12 
1-month postoperative data 
Sphere (D), mean ± SD (range) 
0.03±0.51 (-4.25 to +2.25) 
0.02±0.57 (-3.5 to +1.75) 
0.46 
Cylinder (D), mean ± SD (range) 
-0.20±0.27 (-2.50 to 0.00) 
-0.23±0.29 (-1.75 to 0.00) 
0.002 
MSE (D), mean ± SD (range) 
-0.07±0.53 (-5.25 to +2.00) 
-0.10±0.59 (-3.50 to +1.38) 
0.14 
CDVa [logMar], mean ± SD (range) 
-0.09±0.06 (-0.30 to 0.52) 
-0.08±0.06 (-0.18 to 0.10) 
0.11 
Monocular UDVa [logMar], mean ± SD (range) 
-0.03±0.18 (-0.18 to 2.00) 
-0.02±0.19 (-0.18 to 1.30) 
0.06 
Binocular UDVa [logMar], mean ± SD (range) 
-0.10±0.08 (-0.30 to 0.60) 
-0.10±0.07 (-0.18 to 0.48) 
0.20 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: DOs, day of surgery; PDOs, prior to the day of surgery; sD, standard deviation; Mse, manifest spherical equivalent; CDVa, corrected distance visual acuity; 
UDVa, uncorrected distance visual acuity. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2395 </p>

<p>Consent process for elective refractive surgery </p>

<p>patients stated their consent process for surgery was adequate 
(P=0.98). 
Figure 1 shows the satisfaction with visual acuity 
(Question 5). One month postoperatively, 93.6% of DOS 
and 94.4% of PDOS LVC patients were satisfied or very 
satisfied with their vision. For RLE patients, the percentage 
of satisfied or very satisfied patients was 88.7% DOS and 
88.6% PDOS. Satisfaction with vision was not statistically </p>

<p>significant between DOS and PDOS patients for both, LVC 
and RLE (Figure 1). 
The percentage of patients that would recommend sur-
gery to their friends or relatives (Question 6) was 96.5% 
and 97.8% for LVC DOS and PDOS patients, respectively 
(P=0.22). Of the RLE patients 95.3% of DOS and 93.4% 
of PDOS patients responded affirmative to Question 6 
(P=0.30). </p>

<p>Table 3 Preoperative and 1-month postoperative clinical outcomes of refractive lens exchange patients </p>

<p>Surgeon-patient consent 
discussion on the DOS </p>

<p>Surgeon-patient consent 
discussion PDOS </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Number of patients (eyes) 
812 (1,601) 
167 (332) 
-
Male/female ratio 
55.3%/44.7% 
51.5%/48.5% 
0.37 
age, mean ± SD (range) 
59.0±7.2 (41-83) 
58.4±8.2 (40-76) 
0.21 
Preoperative data 
Sphere (D), mean ± SD (range) 
+1.62±2.76 (-14.50 to +10.00) 
+1.73±2.57 (-7.00 to +11.00) 
0.51 
Cylinder (D), mean ± SD (range) 
-0.73±0.69 (-6.75 to 0.00) 
-0.71±0.68 (-5.75 to 0.00) 
0.75 
MSE (D), mean ± SD (range) 
+1.26±2.76 (-15.25 to +8.88) 
+1.37±2.61 (-8.00 to +11.00) 
0.49 
CDVa [logMar], mean ± SD (range) 
-0.04±0.06 (-0.18 to 0.10) 
-0.04±0.07 (-0.18 to 0.10) 
0.10 
1-month postoperative data 
Sphere (D), mean ± SD (range) 
-0.08±0.56 (-2.50 to +1.75) 
-0.06±0.59 (-2.25 to +2.25) 
0.61 
Cylinder (D), mean ± SD (range) 
-0.46±0.43 (-3.25 to 0.00) 
-0.48±0.40 (-2.00 to 0.00) 
0.38 
MSE (D), mean ± SD (range) 
-0.31±0.56 (-2.88 to +1.50) 
-0.30±0.57 (-2.38 to +2.00) 
0.85 
CDVa [logMar], mean ± SD (range) 
-0.04±0.07 (-0.18 to 0.70) 
-0.04±0.07 (-0.18 to 0.22) 
0.37 
Monocular UDVa [logMar], mean ± SD (range) 
0.08±0.18 (-0.18 to 1.30) 
0.08±0.17 (-0.18 to 1.00) 
0.80 
Binocular UDVa [logMar], mean ± SD (range) 
-0.02±0.10 (-0.20 to 0.80) 
-0.02±0.10 (-0.18 to 0.40) 
0.80 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: DOs, day of surgery; PDOs, prior to the day of surgery; sD, standard deviation; Mse, manifest spherical equivalent; CDVa, corrected distance visual acuity; 
UDVa, uncorrected distance visual acuity. </p>

<p>Figure 1 One-month postoperative satisfaction with vision compared between patients that met their surgeon on the day of surgery (DOS) and prior to the day of surgery (PDOS). </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2396 </p>

<p>schallhorn et al </p>

<p>Table 4 shows the mean scores for visual phenomena 
and dry eye symptoms (Question 7). The mean postopera-
tive score for starburst, glare, and halo was slightly higher 
in PDOS LVC patients compared to DOS patients, and this 
difference was statistically significant (Table 4). However, 
when comparing change between preoperative and postop-
erative mean score, the change in any of the visual phenom-
ena symptoms was not statistically significant. RLE DOS 
and PDOS had comparable outcomes for visual phenomena 
(Table 4). RLE PDOS had statistically significantly higher 
postoperative dry eye symptoms, but the mean change 
between pre-and postoperative symptoms was not statisti-
cally significant. 
Figure 2A (LVC) and B (RLE) plots the difficulties 
patients experienced with tasks related to night driving, 
close-up vision, outdoor or sport activities (Questions 8-10). 
There was no statistically significant difference between DOS 
and PDOS patients in any of the questioned activities. </p>

<p>Factors associated with patient's 
perception of the quality of their consent </p>

<p>Table 5 summarizes the results of regression analysis to pre-
dict outcomes of question: "Do you feel you were properly 
consented for surgery?" Initially, two individual regression 
models for RLE and LVC were created. As the surgery type, 
age, and refraction were not significant factors in univariate 
analysis, and both models had similar outcomes, RLE and 
LVC data were combined, and only one final regression 
model was created. Additionally, as the incidence of the 
response variable was low (only 2.6% of patients felt not </p>

<p>properly consented for surgery), the two datasets (LVC 
and RLE) were combined to create a larger, more powerful 
sample for regression analysis. 
One-month postoperative satisfaction with their vision 
(Question 5) was the strongest predictor of the patient's per-
ception of consent quality, accounting for 46.7% of variance 
explained by the regression model. As an indication of this 
relationship, Figure 3 shows the proportion of patients who 
were satisfied/dissatisfied with their postoperative vision 
in the group of patients who felt properly consented for 
procedure, and those who believed the consenting process 
was inadequate. As much as 23.7% of "not consented prop-
erly" patients were dissatisfied with vision, whereas only 
2.5% of patients were dissatisfied with vision in the group of 
patients who were happy with their consent process. 
The second strongest predictor in regression analysis 
was the postoperative difficulties patients experienced with 
various activities, such as night driving, tasks requiring 
close-up vision, and outdoor and sports activities (Questions 
8-10), responsible for 25.4% of variance explained by 
the model. Figure 4 shows the percentage of patients who 
had a lot of difficulties or were unable to do the activities 
because of their vision. A significantly higher proportion 
of patients who were dissatisfied with the consent process 
experienced postoperative difficulty with any of these 
activities (Figure 4). 
Postoperative visual phenomena (12.2% variance 
explained) and postoperative dry eye difficulties (7.5% vari-
ance explained) were other significant predictors of satisfac-
tion with consent. Figure 5 depicts the percentages of patients </p>

<p>Table 4 Visual phenomena and dry eyes </p>

<p>Postoperative mean score (mean ± SD) 
Mean difference between postoperative and 
preoperative score (mean ± SD) </p>

<p>Surgeon-patient 
consent discussion 
on the DOS </p>

<p>Surgeon-patient 
consent discussion 
PDOS </p>

<p>P-value Surgeon-patient 
consent discussion 
on the DOS </p>

<p>Surgeon-patient 
consent discussion 
PDOS </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Laser vision correction 
Number of patients 
3,653 
319 
2,863 
237 
Starburst 
1.79±1.25 
1.98±1.49 
0.009 
0.54±1.37 
0.70±1.69 
0.08 
glare 
1.89±1.27 
2.10±1.43 
0.005 
0.58±1.43 
0.72±1.67 
0.15 
halo 
1.76±1.23 
1.92±1.41 
0.003 
0.52±1.34 
0.59±1.56 
0.47 
Ghosting/double vision 
1.36±0.89 
1.39±0.97 
0.67 
0.18±1.03 
0.17±1.14 
0.88 
Dry eyes 
2.07±1.24 
2.09±1.28 
0.85 
0.65±1.43 
0.60±1.47 
0.54 
Refractive lens exchange 
Number of patients 
812 
167 
668 
126 
Starburst 
2.14±1.61 
2.17±1.57 
0.79 
0.85±1.70 
0.84±1.64 
0.97 
glare 
2.20±1.53 
2.24±1.53 
0.74 
0.81±1.66 
0.86±1.69 
0.76 
halo 
2.19±1.60 
2.13±1.58 
0.65 
0.90±1.68 
0.81±1.70 
0.58 
Ghosting/double vision 
1.50±1.08 
1.54±1.17 
0.20 
0.30±1.20 
0.22±1.35 
0.49 
Dry eyes 
1.90±1.24 
2.13±1.35 
0.03 
0.49±1.41 
0.71±1.38 
0.12 </p>

<p>Notes: Each patient rated visual phenomena/dry eye difficulties on scale from 1 (= no difficulty) to 7 (= severe difficulty) and the mean score for all patients was calculated. 
Positive difference between postoperative and preoperative score indicates increase in difficulty with visual phenomena/dry eyes. 
Abbreviations: DOs, day of surgery; PDOs, prior to the day of surgery; sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2397 </p>

<p>Consent process for elective refractive surgery </p>

<p>who had significant difficulties (scored 6 or 7 on a scale from 
1 to 7) with postoperative optical side effects or dry eyes. 
Over 10% of patients who felt not consented properly for their 
procedure had significant difficulties with visual symptoms, 
whereas #2.5% patients had significant difficulties in the 
group of patients who were "consented properly." 
Satisfaction with surgeon's care and the surgeon 
answering all patient's questions (Questions 1 and 2, 8.2% </p>

<p>of variance explained) was also a significant predictor in 
regression analysis. Of all the "consented properly" patients, 
78.0% were very satisfied with surgeon's care, whereas 
only 62.6% of patients were very satisfied within the group 
of "not consented properly" patients. A similar pattern was 
seen in Question 2: 76.2% of "consented properly" patients 
and 62.6% of "not consented properly" patients were very 
satisfied with their surgeon answering all their questions. </p>

<p>Figure 2 One-month postoperative difficulties with night driving, close-up vision, and outdoor/sport activities compared between patients who met their surgeon on the day 
of surgery (DOS) and prior to the day of surgery (PDOS). (A) Laser vision correction patients; (B) Refractive lens exchange patients. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2398 </p>

<p>schallhorn et al </p>

<p>Meeting the surgeon PDOS or DOS had no effect on 
patient's perception of adequate consenting process. A simi-
lar percentage of patients who felt consented properly (9.8%) 
and those who believed consenting process was not appropri-
ate (10.7%) have met their surgeon PDOS (P=0.73). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Patients undergoing private refractive surgery often have 
high expectations and some may find it difficult to accept 
outcomes that are not satisfactory. A robust consent process 
is therefore required to educate the patient and provide them 
with the information they need to make an informed decision 
whether to proceed. Literature agrees that better communica-
tion increases patient satisfaction and reduces the number of 
malpractice suits. </p>

<p>21-23   Verbal communication with the treating physician 
alone, however, does not guarantee that the patient will be 
satisfied with the consenting process. 
14-18 A surgeon's verbal 
discussion cannot be easily standardized, as it is extremely 
patient-directed. 
16,17 Some publications previously have 
highlighted the difficulties in performing consent by treat-
ing ophthalmologist in busy clinical practices. 
14-18 Ophthal-
mologist may need to consent several patients a day, which 
often results in a rote and mechanical discussion that may 
not fully educate the patient. 
15,16 If the preoperative consent 
discussion was performed only by the surgeon, without the </p>

<p>help of other medical personnel or other audio/visual aides, 
a longer appointment time would be needed, which could 
result in a reduced availability of consultations and reduced 
affordability of the procedure. As a result, fewer patients 
may have access to the surgery. 
Another concern, raised by several studies, is the amount 
of information patients can remember from a discussion 
with their surgeon. 
9-13 Guerin and O'Keeffe 
9 studied the 
recollection of information from the consenting process in 
102 patients undergoing laser refractive surgery. DOS, only 
2 patients remembered all five main risks outlined preop-
eratively, whereas 11 patients remembered no risks at all. 
Remaining patients only remembered some of the risks. 
Dhingra and colleagues 
10 questioned 82 patients undergoing 
elective phacoemulsification with intraocular lens implanta-
tion. All patients received standardized verbal and written 
information 2 weeks prior to surgery. Only one-third of the 
patients could correctly recollect the consent information 
DOS. Priluck et al 
11 questioned 100 patients undergoing 
a scleral buckling procedure about their informed consent 
discussion. As little as 23% of patients retained some 
information of the surgical risks, concluding that patients 
are likely to remember only the information that seems to be 
in favor of their decision to have surgery. 
To overcome the problem of poor preoperative discus-
sion recollection, several consenting approaches have been </p>

<p>Table 5 results of multivariate regression analysis to predict outcomes of Question 4: "Do you feel you were properly consented 
for surgery?" </p>

<p>Independent variable 
Univariate 
P-value </p>

<p>Multivariate 
P-value </p>

<p>Model 
contribution </p>

<p>age at treatment 
0.01* 
.0.05 
-</p>

<p>gender 
.0.05 
-
-</p>

<p>surgeon appointment on day of surgery/prior to day of surgery 
.0.05 
-
-</p>

<p>Preoperative sphere 
0.04* 
.0.05 
-</p>

<p>Preoperative cylinder 
.0.05 
-
-</p>

<p>Postoperative sphere 
.0.05 
-
-</p>

<p>Postoperative cylinder 
0.03* 
.0.05 
-</p>

<p>Preoperative dry eye difficulties (preoperative Question 7) 
.0.05 
-
-</p>

<p>Preoperative visual symptoms (starburst, glare, halo, ghosting double vision) 
(preoperative Question 7) </p>

<p>.0.05 
-
-</p>

<p>Postoperative UDVa 
0.03* 
.0.05 
-</p>

<p>Change in CDVa 
.0.05 
-
-</p>

<p>Day 1 surgeon care and questions (Questions 1 and 2) 
,0.0001* 
,0.0001* 
8.2% </p>

<p>surgeon 
.0.05 
-
-</p>

<p>Month 1 satisfaction (Question 5) 
,0.0001* 
,0.0001* 
46.7% </p>

<p>Month 1 impact of eyesight on various activities (Questions 8-10) 
,0.0001* 
,0.0001* 
25.4% </p>

<p>Month 1 dry eyes (Question 7) 
,0.0001* 
0.0001* 
7.5% </p>

<p>Month 1 visual symptoms (starburst, glare, halo, ghosting double vision) (Question 7) 
,0.0001* 
,0.0001* 
12.2% </p>

<p>Notes: R 
2 =0.38, P,0.0001. *Statistically significant. See the patient experience questionnaire in Table 1 for full details of Questions 1, 2, 4, 5, and 7-10. 
Abbreviations: UDVa, uncorrected distance visual acuity; CDVa, corrected distance visual acuity. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Consent process for elective refractive surgery </p>

<p>proposed, which mostly consist of combination of written, 
verbal, and audiovisual information. 
1-3,14-17 For example, 
Moseley et al 
15 evaluated the effect of presentation meth-
ods on understanding of cataract surgery and showed that 
subgroup of patients who watched educational video had 
significantly better understanding of the risks and benefits 
of the procedure. In a similar study, Wollinger et al 
16 used 
multimedia software to improve patients' understanding of </p>

<p>cataract surgery, in addition to verbal consent. This interac-
tive tool presented cataract surgery using simple images and 
a clear spoken voice, allowing patients to process information 
in their own time. Patients who watched the video had 
significantly better understanding of cataract surgery than 
patients in control group. Authors attributed this to basic 
concepts of learning, where all senses have to be engaged 
in order to memorize presented information: they state </p>

<p>Figure 3 One-month postoperative satisfaction with vision according to patient's perception of consent quality. </p>

<p>Figure 4 One-month postoperative difficulties with night driving, close-up vision, and outdoor/sport activities according to patient's perception of consent quality. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2400 </p>

<p>schallhorn et al </p>

<p>that only 10%-15% of the read material, 25% of the heard 
material, and 40% of the seen images are kept in memory 
over the long term. This increases to 75% when all senses 
are used simultaneously. 
24 Numerous other studies from all 
areas of medicine confirmed that use of audiovisual tools can 
significantly enhance patients understanding of their medical 
condition or proposed surgical procedure. </p>

<p>24-28   The informed consent process in our practice is very 
standardized, and the optometrist plays a key role. This 
includes discussing patient-specific potential risks, range of 
outcomes, and alternatives. In addition, the optometrist dis-
cusses the content of the educational video after the patient 
has viewed it as well as addressing any patient questions or 
concerns. The surgeon then reiterates all this information 
either DOS or PDOS, according to patient's choice. There 
are specific declarations within the electronic medical 
records system that document these discussions which have 
been completed and signed by the optometrist, the surgeon, 
and the patient. 
This study was conducted to determine whether the 
expectations of those patients who elected to meet the sur-
geon PDOS were better addressed. We specifically analyzed 
whether they felt they were properly consented and they were 
satisfied with the procedure and visual and ocular symp-
toms. This allowed us to evaluate the patient's perspective 
of their consent after they experienced the outcome of their 
procedure. The multivariate regression analysis showed that 
meeting the surgeon PDOS or DOS had no effect on whether 
the patient felt they were properly consented. Meeting the </p>

<p>Figure 5 One-month postoperative difficulties with visual phenomena or dry eyes according to patient's perception of consent quality. 
Note: "Significant difficulty" -patients that scored 6 or 7 on scale between 1 (= no difficulty) and 7 (= severe difficulty). </p>

<p>surgeon also had no effect on satisfaction with visual out-
comes, or postoperative visual acuity. 
We also analyzed factors associated with their perception 
of consent. Perhaps not surprisingly, the patient's satisfac-
tion with the outcome of their procedure was the strongest 
predictor, accounting for 46.7% of variance explained by the 
regression model. Other significant predictors were also asso-
ciated with quality of vision such as postoperative difficulties 
with night driving, close-up vision, sports or outdoor activi-
ties (25.4% explained variance), visual phenomena (12.2% 
explained variance), and ocular comfort (7.5% explained 
variance). Satisfaction with surgeon's care and the surgeon 
answering all questions (regardless of whether patient has met 
the surgeon PDOS or DOS) was also a statistically significant 
factor in regression analysis, responsible for 8.2% of variance 
explained by the regression model. 
A patient being disappointed with their outcome is 
strongly correlated to their belief that the consent process 
was inadequate. This agrees with literature, where the consent 
process is one of the most common causes of malpractice 
suits; 
4-8 however, it is rarely the primary cause of litigation in 
ophthalmology. 
18 It is the negative outcome that initiates liti-
gation, with the lack of adequate consent used as a secondary 
factor in majority of ophthalmology malpractice cases. </p>

<p>18   Despite a thorough preoperative explanation and rep-
etition of information in the consent process, there will 
probably be some patients who will not retain, 
9-13 or even 
deny ever hearing, the information presented to them pre-
operatively. 
11 Some patients who are strongly determined </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2401 </p>

<p>Consent process for elective refractive surgery </p>

<p>to undergo refractive surgery might selectively process the 
information they hear, remembering only the positive facts, 
and unwilling to accept or pay attention to any adverse side 
effects. 
11,16,18 There is also a possibility that the patients were 
truly not sufficiently informed about the risks of the proce-
dure. In our practice, the likelihood of negative outcome is 
presented to all patients in multiple ways, including written 
information, audiovisual tools, and a minimum of two verbal 
discussions (optometrist and surgeon). Additionally, patients 
sign a declaration after each consent step confirming that the 
information was presented to them. However, the intention 
of the study was not to understand why patients do not feel 
they were properly consented, but rather to analyze whether 
meeting the surgeon PDOS or DOS affected their perception 
of the consent 1 month after surgery, and this was not found 
to be a significant factor in the regression analysis. 
As refractive surgery has become more popular, there 
is an increasing public awareness of the procedures. </p>

<p>29-31   Prospective patients have access to nearly unlimited online 
information that can combine scientific facts with unfounded 
assertions, a process that has become known colloquially as 
"Dr Google." Accordingly, patients need to be given precise 
information to help them with their decision process and 
ensure they have realistic expectations about the benefits 
and potential risks of the procedure. Our results show that 
a discussion with the treating physician on either DOS or 
PDOS has no effect on the patient's perception of the quality 
of their consent, their postoperative satisfaction, or visual 
outcomes. The study outcome does not diminish the value 
of the surgeon in consenting process, but rather highlights 
that trained eye care specialists can perform an important 
supporting role in the consent process. 
Our study had some limitations. The main limitation is 
its retrospective nature, and the selection process for DOS 
or PDOS consent, which was based on patient's preference, 
rather than randomly assigned between the two groups. 
Although the questionnaire used in this study was previously 
found effective for reporting quality-of-life outcomes in a large 
number of refractive surgery patients, 
32-34 use of a validated 
quality-of-life instrument would be beneficial. Despite these 
limitations, the authors believe that having a large volume of 
patients who allowed detailed multivariate regression analysis 
significantly added to the value of this study. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>Steven C Schallhorn, MD, is a Chairman of the Optical 
Express Medical Advisor Board, Zeiss Chief Medical Officer, 
and a consultant for Acufocus, and reports no other conflicts 
of interest in this work. None of the other authors have a </p>

<p>financial or proprietary interest in the products and materials 
presented in this work. </p>



</text></tei>