<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5029575" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>This randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel-group study was to determine the pharmacokinetic characteristics, safety, and tolerability 
of multiple doses of inhaled loxapine aerosol in subjects on a stable, oral, chronic antipsychotic regimen. Loxapine was delivered by means of a unique 
thermally generated aerosol comprising drug particles of a size designed for deep lung delivery and absorption. Thirty-two subjects were randomized 
1:1:1:1 to receive inhaled loxapine (total doses of 15, 20, or 30 mg) or inhaled placebo administered in 3 divided doses, given 4 hours apart. Following 
inhalation, the median T max was 2 minutes, and concentrations declined to about half C max approximately 5 minutes later across the 3 dose levels. The 
dose proportionality across data from this study combined with data from the single-dose study showed a slope (90%CI) of log AUC inf versus log dose 
of 0.818 (0.762-0.875) across the 8 doses (n ¼ 60 subjects) studied, indicating reasonable dose proportionality. The most common adverse events 
were cough (3 of 32, 9%), sedation (3 of 32, 9%), and dysgeusia (2 of 32, 6%). The inhalation of multiple doses of inhaled loxapine were well tolerated in 
study subjects and provided a safe, well-tolerated means for rapidly and reliably achieving therapeutic plasma concentrations of loxapine. ClinicalTrials. 
gov identifier: NCT00555412 </p>

<p>2013 for 2 doses. In the United States, it is "indicated for the 
acute treatment of agitation associated with schizophrenia 
or bipolar I disorder in adults." ADASUVE became 
commercially available in the European Union in 2013 and 
in the United States in 2014. 
The objective of this phase 1, randomized, double-blind, 
placebo-controlled, parallel-group study was to determine 
the pharmacokinetic characteristics, safety, and tolerability 
of multiple doses of inhaled loxapine aerosol in subjects on 
a stable, oral, chronic antipsychotic medication regimen. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Human Subject Protection 
The protocol for this study was reviewed and approved by 
the Sterling Institutional Review Board (Atlanta, 
Georgia). Prior to enrollment in the study, written 
informed consent was obtained from each subject. </p>

<p>Subjects 
Participants in this study were male and female subjects 
between 18 and 65 years of age, inclusive, who were on a 
stable, oral, chronic (more than 2 months) antipsychotic 
medication regimen and who were able to tolerate the rapid 
oral dose taper and substitution regimen (half their usual 
oral dose Â 1 day, followed by a quarter oral dose Â 1 day, 
followed by inhaled loxapine or placebo Â 1 day). 
Subjects provided written informed consent prior to the 
initiation of any study procedures and expressed willing-
ness to comply with all requirements of the study. Subjects 
were excluded from the study if they were currently being 
treated with injectable depot neuroleptics within a 1-dose </p>

<p>interval, had a history of drug or alcohol dependence or 
abuse within the preceding year, had a history of asthma or 
chronic obstructive lung disease or a known allergy 
or intolerance to amoxapine or loxapine, or were currently 
taking medications that prolong the QT/QTc interval. 
Female subjects of childbearing potential (and male 
participants if sexually active with a partner of childbearing 
potential) agreed to use a medically accepted method of 
contraception during the study and for 1 week after. </p>

<p>Study Center and Dates 
The study was conducted at Atlanta Center for Medical 
Research (Atlanta, Georgia) between October and 
December 2007. </p>

<p>Study Medication 
The Staccato System (Alexza Pharmaceuticals, Inc., 
Mountain View, California) is designed to provide rapid 
drug delivery via inhalation of thermally generated 
aerosols. This handheld device and its development 
have been described elsewhere. 
21,22 To summarize, the 
flow of inspired air through the delivery device is detected 
by a breath sensor, causing rapid activation of a sealed, 
drug-coated heat source resulting in complete drug 
vaporization in less than 1 second. The vaporized drug 
quickly cools and condenses into aerosol particles with a 
mass median aerodynamic diameter between 1 and 
3.5 mm before leaving the device via the inspired air. 
Drug particles of this size are optimal for deep lung 
delivery and rapid systemic drug absorption. 
23 Figure 1 
shows the delivery system before and during an 
inhalation. The placebo used in this study was identical </p>

<p>Figure 1. Staccato drug-device combination product. </p>



<p>The Journal of Clinical Pharmacology / Vol 55 No 9 (2015) </p>

<p>to the active treatments except there was no drug coated 
onto the heat package. </p>

<p>Study Design 
This phase 1, single-center, randomized, double-blind, 
multiple-dose, placebo-controlled safety and pharmaco-
kinetic study of inhaled loxapine enrolled subjects on a 
chronic, stable antipsychotic regimens. Adult subjects 
(18-65 years, inclusive) were randomized to 1 of the 4 
parallel groups: inhaled loxapine 15, 20, or 30 mg (total 
daily dose) or inhaled placebo (1:1:1:1). Subjects received 
3 doses of study drug in a 24-hour evaluation period: 3 
doses of 5 mg for the 15-mg group, 1 dose of 10 mg and 2 
doses of 5 mg for the 20-mg group, and 3 doses of 10 mg 
for the 30-mg dose group. The doses were separated by 
4 hours. Each of the 5-and 10-mg inhaled loxapine doses 
were administered during a single inhalation. 
The study enrolled 32 subjects, 8 per treatment group. 
Subjects were on stable, oral, chronic (more than 2 
months) antipsychotic medication regimens. In addition, 
subjects were able to tolerate the rapid oral dose taper and 
substitution regimen (half oral dose for 1 day, followed by 
a quarter oral dose for 1 day, followed by loxapine or 
placebo for 1 day). Only subjects who were willing and 
able to comply with the study schedule and requirements 
and stay at the Clinical Research Unit for approximately 
36 hours were enrolled. 
Subjects signed an informed consent form before any 
protocol-related assessments or procedures. As part of the 
screening process, subjects were trained in the use of 
the delivery system, and their ability to use the device 
properly was evaluated. Screening and baseline evalua-
tions were performed during a 3-week period. After 
eligibility was confirmed, each subject was enrolled in the 
study, randomized to 1 of the 4 dose regimens, and dose 1 
of study medication was administered. Doses 2 and 3 were 
administered 4 and 8 hours later </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetic Assessments 
Blood samples (4 mL each) were collected into evacuated 
dipotassium (K 2 ) EDTA tubes from each subject at the 
specified the times (predose, 2, 5, 10, and 20 minutes, 
1 and 2 hours after each dose, and 12, 16, and 20 hours). 
Tubes were gently inverted 8 to 10 times and placed on 
ice, centrifuged (within 30 minutes) for 15 minutes 
(1000g) at 4°C-10°C, plasma was split into 2 equal 
volume samples (set A and set B) and stored upright at 
À70°C or below for storage. Set A was sent to the 
analytical laboratory, and set B was retained at the study 
site until the end of the study. Plasma loxapine, 7-OH-
loxapine, 8-OH-loxapine, and amoxapine concentrations 
were measured using a validated method by Tandem Labs 
(Salt Lake City, UT). Analytical quality controls (QCs) at 
the low (0.150 ng/mL), medium (20.0 ng/mL), and high 
(40.0 ng/mL) levels were assayed in duplicate in each </p>

<p>analytical run. For each dilution level, dilution QCs 
(200 ng/mL, df ¼ 10) were run in triplicate in any 
analytical run that contained diluted subject samples. 
Each internal standard (loxapine-d8, amoxapine-d8, 
7-hydroxyloxapine-d8, and 8-hydroxyloxapine-d8) was 
added to all samples (except blanks). Calibration stand-
ards had to be within AE 15% of target (AE 20% for the 
method lower limit of quantification [LLOQ]) to 
be acceptable. The samples were prepared by a solid-
phase extraction procedure and analyzed by liquid 
chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry. The API 
5000 was operated in the selected reaction monitoring 
mode under optimized conditions for detection of 
loxapine, amoxapine, 7-OH-loxapine, and 8-OH-loxa-
pine, as well as the internal standards loxapine-d8, 
amoxapine-d8, 7-OH-loxapine-d8 and 8-OH-loxapine-d8 
positive ions formed by electrospray ionization. The 
LLOQ of the assay was 0.05 ng/mL for all analytes. 
Individual plasma concentration (C) versus time (t) 
data across the 3 doses were analyzed bymodel-
independent methods to obtain the pharmacokinetic 
parameters for loxapine and its metabolites, where 
appropriate, using WinNonlin software (version 5; Phar-
sight Corporation, Mountain View, California). The 
maximum concentration (C max ) and the time to C max 
(T max ) were the observed values. The time when the 
concentration fell to half of C max , T half-max , was calculated 
based on linear interpolation from the mean concentration 
profiles. The area under the concentration-time curve to 
the last measurable concentration, AUC last , was estimated 
by the linear trapezoidal rule. The AUC inf was calculated 
as AUC last þ C last /k e , where C last is the last measurable 
plasma concentration and k e is the terminal rate constant. 
The half-life was calculated as ln(2)/k e . Clearance 
uncorrected for bioavailability of loxapine (CL/F) was 
calculated as total dose/AUC inf . For each of the 3 
metabolites (7-OH-loxapine, 8-OH-loxapine, and amox-
apine), the AUC inf ratio of each metabolite to loxapine 
was calculated for each subject. 
In the phase 3 trials, it was planned to give the second 
dose, if needed, 2 hours after the first dose, so the 
difference between the 4-hour and 2-hour concentrations 
as a percentage of C max was calculated from the mean 
concentration profiles: C 2 h -C 4 h as a percentage of C max . </p>

<p>Safety Assessments 
Safety measurements included clinical laboratory evalu-
ation (blood chemistry, hematology, and urinalysis), 
physical examination, 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG), 
and sedation assessments. Vital signs (systolic and 
diastolic blood pressure, pulse rate, and respiratory 
rate) were measured immediately before dosing, 10 
minutes after each dose, and at 24 and 48 hours. 
Sedation was measured with a 100-mm visual analog 
scale (VAS) between the verbal anchors extremely sleepy </p>

<p>Spyker et al </p>



<p>(0) and wide awake (100) immediately before dosing, at 
10 and 20 minutes, 1, 2, and 4 hours after each dose, and at 
24 hours. 
Treatment-emergent adverse events (AEs) were 
recorded throughout the study period, with the investiga-
tor reporting an assessment of the severity of each AE and 
its relationship to the study drug. AEs were classified 
according to Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities 
(MedDRA), version 10.0, system organ class and 
preferred terms. </p>

<p>Analyses of Quantitative Safety Measures 
Eleven quantitative safety measures, including vital signs, 
ECG intervals, and sedation scale, were examined across 
the dose groups. Vital signs and ECG intervals were 
measured at 1 time (10 minutes) after each of the 3 doses. 
Sedation was measured at 4 times after each dose. 
The dose effect was evaluated using the following 
steps: </p>

<p>The dose response for each measure was 
examined based on the most recent dose (0, 5, 
or 10 mg) and cumulative dose (0, 5, 10, 15, 
20, or 30 mg) by visual inspection, linear 
regression, and analysis of variance (AN-
OVA) with dose as a nominal variable to 
avoid assumptions on the dose relationship). 
For sedation, the dose response was examined 
for 1, 2, 3, and all 4 time points. 
The following descriptive statistics were 
computed by dose group for each measure: 
number of subjects (n), mean, standard 
deviation (SD), standard error of the mean 
(SEM), and 90% confidence interval (CI). 
Graphic displays of each time-averaged 
measure were then generated and examined, 
and representative graphics were chosen to 
summarize the quantitative safety results. </p>

<p>Statistical Analyses 
The results of clinical laboratory tests, vital signs, ECGs, 
and VAS sedation were summarized by treatment group. 
AEs were coded by body system and preferred term using 
MedDRA version 10.0 and summarized by frequency 
counts and incidence percentages. Subjects with multiple 
episodes of a single AE or multiple AEs that coded to the 
same preferred term or body system were counted only 
once in the event summary. The relation of the quantitative 
safety measures to dose was assessed via ANOVA versus 
last dose received (as a nominal variable). 
The dose proportionality for loxapine was examined 
across the dose groups using the power model (linear 
regression of log AUC inf vs log dose). A slope of 1.00 
would indicate "perfect" dose proportionality (double the </p>

<p>dose ¼ double the exposure). Because within this study, 
the dose range was only 2-fold (30 vs 15 mg), an 
additional power analysis was done including the 16-fold 
dose range (10 vs 0.625 mg) from the single-dose study. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Statistical analyses and preparation of summary tables 
and graphics were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Analysis 
System</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.1.3</rs> for Windows) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS JMP</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 9.0.0</rs> for Windows). No imputation of missing 
data was performed. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In all, 37 subjects were screened, 32 were enrolled and 
randomly assigned to the 4 treatment groups, and all 32 
completed the study (Figure 2). The safety analyses 
included the 32 subjects enrolled into this study and 
pharmacokinetic analyses on the 24 subjects who received 
inhaled loxapine. The age of the 32 subjects (mean AE SD) 
was 44.5 AE 10.0 years, weight was 85.6 AE 14.6 kg, 10 
(31.3%) were female, 28 (87.5%) were smokers, 30 (94%) 
were black, 1 was white, and 1 was Native American. The 
characteristics by treatment group and for all subjects are 
shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetics 
Following repeat administration every 4 hours for 2 
additional doses, the shape of the plasma concentration-
time profiles was similar to that following administration 
of the first dose (Figure 3). Table 2 summarizes the 
pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters by dose group, and 
Table 3 shows the PK parameters across all 3 dose groups. 
The loxapine plasma concentration-time profiles showed 
rapid absorption and distribution across the 3 dose 
regimens administered (total dose range of 15 to 30 mg). 
The median (min, max) T max for the 72 doses was 
2 minutes (2, 120 minutes). Mean peak plasma concen-
trations across all 3 dose groups (mean AE SD, normalized 
to 10 mg) were 69.3 AE 55.0, 101 AE 78.5, and 
107 AE 82.6 mg/mL after the first, second, and third doses, 
respectively. 
The loxapine half-life, T max , and CL/F were similar 
across the 3 dose regimens studied. The terminal half-life 
across all doses was 7.1 AE 1.9 hours, and CL/F was 
103 AE 51.7 mL/h. 
For the 9 mean postdose profiles (Table 2), the 
difference between the 4-and 2-hour concentrations as a 
percentage of C max was 7.6% AE 1.9%.The median (min, 
max) time to half-max (T half-max ) was 6.8 minutes (4.9, 8.4 
minutes). Time after T max (T half-max -T max ) was 4.6 
minutes (2.9, 6.4 minutes). 
The PK parameters AUC inf , AUC last , and C max 
increased with increasing loxapine dose (Table 1). The 
slope of log AUC inf versus log total dose of the 3 doses in 
this study (power analysis) was 0.661, P ¼.328. As seen in 
Figure 4, loxapine AUC inf was dose-proportional across </p>



<p>The Journal of Clinical Pharmacology / Vol 55 No 9 (2015) </p>

<p>the 8 doses (3 doses studied in this multidose study and the 
5 doses studied from the single-dose study). 
20 The slope 
(90%CI) of log AUC inf versus log dose was 0.818 (0.762-
0.875), P &lt; .0001, across the 8 dose groups. 
For the 3 metabolites measured, the mean AUC inf ratio 
to loxapine was 15.0% for 7-OH-loxapine, 103% for 
8-OH-loxapine, and 6.1% for amoxapine (Table 2). </p>

<p>Safety 
All 32 subjects completed all 3 doses; there were no 
premature discontinuations. There were no deaths, 
serious adverse events (AEs), or early study discontin-
uations because of AEs. AEs were reported by 31% of 
subjects (10 of 32); all were mild or moderate in 
intensity. All AEs are tabulated in Table 4. AEs were 
reported by 0%, 38%, 38%, and 50% of those who 
received placebo and total doses of 15, 20, and 30 mg of 
inhaled loxapine, respectively. The most common 
adverse events were cough (3 of 32, 9%), sedation (3 
of 32, 9%), and dysgeusia (2 of 32, 6%). One subject </p>

<p>had an episode of tachycardia, dizziness, and hypoten-
sion, which occurred 31 hours after the last inhaled 
loxapine dose and was judged by the investigator to be 
associated with the restarting of the subject's quetiapine 
750 mg. One subject reported a history of high blood 
sugar for 1 year, had a glucose at screening of 129 mg/ 
dL, 295 mg/dL at baseline (day -2), 318 mg/dL on day 
þ1, and 446 mg/dL at follow-up. A clinic appointment 
was arranged, and the importance of follow-up was 
stressed to the subject. 
For laboratory tests (hematology, blood chemistry, or 
urinalysis), the majority of subjects had results that were 
within the normal reference ranges at baseline and on day 
1. No individual results were judged clinically significant 
by the investigator (with 1 exception), and no results were 
deemed to be adverse events. The exception was 
the subject with high blood glucose described above. 
There were no clinically significant mean changes from 
baseline through the end of the study for any parameter, 
and no means were outside the reference range. All </p>

<p>Figure 2. Subject disposition (safety population). </p>

<p>Spyker et al </p>



<p>physical examinations were normal at screening and at the 
end of the study. 
Based on the methods outlined above (Analyses of 
Quantitative Safety Measures section), the most recent 
dose response was statistically stronger in virtually all 
analyses than the cumulative dose, and are reported 
hereafter. The strongest relationship to dose for sedation 
was for the mean of the first 3 times (10, 20, and 
60 minutes). Figure 5 shows 6 plots that are representative 
of the results for the 11 quantitative safety measures. R 
2 is </p>

<p>shown in each panel of the ANOVA -R 
2 of 0.185 means 
the dose group explained 18.5% of the observed variation. 
All but the QTcF ANOVAs showed statistically signifi-
cant dose-related effects (P &lt; .05). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Acute agitation generally requires prompt pharmacologi-
cal intervention to minimize the likelihood of patient 
injury and distress and to ensure the safety of other </p>

<p>Figure 3. Plasma concentrations of loxapine by dose regimen, first 12 h. Mean AE 1 SD by dose group, all PK subjects (N ¼ 24). </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient Characteristics (Safety Population, N ¼ 32) </p>

<p>Demographic or Baseline 
Characteristic </p>

<p>StaccatoPlacebo 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>StaccatoLoxapine 15 mg 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>StaccatoLoxapine 20 mg 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>StaccatoLoxapine 30 mg 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>Overall Study Population 
(N ¼ 32) </p>

<p>Sex, n (%): 
Female 
3 (37.5%) 
2 (25.0%) 
3 (37.5%) 
2 (25.0%) 
10 (31.3%) 
Male 
5 (62.5%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6 (75.0%) 
5 (62.5%) 
6 (75.0%) 
22 (68.8%) 
Age (years) 
Mean (SD) 
40.4 (10.8) 
42.5 (7.7) 
44.3 (8.1) 
50.9 (11.3) 
44.5 (10.0) 
Median 
40.5 
43.5 
45.0 
53.0 
44.5 
Min, max 
24, 56 
27, 52 
33, 56 
34, 65 
24, 65 
Height (cm) 
Mean (SD) 
169 (5.6) 
164 (15.2) 
173 (6.7) 
175 (9.0) 
170 (10.2) 
Median 
169 
165 
173 
175 
170 
Min, max 
160, 175 
137, 183 
165, 183 
163, 185 
137, 185 
Weight (kg) 
Mean (SD) 
79.0 (12.8) 
91.2 (13.8) 
82.6 (13.2) 
89.4 (17.2) 
85.6 (14.6) 
Median 
74.6 
95.1 
80.3 
92.9 
86.8 
Min, max 
63.5, 95.5 
63.0, 106 
62.5, 104 
61.4, 111 
61.4, 111 
Race, n (%) 
Caucasian 
0 
0 
1 (12.5%) 
0 
1 (3.1%) 
Black 
8 (100%) 
7 (87.5%) 
7 (87.5%) 
8 (100%) 
30 (93.8%) 
Hispanic 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
Asian 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
Native American 
0 
1 (12.5%) 
0 
0 
1 (3.1%) 
Smoking history, n (%) 
Current smoker 
7 (87.5%) 
7 (87.5%) 
7 (87.5%) 
7 (87.5%) 
28 (87.5%) </p>



<p>The Journal of Clinical Pharmacology / Vol 55 No 9 (2015) </p>

<p>patients and staff in the treatment setting. Currently 
available treatments for acute agitation include oral or 
intramuscular formulations of conventional and atypical 
antipsychotics, often used in combination with a 
benzodiazepine. 
24-26 ADASUVE was the first inhaled 
product for the acute treatment of agitation in patients 
with schizophrenia or bipolar I disorder and has 
demonstrated onset of an antiagitation effect in 10 
minutes. </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>Loxapine aerosol for inhalation thus appears to offer a 
number of benefits compared with currently available oral 
and intramuscular treatments for acute agitation in 
patients with schizophrenia, both in terms of speed of 
onset and acceptability to patients, who are often reluctant 
to accept an injection. 
10 Oral administration of a single 
25-mg dose of loxapine resulted in a mean C max of 
20 ng/mL after approximately 2 hours, 
27 whereas oral 
administration of a 50-mg dose of loxapine resulted in a 
mean C max of 33 ng/mL after approximately 1.5 hours. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Intramuscular administration of 20 mg of loxapine 
resulted in a C max of 17.8 ng/mL after approximately 
1 hour. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>By comparison, inhalation of 5 or 10 mg (normalized 
to10 mg loxapine) produced a mean C max of 69.3 ng/mL at 
a median time of 2 minutes (Table 2) following inhalation, 
so that clinical effects would be expected to occur very 
quickly. The &lt;8% difference between the 4-and 2-hour 
concentrations in this study (Table 2) supports the 
administration of a second dose 2 hours after the first 
dose. Onset of a statistically significant reduction in 
agitation at 5 minutes has been demonstrated with this 
formulation in agitated patients with schizophrenia 
18 and 
bipolar disease. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>The lungs contain most of the same drug-metabolizing 
enzymes found in the liver. 
30 However, based on the 
loxapine levels achieved in this study, loxapine does not 
appear to be extensively metabolized in the lung. 
Although the peak plasma concentrations immediately 
following inhalation are higher than for oral loxapine, the 
concentration of loxapine and its metabolites after the 
distribution phase were similar to those reported follow-
ing oral administration. </p>

<p>27,31,32 </p>

<p>We were able to locate 12 articles that reported 
measured loxapine blood concentrations. Only Midha 
et al 
28 reported a loxapine half-life or AUC measured 
over 100 hours after an oral dose. They reported a half-
life mean (CV%) of 7.6 hours (121%) compared with 
6.2 hours (27%) in our single-dose study and 7.1 hours 
(27%) in the present study. They likewise reported a 
dose-normalized 
(per 
milligram) 
AUC inf 
of 
3.4 ng Á h/mL (59%) compared with 17.8 ng Á h/mL 
(27%) and 11.4 ng Á h/mL (50%) in the present study. 
Thus, both AUC and half-life following inhaled 
administration exhibited less (or similar) variability 
compared with oral administration. 
The loxapine metabolites, 8-OH-loxapine and amox-
apine, have little pharmacological activity at the concen-
trations observed in this study. Although 7-OH-loxapine 
has a 5-fold higher affinity for the dopamine D2 receptor 
compared with loxapine, 
33 concentration showed no 
relation to QTc in a thorough QT/QTc study. </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>Our data also showed that inhaled loxapine at doses up 
to 10 mg every 4 hours is safe and well tolerated in subjects 
on a stable, oral, chronic antipsychotic medication </p>

<p>Table 2. Pharmacokinetic Parameters forInhaled Loxapine by Dose 
Group. All subjects receiving loxapine (N ¼ 24 subjects) </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>15 mg 
(5 þ 5 þ 5 mg) 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>20 mg 
(10 þ 5 þ 5 mg) 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>30 mg 
(10 þ 10 þ 10 mg) 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>T max (min) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Dose 1 </p>

<p>2 [2, 5] (8) 
2 [2, 60] (8) 
10 [2, 120] (8) </p>

<p>Dose 2 
2 [2, 5] (8) 
2 [2, 20] (8) 
2 [2, 120] (8) 
Dose 3 
2 [2, 13] (8) 
2 [2, 60] (8) 
2 [2, 120] (8) 
All Doses 
2 [2, 13] (24) 
2 [2, 60] (24) 
2 [2, 120] (24) 
Half-life (h) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>6.6 AE 2.0 (8) 
7.9 AE 2.3 (8) 
6.75 AE 1.3 (8) 
CL/F (mL/h) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>86.6 AE 22.6 (8) 
101 AE 42.4 (8) 
122 AE 75.8 (8) 
AUC inf 
(ng Á h/mL) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>184 AE 49.6 (8) 
226 AE 82.7 (8) 
315 AE 145 (8) </p>

<p>AUC last 
(ng Á h/mL) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>167 AE 46.0 (8) 
197 AE 71.8 (8) 
284 AE 129 (8) </p>

<p>C max (ng/mL) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Dose 1 </p>

<p>32.7 AE 19.1 (8) 
84.8 AE 65.0 (8) 
57.8 AE 61.7 (8) </p>

<p>Dose 2 
52.3 AE 40.6 (8) 
48.8 AE 28.2 (8) 
102 AE 102 (8) 
Dose 3 
62.2 AE 48.9 (8) 
59.4 AE 49.0 (8) 
78.4 AE 63.5 (8) </p>

<p>a ¼ Median [Min, Max] (N) 
b ¼ Arithmetic mean AE standard deviation (N) </p>

<p>Table 3. Pharmacokinetic Parameters for Loxapine and Metabolites 
Across Dose Groups. All subjects receiving loxapine (72 doses in 24 
subjects receiving 3 doses each) </p>

<p>Parameter 
Observations 
All 3 Doses </p>

<p>T max (min) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>72 
2 [2, 120] 
C max (Dose 1) 
b (ng/mL) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>24 
69.3 AE 55.0 
C max (Dose 2) (ng/mL) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>24 
101 AE 78.5 
C max (Dose 3) (ng/mL) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>24 
107 AE 82.6 
AUC inf 7-OH-loxapine (%) </p>

<p>cd </p>

<p>24 
15.0 AE 7.7 
AUC inf 8-OH-loxapine (%) </p>

<p>cd </p>

<p>24 
103 AE 45.0 
AUC inf Amoxapine(%) </p>

<p>cd </p>

<p>24 
6.1 AE 3.5 
Half-life (h) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>24 
7.1 AE 1.9 
CL/F (mL/h) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>24 
103 AE 51.7 
C 2 hr -C 4 hr (% of C max ) </p>

<p>ce </p>

<p>9 
7.6 AE 1.9% 
T half-max (min) </p>

<p>ae </p>

<p>9 
6.8 [4.9, 8.4] 
T half-max -T max (min) </p>

<p>ae </p>

<p>9 
4.8 [2.9, 6.4] </p>

<p>a ¼ Median [Min, Max] 
b ¼ Normalized to 10 mg dose 
c ¼ Arithmetic mean AE standard deviation 
d ¼ As a percent of the loxapine AUCinf 
e ¼ From mean concentration profiles (3 doses in each of the 3 dose groups) </p>

<p>Spyker et al </p>



<p>regimen. Among the 11 quantitative safety measures 
studied, none showed clinically important dose-related 
changes, even though the prescribing information for 
loxapine lists possible cardiovascular effects such as 
tachycardia, hypotension, hypertension, orthostatic hypo-
tension, lightheadedness, and syncope. </p>

<p>Overall, the most frequently reported AEs among the 
24 subjects receiving loxapine were sedation and cough, 
each reported by 3 subjects. None of the AEs were 
serious; all events were mild to moderate in severity, and 
all events resolved without sequelae except for elevated 
blood glucose in 1 subject (Table 4). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Dose proportionality based on AUCinf for all 8 dose groups. Slope (90%CI) ¼ 0.818 (0.762-0.875) across the 8 doses. (Regression [95% 
CI], R 
2 ¼ 0.911, N ¼ 60). þ from single dose study, &amp; from this study. </p>

<p>Table 4. Number (%) of Subjects with Treatment-emergent Adverse Events by System Organ Class and Preferred Term (Safety Population, N ¼ 32) </p>

<p>SYSTEM ORGAN CLASS Adverse Event </p>

<p>Placebo 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>Inhaled Loxapine 15 mg 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>Inhaled Loxapine 20 mg 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>Inhaled Loxapine 30 mg 
(N ¼ 8) </p>

<p>All subjects 
(N ¼ 32) </p>

<p>ANY PRIMARY SYSTEM ORGAN CLASS 
0 
3 (38%) 
3 (38%) 
4 (50%) 
10 (31%) 
CARDIAC DISORDERS 
0 
0 
0 
1 (13%) 
1 (3%) 
Tachycardia </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0 
0 
0 
1 (13%) 
1 (3%) 
GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS 
0 
2 (25%) 
2 (25%) 
0 
4 (13%) 
Constipation 
0 
1 (13%) 
0 
0 
1 (3%) 
Dysgeusia 
0 
1 (13%) 
1 (13%) 
0 
2 (6%) 
Hypoesthesia oral 
0 
1 (13%) 
0 
0 
1 (3%) 
Toothache 
0 
0 
1 (13%) 
0 
1 (3%) 
INVESTIGATIONS 
0 
1 (13%) 
0 
0 
1 (3%) 
Blood glucose increased 
0 
1 (13%) 
0 
0 
1 (3%) 
NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS 
0 
1 (13%) 
1 (13%) 
2 (25%) 
4 (13%) 
Dizziness </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0 
0 
0 
1 (13%) 
1 (3%) 
Sedation 
0 
1 (13%) 
1 (13%) 
1 (13%) 
3 (9%) 
RESPIRATORY, THORACIC, &amp; 
MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS </p>

<p>0 
0 
1 (13%) 
2 (25%) 
3 (9%) </p>

<p>Cough 
0 
0 
1 (13%) 
2 (25%) 
3 (9%) 
VASCULAR DISORDERS 
0 
0 
0 
1 (13%) 
1 (3%) 
Hypotension </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0 
0 
0 
1 (13%) 
1 (3%) </p>

<p>a This episode of tachycardia, dizziness, and hypotension occurred 31 hours after the last Staccato Loxapine dose and was judged by the investigator to be 
associated with the restarting of the subject's quetiapine 750 mg. </p>



<p>The Journal of Clinical Pharmacology / Vol 55 No 9 (2015) </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Inhaled loxapine administered every 4 hours at doses of 5 
or 10 mg up to a total of 30 mg (10 þ 10 þ 10 mg) was safe 
and well tolerated in subjects on chronic, stable 
antipsychotic regimens. Following inhalation, loxapine 
was rapidly absorbed and rapidly distributed and 
exhibited minimal accumulation during a 3-dose regimen 
with a 4-hour dosing interval. Relative to C max , there were 
small differences in loxapine concentration between 2 and 
4 hours after dosing, supporting the administration of a 
second dose 2 hours after the first dose with an expected 
minimal increase in C max . The results of this multidose 
study support repeat dosing of inhaled loxapine after an 
interval of 2 to 4 hours. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Keith Huie, MS, Bioanalysis/ADME 
Scientist, Alexza Pharmaceuticals, Inc., for the management 
and support of the bioanalytical validation and assays. This 
study was supported by Alexza Pharmaceuticals, Inc. </p>

<p>Declaration of Conflicting Interests </p>

<p>D.A.S. was an employee during execution of this study and is 
currently a paid consultant of Alexza Pharmaceuticals. R.A.R. 
was the principal investigator for this study and was paid by 
Alexza Pharmaceuticals to carry out this study. J.V.C. is an 
employee of Alexza Pharmaceuticals. D.A.S. and J.V.C. own 
stock and stock options. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Safety summaries, change from baseline by last dose administered. Arithmetic mean [90% confidence interval] (safety population). A: Sitting 
systolic BP (mmHg); B: Sitting diastolic BP (mmHg); C: Sitting heart rate (/min); D: VAS sedation (mm); E: PR interval (msec); F: QTcF, Fridericia 
corrected QT (msec). </p>

<p>Spyker et al </p>







<p>The Journal of Clinical Pharmacology / Vol 55 No 9 (2015) </p>

</text></tei>