<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5415459" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: We explored correlations between the new International Associa-
tion for the Study of Lung Cancer/American Thoracic Society/European Respira-
tory Society classification, epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) mutation 
status, and prognosis. 
Methods: Data from 293 patients with lung adenocarcinoma were classified accord-
ing to the new classification. Fisher's exact, χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, and log-rank tests and Cox regression 
analysis were used to analyze correlations between EGFR mutation status, lung can-
cer prognosis, and the new histologic subtype. Disease-free survival and progression-
free survival (PFS) were estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. 
Results: Lepidic and non-solid adenocarcinomas showed significantly elevated 
EGFR mutation rates (79.0% and 65.8%, respectively; P &lt; 0.05). EGFR mutation 
status was only associated with gender (P &lt; 0.001). EGFR mutation-positive 
patients who received targeted therapy had better median PFS than those who 
received chemotherapy as first-line treatment (P &lt; 0.001). The median PFS of 
patients with exon 19 and exon 21 mutations who received first-line targeted 
therapy were 12.5 and 9.5 months, respectively (P = 0.970). Patients with micro-
papillary predominant adenocarcinomas had the shortest disease-free survival 
(&lt;18 months) and PFS. Histologic subtype (P = 0.036), treatment type 
(P = 0.031), and EGFR mutation status (P = 0.019) might be good prognostic 
factors for lung adenocarcinoma. 
Conclusion: Patients with exon 19 mutations obtained greater benefits from tar-
geted therapy. In the new classification, EGFR mutation rates are higher in lepi-
dic cases and in cases without the solid subtype. The micropapillary subtype of 
adenocarcinoma has the worst prognosis, while the lepidic subtype has the best. </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Lung cancer is currently one of the major causes of cancer-
related death worldwide. It is the leading cause of cancer-
related death in China, and often results in greater rates of 
morbidity and mortality than heart disease and cerebrovas-
cular disorders. 
1 Pulmonary adenocarcinoma is the most 
common histological subtype of lung cancer. Its incidence 
has increased over the past decades, and it occurs in about 
50% of non-small cell lung cancers (NSCLCs). 
2 In 2011, in 
light of improvements in our understanding of pulmonary </p>

<p>adenocarcinoma, a joint working group of the Interna-
tional Association for the Study of Lung Cancer (IASLC), 
the American Thoracic Society (ATS), and the European 
Respiratory Society (ERS) proposed a new histologic classi-
fication of lung adenocarcinoma. This classification 
method has been referred to as "the new IASLC/ATS/ERS 
lung adenocarcinoma classification" or "the new classifica-
tion." 
3 Using the new classification, it is possible to screen 
for early-stage NSCLC in patients at high risk. Furthermore, 
the new classification can favorably guide postoperative </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>159 </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, 
provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer ISSN 1759-7706 </p>

<p>adjuvant treatment, although there are some limitations for 
advanced lung cancer. 
4-6 Epidermal growth factor receptor-
tyrosine-kinase inhibitors (EGFR-TKIs) have significant sur-
vival benefits for advanced lung cancer. In NSCLC, EGFR 
mutations chiefly occur in adenocarcinomas, followed by 
adenosquamous cell, large-cell undifferentiated, and miscel-
laneous carcinomas, and are least common in squamous 
cell carcinomas (&lt;5%). 
7 In clinical trials of patients with 
advanced pulmonary adenocarcinoma and EGFR mutations, 
chemotherapy was inferior to EGFR-TKIs, which pro-
longed median survival to 3.5 years. 
8-13 Therefore, pre-
treatment genetic testing is recommended by the National 
Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN), the European 
Society for Medical Oncology (ESMO) and the American 
Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) for cases of 
advanced lung cancer. In 2014 in China, however, the 
proportion of patients who received a genetic test was 
only 27% (although a higher testing rate of 51% was 
observed in the larger cities, Beijing, Shanghai, and 
Guangzhou). 
14 These relatively low proportions may be 
explained by the use of mainly exploratory techniques 
that are yet to be widely adopted, as well as by the pres-
ence of notable limitations to specimens. Several studies 
have attempted to explore the predictive value of the new 
classification in cases with EGFR mutation. 
15,16 At pres-
ent, we are unable to determine the larger clinical impli-
cations because some outcomes associated with the 
EGFR mutation rate are higher in micropapillary pre-
dominant adenocarcinomas than in invasive mucinous 
and solid predominant adenocarcinomas, both in China 
and internationally. 
We reviewed data from patients diagnosed with lung 
adenocarcinoma at Peking University Third Hospital 
between 1 November 2011 and 31 December 2014. Addi-
tionally, we analyzed the relationships between the new 
classification and outcomes during follow-up in order to 
clarify the implications of the new classification and EGFR 
mutation status for prognosis and therapeutic choices. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>We analyzed medical records from a population of 
patients who were diagnosed with and treated for pul-
monary adenocarcinoma between 2011 and 2014. The 
inclusion criteria were: (i) primary lung adenocarcinoma 
histopathologically confirmed after treatment in the hos-
pital, (ii) stage I-II or stage III for clear resection types 
and stage IV for non-resected lesions, (iii) lung adeno-
carcinoma with determined subtypes, and (iv) Eastern </p>

<p>Cooperative Oncology Group performance status 
(ECOG PS) ≤2. The exclusion criteria were: (i) unclear 
classification, (ii) metastatic lung adenocarcinoma, and 
(iii) EGOG PS ≥2. The cases were selected on the basis 
of availability of archival slides and tissues. The patients' 
characteristics are summarized in Table 1, including 
information on age, gender, clinical stage, EGFR muta-
tion status, and treatment. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The new classification includes adenocarcinoma in situ 
(AIS), minimally invasive adenocarcinoma (MIA), invasive 
carcinoma (lepidic, acinar, papillary, solid, and micropapil-
lary predominant), and variants of invasive adenocarcino-
mas (invasive mucinous adenocarcinoma [IMA], colloid, 
fetal, and enteric). 
3 A large number of pathologists decided 
the different subtypes of the new classification by morphol-
ogy. In the new classification, evidence of a subtype present 
in &gt;5% of the specimen confirms a diagnosis of that sub-
type, a subtype present in &gt;40% of the specimen was </p>

<p>Table 1 A baseline comparison of 293 lung adenocarcinoma cases </p>

<p>Clinical features 
Cases (n) 
% </p>

<p>Age 
&lt;62 
142 
48.5 
&gt;62 
151 
51.5 
Age 
29-84 
ND 
Median age 
62 
ND 
Gender 
Female 
117 
40.0 
Male 
176 
60.0 
T 
T1 
63 
21.5 
T2 
113 
38.6 
T3 
65 
22.2 
T4 
52 
17.7 
N 
N0 
75 
25.6 
N1 
74 
25.2 
N2 
86 
29.4 
N3 
58 
19.8 
M 
M0 
165 
56.3 
M1 
128 
43.7 
TNM 
Stage I 
46 
15.7 
Stage II 
57 
19.4 
Stage III 
62 
21.2 
Stage IV 
128 
43.7 
Specimens 
Resect 
132 
45.0 
Biopsy 
112 
38.3 
Hydrothorax 
49 
16.7 </p>

<p>ND, no data; TNM, tumor node metastasis. </p>



<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>New IASLC/ATS/ERS classification 
Z. Guo et al. </p>

<p>defined as predominant, and other subtypes were consid-
ered mixed. We used the American Joint Committee on 
Cancer tumor node metastasis (TNM) classification cri-
teria. 
17 The resected tumor specimens were subjected to 
EGFR mutational analysis using DNA sequencing, as well 
as fluorescence PCR analyses of biopsy specimens. The 
results were regarded as reliable because biopsy specimens 
show only pathologic analysis and not variety. 
DNA sequencing was conducted as follows. 
DNA extraction: The specimens were cut serially into 
coronal and sagittal slices of 4 μm thickness using a 
microtome. The tumor cells were enriched to determine 
which cells contained ≥70% evidence of cancer. DNA 
from paraffinized tissues samples was isolated using a 
QIAamp DNA FFPE Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). 
Nucleic acid protein concentrations were measured 
along with DNA purity and concentration using a 
Nanodrop 2000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, 
Waltham, MA, USA). DNA concentration was adjusted 
to 20-30 ng/μL and stored at −20 
C. 
Epidermal growth factor receptor amplification and 
purification: EGFR gene PCR amplification and sequencing 
primers were tested and synthesized by Yingjun Life Tech-
nologies Co. Ltd. to directly target EGFR tyrosine coding 
region exon ranges from 18 to 21 in order to synthesize 
primers. The exon 18 upstream primer was 5 
0 -
AGCATGGTGAGGGCTGAGGTGAC-3 
0 (23 bp) and the 
downstream primer was 5 
0 -ATATACAGCTTGCAAG-
GACTCTGG-3 
0 (24 bp). The exon 19 upstream primer 
was 
5 
0 -CCAGATCACTGBGCAGCATGTGGCACC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(27 bp) and the downstream primer was 5 
0 -
AGCAGGGTCTAGAGCAGAGCAGCTGCC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(27 bp). 
The exon 20 upstream primer was 5 
0 -GATCGCATT-
CATGCGTCTYCACC-3 
0 (23 bp), and the downstream 
primer was 5 
0 -TrGcTATCCCAGGAGCGCAGACC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(23 bp). The exon 21 upstream primer was 5 
0 -TCA-
GAGCCTGGCATGAACATGACCCTG-3 
0 (27 bp) and the 
downstream primer was 5 
0 -GGTCCCTGGTGTCAG-
GAAAATGCTGG-3 
0 (26 bp). PCR products 262, 265, 
362, and 297 bp were maintained with PCR amplification 
according to the clarification. Five microlitres of the PCR 
amplification product was run on 1% agarose gel to 
observe PCR production and was documented by absorp-
tion analysis. 
Reaction, purification, and sequencing: 0.5 μL purified 
PCR products, 1 μL reagents of sequencing, 2 μL sequence 
primers, and 2.5-Ul ddH 2 O were maintained with sequen-
cing. To purify the samples after the sequencing reaction 
was completed, 1 μL NaAc and 15 μL alcohol were added 
to each sample. Ten microlitres of Hi-Di was subsequently 
added to the samples to filter DNA alcohol volatilization. 
The samples were then degenerated by the PCR instru-
ment, spotted in 96-well plates, and analyzed with </p>

<p>ABI-3500 Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster 
City, CA, USA), using chroma or alignment for analysis. 
Fluorescence PCR: Procedures were performed using an 
EGFR mutation kit (Qiagen) comprised of 8-PCR tube 
reaction strips (reagents include E18, E19, E20, and E21 
mutation sites), Taq enzymes, and EGFR-positive control 
material, according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Analysis was performed for each sample, positive control 
material, and a negative control (purified water) during 
each PCR reaction. The samples were harvested from posi-
tive control material and Taq enzyme (EGFR) and centri-
fuged rapidly for 15 minutes. Subsequently, 2.7 μL Taq 
enzyme (EGFR) was added to the 42.3 μL tested DNA 
samples, the 42.3 μL positive control material samples, and 
42.3 μL purified water samples to admix in 15 seconds on 
amalgamation. The samples were then centrifuged rapidly 
for 15 seconds. The manufacturer recommended adding 
1.5-3 ng/μL DNA samples from paraffin sections (i.e. each 
reaction tube included additional DNA of 7.05-14.1 ng), 
which is different to adding DNA according to the sample 
duration of paraffin sections. It is recommended to be 
Analyis was performed directly after DNA extraction of 
blood plasma and serum, as per the manufacturer's recom-
mendation. TE buffer (pH8.0) is recommended to dilute 
the DNA sample. Each 5 μL mixed DNA sample along the 
PCR tubal wall was added to an 8-PCR tube reaction strip. 
Lids were then placed and the samples were centrifuged 
before being added to 8-PCR tube reaction strips. Reac-
tions were subject to placement of the 8-PCR tube reaction 
strips into PCR instruments, according to standard 
procedure. </p>

<p>Endpoints </p>

<p>Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 
version 1.1 was used to determine clinical therapeutic 
effects. 
18 The endpoints of the study were disease-free sur-
vival (DFS) and progression-free survival (PFS) rates. </p>

<p>Follow-up </p>

<p>Patients were followed up by review, telephone, and clinic 
service. Loss of follow-up occurred when patient informa-
tion was altered without notification or a patient refused to 
continue. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Epidermal growth factor receptor mutation status and his-
tologic subtype were analyzed statistically using the χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-test, 
and Fisher's exact test was used when the sample size was 
lower than five. Log rank tests and Cox regression analyses 
were also employed. DFS and PFS were estimated using </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>



<p>Z. Guo et al. 
New IASLC/ATS/ERS classification </p>

<p>the Kaplan-Meier method. Statistical analyses were per-
formed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 20</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>., Armonk, 
NY, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Cohort characteristics </p>

<p>We analyzed the medical records of patients who had been 
diagnosed with lung adenocarcinoma at Peking University 
Third Hospital between 1 November 2011 and 
31 December 2014. Of the 377 selected adenocarcinoma 
cases, 84 cases with unclear subtypes were excluded. In 
total, 293 patients were included in the study: 176 women 
and 117 men. The age range at diagnosis was 29-84 years 
(mean 62). Specimens were available from surgically 
resected adenocarcinomas (wedge or segmental resections) 
in 132 patients, needle or incisional biopsy in 112 patients, 
and pleural cytology in 49 patients. Patient details are sum-
marized in Table 1 and Figure 1. </p>

<p>The new classification, epidermal growth 
factor receptor (EGFR) mutation status and 
patients </p>

<p>The new classification and patients 
Lepidic predominant disease was the most common histo-
pathologic type, while micropapillary predominant disease 
was the least common according to the new classification. 
The details of the patient cohort are summarized in </p>

<p>Table 2. There were three cases of AIS, three cases of MIA, 
and 287 cases of invasive adenocarcinoma; 126 were acinar 
predominant (43.9%), 66 were lepidic predominant 
(23.0%), 31 were papillary predominant (10.8%), 35 were 
solid predominant (12.2%), and 10 were micropapillary 
predominant (3.5%). Following the World Health Organi-
zation (WHO) lung adenocarcinoma classification, mixed 
subtypes (61.1%) and non-mixed subtypes (62.4%) were 
found in 173 and 120 patients, respectively. </p>

<p>Analysis of epidermal growth factor 
receptor (EGFR) mutation status </p>

<p>A total of 293 lung adenocarcinoma patients were included 
in this study. EGFR gene status was tested in 211 cases. 
EGFR mutation was found in 130 cases (130/211, 61.6%), 
while 81 cases showed wild-type EGFR (81/211, 38.4%). 
Among the cases of EGFR mutation, 54 cases were deletion 
mutations in exon 19 (41.3%) and 50 were L858R missense 
mutations in exon 21 (38.5%). EGFR mutation status was 
related to gender (P &lt; 0.001), but was unrelated to tumor 
stage, age, or histologic subtype. Patient details are sum-
marized in Tables 3 and 4. </p>

<p>Lepidic and non-solid adenocarcinoma and 
EGFR status </p>

<p>Epidermal growth factor receptor mutation genetic testing 
was not performed on the six patients with AIS or MIA 
as the sample size was inadequate. Correlation between 
the new classification and EGFR status was complicated. 
Patient details are summarized in Table 5. Lepidic adeno-
carcinomas and non-solid adenocarcinomas showed sig-
nificantly elevated EGFR mutation rates (79.0% and 
65.8%, respectively; P &lt; 0.05). The EGFR-mutation posi-
tive patients who received targeted therapy had better 
median PFS rates than those who received chemotherapy 
as first-line treatment (P &lt; 0.001). Lepidic containing and 
predominant were the most common and statistically sig-
nificant (51.5%, P = 0.004 and 51.4%, P = 0.008, respec-
tively). EGFR mutation rates were relatively unusual in 
acinar and papillary predominant and containing cases 
compared with lepidic adenocarcinoma, and no statisti-
cally significant differences were observed (50.0%, 51.4%, 
45.2%, 53.2%; P = 0.694, 0.215, 0.726, 0.213, respectively). 
The mutation rate was lowest in solid containing cases 
(21.9%), and was statistically significant (P &lt; 0.001). Fol-
lowing the WHO lung adenocarcinoma classification, 
mixed subtypes and non-mixed subtypes did not show 
significantly different EGFR mutation rates (61.1% and 
62.4%, respectively). 
Fifty-five enrolled patients had stage IV disease with 
EGFR mutations and 33 patients had stage IV disease with </p>

<p>377 ADC cases between 2011 and 2014 </p>

<p>84 cases of unclear subtype </p>

<p>293 cases selected </p>

<p>3 cases MIA 
287 cases invasive ADC </p>

<p>211 cases EGFR genotyping </p>

<p>130 cases EGFR mutation 
81 cases EGFR wild-type </p>

<p>Figure 1 Screening steps for the collection of data of lung adenocar-
cinoma patients between 2011 and 2014. ADC, adenocarcinoma; 
EGFR, epidermal growth factor receptor; MIA, minimally invasive 
adenocarcinoma. </p>



<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>New IASLC/ATS/ERS classification 
Z. Guo et al. </p>

<p>wild-type EGFR. Among EGFR mutation cases, 13 included 
bone metastases and 10 included cerebral metastases. Of 
the wild-type EGFR cases, nine involved bone metastases 
and five involved cerebral metastases. There were 
42 patients with exon 19 and exon 21 mutations. Of those 
with exon 19 mutations, five had bone metastases and 
three had cerebral metastases. </p>

<p>Correlation of EGFR status, the new 
classification, and progressive disease </p>

<p>The median PFS in stage III-IV patients with exon 
19 mutations was longer than in patients with exon 
21 mutations when treated with targeted first-line therapy. 
These 79 patients with mutations were compared with 
51 patients who received chemotherapy. The median PFS </p>

<p>Table 2 The new classification for 293 cases </p>

<p>Histotype 
Cases (n) 
% </p>

<p>New classification 
AIS 
3 
1.0 
MIA 
3 
1.0 
Invasive carcinoma 
287 
Predominant 
5-10% 
10-20% 
20-30% 
30-40% 
&gt;5% 
Predominant 
Lepidic 
126 
17 
12 
13 
15 
183 
43.9 
Acinar 
66 
11 
10 
10 
12 
109 
23.0 
Papillary 
31 
15 
10 
8 
15 
79 
10.8 
Solid 
35 
9 
7 
7 
12 
64 
12.2 
Micropapillary 
10 
11 
6 
4 
4 
35 
3.5 
Unclear 
19 
Variants of invasive adenocarcinomas 
2 
0.7 
IMA 
2 
WHO 
Non-mixed subtypes 
120 
40.9 
Mixed subtypes 
173 
59.1 </p>

<p>AIS, adenocarcinoma in situ; IMA, invasive mucinous adenocarcinoma; MIA, minimally invasive adenocarcinoma; WHO, World Health Organization. </p>

<p>Table 3 Adenocarcinoma EGFR mutation and clinical characteristics for 211 cases </p>

<p>Pathology 
Cases (n) 
EGFR mutation (n) 
EGFR wild (n) 
Mutation rate (%) 
P </p>

<p>Age 
&lt;62 
102 
65 
37 
63.7 
0.541 
&gt;62 
109 
65 
44 
59.6 
Gender 
Male 
95 
47 
48 
49.5 
&lt;0.001 
Female 
116 
83 
33 
71.5 
T 
T1 
43 
27 
16 
62.8 
0.591 
T2 
93 
53 
40 
57.0 
T3 
45 
29 
16 
64.4 
T4 
30 
21 
9 
70.0 
N 
N0 
65 
40 
25 
61.5 
0.738 
N1 
49 
33 
16 
67.3 
N2 
61 
37 
24 
60.6 
N3 
36 
20 
16 
55.6 
M 
M0 
123 
75 
48 
60.9 
0.822 
M1 
88 
55 
33 
62.5 
Specimens 
Resection 
95 
60 
35 
62.1 
0.857 
Needle biopsy 
81 
48 
33 
59.3 
Pleural cytology 
35 
22 
13 
62.8 </p>

<p>EGFR, epidermal growth factor receptor. </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>



<p>Z. Guo et al. 
New IASLC/ATS/ERS classification </p>

<p>was 13 months in the patients who received targeted ther-
apy and 7.5 months in those who received chemotherapy 
(P &lt; 0.001). The results indicated that median PFS was sig-
nificantly prolonged in patients with EGFR mutations who 
had been selected for targeted therapy. The details are 
summarized in Figure 2. 
Among the cases of EGFR mutation in metastatic 
tumors, 35 cases were deletion mutations in exon 19 and 
32 cases were L858R missense mutations in exon 21. The 
median PFS rates of patients with exon 19 and exon 
21 mutations who received first-line EGFR-targeted ther-
apy were 12.5 and 9.5 months, respectively (P = 0.970). 
The median PFS of patients with exon 19 and exon 
21 mutations who received first-line chemotherapy were 
six and nine months, respectively (P = 0.341). Patients 
with exon 19 mutations may have greater sensitivity to </p>

<p>Table 4 Analysis of EGFR mutation status </p>

<p>Gene 
Mutation 
Cases (n) </p>

<p>E18 
G719S 
1 
E19 
E746-A750, L747-A750 (ins P), L747-P753 
(ins S) </p>

<p>54 </p>

<p>E20 
Q787Q, T790M, D770-N771 (ins G) 
7 
E21 
L858R, L861Q 
50 
E18, 19 
G719S, E746-A750 
1 
E18, 20 
G719A, S768I 
3 
E18, 21 
G719A, L858R, L861Q 
1 
E19, 20 
L747-P753 (ins S), E746-A750, L747-T751, 
T790M, S768I, V769L </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>E19, 21 
E746-A750, L858R 
3 
E20, 21 
T790M, Q787Q, L858R 
3 
E18-20 
G719A, L747S, Q787Q 
1 </p>

<p>EGFR epidermal growth factor receptor. </p>

<p>Table 5 Adenocarcinoma EGFR mutation status and pathological subtypes for 293 cases </p>

<p>Histotype 
Cases (n) 
EGFR mutation 
EGFR wild 
EGFR unclear 
Mutation rate% 
P </p>

<p>The new classification 
Acinar predominant 
126 
63 
37 
26 
63.0 
0.002 
Lepidic predominant 
66 
34 
9 
23 
79.0 
Papillary predominant 
31 
14 
10 
7 
58.3 
Solid predominant 
35 
7 
17 
11 
29.1 
Micropapillary predominant 
10 
3 
5 
2 
37.5 
Variants 
2 
0 
0 
2 
0 
Semiquantitative 
Acinar predominant 
126 
63 
37 
26 
63.0 
0.694 
Non-acinar predominant 
167 
67 
44 
56 
60.3 
Lepidic predominant 
66 
34 
9 
23 
79.0 
0.008 
Non-lepidic predominant 
227 
96 
72 
59 
57.1 
Papillary predominant 
31 
14 
10 
7 
58.3 
0.726 
Non-papillary predominant 
262 
116 
71 
75 
64.1 
Solid predominant 
35 
7 
17 
11 
29.1 
0.726 
Non-solid predominant 
258 
123 
64 
71 
65.8 
Micropapillary predominant 
10 
3 
5 
2 
37.5 
0.265 
Non-micropapillary predominant 
283 
127 
76 
80 
62.6 
Variants of invasive 
2 
0 
1 
1 
0 
NS 
Invasive carcinoma 
287 
130 
81 
82 
61.6 
Acinar contained 
183 
94 
52 
37 
64.4 
0.215 
Non-acinar containing 
110 
36 
29 
45 
55.4 
Lepidic contained 
109 
56 
19 
34 
74.7 
0.004 
Non-lepidic containing 
184 
74 
62 
48 
54.4 
Papillary contained 
79 
42 
20 
17 
67.7 
0.213 
Non-papillary containing 
214 
188 
61 
65 
75.5 
Solid contained 
64 
14 
32 
18 
30.4 
&lt;0.001 
Non-solid containing 
229 
116 
49 
64 
70.3 
Micropapillary containing 
35 
15 
11 
9 
57.7 
0.661 
Non-micropapillary containing 
258 
115 
70 
73 
62.1 
Variants containing 
2 
0 
1 
1 
0 
NS 
Non-variants containing 
291 
130 
80 
81 
61.9 
WHO 
Non-mixed subtypes 
120 
53 
32 
35 
62.4 
0.856 
Mixed subtypes 
173 
77 
49 
47 
61.1 </p>

<p>EGFR, epidermal growth factor receptor; NS, not significant; WHO, World Health Organization. </p>



<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>New IASLC/ATS/ERS classification 
Z. Guo et al. </p>

<p>EGFR-targeted therapy than those with exon 21 mutations. 
The details are summarized in Figure 3. </p>

<p>Different subtypes and progressive 
disease </p>

<p>Only one patient in the study had micropapillary predomi-
nant stage I-II disease, and achieved DFS of 19 months. 
Twelve patients had micropapillary containing disease, 
with a one-year DFS rate of 16.7%, the minimum adequate 
length for analysis. DFS rates at 12, 18, and 24 months 
were 62.5%, 40.0% and 22.9% in lepidic predominant cases. 
The details are summarized in Figure 4a and Table 6. 
Thus, the patients with lepidic predominant adenocarci-
noma had the longest DFS of all the patients with stage I-
II lung adenocarcinoma, while patients with micropapillary 
cancers had the shortest DFS. In patients with micropapil-
lary predominant stage III-IV adenocarcinoma, the PFS 
rate at one year was 11.3%. In patients with lepidic con-
taining disease, PFS rates at 6, 12, 18, and 24 months were 
76.5%, 70.7%, 52.9%, and 3.9%, respectively. The details 
are summarized in Figure 4b and Table 7. </p>

<p>Cox regression analysis </p>

<p>Cox regression analysis showed that histologic subtypes 
(P = 0.036), treatment type (P = 0.031), and EGFR </p>

<p>mutation status (P = 0.019) may be good prognostic fac-
tors for lung adenocarcinoma. Details of the regression 
analysis are summarized in Table 8. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>As has been discussed previously by many researchers, the 
2004 WHO diagnostic criteria and disease classification 
improved lung adenocarcinoma classification as it consid-
ered heterogeneous clinical, pathological, radiologic, and 
molecular criteria for this disease. Histologic subtypes and 
molecular typing had gradually become more important 
following the discovery of the target EGFR in 2004. 
19 In 
response to our improved understanding of the histopa-
thology of lung adenocarcinoma, in 2011, a joint working 
group of IASLC/ATS/ERS proposed a new histologic classi-
fication of this cancer. 
3 This classification includes AIS, 
MIA, and invasive adenocarcinoma, but discards mixed 
adenocarcinoma. It further includes acinar, lepidic, papil-
lary, solid, and micropapillary predominant disease. In the 
new classification, a subtype with &gt;5% presence is consid-
ered contained, a subtype with &gt;40% presence is defined as 
predominant, and other percentages are defined as mixed. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Studies from Europe and the United States reported a ratio 
of &lt;20% prevalence of lepidic predominant and papillary 
predominant cases, 10-40% prevalence of acinar predomi-
nant cases, 20-40% prevalence of solid predominant cases, </p>

<p>Figure 2 The relationship between epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) mutation and the choice of first-line treatment in patients with stage 
III-IV adenocarcinomas. (a) Progression-free survival (PFS) rates were longer with targeted therapy than with chemotherapy as first-line treatments in 
patients with EGFR mutations. (b) PFS rates were similar for targeted therapy and chemotherapy in patients with wild-type EGFR. (0: chemotherapy: 
1-targeted therapy.) m, median. </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>



<p>Z. Guo et al. 
New IASLC/ATS/ERS classification </p>

<p>and &lt;5% prevalence of micropapillary predominant 
cases. 
4,5,21,22 These studies support the suggestion that the 
prevalence of lepidic, papillary, micropapillary, and aci-
nar predominant cases are elevated in Asia, and that the 
rate of solid cases is lower in Asia than in Europe or 
America. 
6,22-26 In this study, there were 126 acinar 
(43.9%), 66 lepidic (23.0%), 31 papillary (10.8%), 35 solid 
(12.2%), and 10 micropapillary predominant (3.5%) cases, 
similar to the results of a prior study. 
3 The frequency of 
patients with micropapillary disease in our study was low, 
which is possibly a result of the small sample size of the 
included cohort or the possible differences in race and 
region when compared with European populations. </p>

<p>Epidermal growth factor receptor mutation is reportedly 
most common in lepidic (40-70%), micropapillary (70-80%), 
papillary (60%), and acinar (50%) cases, but is less common 
in solid predominant (25%) cases. 
4,16,27 In the present study, 
EGFR mutation occurred in individuals with lepidic predomi-
nant (79.0%) and non-solid predominant (70.3%) disease. No 
EGFR testing was performed for the AIS and MIA cases 
because of the small number of relevant patients in the study. 
Other conclusions are similar to relevant trials. There was a 
statistically significant relationship between EGFR mutation 
and solid adenocarcinomas (P &lt; 0.001). 
In the IPASS study, the response and PFS rates in 
NSCLC with EGFR mutation were longer in the gefitinib </p>

<p>Figure 3 Correlations between treatment type and exon 19 and 21 mutations in patients with stage III-IV adenocarcinoma. Targeted therapy versus 
chemotherapy for (a) exon 19 mutations and (b) exon 21 mutations (0: chemotherapy; 1: targeted therapy). (c) Correlation between exon 19 and 
exon 21 mutation status and targeted therapy, (d) correlation between exon 19 and exon 21 mutation status and chemotherapy (0: exon 19 muta-
tion; 1: exon 21 mutation). mPFS, median progression-free survival. </p>



<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>New IASLC/ATS/ERS classification 
Z. Guo et al. </p>

<p>than in the chemotherapy group (71.2% vs. 47.3%, 
P &lt; 0.001; 9.5 m vs. 6.3 m, P &lt; 0.001). 
8,28 The median PFS 
rate was 3.5 years for patients with EGFR mutation who 
received treatment with EGFR-TKIs. The NCCN, ESMO, 
and ASCO recommend performing EGFR gene testing 
before the initiation of treatment; however, some patients 
received chemotherapy after receiving a diagnosis and gene 
testing results, after receiving unclear results, or because 
they refused to wait for results. In our study, the median 
PFS rate in patients with stage III-IV disease and EGFR 
mutations who received targeted therapy was significantly 
longer than that for patients who received chemotherapy. 
Furthermore, the difference in PFS was statistically signifi-
cant (P &lt; 0.001), similar to the results of previous 
studies. 
3,8-13,28 Thus, EGFR status is important for therapy </p>

<p>selection. In 2015, ASCO noted that the median PFS in 
patients who received targeted therapy was longer in 
patients with exon 19 mutations than in patients with exon 
21 mutations. In addition, patients with exon 19 mutations 
who received targeted therapy had longer PFS than 
patients with exon 21 mutations who received chemother-
apy; however, the difference was not statistically significant 
in our study. This finding may prompt research into 
whether patients with exon 19 mutations can benefit from 
targeted therapy. No statistically significant results were 
observed for bone or cerebral metastases in the present 
study, as a result of the small sample sizes of EGFR muta-
tion and wild-type EGFR cases; however, cerebral metas-
tases are more common in patients with EGFR mutations. 
Sample sizes need to be increased in future research. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Correlations between histologic subtype progression and disease prognosis. (a) Histologic subtypes and disease recurrence in patients with 
stage I-II adenocarcinoma. (b) Histologic subtypes and disease progression in patients with stage III-IV disease (1: micropapillary predominant; 2: lepi-
dic predominant; 3: acinar predominant; 4: solid predominant; 5: papillary predominant; 6: micropapillary containing; 7: lepidic containing). DFS, 
disease-free survival. </p>

<p>Table 7 Progression-free survival for patients with stage III-IV lung 
cancer </p>

<p>Pathological subtypes (n) </p>

<p>PFS (months) </p>

<p>6 
1 2 
1 8 
2 4 </p>

<p>Micropapillary predominant (9) (%) 
85.7 
0 
0 
0 
Lepidic predominant (41) (%) 
97.4 
81.6 
15.8 
2.6 
Acinar predominant (86) (%) 
78.9 
49.2 
17.0 
1.4 
Solid predominant (23) (%) 
61.9 
23.8 
0 
0 
Papillary predominant (25) (%) 
60.3 
51.0 
12.4 
2.1 
Micropapillary containing (8) (%) 
12.5 
0 
0 
0 
Lepidic containing (18) (%) 
76.5 
70.7 
52.9 
3.9 </p>

<p>PFS, progression-free survival. </p>

<p>Table 6 Disease-free survival for patients with stage I-II lung cancer </p>

<p>Pathological subtypes(n) </p>

<p>DFS (months) </p>

<p>12 
18 
24 </p>

<p>Micropapillary predominant (1) 
100% 
100% 
0 
Lepidic predominant (25) 
62.5% 
40.0% 
22.9% 
Acinar predominant (40) 
73.0% 
52.1% 
24.3% 
Solid predominant (12) 
48.6% 
37.2% 
17.0% 
Papillary predominant (6) 
/ 
/ 
/ 
Micropapillary containing (12) 
16.7% 
0 
0 
Lepidic containing (25) 
91.3% 
80.5% 
53.9% </p>

<p>DFS, disease-free survival. </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>



<p>Z. Guo et al. 
New IASLC/ATS/ERS classification </p>

<p>Many studies have reported 100% five-year DFS and 
overall survival rates in patients with AIS and 
MIA. 
4-6,22-26 Our study only included six cases of AIS and 
MIA. The follow-up period was one to two years, and the 
patients showed no evidence of metastasis or relapse. In 
previous studies of stage I-II invasive adenocarcinoma in 
Asia, the five-year DFS rates were 70-95%, 60-80%, 
0-50%, 55-70%, and 40-60% for lepidic, acinar, micro-
papillary, papillary, and solid cases, respectively. </p>

<p>4-6,22-26 </p>

<p>These findings may have been a consequence of the high 
rates of EGFR mutations in lepidic cases. Furthermore, in 
patients with stage I-IV invasive adenocarcinomas, over-
all survival rates were 70, 60, 50, 55, and 45 months for 
lepidic, acinar, solid, papillary, and micropapillary pre-
dominant cases, respectively. 
11,21,22 In our study, the one-
year PFS rates were 11.3%, 70.7%, 49.2%, and 51.0% for 
micropapillary, lepidic, acinar, and papillary predomi-
nant cases. The difference between our rates and the 
findings of previous studies might be explained by the 
absence of sufficient preoperative staging, personalized 
therapy for surgical approaches, drugs, and duration of 
therapy. 
The high EGFR mutation rates of lepidic and solid pre-
dominant cases in our study are informative for therapy 
selection. The findings generally support the idea that 
patients with exon 19 mutations can achieve greater bene-
fits from targeted therapy; however, more clinical trials are 
needed on this topic. Micropapillary predominant cases 
had the shortest DFS and PFS and the highest degree of 
malignancy. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This study was supported in part by a grant from the Chinese 
Geriatric Oncology Society (CGOS, No. 0220141100300). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>No authors report any conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Table 8 Lung adenocarcinoma patients included in Cox regression 
analysis </p>

<p>Wald 
SE 
P 
95% CI </p>

<p>Gender 
0.377 
0.299 
0.539 
0.463-1.496 
Age 
1.056 
0.013 
0.304 
0.961-1.013 
EGFR mutation 
5.539 
0.195 
0.019 
0.431-0.926 
Pathological subtypes 
3.599 
0.166 
0.036 
0.808-1.047 
Therapy 
4.652 
0.270 
0.031 
1.055-3.037 </p>

<p>CI, confidence interval; EGFR, epidermal growth factor receptor; SE, 
standard error. </p>



<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>New IASLC/ATS/ERS classification 
Z. Guo et al. </p>



<p>Thoracic Cancer 8 (2017) 159-169 
© 2017 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>



<p>Z. Guo et al. 
New IASLC/ATS/ERS classification </p>

</text></tei>