<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5306244" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background and Objective When eye diseases are treated 
by topical administration, the success of treatment lies in 
the effective drug concentration in the target tissue. This is 
why the drug's pharmacokinetic, in the different sub-
structures of the eye, needs to be explored more accurately 
during drug development. The aim of the present analysis 
was to describe by rabbit model, the distribution of a drug 
after ocular instillation in the selected eye tissues and 
fluids. 
Methods By a top-down population approach, we devel-
oped and validated a population pharmacokinetics (PopPK) 
model, using tissue concentrations (tear, naso-lacrymal 
duct, cornea and aqueous humor) of a new src tyrosine 
kinase inhibitor (FV-60165) in each anterior segment's 
tissue and fluid of the rabbit eye. Inter-individual vari-
ability was estimated and the impact of the formulation 
(solution or nanosuspension) was evaluated. 
Results The model structure selected for the eye is a 
4-compartment model with the formulation as a significant 
covariate on the first-order rate constant between tears and 
the naso-lacrymal duct. The model showed a good pre-
dictive performance and may be used to estimate the </p>

<p>concentration-time profiles after single or repeated 
administration, in each substructure of the eye for each 
animal included in the analysis. 
Conclusions This analysis allowed describing the distri-
bution of a drug in the different selected tissues and fluids 
in the rabbit's eyes after instillation of the prodrug as a 
solution or nanosuspension. </p>

<p>Key Points </p>

<p>This study shows the benefit of the population 
approach to describe pharmacokinetics in non-
clinical studies of ophthalmic drugs after topical 
administration. The pharmacokinetics modeling is a 
particularly added value to provide tailored answers 
with sparse data. </p>

<p>To improve the predictive performance of the 
models, sampling protocol must be optimized. When 
data are available, this approach could allow the 
prediction of drug concentrations in the target tissue 
(eye substructure) and the evaluation of drug 
efficacy. </p>

<p>The eye is a delicate organ extremely well protected by its 
anatomy, physiology and by systemic circulation (blood-
aqueous and blood-retinal barriers). Owing to these fea-
tures, a clinically relevant drug concentration is hardly 
reaching within the target ocular tissue following topical 
drug administration. Topical administration is the route of </p>

<p>&amp; Sonia Khier 
sonia.khier@univ-montp1.fr </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Disposition Safety and Animal Research, Sanofi Recherche 
and Developpement, Montpellier, France </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Research and Drug Discovery, Ophthalmology Division, 
Sanofi Paris, Paris, France </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Pharmacokinetics, Université de Montpellier, 
34090 Montpellier, France </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>INSERM, U1194, IRCM, Institut de Recherche en 
Cancérologie de Montpellier, 34298 Montpellier, France </p>

<p>Eur J Drug Metab Pharmacokinet (2017) 42:59-68 
DOI 10.1007/s13318-016-0319-4 </p>

<p>choice for the treatment of anterior segment diseases, most 
often with a local therapeutic effect. This route is non-
invasive, painless and offers many advantages: fast effect, 
small dose required and not inducing systemic adverse 
effects. Topical bioavailability is, however, limited due to 
the precorneal loss factors increasing drug clearance and 
the cornea barrier limiting the distribution. All these factors 
contribute to the low bioavailability and low distribution of 
topically applied drugs and it is generally assumed that 
only 5 % or less of the instilled dose can effectively be 
distributed through the cornea [1, 2]. Describing pharma-
cokinetics in ocular target tissues is definitely a major 
challenge considering the eye complex anatomy and its 
dynamic physiological protection. During drug develop-
ment, human pharmacokinetics is generally assessed after 
per os or intravenous administration by sampling plasma at 
different time points. But, for drugs administered by topical 
ocular route with a local therapeutic effect, the target tis-
sues located in the eye can generally not be sampled. 
Exceptions are made in very rare cases of monitoring of 
drug levels in biopsies [3] or aqueous humor [4] collected 
from patients subjected to ophthalmic surgical procedures. 
That is why, for studying drugs distribution in ocular tis-
sues, animal models are used. The ocular characteristics of 
these models permit to extrapolate to human pharmacoki-
netics. The rabbit remains the species of choice for the 
evaluation of ophthalmic compounds as this animal is easy 
to handle and provides a relatively reliable model for the 
evaluation of ocular kinetics [5]. We are developing a new 
src tyrosine kinase inhibitor (FV-60165, drug) investigated 
for the management of corneal neovascularization [6], 
which is a key step in stromal keratitis caused by Herpes 
Simplex Virus infection. To improve the therapeutic effi-
cacy of drug candidates by improving its bioavailability, a 
prodrug strategy was retained and a lipophilic prodrug was 
designed. Due to its lipophilic nature, the prodrug (FV-
80228, prodrug) can penetrate the corneal epithelium 
where enzymes hydrolyze it to the active hydrophilic 
compound (drug). The drug is then released into the stroma 
and, by diffusion, reaches the eye anterior chamber. Two 
formulations (solution or nanosuspension) were investi-
gated during development process. The objective of this 
study was to describe a posteriori pharmacokinetics of our 
compound with a top-down population approach. Contrary 
to usual compartmental pharmacokinetic analyses [7, 8], 
population modeling allows estimating the individual drug 
penetration into different specific compartments of the eyes 
with only few samples. The present analysis aimed at 
developing and validating a population pharmacokinetic 
model able to predict the individual concentrations of the 
drug in selected ocular tissues and fluids. The inter-indi-
vidual variability of all model parameters was planned to 
be assessed as well. It is worth emphasizing that this kind </p>

<p>of methods would be helpful in preclinical drug develop-
ment phase, in term of efficacy (predict the individual 
concentration available in the compartment of interest, here 
cornea) and safety (i.e., relationship between concentration 
in a compartment and side effect). </p>

<p>2 Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Animal studies and procedures of our laboratories comply 
with the Directive 2010/63/EU of the European parliament 
and the related French transposition texts. The experi-
mental design was approved by the local ''Comité d'Ethi-
que pour la Protection des Animaux de Laboratoire'' 
(Animal Care and Use Committee) and the study was 
performed in accordance with the internal Charter on the 
Humane Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. </p>

<p>2.1 Compounds </p>

<p>Drug (FV-60165) has following physico-chemical charac-
teristics: MW = 450; Log P = 4.7 and Log D at pH 
7.4 = 2.5. The prodrug (FV-80228) has following physico-
chemical characteristics: MW = 554; Log P = 6.5 and 
Log D at pH 7.4 = 4.3. The prodrug is more lipophilic than 
the drug, thus penetrates the corneal epithelium where 
enzymes hydrolyze it to the active hydrophilic compound 
(drug). </p>

<p>2.2 Administration Protocol </p>

<p>Forty-two male HY79b pigmented rabbits (approximately 
2-2.5 kg) were obtained from Hypharm-Roussay (France). 
All animals were housed individually in a temperature-
controlled animal housing facility, with a 12 h light/night 
cycle and with free access to food and water. Prodrug was 
administered to animals. Two formulations were evaluated: 
a 0.6 % solution in 2-hydroxy-propyl-betacyclodextrine 
7 % at pH 5, and a 0.6 % nanosuspension in 0.5 % car-
boxymethylcellulose 7 LFPH and 0.015 % tween 80 in 
phosphate buffered saline at pH 7.4. The rabbits were 
randomly assigned to two groups: those from ''Group 1'' 
(21 animals) received the solution and those from ''Group 
2'' (21 animals) received the nanosuspension. Each rabbit 
received two 30 lL drops of either formulation into both 
eyes (with a 10-min interval between administrations of the 
first and of the second drop), corresponding to a total dose 
of prodrug of 720 lg per animal (2 9 180 lg/eye). The 
eye drops was instilled with a calibrated adjustable mi-
cropipette fitted with disposable tips into the lower con-
junctival sac of the eye by pulling the lower lid away from 
the eyeball. After instillation, the upper and the lower lids 
were held together for a few seconds to avoid rapid </p>

<p> 
N. Djebli et al. </p>

<p>removal of the eye drop from the ocular surface. Animals 
were observed for overall health and local tolerance to the 
formulations until the end of the study. </p>

<p>2.3 Sampling Protocol </p>

<p>At predetermined time-intervals after administration, ani-
mals (n = 3 per sampling time and per formulation) were 
anesthetized with an intramuscular injection of a mixture, 
ketamine/xylazine (25/5 mg/kg). Just before killing, tear 
fluid was collected from the left and the right eyes of each 
rabbit with Schirmer tear strips, and blood was collected by 
intracardiac puncture into tubes containing lithium heparin 
as anti-coagulant and processed to obtain plasma. Blood 
samples were obtained at 0.083, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, and 8 h. 
The rabbits were killed immediately after blood sample 
extraction. Just after killing, the two eyes of each animal 
were removed and dissected to extract surgically the dif-
ferent eye substructures. Samples from cornea, aqueous 
humor, vitreous, choroid, retina and sclera were obtained 
from each eye. In parallel, the nasolacrimal duct was iso-
lated from the skull. The ocular tissue and fluid samples 
were collected into pre-weighed, labeled cryotubes and 
then carefully weighed to determine the amount of each 
tissue (or fluid) collected. After collection, ocular samples 
were stored frozen until thawed for analysis. Concentra-
tion-time points of both prodrug and drug, were obtained 
from each matrix (tear fluid, naso-lacrymal duct, cornea 
and aqueous humor) after ocular instillation of the prodrug 
in rabbits. Standard pharmacokinetic parameters were 
calculated from the drug concentration in each matrix in 
each eye of each animal. </p>

<p>2.4 Analytical Methods </p>

<p>Each matrix is mixed with water and PMSF (Interchim) 
30 mg/mL (10 % of the global weight) in Precellys 24 
(Ozyme). An electrospray LC-MS/MS (LC system: Nexera 
X2, Shimadzu; MS/MS detector: API4000, AB Sciex) was 
used for prodrug and drug quantification in rabbit ocular 
tissue homogenates involving protein precipitation fol-
lowed by chromatographic separation and tandem MS 
detection. The compounds were dissolved in DMSO and 
the working solutions for quality controls (QCs) and cali-
bration curves were prepared separately in tubes acetoni-
trile, by successive dilutions. Stock and working solutions 
were stored at ?5 ± 3°C in their stability period 
(\24 days). 50 lL of ocular tissues homogenates for cali-
bration standards and QCs was spiked with 5 lL of 
working solution. 150 lL of ACN was added. The tubes 
were capped, homogenized, centrifuged (10 min, 
15,338 9 g) and recovered in polypropylene 96 well-
plates. The lower limit of quantification (LLOQ) of </p>

<p>prodrug and drug was 0.5 ng/mL in plasma, 2 ng/mL in 
aqueous humor and 100 ng/mL in the tears with a range of 
quantification (RQ) of 0.5-100, 2-100, 100-10,000 ng/mL, 
respectively. For the cornea homogenate (dilution factor 
for homogenate = 1/6), the LLOQ was 1 ng/mL for the 
prodrug (RQ = [1-100 ng/mL]) and 10 ng/mL for the 
drug (RQ = [10-1000 ng/mL]). For the nasolacrimal duct 
homogenate (dilution factor for homogenate = 1/11) the 
LLOQ was 1 ng/mL for the prodrug (RQ = [1-100 ng/ 
mL]) and 2.5 ng/mL for the drug (RQ = [2.5-1000 ng/ 
mL]). Accuracy and precision fulfilled criteria used for 
drug determination in tissues using exploratory methods 
(\20 % except for LLOQ \25 %). </p>

<p>2.5 Population Pharmacokinetic Analysis </p>

<p>Analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">NONMEM</rs> (v <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">7.2.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">ICON Development Solutions</rs>, MD, USA). The different tissues 
(tear, naso-lacrymal duct, cornea, aqueous humor) were 
considered as different compartments. Because of its 
physiology, each eye was considered as an individual [8,  9]. So, a total of 84 individuals were considered in the 
dataset. </p>

<p>2.5.1 Pharmacostatistical Model (PSM) </p>

<p>In addition to the global multi-compartmental structure, 
many model configurations were tested, e.g., first-order rate 
constant or inter-compartmental clearance between the 
different compartments, a drug cleared or not from the 
naso-lacrymal duct, a drug cleared or not from the cornea, 
either fixed volumes of distribution at known physiological 
values to avoid an over-parameterization of the model or 
let free to be estimated by <rs type="software">NONMEM</rs>. Regarding the 
nanosuspension formulation, two kinetics of administration 
situations were tested for nanosuspensions (1) administra-
tion with zero-order kinetic in the tear, in this case it would 
allow estimating the duration of the nanosuspension dis-
solution in the tear or (2) administration as a bolus as it was 
done for the solution. In the last case, the only way to take 
into account the formulation was to test it as a binary 
covariate on the relevant model parameters. The estimation 
of inter-individual variability (g) was evaluated using 
either a constant coefficient variation (CV) or proportional 
error model. The full non diagonal matrix (x-block) and 
the different combinations of g correlations were evaluated 
as well as the possibility to fix some x 
2 to zero. The 
selection of a x-block, if any, was made on the basis of the 
objective function value (OFV) decrease. Many algorithms 
were tested only one by one or by a combination. Given the 
complexity of the current model and the multi-compart-
mental structure, several differential equation solvers were 
evaluated. The model selection was performed on the basis </p>

<p>PopPK Model of Ocular Drug Distribution </p>

<p>
of the knowledge of the eye structure, the minimization 
status (i.e., successful), the covariance phase (i.e., com-
pleted without any warning message), the absence of any 
correlation between parameter estimates larger than 0.95, 
the examination of standard error of the parameter esti-
mates (i.e., B50 %), significant digit of the final parameter 
estimates (i.e., 3.0). The best pharmacostatistical model 
was selected based on the lowest OFV and the inspection 
of goodness of fits, i.e., population and individual weighted 
residuals (CWRES and IWRES), observed tissue concen-
trations (DV, for dependent variable) plots versus popula-
tion and individual predicted concentrations (PRED and 
IPRED). </p>

<p>2.5.2 Handling of Topical Administration </p>

<p>In the current analysis, the distribution of the drug was 
analyzed after topical administration (2 9 30 lL of the 
prodrug). Given the fact that a maximum of only 10 lL 
could remain as administered in the tear (1/3rd of the 
administered dose was documented in the dataset) and 
based on the known huge inter-individual variability 
(linked to the naso-lacrymal and wink-mediated clearance), 
the fraction of drug that appears in the tears after prodrug 
administration (relative bioavailability in the tears: F 1 ) was 
also evaluated. </p>

<p>2.5.3 Covariate Screening </p>

<p>The only relevant covariate available in the current analysis 
is the formulation covariate. This covariate was tested on 
all the major parameters linked to the dissolution in the 
tears and to the distribution to the naso-lacrymal duct and 
to cornea. The significance of a parameter-covariate rela-
tionship was reflected by a decrease of OFV of at least 3.84 
(p value \0.05 with one degree of freedom). </p>

<p>2.5.4 Final Model Validation </p>

<p>Depending on the method(s) retained in the selected final 
model, the standard error parameters' estimates (SEE) were 
computed. SEEs were calculated as percentage of RSE 
(relative standard error, % RSE = 100 9 SEE/parameter 
estimate). The individual predicted pharmacokinetic 
parameters were computed from the population parameters 
using all available sources of information (i.e., with indi-
vidual covariates if any). Mean prediction error, and their 
associated 95 % CIs were also evaluated. The gs were 
plotted against covariates to evidence a possible bias in 
covariate inclusion. Prediction-corrected visual predictive 
check (PcVPC) was used to evaluate the performance of 
the final model for each tissue compartment. The PcVPC 
method is based on 1000 simulations data from the model </p>

<p>and the underlying design of the observed data [10]. As an 
improvement to the classical VPC, in the PcVPC, the 
variability coming from binning across independent vari-
ables was removed by normalizing the observed and sim-
ulated dependent variable based on the typical population 
prediction for the median independent variable in the bin 
[11]. 
Simulations were performed to predict for each rabbit 
eye, in each compartment, the full concentration-time 
profiles using the individual predicted model parameters, 
based on a single observed time point. To do this, addi-
tional virtual sampling was generated in the data set used to 
perform the simulations. In addition, to predict the tissue 
concentration-time profiles for a typical rabbit eye, simu-
lations were performed using the estimated typical value 
for each model parameter, after topical administration of 
solution or nanosuspensions' formulations. </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>Most of the prodrug concentrations were below the LLOQ 
in plasma, ocular tissues and fluid samples, except in the 
tears (i.e., the site of drug administration) where the pro-
drug high concentrations was quantified. As expected, 
these results strongly suggested very quick hydrolysis of 
the prodrug into the drug in the tear fluid and cornea. 
Consequently, only the drug concentrations were docu-
mented in the data set and a total of 336 tissue drug con-
centrations values were collected. The multi-
compartmental model structure of the eye finally selected 
in the current analysis is presented in Fig. 1. Describing the 
kinetic of administration of the nanosuspension as a zero-
order administration in the tears, and the solution as a bolus 
administration was not successful. That is why the for-
mulation was described as bolus administration in the tears 
for both formulations. Nevertheless, the quality of the 
results obtained with this model was not satisfactory: RSE 
% on volume of distribution of naso-lacrymal duct (V 2 ) 
was 52 % and on r was 188 %. Consequently, the for-
mulation was tested as a covariate on all the relevant model 
parameters and retained in the structural model on the first-
order rate constant from the tears to naso-lacrymal duct 
(k 12 ) as follows: k 12 = h i 9 FORMULATION ? h j 9 (1-
FORMULATION). This choice improved the model 
quality criteria (RSE % on V 2 = 39.3 % and on 
r = 107 %, with mean r value of approximately 0.491 %). 
The proportional error model was selected to describe 
inter-individual variability. All the model parameters (F 1 , 
k 12 , k 13 , V 1 , V 2 , V 3 , Cl nl , Q, V 4 , and Cl ah , see Table 1 for 
parameters definition) and the corresponding inter-indi-
vidual variabilities, were fitted except the Cl c , fixed to 
10 % of the Cl ah . This value was the result of an intensive </p>

<p> 
N. Djebli et al. </p>

<p>sensitivity analysis (i.e., 25 runs launched with different 
fixed values of the Cl c as fraction of Cl ah from 0.1 to 2). 
This finding is consistent with the physiology (i.e., aqueous 
humor being a fluid with a higher turnover compared to the 
cornea tissue). None of the x-block tested was selected, 
since they did not lead to any improvement of the model, 
and the diagonal matrix was therefore selected. Among the 
different models tested for residual variability, the model 
selected was the proportional error model for all com-
partments taken together leading to estimate only one r. 
This was a logical outcome if we considered that the 
residual variability was linked to bioanalysis and that the 
analytical method was the same for all compartments. 
Among all the algorithms tested and previously mentioned, 
the classical FOCE-Interaction method followed by the 
MCMC Bayesian analysis method was selected and 
ADVAN13 subroutine was selected to solve the differential 
equations. The final model parameters were presented in 
Table 1. The final model was the PSM model, since the 
only covariate to be tested was the formulation as the latter 
was included straightaway in the structural model, to 
ensure higher model stability and better quality criteria. 
PRED and IPRED values were plotted versus DV in Fig. 2 
to evaluate the global quality of the model fitting. This 
figure showed a good fit regarding both IPRED and PRED 
since all the weighted residuals were within the range [-4, 
?4] (Fig. 3), suggesting a good predictive performance of </p>

<p>the model. The CWRES and IWRES were plotted versus 
PRED and IPRED, respectively, in Fig. 3. The model 
parameters' estimates, their RSE % and 95 % CIs are 
presented in Table 1. All the percentage of RSE was lower 
than 20 %, except the RSE % of V 2 (population parameters 
of the volume of distribution of the naso-lacrymal duct) 
which was 39.3 % (lower than 50 %, so that the CI 95 % 
did not include zero) and of the proportional residual error 
which was 107 %. Nevertheless, the estimated proportional 
residual error was only about 0.491 %. The individual 
predicted pharmacokinetics parameters (P ind ) were com-
puted from the population parameters, using covariate 
included in the model (formulation on k 12 ). Mean predic-
tion error of P ind toward the population predicted param-
eters (P pop ) and their associated 95 % CIs are presented in 
Table 1. The results showed a slight, but significant mean 
prediction error for Cl ah , k 12 , V 1 , V 4 , and for F 1 . They 
showed no significant mean bias for Q, k 13 , Cl nl , V 2 , and 
V 3 . PcVPC was used to evaluate the predictive perfor-
mance of the final model at steady state. The results of the 
simulations performed are presented in Fig. 4 for each 
tissue compartment. Due to the huge range of concentration 
(0.0202-6260 ng/lL), Pc-VPC was represented in log 
scale. For each tissue compartment, all the observed con-
centration values were in the range of 5th to 95th percentile 
of predicted values from 1000 simulations using the final 
model. This PcVPC figure showed the good predictive 
performance of the model. In addition, the individual full 
concentration-time profiles predicted using the estimated 
individual model parameters, presented in Fig. 5, show the 
distribution behavior of the drug, in each compartment, for 
each rabbit eye used in the data set. Moreover, the pre-
dicted concentration-time profiles in each compartment, 
presented in Fig. 6, when considering a typical rabbit eye, 
after topical administration of solution or nanosuspensions' 
formulations allow focusing on the predicted distribution 
of the drug in each compartment for each formulation, 
regardless of the inter-individual variability parameters. </p>

<p>4 Discussion </p>

<p>The eyes are strongly protected against the environment 
and the systemic circulation by the blood-retinal barrier. 
Furthermore, after topical administration in the contralat-
eral eye, each eye is considered as isolated [8, 9]. There-
fore, each eye was considered as an individual and may be 
considered as a holistic multi-compartmental structure. The 
challenge of this work was (1) to develop and validate a 
population pharmacokinetic model able to predict the 
individual concentrations of a drug in each tissue of the 
anterior segment of the rabbit eye from the drug concen-
trations obtained in tears, cornea, naso-lacrymal duct and </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Multi-compartimental model of eye selected. F 1 relative 
bioavailability in the tears, k 12 (h </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) rate constant (tear to the naso-
lacrymal duct) in nanosuspensions, k 12 (h </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) rate constant (tear to the 
naso-lacrymal duct) in solution, k 13 (h </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) rate constant (tear to 
cornea), Q (lL/h) inter-compartmental clearance (cornea/aqueous 
humor), Cl nl (lL/h) clearance from naso-lacrymal duct, Cl ah (lL/h) 
clearance from aqueous humor, Cl c clearance from cornea compart-
ment = 0.1 9 Cl ah , V 1 (lL) volume of distribution (tear), V 2 (lL) 
volume of distribution of naso-lacrymal duct, V 3 (lL) volume of 
distribution of cornea, V 4 (lL) volume of distribution of the aqueous 
humor </p>

<p>PopPK Model of Ocular Drug Distribution </p>

<p>
aqueous humor and (2) to determine the inter-individual 
variability of the model parameters. Furthermore, we nee-
ded to evaluate the impact of the formulation (solution or 
nanosuspension) on the drug pharmacokinetics. We 
developed and validated a PopPK model describing the 
pharmacokinetic of the drug in the different tissues of the 
anterior segment in the rabbit eye after topical adminis-
tration of the prodrug. The model has good quality criteria 
for the prediction of ocular drug distribution over time. 
Overall, the estimated values for the PopPK model 
parameters were in the same magnitude as those published 
in the review of Worakol et al. [7] linked to the physiology 
of the rabbit eye: for instance, the published estimated 
clearance from the aqueous humor in the rabbit is </p>

<p>approximately 3-4.7 lL/min (180-282 lL/h) while the 
PopPK model estimate we obtained was 231 lL/h for the 
Cl ah . Nevertheless, there is a probable perfect fit of the 
model to the data, illustrated by the very low IWRES of the 
drug together with the high g-shrinkage observed for some 
parameters (e.g., 74.4 % for Cl ah , 91.5 % for k 12 , 98.5 % 
for V 3 , and 81.8 % for V 4 ). These warnings regarding a 
probable perfect fit could suggest an over-parameterization 
of the model. However, the very low conditional number of 
2.78, a numerical criterion that is usually higher than 1000 
when the model is over-parameterized, mitigates this 
statement. The probable perfect fit and the high g-shrinkage 
observed are probably linked to the naive pooled nature of 
the data (only a single sampling time point per </p>

<p>Table 1 Final model: population parameters </p>

<p>Parameter 
Estimate 
% RSE 
[95 % CI] 
Mean prediction error (%); [95 %CI] </p>

<p>F 1 
0.300 
6.65 
[0.260; 0.340] 
21.7 [10.4; 33.1] </p>

<p>k 12 (h </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) nanosuspensions 
0.259 
12.1 
[0.197; 0.322] 
-25.0 [-29.6; -20.4] </p>

<p>k 12 (h </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) solution 
0.299 
12.6 
[0.224; 0.375] 
-25.0 [-29.6; -20.4] </p>

<p>k 13 (h </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) 
0.340 
5.28 
[0.304; 0.376] 
2.53 [-1.23; 6.29] </p>

<p>Q (lL/h) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.136 
19.8 
[0.0821; 0.190] 
32.2 [-2.45; 66.37] </p>

<p>Cl nl (lL/h) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>275 
9.87 
[220; 329] 
20.5 [-17.7; 58.7] </p>

<p>Cl ah (lL/h) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>231 
9.58 
[187; 274] 
13.8 [5.09; 22.5] </p>

<p>V 1 (lL) 
155 
16.4 
[104; 206] 
39.7 [17.6; 61.9] </p>

<p>V 2 (lL) 
1.24 
39.3 
[0.266; 2.22] 
93.1 [-11.0; 196] </p>

<p>V 3 (lL) 
42.8 
5.54 
[38.1; 47.6] 
0.220 [-2.74; 3.18] </p>

<p>V 4 (lL) 
218 
14.5 
[155; 282] 
29.4 [2.98; 55.7] </p>

<p>Estimate (%) 
CV % 
[95 % CI]-shrinkage % </p>

<p>Inter-individual variability </p>

<p>F 1 
60.5 
17.6 
[48.7; 70.3]-1.97 </p>

<p>k 12 
80.0 
18.3 
[63.8; 93.6]-91.5 </p>

<p>k 13 
45.3 
16.7 
[37.0; 52.3]-59.7 </p>

<p>Q 
172 
17.3 
[139; 199]-17.8 </p>

<p>Cl nl 
90.5 
16.7 
[73.9; 104]-19.2 </p>

<p>Cl ah 
92.0 
16.9 
[74.9; 106]-74.4 </p>

<p>V 1 
153 
17.0 
[124; 177]-47.4 </p>

<p>V 2 
437 
18.4 
[347; 511]-60.6 </p>

<p>V 3 
51.1 
18.2 
[40.8; 59.7]-98.5 </p>

<p>V 4 
265 
18.6 
[210; 311]-81.8 </p>

<p>Residual variability 
r 
0.491 
107 
[NA; 0.871]-99.8 </p>

<p>CI confidence interval, NA not applicable, F 1 relative bioavailability in the tears, k 12 (h </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) rate constant (tear to the naso-lacrymal duct) in 
nanosuspensions and in solution, k 13 (h </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) rate constant (tear to cornea), k 34 rate constant (cornea to aqueous humor, k 43 rate constant (from 
aqueous humor to cornea, k 20 elimination rate constant from naso-lacrimal duct, k 40 elimination rate constant from aqueous humor, Q (lL/h) 
inter-compartmental clearance (cornea/aqueous humor), Cl nl (lL/h) clearance from naso-lacrymal duct, Cl ah (lL/h) clearance from aqueous 
humor, V 1 (lL) volume of distribution (tear), V 2 (lL) volume of distribution of naso-lacrymal duct, V 3 (lL) volume of distribution of cornea, V 4 
(lL) volume of distribution of the aqueous humor 
a Q = k 34 9 V 3 = k 43 9 V 4 </p>

<p>b Cl nl = k 20 9 V 2 </p>

<p>c Cl ah = k 40 9 V 4 </p>

<p> 
N. Djebli et al. </p>

<p>compartment was reported per eye) and to the intrinsic 
physiology of the eye requiring a structural model with 
numerous flow rates and volumes of distribution (i.e., 
estimation of many first-order rate constants k 12 , k 13 , k 30 , 
k 34 , k 43 , and k 40 and volumes V 1 , V 2 , V 3 , and V 4 ). A sim-
plification of the structural model would have been an </p>

<p>option to avoid the high g-shrinkage. However, given that 
the target tissue is the cornea and that it was important to 
estimate the individual concentrations in the target tissue, it 
would not have been possible to further simplify the 
structural model. Formulation's inclusion led to an esti-
mated mean population value for k 12 of 0.299 h 
-1 for the </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Relationship between individual predicted (IPRED, red solid dots) and population predicted (PRED, blue open circles) versus observed 
tissue concentrations in log-log scale in tears, nasolacrimal duct, cornea and aqueous humor </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Relationship between individual weighted residuals (IWRES) 
and individual predicted concentrations in log scale (a); relationship 
between conditional weighted residuals (CWRES) and population </p>

<p>predicted concentrations in log scale (b) from pooled data set (tears, 
nasolacrimal duct, cornea, and aqueous humor) of the 84 rabbit eyes </p>

<p>PopPK Model of Ocular Drug Distribution </p>

<p>
Fig. 4 Prediction corrected 
visual predictive check of the 
final model (log scale) in the 
tears, in the nasolacrimal duct, 
in the cornea and in aqueous 
humor. Blue areas represent the 
95 % CI of the 5th and 95th 
percentiles of the predictions; 
pink area represents the 
95 % CI of the median of 
predictions; purple area 
represents the overlap between 
blue and pink areas; blue dots 
are observed tissue 
concentrations; solid red line 
represents the median of 
observations and dashed red 
lines represent the 5th and 95th 
percentiles of observations </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Predicted tissue 
concentration-time profiles 
(solid lines) and observed 
concentrations (dots) in the 
tears, nasolacrimal duct with 
solution formulation (red) and 
with nanosuspension 
formulation (blue), cornea and 
aqueous humor in each eye </p>

<p> 
N. Djebli et al. </p>

<p>solution, and of 0.259 h 
-1 for the nanosuspension sug-
gesting a low impact of the formulation on the drug tissue 
distribution. Cl nl was found to be the highest clearance for 
the drug which is a result consistent with physiological 
considerations. Because of the inherent difficulty in mea-
suring concentrations in eye tissues and fluids (small size 
of the samples making difficult dissection and collection, 
and relatively low drug concentrations in these samples), 
pharmacokinetics/pharmacodynamics modeling may be 
used to anticipate on the results obtained in non-clinical 
studies of ophthalmic drugs. It is particularly of added 
value to provide fit-for-purpose pharmacokinetics/phar-
macodynamics models when enough data is available. The 
warnings reported in the present analysis, could be 
addressed if the study has been designed according to the 
specifications of a population analysis. Nevertheless, the 
present modeling work has been performed retrospectively 
once pharmacokinetic data were provided. When the 
appropriate pharmacokinetics or pharmacodynamics data 
are available, this approach could allow the prediction of 
drug concentrations in the target tissue, the evaluation of 
efficacy and/or safety (e.g., change of the pharmacokinetics 
variable in the target tissue) and the identification of the 
impact of covariates on tissue distribution in specific 
populations (e.g., albino or pigmented rabbits and genetic 
polymorphisms). This is all the more interesting if there are 
more covariates to evaluate (in the present analysis, only 
the impact of the formulation was investigated). Based on 
simulations, this population pharmacokinetic model may 
be used to optimize sampling schemes in future experi-
ments, and improve the predictive performance of subse-
quent population pharmacokinetic models. As shown in 
Fig. 5, concentration-time profiles were simulated in tears, 
naso-lacrymal duct, cornea and aqueous humor for each 
rabbit eye, using only a single sampling time point for each 
simulated profile. In addition, Fig. 6 shows the predicted 
tissue concentration-time profiles for a typical rabbit eye </p>

<p>after solution and nanosuspensions' formulations. Despite 
the statistically significant relationship between the for-
mulation covariate and k 12 , there was only a 13.4 % dif-
ference between the estimated typical value of k 12 between 
the two formulations (0.299 h 
-1 for the solution and 
0.259 h 
-1 for nanosuspensions). In literature, only three 
cases of pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic models [12- 14] were reported concerning drug pharmacokinetics in the 
eye after topical administration and none with PopPK 
model describing pharmacokinetics in ocular tissue sam-
ples. Pamulapati et al. [12] described pharmacokinetics 
with a three physiologically based compartmental model 
(cornea, aqueous humor and iris-ciliary body) with zero-
order rate constant on cornea, but without including tears 
or the nasolacrimal compartment. In fact, Pamulapati 
choice of structural model may have a huge impact on 
pharmacokinetics after topical administration. For Saka-
naka et al. [13, 14] pharmacokinetic parameters were 
estimated by a nonlinear least-squares computer program 
with six (for timolol) or seven (for bunazosin) compart-
mental model. The authors [12-14] used a naive pool data 
approach by considering the samples as collected from 
only one ''mean'' individual (no population approach 
assessed) closing the door to any estimation of inter-indi-
vidual variability. We found only one published top-down 
analysis after topical administration of fluorescein in the 
human eye [15], based on in vivo fluorimetric measure-
ments. Nevertheless, this measurement technique is not 
applicable to compounds during preclinical drug develop-
ment stage. This model is in agreement with the pharma-
cokinetics principle of parsimony and, at the same time, 
allows adequate fitting of the data. 
The challenge in ophthalmic pharmaceutical research is 
to optimize the pharmacokinetic parameters of drugs par-
ticularly in terms of bioavailability and distribution. Fur-
ther simulations, based on the developed and qualified 
model for a particular compound, can be performed using 
specific dosing regimen or subpopulations of interest to 
answer specific questions linked to drug distribution. Rare 
cases concerning pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic 
modeling were reported in the literature. Even if the 
strategy of drug delivery is mainly based on pharmacoki-
netics [16, 17], little is known about drug distribution in the 
eye after topical application because only few analyses 
have been performed. </p>

<p>5 Conclusion </p>

<p>We developed and validated a PopPK model describing the 
pharmacokinetics of the drug in the different tissues of the 
anterior segment in the rabbit eye after topical adminis-
tration of the prodrug. If optimized pharmacokinetic </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Predicted tissue concentration-time profiles in the tears, 
nasolacrimal duct, cornea and aqueous humor for a typical rabbit 
eye with the solution or nanosuspensions </p>

<p>PopPK Model of Ocular Drug Distribution </p>

<p>
sampling schemes and relevant safety and efficacy data 
available, this approach could allow the prediction of drug 
concentrations in the target tissue, the evaluation of effi-
cacy and/or safety (e.g., change of the pharmacodynamics 
variable in the target tissue) and the identification of the 
impact of covariates on tissue distribution in specific 
populations (e.g., albino or pigmented rabbits and genetic 
polymorphisms). This is all the more interesting if there are 
more covariates to evaluate (in the present analysis, only 
the impact of the formulation was investigated). Based on 
simulations, this population pharmacokinetic model may 
be used to optimize sampling schemes in future experi-
ments, and improve the predictive performance of subse-
quent population pharmacokinetic models. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments Many thanks to Serge Burgell, Christelle Car-
bonnier, Julien Fanelli, and Franck Pineau (Animal Study Conduct 
Team 1, Animal Research and Welfare) for their part in eye tissue 
collection, to Marilyn Calderone (Chemical Development, Lead 
Generation and Candidate Release) for her involvement in the for-
mulations area and to Catherine Bougette (Shared Services, Dispo-
sition Safety and Animal Research) for her assistance in drafting. </p>

<p>Compliance with Ethical Standards </p>

<p>Funding No sources of funding were received for the conduct of 
this study. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest ND, SK, FG, A-LC, AT, GF, CL and DF have 
no potential conflicts of interests to declare. </p>

<p>Ethical approval The experimental design was approved by the 
local ''Comité d'Ethique pour la Protection des Animaux de Labo-
ratoire'' (Animal Care and Use Committee) and the study was per-
formed in accordance with the internal Charter on the Humane Care 
and Use of Laboratory Animals. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which per-
mits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original 
author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons 
license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p> 
N. Djebli et al. </p>

</text></tei>