<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5414882" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Exposure of cancer cells to particular chemotherapeutic agents or g-irradiation induces a form of cell death 
that stimulates an immune response in mice. This "immunogenic cell death" requires calreticulin (CRT) 
translocation to the plasma membrane, which has been shown to promote cancer cell phagocytosis. 
However, it remains unclear whether the effect of CRT on cancer cell phagocytosis is alone sufficient to 
affect tumor immunity. Acute myeloid leukemia (AML) cells expressing cell-surface CRT were generated in 
order to characterize the mechanism(s) through which CRT activates tumor immune responses. Potent 
immune-mediated control or rejection of AML was observed in mice with CRT-expressing leukemia. The 
"CRT effect" was ultimately T-cell dependent, but dendritic cells (DCs), and CD8a C DCs in particular, were 
also necessary, indicating that CRT might act directly on these DCs. CRT-expressing AML cells were slightly 
more susceptible to phagocytosis by DCs in vivo, but this effect was unlikely to explain the potent 
immunity observed. CRT did not affect classical DC maturation markers, but induced expression of type I 
interferon (IFN), which was critical for its positive effect on survival. In conclusion, CRT functions as a 
"danger signal" that promotes a host type I IFN response associated with the induction of potent 
leukemia-specific T-cell immunity. </p>

<p>Exposure of cancer cells to particular chemotherapeutic drugs or 
g-irradiation induces a form of apoptosis that stimulates an 
immune response in mice. 1,2 This "immunogenic cell death" 
requires translocation of a chaperone protein called calreticulin 
(CRT) from the endoplasmic reticulum (ER), where it normally 
resides, to the plasma membrane. 3 Under homeostatic conditions, 
calreticulin is involved in major histocompatibility complex 
(MHC) class I assembly, and in the maintenance of ER calcium 
homeostasis. 4 Cell surface CRT translocation requires activation of 
pancreatic ER kinase (PERK), which phosphorylates eukaryotic 
translation initiation factor (eIF2a). eIF2a-mediated triggering of 
ER stress pathways culminates in anterograde transport of CRT 
through the Golgi to the cell surface. 3 Following translocation, 
CRT functions as an "eat me" signal to promote efferocytosis by 
APCs through a receptor called low-density lipoprotein-related 
protein (LRP; CD91). 5,6 CRT translocation also occurs in viable 
malignant cells, 7 suggesting that apoptosis may not be required for 
CRT translocation, and that activation of "ER stress" programs can 
be sufficient to promote its cell surface expression. 
A major unanswered question regarding CRT is whether its 
effect on tumor immunity depends exclusively on its ability to 
enhance cancer cell engulfment. By inducing phagocytosis of 
apoptotic tumor cells by APCs, CRT might promote cross-pre-
sentation of tumor antigens to T cells. However, antigen cross-</p>

<p>presentation by immature dendritic cells (DCs) results in T-cell 
tolerance, rather than activation. 8 We therefore hypothesized 
that CRT might also directly stimulate APCs, leading to 
increased cross-priming of tumor-specific T cells. In support of 
this hypothesis, soluble CRT was recently shown to stimulate 
production of NF-kB-related cytokines by peritoneal macro-
phages in a CD91-dependent manner. 9 
Increased cell-surface CRT exposure on malignant cells has 
been reported in a number of human cancers, 7,10-12 including 
acute myeloid leukemia. 7,13 In a recent study, the degree of cell-
surface CRT expression on human acute myeloid leukemia 
(AML) cells was found to correlate with enhanced T-cell 
immunity to AML-associated antigens and improved clinical 
outcomes. 14 In addition, our laboratory is interested in charac-
terizing pathways that promote innate immune sensing of 
AML. 15 With these notions in mind, we sought to investigate 
mechanisms through which CRT translocation on AML cells 
might promote anti-leukemia immunity. Thus, AML cells with 
stable cell-surface CRT expression were generated in order to 
investigate how CRT, as an isolated variable (i.e., without the 
requirement for chemotherapy or radiation exposure), affects 
anti-leukemia immunity. In a systemic disease model known to 
induce a potent T-cell tolerant state, 16 CRT expression on AML 
cells was associated with prolonged survival in wild-type, but 
not in T-cell-deficient mice. Moreover, leukemia-specific CD8 C </p>

<p>CONTACT Justin Kline M.D., 
jkline@medicine.bsd.uchicago.edu 
Department of Medicine, University of Chicago, 5841 S. Maryland Avenue, MC 2115, Chicago, IL 
60637, USA. 
Supplemental data for this article can be accessed on the publisher's website. </p>

<p>Published with license by Taylor &amp; Francis Group, LLC © Xiufen Chen, Dominick Fosco, Douglas E. Kline, and Justin Kline. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/), 
which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, and is not altered, transformed, or built upon in any way. </p>

<p>ONCOIMMUNOLOGY 
2017, VOL. 6, NO. 4, e1278332 (11 pages) 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/2162402X.2016.1278332 </p>

<p>T-cell responses were significantly augmented in mice harbor-
ing CRT-expressing AML, indicating that T cells were required 
to mediate the CRT effect on anti-leukemia immunity. CD8a C 
DCs were also necessary for the "CRT effect," which suggested 
that CRT acts upstream of adaptive immunity. A modest 
increase in engulfment of CRT-expressing AML cells by DCs 
was observed, but did not appear to explain its potent effect on 
immunity. Rather, CRT-induced expression of type I interferon 
(IFN) in leukemia-bearing mice, and host type I IFN signaling, 
was required for the effect of CRT on AML survival. In conclu-
sion, CRT functions as a "danger signal" to promote innate 
immune sensing of cancer through type I IFN. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Generation of CRT-expressing C1498 AML cells </p>

<p>To investigate how CRT, as an isolated variable, regulates antitu-
mor immune responses, its cell surface expression was engineered 
on C1498 and C1498.SIY AML cells through a GPI anchor 
(Fig. 1A). GPI-mediated protein anchoring to the plasma </p>

<p>membrane is sensitive to enzymatic cleavage by phospholipase C. 17 
Treatment of CRT-expressing C1498 cells with phospholipase C 
resulted in significantly decreased cell surface CRT (Fig. S1A and 
B), clearly demonstrating its GPI-dependent anchoring to the 
plasma membrane. Cell surface CRT expression on engineered 
C1498 AML cells was only slightly higher than that on control 
C1498 cells undergoing doxorubicin-induced apoptosis (Fig. S1C). 
Thus, we have generated an AML cell line that expresses cell surface 
CRT at a similar level to that observed following treatment with a 
chemotherapy agent known to induce CRT translocation. 2 
CRT is a member of a multi-protein peptide-loading com-
plex (PLC), which is involved in MHC class I folding and pep-
tide loading. 4 Thus, engineered CRT expression could 
conceivably affect the MHC class I presentation pathway in 
C1498 cells. However, equivalent cell surface K b levels were 
observed on CRT-expressing and control C1498 cells (Fig. 1B). 
Also, SIY-specific CD8 C 2C T cells proliferated similarly when 
cultured with C1498.SIY or C1498.SIY.CRT cells, indicating 
that MHC class I presentation of the SIY peptide antigen was 
not influenced by induced CRT expression (Fig. 1C). Last, the 
in vitro growth of C1498 and C1498.CRT cells was identical, </p>

<p>Figure 1. Generation of CRT-expressing AML cells. Representative FACS plots depicting expression of (A) CRT and (B) H-2K b on control C1498 and C1498.CRT cells. (C) CTV-
labeled 2C T cells were cultured in vitro for 3 d with parental C1498 cells (left), C1498.SIY cells (center) or C1498.SIY.CRT cells (right). Representative FACS plots demon-
strating CTV dilution of 2C T cells are shown after gating on live CD8 C 1B2 C cells. Numbers indicate the percentage of divided 2C T cells. Quantified data are shown to the 
right. (D) MTS assay of in vitro cultured C1498 and C1498.CRT cells. n.s.: not significant. (C, D) Data are representative of 2-4 experiments, each performed in triplicate. </p>

<p>e1278332-2 
X. CHEN ET AL. </p>

<p>demonstrating that engineered CRT expression did not affect 
AML cell viability or proliferation (Fig. 1D). </p>

<p>CRT expression on AML cells is associated with impaired 
tumor development </p>

<p>To determine whether CRT expression on C1498 cells affected 
their capacity to develop and progress as localized tumors, 
C1498 or C1498.CRT cells were inoculated subcutaneously (SC) 
into recipient hosts. Control C1498 tumors progressed rapidly in 
C57BL/6 mice. However, following SC C1498.CRT inoculation, 
70% of mice remained tumor-free (Fig. 2A). Conversely, both 
control and C1498.CRT tumors progressed similarly in Rag2 ¡/¡ 
hosts (Fig. 2B), which indicated that the adaptive immune sys-
tem was necessary to prevent localized growth of CRT-express-
ing C1498 tumors. Further, wild-type mice that rejected a SC 
C1498.CRT challenge were resistant to re-challenge with parental 
C1498 cells, suggesting that CRT expression on AML cells was 
sufficient to promote immunological memory against native leu-
kemia antigens (Fig. 2C). This result also indicates that CRT 
itself is not a direct antigenic target of adaptive immune cells in 
mice harboring CRT-expressing tumors. Collectively, these 
results demonstrate that CRT expression on cancer cells </p>

<p>negatively impacts localized tumor progression through a mecha-
nism which requires adaptive immunity. </p>

<p>CRT promotes enhanced survival in animals with systemic 
AML </p>

<p>It was next of interest to determine whether a similar result 
would occur in a systemic AML setting known to induce a T-
cell tolerant state, and which more accurately recapitulates 
human AML progression. 16 To that end, survival of C57BL/6 
mice was assessed following an intravenous (IV) challenge with 
C1498 or C1498.CRT cells. As shown in Fig. 2D, survival of 
mice harboring disseminated C1498.CRT AML was signifi-
cantly prolonged compared to those with control C1498 leuke-
mia. The effect on survival was much more striking when 
CRT-expressing C1498.SIY cells were introduced IV, where 
90% of mice survived long-term (Fig. 2E), and were consis-
tently able to reject a secondary C1498.SIY cell challenge 
(Fig. 2F). Thus, CRT expression on AML cells is sufficient to 
generate effective immunological memory responses, even in a 
disease setting associated with a profound T-cell tolerant state. 
Adaptive immunity was also required to promote CRT-
mediated survival in mice with systemic AML, as the survival </p>

<p>Figure 2. CRT expression impairs tumor development and delays progression of systemic AML. C1498 or C1498.CRT cells were inoculated SC into groups of C57BL/6 (A) or 
Rag2 ¡/¡ (B) mice, and tumor growth was assessed. Data represent tumor growth in individual mice. (C) Mice from (A) that remained tumor-free for 60 d after a SC C1498. 
CRT challenge received a secondary challenge with parental C1498 cells in the opposite flank. Tumor growth was compared to mice receiving a primary C1498 challenge. 
(D, E) Survival of C67BL/6 mice challenged with C1498 versus C1498.CRT IV (D) or with C1498.SIY versus C1498.SIY.CRT IV (E). (F) Mice from (E) that remained alive for 60 
d after an IV C1498.SIY.CRT challenge received a secondary challenge with C1498.SIY cells IV. Survival was compared to mice receiving a primary IV C1498.SIY challenge; </p>

<p>ÃÃÃ </p>

<p>p &lt;0.001. (G and H) Survival of C57BL/6 versus TCRb/d ¡/¡ mice challenged with C1498 versus C1498.CRT IV (G) or with C1498.SIY versus C1498.SIY.CRT IV (H). ÃÃ p 
&lt;0.001 for comparison of survival between C57BL/6 and TCRb/d ¡/¡ challenged with C1498.CRT cells. ÃÃÃ p &lt;0.0001 for comparison of survival between C57BL/6 and 
TCRb/d ¡/¡ challenged with C1498.SIY.CRT cells. (A-H) Data are pooled from two to three independent experiments, each with 2-5 mice/group. </p>

<p>ONCOIMMUNOLOGY 
e1278332-3 </p>

<p>benefit associated with CRT expression on leukemia cells was 
abrogated in Rag2 ¡/¡ mice (Fig. S2A), in TCRb/d ¡/¡ hosts 
(Fig. 2G and H), and also in C57BL/6 mice depleted of CD4 C 
and CD8 C T cells (Fig. S2B). In conclusion, the enhanced sur-
vival of mice with systemic CRT-expressing AML requires the 
adaptive immune system, and T cells in particular. </p>

<p>Augmented leukemia-specific T-cell responses in mice with 
CRT-expressing AML </p>

<p>Because T cells were found to be necessary for the CRT-medi-
ated effect on systemic leukemia progression, their ability to 
promote leukemia-specific T-cell responses was investigated. 
Six days following AML induction, SIY/K b pentamer staining 
revealed a significantly higher frequency (Fig. 3A and B) and </p>

<p>absolute number (Fig. 3B) of SIY antigen-specific CD8 C T cells 
in the spleens of mice with C1498.SIY.CRT versus control 
C1498.SIY AML. More impressive was the capacity for SIY-
specific CD8 C T cells from C1498.SIY.CRT-challenged mice to 
produce IFNg upon in vitro re-stimulation, which was approxi-
mately 6-fold higher compared to mice challenged with control 
C1498.SIY (Fig. 3C). 
To track the proliferation and accumulation of leukemia 
antigen-specific CD8 C T cells in leukemia-bearing mice, a T-
cell adoptive transfer model was employed. CTV-labeled, SIY 
antigen-specific, T-cell receptor (TCR) transgenic 2C T cells 
were transferred, and 1 d later, animals received C1498.SIY or 
C1498.SIY.CRT cells IV. 2C T cells accumulated poorly in mice 
with C1498.SIY leukemia as we have previously demonstrated 
(Fig. 3D and E). 16 However, 2C T-cell accumulation was </p>

<p>Figure 3. CRT promotes enhanced leukemia antigen-specific T-cell responses. (A) Representative FACS plots depicting the frequency of SIY/K b pentamer-reactive CD8 C T 
cells in the spleen of C57BL/6 mice challenged 6 d earlier with C1498.SIY (left) or C1498.SIY.CRT (right) IV. Numbers indicate the frequency of SIY C CD8 C cells among the 
entire CD8 C T-cell population. (B) Quantification of the frequency (left) and absolute number (right) of SIY/K b pentamer-reactive splenic CD8 C T cells following IV chal-
lenge with C1498.SIY versus C1498.SIY.CRT cells; Ã p &lt;0.05; ÃÃ p &lt;0.01. (C) Spleen cells from individual mice challenged IV with C1498.SIY versus C1498.SIY.CRT 6 d earlier 
were re-stimulated overnight in the presence of media or SIY peptide in an IFNg ELISPOT assay; ÃÃÃ p &lt;0.001. (D) Representative FACS plots demonstrating CTV dilution 
of 2C T cells 7 d following adoptive transfer into mice challenged IV with C1498.SIY (left) versus C1498.SIY.CRT (right). Numbers indicate 2C T-cell frequency among the 
entire CD8 C T-cell population. (E) Quantification of data in (D). ÃÃÃ p &lt;0.001. (F, G) In vivo cytolysis of SIY or OVA peptide-pulsed, CTV-labeled B6.SJL splenocytes (CD45 .1/ </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>) 6 h after IV inoculation into C57BL/6 mice (CD45 .2/.2 ) that previously received adoptive 2C T-cell transfer and IV challenge with C1498.SIY or C1498.SIY.CRT cells. Repre-
sentative plots are shown in (F) after gating on CD45.1 C donor cells. Numbers indicate the relative frequency of CTV-labeled CD45.1 C cells pulsed either with SIY or OVA 
peptide. Data are quantified in (G); ÃÃÃ p &lt;0.0001. (B, E, G) Data are pooled from two independent experiments each with 3-4 mice/group. (C) Data are representative of 
three independent experiments each with 3-4 mice/group. </p>

<p> 
X. CHEN ET AL. </p>

<p>enhanced 2-fold in C1498.SIY.CRT-bearing mice (Fig. 3D and 
E; Fig. S3A and B). CRT expression on AML cells also led to an 
improved capacity of 2C T cells to produce IFNg (Fig. S3C), 
and to lyse SIY antigen-pulsed targets in vivo (Fig. 3F and G). 
Taken together, these data reveal that CRT-expression on leu-
kemia cells significantly enhances the priming of highly func-
tional antigen-specific CD8 C T cells with the capacity to 
control, and even eradicate leukemia. </p>

<p>CRT modestly enhances the uptake of AML cells by splenic 
DCs in vivo </p>

<p>To determine whether cell surface CRT would enhance leuke-
mia cell engulfment in vivo, C1498 and C1498.CRT cells were 
labeled with unique fluorescent dyes (CFSE and CTV, respec-
tively) and were co-injected IV into mice in equal numbers. 
Three hours later, spleens of recipient animals were analyzed 
by flow cytometry for the frequency of fluorescence-containing 
CD11b C CD11c ¡ and CD11c C cells as a readout for phagocyto-
sis. Very few CD11b C cells from mice challenged with either 
C1498 or C1498.CRT cells contained a CFSE or CTV signal, 
suggesting that macrophages were not adept at AML cell 
uptake (Fig. 4A and B). However, a small population of </p>

<p>CD11c C cells was also CTV C or CFSE C , indicating that splenic 
DCs engulf AML cells in vivo (Fig. 4A and B). Moreover, the 
frequency of CD11c C cells that were CTV C was significantly 
higher than for CFSE (Fig. 4A and B), demonstrating in a com-
petitive setting that CRT modestly enhances DC-mediated 
phagocytosis of AML cells in vivo. To control for the possibility 
that the difference in observed uptake of cellular material from 
control and CRT-expressing AML cells was dependent on the 
particular fluorescent dye utilized, control C1498 cells were 
labeled either with CFSE or with CTV and a similar experiment 
was performed. Here, identical frequencies of CD11c C cells 
contained CTV versus CFSE fluorescence (Fig. S4A and B), 
indicating that the enhanced uptake of C1498.CRT cells by 
CD11c C cells was not an experimental artifact. </p>

<p>DCs are required for the CRT effect on survival in 
leukemia-bearing hosts </p>

<p>The role of DCs in regulating the effect CRT expression on 
AML survival was next examined. To ablate DCs from leuke-
mia-bearing hosts, CD11c DTR/GFP BMC mice were generated. 
DT-mediated elimination of CD11c-expressing cells was asso-
ciated with a rapid demise of mice harboring both control and </p>

<p>Figure 4. DCs are required to mediate the CRT effect in vivo. (A, B) C1498 or C1984.CRT cells were labeled with CFSE or CTV, respectively, were mixed at a 1:1 ratio, and were 
co-inoculated IV into recipient C57BL/6 mice. Three hours later, spleens were harvested and CD11b C or CD11c C cells were analyzed by flow cytometry for CTV and CFSE fluo-
rescence. (A) Representative flow plots are shown after gating on CD11c C (top row) and CD11b C cells (bottom row) from spleens of naive (left column) and leukemia-chal-
lenged (right column) mice. Numbers indicate the frequency of CD11c C or CD11b C cells that contained CFSE, CTV (or both) fluorescence. (B) Summary of data from (A); ÃÃ p 
&lt;0.001. (C) CD11c DTR/GFP bone marrow chimeric (BMC) mice were treated with DT or PBS as indicated, and received an IV challenge with C1498.SIY or C1498.SIY.CRT. Survival 
is shown. ÃÃÃ p &lt;0.0001 for survival comparison of C1498.SIY.CRT challenged mice treated with DT versus PBS. (D) C1498.SIY or C1498.SIY.CRT cells were inoculated IV into 
groups of C57BL/6 or Batf3 ¡/¡ mice, and survival was monitored. ÃÃÃ p &lt;0.0001 for survival comparison of C57BL/6 and Batf3 ¡/¡ mice challenged with C1498.SIY.CRT. (B, C) 
Data are pooled from two independent experiments each with 4-5 mice/group. (D) Data are pooled from three independent experiments each with 3-5 mice/group. </p>

<p>ONCOIMMUNOLOGY 
e1278332-5 </p>

<p>CRT-expressing C1498.SIY leukemia (Fig. 4C), indicating that 
DCs are critical to control the progression of disseminated 
AML in general. The extended survival observed in mice with 
CRT-expressing leukemia was lost following CD11c C cell 
depletion (Fig. 4C), revealing that the CRT-mediated effect on 
anti-leukemia immunity requires DCs. 
Our laboratory has recently identified that splenic CD8a C DCs, 
uniquely capable of engulfing and cross-presenting leukemia-
derived antigens to CD8 C T cells in vivo, mediate a form of deletio-
nal T-cell tolerance in mice with AML (D. Kline, unpublished 
observation). To investigate the role of CD8a C DCs in mediating 
the CRT effect, Batf3 ¡/¡ mice, which lack CD8a C DCs, 18 were uti-
lized. As shown in Fig. 4D, the survival benefit associated with a 
CRT-expressing AML cell challenge was completely abolished in 
the absence of CD8a C DCs. Collectively, these data suggest that, 
although T cells are ultimately essential as effectors in leukemia cell 
killing, CRT likely acts upstream of adaptive immunity-possibly 
through CD8a C DCs. </p>

<p>CRT does not induce classical measures of DC activation in 
vivo </p>

<p>The requirement for DCs, and specifically for CD8a C DCs, to 
mediate the powerful CRT effect in vivo suggested that its 
expression on leukemia cells might directly activate DCs, 
enhancing their ability to cross-prime leukemia-specific CD8 C 
T cells. First, the phenotypes of DCs from leukemia-bearing 
mice were analyzed. Surprisingly, expression of co-stimulatory 
B7 and MHC class I and II molecules was identical among 
CD11c C DCs that engulfed CRT-expressing or control C1498 
AML cells in vivo (Fig. 5A). IL-12 production by 
CD8a C CD11c C cells that had acquired AML cells in vivo was 
higher than those that had not (Fig. 5B and C), suggesting 
either that phagocytosis of AML cells induced IL-12 production 
by DCs, or that a subpopulation of IL-12-producing DCs was 
more efficient at AML cell uptake. Regardless, there was no dif-
ference between the frequencies of IL-12-producing 
CD8a C CD11c C cells that had acquired C1498 versus C1498. 
CRT cells in vivo (Fig. 5B and C). Furthermore, purified 
CD8a C DCs from C1498.SIY or C1498.SIY.CRT-bearing ani-
mals equivalently induced the proliferation of 2C T cells 
directly ex vivo (Fig. 5D and E), demonstrating that CRT 
expression on AML cells did not appear to enhance cross-pre-
sentation of leukemia cell-derived antigens by DCs to T cells. 
Taken together, these results indicate, at least at the time points 
chosen for analysis, that CRT does not appear to activate classi-
cal pathways associated with DC maturation. </p>

<p>CRT activates the host type I IFN pathway </p>

<p>Type I IFNs are essential for bridging innate and adaptive 
immune responses against solid tumors. 19,20 However, we 
recently observed that disseminated AML fails to induce a host 
type I IFN response, 15 which may help to explain the dense T-
cell tolerant state that exists in leukemia-bearing hosts. To 
determine whether CRT expression on AML cells would induce 
type I IFN transcription, levels of ifnb mRNA were measured in 
spleen cells from mice challenged with C1498.CRT or control 
C1498 AML. Interestingly, a 2-fold increase in ifnb mRNA </p>

<p>expression was detected in spleens of mice as early as 24 h fol-
lowing IV challenge with C1498.CRT cells (Fig. 6A). Experi-
ments were performed to identify the specific cell type(s) in 
which ifnb mRNA expression was induced in the spleen follow-
ing exposure to CRT-expressing AML cells. Here, CD11b C 
cells, but not CD11c C or CD11b ¡ CD11c ¡ cells, were found to 
express increased ifnb mRNA following an IV C1498.CRT cell 
versus control C1498 cell challenge (data not shown). To test 
whether enhanced ifnb expression in mice harboring C1498. 
CRT AML cells correlated with improved outcome, wild-type 
and Ifnar ¡/¡ mice (defective in type I IFN signaling) were chal-
lenged with C1498.SIY or C1498.SIY.CRT cells, and survival 
was assessed. As previously demonstrated, 15 the survival of 
wild-type and Ifnar ¡/¡ mice with control C1498.SIY cells was 
similar (Fig. 6B). Nearly all wild-type mice challenged with 
C1498.SIY.CRT cells survived long-term, as expected (Fig. 6B). 
Strikingly, the enhanced survival associated with CRT-express-
ing AML cells was nearly completely abrogated in Ifnar ¡/¡ 
mice (Fig. 6B). Collectively, these results reveal that CRT-
expressing AML cells stimulate a type I IFN response in vivo, 
and that type I IFN signaling in host cells is essential for the 
CRT-mediated effect on survival. Thus, the type I IFN pathway 
is an important mechanism through which CRT promotes 
anti-leukemia immunity. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>"Danger signals" released by dying tumor cells, including 
tumor-derived nucleic acids and their byproducts, facilitate 
innate immune sensing of cancer. 21 CRT translocation is also 
an important mechanism through which stressed or dying can-
cer cells place the immune system on alert, 2 possibly through 
its ability to promote malignant cell phagocytosis. 2,5 The role of 
CRT in activating antitumor immunity has been demonstrated 
in multiple murine tumor models, 1,2 and in human studies 
including acute myeloid leukemia, non-Hodgkin lymphoma, 
bladder cancer, ovarian cancer and non-small cell lung cancer, 
where CRT exposure correlates with favorable clinical out-
comes. 7,10,11,14 Within tumor microenvironment, hyperploid 
cancer cells undergoing constitutive ER stress were shown to 
trigger the CRT translocation to promote early cancer immu-
noserveillance. 22 Long non-coding RNA expressed from tumor 
suppressor retinoblastoma bidirectional promoter were 
reported as one mechanism that regulated CRT cell surface 
translocation in response to chemotherapy. 23 However, the pre-
cise mechanism through which CRT stimulates antitumor 
immunity remains unknown, and the impact of CRT transloca-
tion on tumor immune responses has been described only after 
exposure of cancer cells to chemotherapy or radiation, 1,2 which 
could result in CRT-independent effects. To circumvent this 
problem, AML cells exhibiting stable cell surface CRT expres-
sion were generated to directly examine its effect on anti-leuke-
mia immunity. 
Our results reveal that CRT expression on leukemia cells 
leads to potent immune-mediated control, and in some cases, 
eradication of disseminated AML. This observation is particu-
larly interesting in light of our previous studies, which have 
revealed that a dense T-cell tolerant state is present in mice 
with AML. 16 Furthermore, the finding that CRT expression on </p>

<p>e1278332-6 
X. CHEN ET AL. </p>

<p>AML cells enhanced functional leukemia-specific CD8 C T-cell 
responses, and generated effective immunological memory, 
indicated that adaptive immunity was crucial for its effect. 
However, the observation that DCs were also required to medi-
ate enhanced survival in mice with CRT-expressing AML 
argued against a direct effect of CRT on T cells. The data pre-
sented in Fig. 3 reveal that a major effect of CRT is to promote </p>

<p>the activation of leukemia-specific CD8 C T cells. Experiments 
in which CD8 C or CD4 C T cells are separately depleted could 
also be performed to examine whether one or both populations 
are required to mediate anti-leukemia immunity downstream 
of CRT. 
It has been demonstrated that CRT translocation on malig-
nant cells promotes their phagocytosis by macrophages and </p>

<p>Figure 5. CRT does not affect expression of DC activation molecules or enhance ex vivo antigen cross-presentation. (A) Expression of CD80, CD86, H-2K b and I-A b on live 
splenic CD11c C cells from naive C57BL/6 mice or those challenged 12 h earlier with C1498 or C1498.CRT cells IV. (B) C1498 or C1498.CRT cells were labeled with CTV and 
inoculated IV into IL-12 YFP reporter mice. Six hours later, YFP expression was analyzed by flow cytometry in splenic CTV C or CTV ¡ CD8a C CD11c C cells. Data are summa-
rized in (C). (D, E) 4£10 6 C1498.SIY or C1498.SIY.CRT cells were inoculated IV into C57BL/6 mice, and 3 h later, splenic CD8a ¡ or CD8a C DCs were isolated by FACS and 
cultured with CTV-labeled CD8 C 2C T cells for 65-72 h. Subsequently, 2C T-cell division was monitored by flow cytometry. (D) Representative FACS plots depicting CTV 
dilution of 2C T cells after gating on CD8 C 1B2 C cells. (E) Summary of data from (D). (C) Data are pooled from two independent experiments each with 3 mice/group. (E) 
Data are representative of three independent experiments each with 3 mice/group. </p>

<p>ONCOIMMUNOLOGY 
e1278332-7 </p>

<p>DCs. 2,5 This observation has led to the hypothesis that CRT-
induced efferocytosis, particularly by DCs, augments cross-pre-
sentation of tumor-derived antigens to T cells, which ultimately 
drives the protective immunity that ensues. This model relies 
on the theory that tumor antigen cross-presentation by DCs is 
a limiting factor in generating functional antitumor T-cell 
responses. However, the activation status of DCs is also critical 
in their ability to either prime or tolerize antigen-specific T 
cells. For example, targeting antigen for cross-presentation by 
DCs leads to deletional T-cell tolerance, unless an activating 
signal is also provided. 8 Thus, in addition to promoting engulf-
ment of cancer cells, we hypothesized that CRT might also 
directly activate DCs, licensing them to stimulate superior anti-
tumor T-cell responses. 
In agreement with published studies, CRT expression on 
AML cells did result in their enhanced uptake by splenic DCs 
in vivo, although the effect was not striking (Fig. 4A and B). In 
our opinion, this finding did not likely explain the marked dif-
ferences in functional CD8 C T-cell responses generated in mice 
with CRT-expressing versus control AML (Fig. 3A, F and G). 
We therefore examined the phenotypes of DCs that had been 
exposed or not to CRT-expressing leukemia cells in vivo, and 
found no differences in expression of classical maturation 
markers or production of IL-12. On the surface, these results 
seemed to argue against a hypothesis supporting direct activa-
tion of antigen-presenting cells by CRT, until it was observed 
that splenocytes (and CD11b C cells specifically) from mice 
with CRT-expressing AML expressed significantly higher levels 
of ifnb mRNA, which is interesting in lieu of our recent finding 
that disseminated AML fails to induce a host type I IFN 
response. 15 
A clear role for type I IFN in mediating the CRT effect was 
demonstrated in an experiment in which CRT-expressing or 
control AML cells were inoculated into wild-type or Ifnar ¡/¡ 
mice. As previously demonstrated, 15 host type I IFN signaling 
played no role in regulating survival of mice with control AML. 
Strikingly, however, the survival benefit associated with CRT 
expression on AML cells was almost completely abolished in </p>

<p>Ifnar ¡/¡ hosts. Together, these observations support a model in 
which CRT stimulates a host type I IFN response that may act 
through CD8a C DCs to promote their ability to cross-prime 
leukemia-specific CD8 C T-cell responses. Although speculative, 
our result demonstrating that the CRT effect on survival was 
completely eliminated in Batf3 ¡/¡ mice strongly supports the 
conclusion that this DC subset is the target of type I IFN in 
vivo. Others have shown that type I IFN produced in solid 
tumor-bearing hosts acts directly on CD8a C DCs, licensing 
them to prime antitumor CD8 C T-cell responses. 19 
Immunotherapeutic approaches aimed at enhancing CRT 
translocation with chemotherapeutic agents or radiation have been 
difficult to develop because these modalities can concomitantly 
induce apoptosis of the immune cells necessary to mediate the 
CRT effect in vivo. However, the observation that CRT stimulates 
type I IFN suggests that activating this pathway, for example, with 
stimulator of interferon genes (STING) agonists, 15,24 may be an 
efficacious alternative immunotherapeutic strategy. Regardless, the 
identification of type I IFN as a mechanism through which CRT 
translocation stimulates host antitumor immunity represents an 
important step forward in our understanding of how cancers are 
sensed by the host immune system. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Mice </p>

<p>Mice were maintained in a specific pathogen-free environment. 
Animal experimentation was carried out under a protocol 
approved by an Institutional Animal Use and Care Committee. 
C57BL/6 mice (H-2 b ; CD45 .2/.2 ) were purchased from Taconic. 
Rag2 ¡/¡ and 2C TCR transgenic mice were bred in our facility. 
TCRb/d ¡/¡ mice were provided by M. Alegre (University of 
Chicago). CD11c DTR/GFP B6.FVB-Tg (Itgax-DTR/EGFP) mice 
and Ifnar ¡/¡ mice were provided by X.Y. Fu (University of 
Texas Southwestern). YET40 B6.129-Il12b tm1Lky /J mice, B6.SJL-
Ptprc a Pepc b /BoyJ mice (CD45 .1/.1 ) and Batf3 ¡/¡ mice were 
purchased from Jackson Labs and bred in our facility. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Type I IFN signaling mediates prolonged survival in mice with CRT-expressing AML. (A) C1498.SIY or C1498.SIY.CRT cells were inoculated IV into C57BL/6 mice. 
Twenty-four hours later, ifnb expression was analyzed by qRT-PCR in bulk spleen cells. Ifnb expression levels were normalized to those measured in spleen cells of naive 
C57BL/6 mice. 18S was used as an internal control; ÃÃ p &lt;0.01. Data are pooled from three independent experiments each with 2-3 mice/group. (B) C1498.SIY or C1498. 
SIY.CRT cells were inoculated IV into groups of C57BL/6 or Ifnar ¡/¡ mice, and survival was monitored. Data are pooled from three experiments each with 4-6 mice/group. </p>

<p>ÃÃÃ </p>

<p>p &lt;0.01 for comparison of C1498.SIY.CRT challenged C57BL/6 versus Ifnar ¡/¡ mice. </p>

<p>e1278332-8 
X. CHEN ET AL. </p>

<p>Cell lines </p>

<p>The C1498 AML cell line (H-2 b ) 25 was purchased from ATCC. 
C1498 cells expressing the K b -restricted model SIY (SIYR-
YYGL) peptide antigen were previously generated to facilitate 
monitoring of endogenous antigen-specific CD8 C T-cell 
responses in leukemia-bearing animals. 26 SIY is also the cog-
nate antigen for the 2C transgenic TCR. C1498 and C1498.SIY 
cells were transduced by the retroviral pRetroX-IRES-DsRed 
Express vector containing full-length murine CRT cDNA in-
frame with the cDNA of the 5 0 end of decay accelerating factor 
(DAF), which encodes a signal sequence for attachment of a 
glycophosphatidylinositol (GPI) anchor to the C-terminus of 
the resulting CRT-DAF fusion protein to facilitate CRT 
anchoring in the plasma membrane (C1498.CRT and C1498. 
SIY.CRT). The CRT-GPI construct contains an IRES-DSRED; 
an empty IRES-DSRED construct was also transduced to gener-
ate control C1498 and C1498.SIY cells. All C1498 derivative cell 
lines were cultured in DMEM (Invitrogen) supplemented with 
10% FBS, 2-mercaptoethanol, essential amino acids, penicillin 
and streptomycin. </p>

<p>C1498 AML model </p>

<p>To induce systemic AML, 10 6 C1498 cells were injected IV 
through the lateral tail vein. For in vivo CD4 C and CD8 C T-cell 
depletion, anti-CD4 (L3T4) and anti-CD8a (2.43) antibodies 
(BioXCell) were administered intra-peritoneal (IP) at a dose of 
200 mg on day ¡1, and 100 mg on day 0, and every 3 d thereaf-
ter until day 14. To induce localized tumor growth, 10 6 C1498 
cells were inoculated subcutaneously (SC) in the lower lateral 
abdominal wall. Tumor growth was monitored 2-3 times per 
week with calipers, and mean tumor diameter was recorded. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry </p>

<p>Following red blood cell lysis and blockade of Fc receptors with 
anti-CD16/32 antibodies, spleen cells were stained with the fol-
lowing directly conjugated antibodies: CD11b (M1/70), CD11c 
(HL3), CD86 (GL1), I-A/I-E (M5/114.15.2) and H-2K b (AF6-
88.5) (BD Biosciences); CD8a (53-6.7), CD80 (16-10A) and 
CD19 (eBio1D3) (eBiosciences); CD45.2 (104) CD45.1 (A20), 
and CD3e (145-2C11) (BioLegend). Rabbit anti-calreticulin 
monoclonal antibody and fluorescence-labeled goat-anti-rabbit 
IgG polyclonal secondary antibody were purchased from Abcam. 
Fixable viability dyes (Invitrogen) were used to exclude dead cells. 
Flow cytometry was performed on LSRII or LSRFortessa cytome-
ters (BD Biosciences). Analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">FlowJo</rs> soft-
ware (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Treestar</rs>). Fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) was 
performed using a FACSAria (BD Biosciences). 
For DC isolation, spleens were injected with 1 mg/mL collage-
nase IV (Sigma), 20 mg/mL DNAse I (Roche) were incubated at 
37 C for 15-20 min, and passed through a 70-mm filter to generate 
single cell suspensions. Cells were stained with CD3e (145-2C11) 
and CD19 (eBio1D3) biotinylated antibodies, followed by second-
ary streptavidin staining to eliminate T and B cells. </p>

<p>IFNg ELISPOT </p>

<p>At the indicated time points, 10 6 spleen cells from individual 
leukemia-bearing animals were re-stimulated with media alone 
or with SIY peptide (100 nM) in triplicate overnight in 96-well, 
flat-bottom plates using the mouse IFNg ELISPOT kit (BD Bio-
sciences). 16 ELISPOT plates were read with an ImmunoSpot 
Series 3 Analyzer. Data were analyzed with ImmunoSpot soft-
ware (Cellular Technology, Ltd.). </p>

<p>Adoptive transfer of 2C T cells into leukemia-bearing mice </p>

<p>2C CD8 C T cells were isolated with a mouse CD8 microbead kit 
(Miltenyi), labeled with CellTrace Violet (CTV) (Invitrogen), 
and 10 6 were injected IV. Twenty-four hours later, mice were 
challenged IV with 10 6 C1498.SIY or C1498.SIY.CRT cells. Six 
days later, spleen cells of recipient mice were stained with anti-
CD8a and anti-1B2 antibodies (the 1B2 antibody specifically 
binds the 2C TCR). Flow cytometry was performed to assess 
the frequency and dilution of the CTV signal in 2C T cells (as a 
read-out of in vivo 2C T-cell proliferation). </p>

<p>In vivo cytolysis assay </p>

<p>4£10 6 2C T cells were transferred into C57BL/6 mice (CD45 .2/ 
.2 ) on day ¡1. On day 0, half of the mice were challenged with 
C1498.SIY or C1498.SIY.CRT cells IV. Six days later, spleen 
cells isolated from naive B6.SJL (CD45 .1/.1 ) mice were sepa-
rately labeled with different concentrations of CTV (2.5 mM, 
50 nM), and were pulsed with SIYRYYGL or SIINFEKL (irrele-
vant control) peptides, respectively. CTV-labeled, peptide-
pulsed cells were mixed 1:1, and a total of 8£10 6 were injected 
IV into leukemia-bearing C57BL/6 mice. Six hours later, spleen 
cells were stained with an anti-CD45.1 antibody, and analyzed 
by flow cytometry. After gating on CD45.1 C cells, the ratio of 
CTV hi to CTV lo cells present was calculated using the following 
equations: </p>

<p>Ratio D % CTV lo OVA pulsed CD45:1 C cells 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>: % CTV hi SIY pulsed CD45:1 C cells 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>% specific lysis D ½1 ¡ ratio leukemia À free mice 6 
ð </p>

<p>ratio leukemia ¡ bearing mice£100: </p>

<p>In vivo phagocytosis and cross-presentation assays </p>

<p>C1498 or C1498.CRT cells were labeled with carboxyfluores-
cein diacetate succinimidyl ester (CFSE) or CTV, respectively, 
were mixed at a 1:1 ratio, and 8£10 6 cells were injected IV into 
C57BL/6 mice. Three hours later, spleen cells were stained with 
antibodies against CD11c, CD11b, CD8a, CD3e and CD19. 
The frequency of CD11c C and CD11b C CD11c ¡ cells that con-
tained either a CFSE or CTV signal was analyzed by flow 
cytometry. For antigen cross-presentation assays, C1498.SIY or </p>

<p>ONCOIMMUNOLOGY 
e1278332-9 </p>

<p>C1498.SIY.CRT cells (4£10 6 ) were inoculated IV into C57BL/6 
mice. Splenic CD8a C and CD8a ¡ DCs from these animals 
were isolated by FACS. Sorted DC populations were cultured 
1:1 with purified CTV-labeled 2C T cells for 65-72 h, followed 
by analysis of CTV dilution by 2C T cells. </p>

<p>Generation of bone marrow chimeric (BMC) mice </p>

<p>C57BL/6 mice were lethally irradiated (900 rads) and reconsti-
tuted 1 d later with 2.5£10 6 bone marrow cells from 
CD11c DTR/GFP mice. Eight weeks later, mice were utilized exper-
imentally. To deplete CD11c C cells from leukemia-bearing 
CD11c DTR/GFP BMC mice, diphtheria toxin (DT) (500 ng) was 
administered IP 1 d prior to C1498 cell inoculation and contin-
ued every 48 h until day 11. </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR analysis </p>

<p>C57BL/6 mice were challenged with 5£10 6 C1498.SIY or 
C1498.SIY.CRT cells IV. Twenty-four hours later, spleen cells 
from recipient mice were re-suspended in Trizol (Life Technol-
ogies). Total RNA was isolated via chloroform extraction. 
cDNA was synthesized using the High Capacity cDNA Reverse 
Transcription Kit (Applied Biosystems). Ifnb expression was 
measured by real-time quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) using spe-
cific primers/probes, as previously reported. 24 </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Grouped data were analyzed via two-way ANOVA with Bon-
ferroni post-tests. Survival differences were analyzed with the 
Log-rank test. Statistics were performed using <rs type="software">GraphPrism</rs> 
software. Data are presented as mean  § SD unless otherwise 
indicated. A p value of &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>Disclosure of potential conflicts of interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was funded by R01 CA166770 (J.K.) and Wendy Will Case 
Foundation (J.K.). D.E.K. is funded by the immunology training grant at 
the University of Chicago (T32 AI007090). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>X.C. designed and executed experiments, analyzed data and drafted and 
reviewed the manuscript. D.F. designed and executed experiments, ana-
lyzed data and reviewed the manuscript. D.E.K. designed experiments and 
reviewed the manuscript. J.K. designed experiments, analyzed data, drafted 
and reviewed the manuscript. </p>



<p>ONCOIMMUNOLOGY 
e1278332-11 </p>

</text></tei>