<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5121256" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Among the neurological diseases, cerebrovascular diseases are 
the most common in developed countries. Stroke is the most 
common cause of death in these countries, and neoplastic diseases 
(cancer and hematologic tumors) are the second most common 
cause. However, stroke is a rare complication of cancer therapy, and 
does not occur as often as metastasis or neurotoxicity. 1,2 </p>

<p>A retrospective autopsy study of a large cohort of cancer pa-
tients performed by Graus et al showed that 15% of cancer patients 
have evidence of cerebrovascular disease, and about half of these 
patients have clinical symptoms of stroke. 3 
In this study, we retrospectively analyzed the demographic, 
clinical, and laboratory data of cancer and cancer-free patients that 
presented with acute ischemic stroke in the emergency department. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Study population </p>

<p>A retrospective cross-sectional study including 178 adult pa-
tients was carried out after taking approval from institutional ethics 
committee. We retrospectively investigated patients who were </p>

<p>* Corresponding author. Department of Emergency Medicine, Haseki Training </p>

<p>and Research Hospital, Millet Street, Fatih, 34096, Istanbul, Turkey. Tel.: þ90 
5057472163, þ90 505747216 (mobile). 
E-mail address: yigitacil@gmail.com (M. Yigit). 
Peer review under responsibility of The Emergency Medicine Association of 
Turkey </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>Turkish Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / w w w . e l s e v i e r. c o m / l o ca t e / T J E M </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tjem.2015.11.013 
2452-2473/Copyright © 2016 The Emergency Medicine Association of Turkey. Production and hosting by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of the Owner. This is an open access article 
under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Turkish Journal of Emergency Medicine 16 (2016) 65e68 </p>

<p>admitted to our emergency department (ED) with ischemic stroke 
between January 1st, 2011 and July 15th, 2014. Medical history and 
physical examination data were obtained from all patients who 
were diagnosed with acute ischemic stroke. Acute ischemic stroke 
diagnoses were confirmed by further imaging tests of the brain, 
including computed tomography (CT) and diffusion-weighted 
magnetic resonance imaging (DW-MRI). 
The ischemic stroke patients were divided into two groups: 
group 1; patients with active cancer (Trousseau's) and group 2; 
those without. Active cancer was defined as a confirmed malig-
nancy, which was either treated or untreated in the six months 
before stroke. 4 Demographic characteristics and clinical data were 
collected and evaluated. These two groups were then divided into 
subgroups: those who had had one stroke (groups 1A and 2A) and 
those who had more than one (groups 1B and 2B). Patients who 
were diagnosed with transient ischemia or who had no evidence of 
either acute or chronic infarction after neuroimaging were 
excluded from the study. Patients with primary brain cancer and 
patients who had intracranial metastases were also excluded since 
these patients were thought to have different underlying stroke 
mechanisms. </p>

<p>2.2. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All data was analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 15.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL). The chi-square test was used to compare stroke 
risk factors and subtypes between cancer patients who had expe-
rienced one ischemic stroke and those who had experienced more 
than one. A student's t-test was used to compare biomarkers be-
tween the two groups. P value of &lt;0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>Among the 200 adult patients referred to the ED with stroke, we 
identified 178 patients who were diagnosed as acute ischemic 
stroke. Nine patients with transient ischemia, eight patients with 
primary brain cancer and five patients who had intracranial me-
tastases were excluded from the study. The active cancer group 
(group 1) included 91 patients (60 male, 31 female), and the stroke 
without cancer group (group 2) included 87 (56 male, 31 female). 
The mean age was 65.18 ± 11.98 among those with cancer and 
62.80 ± 12.23 among those without; this difference was not sig-
nificant (p ¼ 0.193). Among the patients with active cancer, 24 had 
previously experienced a stroke whereas in the group without 
cancer, 15 had previously experienced a stroke. The demographic 
and clinical characteristics are shown in Table 1. 
Laboratory tests, including blood urine nitrogen, creatinine, 
aspartate transaminase, alanine transaminase, hematocrit, D-
dimer, C-reactive protein, hemoglobin, and platelet counts, were 
obtained for all patients, and significant differences were found 
between groups for all parameters (p &lt; 0.05). The patients' labo-
ratory values are shown in Table 2. 
Patients with active cancer were divided into two subgroups 
based on the number of strokes experienced after malignancy 
diagnosis: only one stroke (n ¼ 67; group 1A) or more than one 
(n ¼ 24; group 1B) were. Hemoglobin and hematocrit levels were 
significantly greater among patients who had only one stroke: 
hemoglobin, 12.29 ± 1.81 vs. 10.94 ± 2.00 (p ¼ 0.004, Fig. 1) and 
hematocrit, 37.15 ± 5.34 vs. 33.70 ± 6.51 (p ¼ 0.012). Laboratory 
values for the two subgroups are shown in Table 3. 
Among patients without cancer, laboratory values did not differ 
between those who had experienced only one stroke (n ¼ 72; group 
2A) and those who had multiple strokes (n ¼ 15; group 2B) 
(Table 4). </p>

<p>Table 1 
Demographic and clinical characteristics of ischemic stroke patients with malig-
nancy (group 1) versus those with no malignancy (group 2). </p>

<p>Group 1 (n ¼ 91) 
Group 2 (n ¼ 87) 
p a </p>

<p>Age (years) 
65.18 ± 11.98 
62.80 ± 1 2.23 
0.193 
Gender (Female/Male) 
31/60 
31/56 
0.828 
Smoking 
64 
52 
Drinking 
44 
21 
Previous stroke history 
24 
15 
Hypertension 
50 
59 
Diabetes mellitus 
27 
36 
CAD 
40 
32 
Hyperlipidemia 
18 
4 
COPD 
11 
7 
CHF 
9 
1 
Liver Cirrhosis 
5 
e </p>

<p>CRF 
3 
1 </p>

<p>Group 1, the ischemic stroke patients with malignancy (trousseau group); Group 2, 
the ischemic stroke patients with no malignancy; CAD, coronary arterial disease; 
COPD, chronical obstructive pulmonary disease; CHF, chronical heart failure; CRF, 
chronical renal failure. 
a Student's t-test. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Laboratory values of ischemic stroke patients with malignancy (group 1) and those 
patients with no malignancy (group 2) at the time of presentation. </p>

<p>Parameters 
Group 1 (n ¼ 91) 
Group 2 (n ¼ 87) 
p a </p>

<p>BUN (mg/dl) 
25.19 ± 14.29 
18.05 ± 7.01 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Cre (mg/dl) 
1.02 ± 0.47 
0.90 ± 0.30 
0.034 
AST (U/L) 
(13e584) 
(9e88) 
0.004 
ALT (U/L) 
(6e236) 
(6e71) 
0.001 
Hematocrit (%) 
36.24 ± 5.84 
41.20 ± 5.20 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>D.dimer (ug FEU/ml) 
(0.10e11.55) 
(0.10e8.70) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>CRP (mg/dl) 
(0.10e27.60) 
(0.10e14.40) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin (g/dl) 
11.93 ± 1.98 
13.61 ± 1.92 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Platelets (Â10 3 mL) </p>

<p>262.58 ± 107.45 
233.25 ± 66.35 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Group 1, the ischemic stroke patients with malignancy (trousseau group); Group 2, 
the ischemic stroke patients with no malignancy. BUN, blood urine nitrogene; Cre, 
creatinine; AST, aspartate transaminase; ALT, alanine transaminase; CRP, c-reactive 
protein. 
a Student's t-test. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Comparison of hemoglobin levels (median (interquartile range)) between 
Trousseau's group patients who had one stroke (group 1A) and those patients who had 
more than one stroke (group 1B) at the time of presentation. </p>

<p>M. Yigit et al. / Turkish Journal of Emergency Medicine 16 (2016) 65e68 </p>

<p>
Among patients with cancer, 21 patients were diagnosed with 
prostate cancer, 14 with lung cancer, 11 with gastric cancer, and 
nine with skin cancer (Table 5). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Kim et al 5 reported that d-dimer, pro-BNP, and fibrinogen levels 
were higher in ischemic stroke patients with cancer compared to 
those without. Consistent with the literature, 5 d-dimer levels in the 
present study were significantly higher in cancer patients. These 
results imply a relationship between cancer and inflammation, 
thrombus formation, and coagulopathy, which could explain the 
increased frequency of ischemic stroke in cancer patients compared 
with non-cancer patients. 5 
Kim et al found that among stroke patients with cancer, 33 
(21.2%) had gastric cancer, 25 (16%) had lung cancer, 22 (14.1%) had 
colon cancer, 20 (12.8%) had hepatobiliary cancer, and 84 (53.8%) had 
metastases. 4 In the present study, 21 patients were diagnosed with 
prostate cancer (23.08%), 14 with lung cancer (15.38%), 11 with 
gastric cancer (12.09%), and 9 with skin cancer (9.89%). 
C-reactive protein is an acute peptide related to inflammation and the 
progression of hemangioendothelioma, and increases during systemic 
inflammation and atherosclerotic disease. 6 Previous studies showed that 
leukocyte count and levels of fibrinogen and C-reactive protein (CRP) may 
serve as markers of inflammatory activity. Inflammatory activity increases 
the risk for vascular events and worsens prognosis after a stroke. 7e15 In the 
present study, CRP levels were 0. 10e27.60 Unit (U) acute ischemic stroke 
patients with malignancy (Trousseau's syndrome), and 0. 10e14.40 U in 
stroke patients with no malignancy, a statistically significant difference 
(p &lt; 0.001). 
Among the hematopoietic growth factors, erythropoiesis-stimulating 
agents (ESAs) are frequently used in oncology due to their ability to cor-
rect chemotherapy-induced bone marrow suppression and anemia; how-
ever, administration of ESAs to patients with cancer is associated with 
increased risks for venous thromboembolism, higher mortality, 16, 17 and even 
tumor progression. 18 In the present study, hemoglobin levels were 
11.93 ± 1.98 in stroke patients with malignancy (Trousseau's syndrome), and 
13.61 ± 1.92 in stroke patients without, also a significant difference 
(p &lt; 0.001). Thus, in patients with malignancies, stroke is strongly associated 
with anemia. In our study, among the subgroups, hemoglobin levels were 
12.29 ± 1.81 for the patients who had experienced only one stroke, and 
10.94 ± 2.14 for the patients who had experienced multiple strokes, and 
again, these values were significantly different (p ¼ 0.004). This data sug-
gests that there is a strong correlation between increased number of strokes 
and degree of anemia. 
Smoking is a common risk factor in both ischemic stroke and 
cancer, and is also the cause of most ischemic strokes in cancer </p>

<p>patients. 2,11 Most reports have found that hypertension and 
smoking are the most common causes of ischemic stroke in cancer 
patients, 11e15 and these results correlate well with our findings. In 
our study, there was a higher incidence of both smoking and hy-
pertension among Trousseau's patients (n ¼ 64, 70.32%; n ¼ 50, 
54.94%, respectively). </p>

<p>5. Limitations </p>

<p>One limitation of this presented cross-sectional, retrospective 
analysis is that the sample is small and the other is that the study 
design limits the degree of change in anemia which may have led to 
recurrence of ischemic stroke in patients with Trousseau's syn-
drome. This issue in limitation should be considered in case-control 
studies with larger sample size. </p>

<p>6. Conclusions </p>

<p>In this preliminary study, we observed that repeated episodes of 
stroke in patients with Trousseau's syndrome seem to occur more 
frequently in the presence of anemia. Therefore, we suggest that 
restoration of hemoglobin levels may help prevent recurrent stroke 
in patients with Trousseau's syndrome. </p>



<p>Table 3 
Laboratory values of trousseau group patients who had one stroke (group 1A) and 
those patients who had more than one stroke (group 1B) at the time of presentation. </p>

<p>Parameters 
Group 1A (n ¼ 67) 
Group 1B (n ¼ 24) 
p a </p>

<p>BUN (mg/dl) 
25.43 ± 14.46 
24.50 ± 14.08 
0.785 
Cre (mg/dl) 
1.04 ± 0.49 
0.98 ± 0.41 
0.564 
AST (U/L) 
(14e584) 
(13e78) 
0.346 
ALT (U/L) 
(7e236) 
(6e145) 
0.732 
Hematocrit (%) 
37.15 ± 5.34 
33.70 ± 6.51 
0.012 
D-dimer (ug FEU/ml) 
(0.10e8.10) 
(0.30e8.70) 
0.445 
CRP (mg/dl) 
(0.10e27.60) 
(0.20e26.80) 
0.534 
Hemoglobin (g/dl) 
12.29 ± 1.81 
10.94 ± 2.14 
0.004 </p>

<p>Platelets (Â10 3 mL) </p>

<p>255.92 ± 96.70 
281.17 ± 133.66 
0.326 </p>

<p>Group 1A, consisted of trousseau group patients who had one stroke; Group 2B, 
consisted of trousseau group patients who had more than one stroke. BUN, blood 
urine nitrogene; Cre, creatinine; AST, aspartate transaminase; ALT, alanine trans-
aminase; CRP, c-reactive protein. 
a Chi-square test. </p>

<p>Table 4 
Laboratory values of cancer-free patients who suffered their first stroke (group 2A) 
and those patients who suffered recurrent stroke (group 2B) at the time of 
presentation. </p>

<p>Parameters 
Group 2A (n ¼ 72) 
Group 2B (n ¼ 15) 
p a </p>

<p>BUN (mg/dl) 
17.85 ± 6.84 
19.06 ± 7.97 
0.545 
Cre (mg/dl) 
0.90 ± 0.32 
0.87 ± 0.15 
0.706 
AST (U/L) 
23.10 ± 10.74 
23.20 ± 6.04 
0.972 
ALT (U/L) 
21.79 ± 11.75 
22.40 ± 9.37 
0.851 
Hematocrit (%) 
41.69 ± 5.16 
38.89 ± 4.90 
0.058 
D.dimer (ug FEU/ml) 
(0.10e11.55) 
(0.10e14.40) 
0.649 
CRP (mg/dl) 
(0.30e1.60) 
(0.20e3.90) 
0.874 
Hemoglobin (g/dl) 
13.77 ± 1.87 
12.83 ± 2.00 
0.084 </p>

<p>Platelets (Â10 3 mL) </p>

<p>230.05 ± 64.38 
249.73 ± 75.41 
0.299 </p>

<p>Group 2A, consisted of ischemic stroke patients who had one stroke; Group 2B, 
consisted of ischemic stroke patients who had more than one stroke. BUN, blood 
urine nitrogene; Cre, creatinine; AST, aspartate transaminase; ALT, alanine trans-
aminase; CRP, c-reactive protein. 
a Chi-square test. </p>

<p>Table 5 
Types of cancer in ischemic stroke patients with malignancy (Traussea's group). </p>

<p>Cancer type 
Patient numbers and percentages (n ¼ 91) (%) </p>

<p>Prostate cancer 
21 (23.08%) 
Lung cancer 
14 (15.38%) 
Skin cancer 
9 (9.89%) 
Gastric cancer 
11 (12.09%) 
Colon cancer 
6 (6.59%) 
Lymphoma 
4 (4.39%) 
Hepatocellular carcinoma 
5 (5.49%) 
Breast cancer 
5 (5.49%) 
Renal cancer 
5 (5.49%) 
Cervix cancer 
3 (3.31%) 
Pancreatic cancer 
3 (3.31%) 
Others 
5 (5.49%) </p>

<p>M. Yigit et al. / Turkish Journal of Emergency Medicine 16 (2016) 65e68 </p>



<p>
M. Yigit et al. / Turkish Journal of Emergency Medicine 16 (2016) 65e68 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>