<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5078599" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The current epidemic of Zika virus (ZIKV) has underscored the urgency to establish experimental systems for 
studying viral replication and pathogenesis, and countermeasure development. Here we report two ZIKV repli-
con systems: a luciferase replicon that can differentiate between viral translation and RNA synthesis; and a stable 
luciferase replicon carrying cell line that can be used to screen and characterize inhibitors of viral replication. The 
transient replicon was used to evaluate the effect of an NS5 polymerase mutation on viral RNA synthesis and to 
analyze a known ZIKV inhibitor. The replicon cell line was developed into a 96-well format for antiviral testing. 
Compare with virus infection-based assay, the replicon cell line allows antiviral screening without using infec-
tious virus. Collectively, the replicon systems have provided critical tools for both basic and translational research. 
Zika virus (ZIKV) is a mosquito-borne member of the genus flavivirus 
within the family Flaviviridae. Many flaviviruses, such as the four sero-
types of dengue virus (DENV-1 to -4), yellow fever (YFV), West Nile 
virus (WNV), Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV), and tick-borne enceph-
alitis virus (TBEV), cause significant human diseases. The current epi-
demic of ZIKV in the Americas poses an international public health 
emergency. Symptomatic ZIKV infection presents with "dengue-like" 
manifestations, such as fever, headaches, lethargy, conjunctivitis, rash, 
arthralgia, and myalgia. Severe diseases associated with ZIKV infection 
include neurotropic Guillain-Barre syndrome and congenital micro-
cephaly (Shan et al., 2016a). Despite urgent medical needs, neither vac-
cine nor therapeutics are currently available for ZIKV. 
Flaviviruses have a positive single-strand RNA genome of approxi-
mately 11,000 nucleotides in length. The genome contains a 5′ untrans-
lated region (UTR), long open-reading frame (ORF), and 3′UTR. The ORF 
encodes three structural (capsid [C], precursor membrane [prM], and 
envelope [E]), and seven non-structural (NS1, NS2A, NS2B, NS3, NS4A, 
NS4B, and NS5) proteins. The structural proteins form viral particles. 
The nonstructural proteins participate in viral replication, virion assem-
bly, and evasion of the host immune response (Lindenbach et al., 2013). 
In response to the current ZIKV emergence, we urgently need to de-
velop experimental systems that could be used to study why ZIKV has </p>

<p>become epidemic with increased disease severity (Guillain-Barre syn-
drome and microcephaly). It is equally urgent to establish tools for vac-
cine and antiviral development. Flavivirus replicon is a self-replicative 
viral RNA. Compare with the complete viral genome, the replicon con-
tains a deletion of viral structural gene(s) (Khromykh and Westaway, 
1997). The replicon can be launched through transfection of susceptible 
cells with in vitro transcribed RNA, or introduced from plasmids that en-
code the replicon cDNA under a CMV or SV40 promoter. Flavivirus rep-
licon can also be stably expressed in cells when a selection marker (such 
as Neomycin resistance gene [Neo]) is engineered into the system. Such 
replicon systems have been established for WNV (Khromykh and 
Westaway, 1997; Lo et al., 2003a; Shi et al., 2002), YFV (Corver et al., 
2003; Jones et al., 2005), DENV (Ng et al., 2007; Puig-Basagoiti et al., 
2006), TBEV (Gehrke et al., 2003), and JEV (Li et al., 2013). They have 
been successfully used to study viral translation/replication (Manzano 
et al., 2011; Wang et al., 2011), to produce single-round infectious par-
ticles as vaccine candidate (Harvey et al., 2004; Qing et al., 2010), and to 
screen compound libraries for antiviral inhibitors (Lo et al., 2003b; Xie 
et al., 2011). 
We recently developed an infectious cDNA clone for ZIKV (Shan et 
al., 2016b). Compared with the infectious cDNA clone, replicon systems 
allow analyzing viral replication events (i.e., viral translation and RNA 
synthesis) in the absence of virus entry or virion assembly. This feature 
of replicon is particularly useful when studying antiviral mechanism of 
inhibitors. Due to the lack of viral structural genes, the replicon system 
is non-infectious, thus reducing the biosafety concern when used to 
screen large compound libraries. The goal of this study was to develop 
the replicon system of ZIKV. </p>

<p>EBioMedicine 12 (2016) 156-160 </p>

<p>⁎ Corresponding author at: Department of Biochemistry &amp; Molecular Biology, 
University of Texas Medical Branch, Galveston, TX, USA. 
E-mail address: peshi@utmb.edu (P.-Y. Shi). </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2016.09.013 
2352-3964/© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>EBioMedicine </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e b i o m e d i c i n e . c o m </p>

<p>2. Materials and Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Cell Culture and Antibodies </p>

<p>Huh7 cells (RRID:CVCL_0336) were maintained in a high-glucose 
Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, 
CA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Hyclone Labora-
tories, Logan, UT), 1% penicillin-streptomycin (Invitrogen) at 37°C with 
5% CO 2 . The following antibodies were used: a mouse monoclonal anti-
body (mAb) J2 anti-double strand RNA (dsRNA) (English and Scientific 
Consulting, Hungary, Cat# 10010200), a mouse mAb 44-4-7 cross-reac-
tive with DENV and ZIKV NS4B (Xie et al., 2014), and goat anti-mouse 
IgG conjugated with Alexa Fluor®488 (Thermo Fisher Scientific Cat# 
A-11029, RRID:AB_2534088). </p>

<p>2.2. Plasmid Construction </p>

<p>The Renilla luciferase (Rluc) replicon plasmid was constructed from 
an infectious clone pFLZIKV that contains a T7 promoter and hepatitis 
delta virus ribozyme sequence (HDVr) at the 5′ and 3′ end of the 
cDNA sequence of Cambodian strain (FSS13025), respectively (Shan et 
al., 2016b). Standard overlap PCR was performed to amplify the DNA 
fragment between unique restriction enzyme sites NotI and SphI. This 
DNA fragment contains the T7 promoter, 5′UTR, and a DNA cassette 
(C 38 -Rluc2A-E 30 ) in-frame fused with the ORF (Fig. 1). The C 38 -
Rluc2A-E 30 cassette encodes the N-terminal 38 amino acids of C protein 
(C 38 ), Rluc reporter, foot-and-mouth disease virus (FMDV) 2A protease, 
and the C-terminal 30 amino acids of the E protein (E 30 ). The codons of 
C 38 contain the flavivirus-conserved cyclization sequence required for 
viral RNA replication (Hahn et al., 1987; Khromykh et al., 2001). The 
E 30 serves as a signal peptide for proper translocation of NS1 into the en-
doplasmic reticulum (ER) lumen. The purified PCR fragment was cloned 
into pFLZIKV through the NotI and SphI sites to replace the structural 
genes, resulting in plasmid pZIKV Rep WT (wild-type). As a control, </p>

<p>the flavivirus-conserved polymerase motif GDD (corresponding to resi-
dues Gly664, Asp665, and Asp666 in ZIKV polyprotein) was mutated to 
Ala (G664A-D665A-D66A) using QuikChange II XL Site-Directed Muta-
genesis Kit (Agilent Technologies), resulting in plasmid Rep NS5ΔGDD. 
The cDNA clone of ZIKV Rep-Neo was constructed through engineer-
ing an IRES-Neo cassette into plasmid pZIKV Rep WT (Fig. 2). The IRES-
Neo cassette (containing a neomycin phosphotransferase [Neo] gene 
driven by an internal ribosomal entry site [IRES] from encephalomyo-
carditis virus) was inserted downstream of the first 28 nucleotides of 
3′UTR. The IRES-Neo cassette was amplified by PCR using WNV Rluc/ 
NeoRep as a template (Lo et al., 2003b). Overlap PCR was performed 
to fuse the IRES-Neo cassette with the 3′UTR, resulting in a DNA frag-
ment spanning restriction enzyme sites EcoRI and ClaI. This fragment 
was cloned into pZIKV Rep WT through the EcoRI and ClaI sites, 
resulting in plasmid Rep-Neo. All plasmids were validated by restriction 
enzyme digestion and DNA sequencing. The complete DNA sequences 
of plasmids pZIKV Rep WT and Rep-Neo are shown in Supplemental 
Materials. Primer sequences are available upon request. All restriction 
enzymes were purchased from New England BioLabs. </p>

<p>2.3. RNA Transcription and Transfection </p>

<p>Replicon RNAs were in vitro transcribed as described previously 
(Shan et al., 2016b). WT replicon or Rep-NS5ΔGDD RNAs (10 μg) 
were electroporated into Huh7 cells (8 × 10 
6 cells) by pulsing once </p>

<p>at 0.27 kV/950 μF in 4-mm cuvettes using a GenePulser apparatus 
(Bio-Rad). After electroporation, 1 × 10 
5 cells per well were seeded </p>

<p>into a 24-well plate. At various time points post-transfection (p.t.), 
cells were washed twice with PBS and lysed in 100 μl 1 × Renilla 
luciferase lysis buffer (Promega). Lysates (15 μl) were mixed with 
Renilla luciferase substrates (50 μl). Luciferase signals were immediately 
measured by Cytation 5 (Biotek) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Characterization of ZIKV luciferase replicon. (a) Diagram for ZIKV replicon construction. C 38 and E 30 represent DNA sequences encoding the first 38 amino acids of C protein and the 
last 30 amino acids of E protein, respectively. Rluc2A represents the gene cassette expressing Renilla luciferase (Rluc) and foot-and-mouth disease virus 2A protease (Rluc2A). HDVr, 
hepatitis delta virus ribozyme sequence. (b) Transient replicon assay. Equal amount of wild-type (WT) and NS5ΔGDD mutant RNAs (10 μg) were electroporated into Huh7 cells. 
Cellular Rluc signals were measured at indicated time points. The means and standard deviations from three independent experiments are shown. (c) Antiviral activity of NITD-008. 
Huh7 cells were electroporated with 10 μg of WT Rluc replicon. The transfected cells were treated immediately with NITD-008 (1 or 5 μM) or 0.9% DMSO as a control. The relative Rluc 
activities harvested at 24 and 32 h p.t. are indicated in percentages of the Rluc activities derived from the DMSO control cells (set as 100%). N.S., not significant; *, significant 
(p b 0.05); **, highly significant (p b 0.01). </p>

<p> 
X. Xie et al. / EBioMedicine 12 (2016) 156-160 </p>

<p>2.4. Cell Line Selection </p>

<p>Approximately 8 × 10 
6 Huh7 cells were electroporated with 10 μg </p>

<p>Rep-Neo RNA as described above. The transfected cells were seeded in 
a 10-cm dish. At 48 h p.t., G418 (ThermoFisher Scientific) was added 
to a final concentration of 0.3 mg/ml in culture medium. Medium was 
changed every 3-4 days. Cell foci formed after 12 days of G418 selection. 
All cells were trypsinized and pooled together in a T-175 flask for ex-
pansion. The cells were continually cultured under G418 selection for 
6 passages (P6 Rep-Neo cells; 3-4 days per passage). The P6 cells </p>

<p>were aliquoted in a cryo-medium containing 90% FBS plus 10% dimethyl 
sulfoxide (DMSO) and stored in a liquid nitrogen tank. </p>

<p>2.5. Immunofluorescence Assay (IFA) </p>

<p>IFA was performed according to a previously described protocol 
(Shan et al., 2016b) with some modifications. In brief, after fixation 
and blocking, the cells were incubated with primary antibody (anti-
dsRNA antibody J2 or anti-NS4B mAb 44-4-7) followed by secondary 
antibody (goat anti-mouse IgG conjugated with Alexa Fluor®488). The </p>

<p>Fig. 2. A Huh7 cell line stably expressing luciferase and Neo ZIKV replicon (Huh7 Rep-Neo cell). (a) Schematic diagrams of the full-length cDNA clone of ZIKV (top) and the cDNA clone of 
ZIKV Rep-Neo (bottom). In the ZIKV Rep-Neo construct, a fragment containing internal ribosome entry site (IRES) and neomycin resistance gene (Neo) was inserted downstream of the 
first 28 nucleotides of 3′UTR. The nucleotide lengths of complete 5′UTR and 3′UTR are indicated. (b) Development of Huh7 Rep-Neo cell line. The flowchart outlines the major steps to 
generate the stable replicon carrying cell line. (c) Transient luciferase assay. Huh7 cells were electroporated with equal amounts (10 μg) of WT Rep-Neo RNA or an NS5 polymerase 
GDD active site mutant replicon (Rep NS5ΔGDD) RNA. At 24 and 48 h p.t., luciferase signals were measured from lysates of about 20,000 transfected cells or naïve Huh7 cells. The 
average and standard deviations from three independent measurements are presented. (d) Detection of viral dsRNA. Rep-Neo cells (P6) were analyzed for dsRNA by IFA using mAb J2 
and goat-anti-mouse IgG conjugated with Alexa Fluor®488 as primary and secondary antibodies, respectively. Nucleus was stained by DAPI. (e) Detection of viral NS4B protein. The 
expression of NS4B protein was detected in Rep-Neo cells (P6) using mAb 44-4-7 and goat-anti-mouse IgG conjugated with Alexa Fluor®488 as primary and secondary antibodies, 
respectively. (f) Luciferase assay of P6 Rep-Neo cells. Luciferase activities were measured from the lysates of 20,000 P6 Rep-Neo cells or naive Huh7 cells. (g) Antiviral testing using 
Rep-Neo cells. Rep-Neo cells (P6) were seeded into a 96-well plate. The cells were incubated with NITD-008 at indicated concentrations and measured for luciferase activities at 48 h 
post-treatment. See experimental details in Materials and Methods. </p>

<p> 
X. Xie et al. / EBioMedicine 12 (2016) 156-160 </p>

<p>cells were mounted in a mounting medium with DAPI (4′, 6-diamidino-
2-phenylindole; Vector Laboratories, Inc.). Fluorescence images were 
acquired by a fluorescence microscope equipped with a video docu-
mentation system (Olympus). </p>

<p>2.6. Antiviral Screening Assay </p>

<p>Approximately 1.5 × 10 
4 Rep-Neo cells/well were seeded in a phenol </p>

<p>red-free DMEM medium (Invitrogen) with 10% FBS in an opaque (for 
Rluc assay) or a clear (for cytotoxicity assay) 96-well plate (Corning). 
At incubating the cells at 37°C for 16 h, medium was replaced with 
fresh phenol red-free medium containing 2% FBS. The reason for using 
2% FBS phenol red-free medium (rather than 10% FBS medium) is to 
minimize protein binding of compounds. Compounds NITD-008 (a gift 
from Novartis Institute for Tropical Diseases) with 10-fold serial dilu-
tions were added to cells. Cells were also treated with 0.9% DMSO as a 
negative control. After 48 h of treatment at 37°C, cells were assayed 
for Rluc activity using ViviRen substrates (Promega) or cell viability 
using Cell counting kit-8 (CCK-8, Sigma) as previously described (Xie 
et al., 2011). The 50% effective concentration (EC 50 ) and 50% cytotoxic-
ity concentration (CC 50 ) were estimated by using a four-parameter lo-
gistic regression model from the <rs id="software-1" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software Inc.</rs>., San Diego CA). For the antiviral screening 
assay, we chose ViviRen substrate, rather than Renilla lysis buffer/sub-
strate (as described for transient replicon assay), to improve the assay 
throughput. This is because ViviRen substrate is able to penetrate into 
cells, thus eliminating the step of cell lysis during antiviral screening. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. A Luciferase Reporter ZIKV Replicon </p>

<p>Fig. 1a depicts the ZIKV replicon containing a Renilla luciferase (Rluc) 
gene (pZIKV Rep WT). The pZIKV Rep WT was constructed by replacing 
the viral structural genes with Rluc using a full-length cDNA infectious 
clone (pFLZIKV) (Shan et al., 2016b). As a control, Rep-NS5ΔGDD was 
constructed by mutating the viral polymerase GDD active site to Ala 
(G664A-D665A-D66A in ZIKV; Fig. 1a). A T7 promoter and a hepatitis 
delta virus ribozyme (HDVr) sequence were engineered at the 5′ and 
3′ ends of the replicon cDNA for in vitro transcription and for generation 
of the authentic 3′ end of the RNA transcript, respectively. Upon trans-
fection into Huh7 cells, wild-type (WT) replicon RNA generated two 
distinct Rluc peaks (Fig. 1b). The first peak appeared at 2 h post-trans-
fection (p.t.) and decreased from 4 to 8 h. At 24 h p.t., the Rluc signal in-
creased by 200 folds above that of 2 h post-transfection. At 32 h p.t., the 
Rluc signal reached the second peak. Mutation of the viral polymerase 
GDD motif (Rep-NS5ΔGDD) abolished the second Rluc peak, but did 
not affect the first Rluc peak. Collectively, the results indicate that the 
first and second Rluc peaks represent the translation of the input RNA 
and the translation of the newly synthesized RNA, respectively. These 
results are in agreement with the previously reported flavivirus 
replicons (Lo et al., 2003a). 
We demonstrated the use of replicon in drug discovery by testing an 
inhibitor NITD-008, an adenosine nucleotide analogue with a broad an-
tiviral spectrum (Lo et al., 2016; Yin et al., 2009). This compound was re-
cently shown to inhibit ZIKV in cell culture and A129 mice (Deng et al., 
2016; Shan et al., 2016b). We treated the replicon-transfected cells with 
NITD-008 (1 or 5 μM in medium containing 0.9% dimethyl sulfoxide 
[DMSO] because the compound was initially dissolved in 100% 
DMSO). Fig. 1c shows the Rluc signals collected up to 32 h p.t.; data 
points after 32 h were not presented because the Rluc signals dramati-
cally decreased. No significant differences in Rluc signal were observed 
from 2 to 8 h p.t. between the NITD-008-treated cells and DMSO control, 
indicating that NITD-008 does not affect viral RNA translation. In con-
trast, at 24 and 32 h p.t., the Rluc signals were markedly suppressed 
by NITD-008 in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. 1c), indicating that the </p>

<p>compound inhibits viral RNA synthesis. Notably, NITD-008 suppressed 
Rluc signals less efficiently at 32 h than that at 24 h in the transfected 
cells, possibly due to the difference in conversions of NITD-008 to its tri-
phosphate (the active antiviral form) at different time points. Neverthe-
less, the results demonstrate the utility of the replicon in analyzing the 
mode-of-action of antiviral compounds. </p>

<p>3.2. A Luciferase and Neo ZIKV Replicon Cell Line </p>

<p>Fig. 2a shows the second ZIKV replicon containing Rluc and Neo 
genes (Rep-Neo). The dual reporter replicon was constructed by 
inserting an EMCV IRES (encephalomyocarditis virus internal ribosomal 
entry site)-Neo into the 3′UTR of the above Rluc replicon. The Rep-Neo 
RNA were transfected into Huh7 cells; the transfected cells were select-
ed under Geneticin (G418). Fig. 2b depicts the selection flowchart for 
the Rep-Neo cells. For evaluating the replication competency of Rep-
Neo RNA, 1 × 10 
5 transfected cells/well were seeded into a 24-well </p>

<p>plate. At 24 and 48 h p.t., the cells were assayed for Rluc activity; the 
Rep-Neo RNA-transfected cells produced N 1 × 10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>-fold higher lucifer-
ase signals than naïve Huh7 cells; almost background levels of Rluc ac-
tivities were detected in the cells transfected with an NS5 polymerase 
GDD active site mutant RNA (NS5ΔGDD Rep) (Fig. 2c). The results dem-
onstrate that Rep-Neo RNA is replication-competent. 
After 12 days of G418 selection, cells transfected with the Rep-Neo 
RNA produced foci. All surviving cells were pooled, expanded, and pas-
saged for six generations (P6). In contrast, cells transfected with the 
non-replicative polymerase GDD mutant RNA did not produce any foci 
under the identical G418 selection; this is expected because replication 
of viral RNA is required to express Neomycin resistance gene. Next, we 
examined the P6 Rep-Neo cells for viral RNA, protein expression, and lu-
ciferase signals. Immunofluorescence assay (IFA) using anti-double 
strand RNA (dsRNA) or anti-NS4B mAb showed viral dsRNA and NS4B 
protein in all Rep-Neo cells; in contrast, neither dsRNA nor NS4B signals 
were detected in naïve Huh7 cells (Fig. 2d &amp; e). In addition, Rep-Neo 
cells generated 2000-fold higher luciferase signals than naïve Huh7 
cells (Fig. 2f). Similar IFA and luciferase results were obtained for P1 
Rep-Neo cells (data not shown). Altogether, the results demonstrate 
that the Rep-Neo cell line stably maintains the Rluc-Neo replicon. 
The Rep-Neo cells were applied to testing NITD-008 in a 96-well for-
mat. As shown in Fig. 2g, NITD-008 reduced Rluc signal in a dose-depen-
dent manner with a calculated 50% effective concentration (EC 50 ) of 
0.8 μM; no obvious cytotoxicity was observed at the highest tested con-
centration of 25 μM. The EC 50 value in Huh7 was more potent than the 
EC 50 values previously reported in Vero cells (3.6 and 2.5 μM derived 
from plaque assay and a luciferase virus infection assay, respectively) 
(Shan et al., 2016b); this is most likely because the kinases that convert 
NITD-008 to its triphosphate form are more robust in Huh7 cells than 
those in Vero cells (Deng et al., 2016). Overall, the data are consistent 
with the known antiviral activity of NITD-008 against DENV and ZIKV 
(Shan et al., 2016b; Yin et al., 2009), demonstrating that the ZIKV Rep-
Neo cell line could be used for compound library screening. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Replicon-based cell lines have been widely used for flaviviruses, in-
cluding DENV (Ng et al., 2007), WNV (Khromykh and Westaway, 
1997; Lo et al., 2003b), and hepatitis C virus (Blight et al., 2000). The 
two genes (Rluc and Neo) engineered into the current replicon con-
structs could be replaced by other reporter (such as NanoLuc, GFP, or 
mCherry) and selection marker (such as puromycin N-acetyl-transfer-
ase [PAC]). The ZIKV Rep-Neo cells could be readily adapted for high-
throughput screening in a 384-and 1536-well format (Xie et al., 
2011). Because replicon assay does not generate infectious particles, it 
eliminates the risk of laboratory-acquired viral infection. Since the rep-
licon assay examines cell permeability of compounds, inhibitors identi-
fied through such assay (in comparison with viral enzyme-based </p>

<p> 
X. Xie et al. / EBioMedicine 12 (2016) 156-160 </p>

<p>screening assays) might have a high success rate during preclinical de-
velopment (Shi, 2002). Although the replicon-based assay covers all tar-
gets involved in viral translation and RNA synthesis, it does not include 
targets required for viral entry and virion assembly/release. Those tar-
gets could be covered by using a replicon-derived virus-like particle 
(VLP)-based assay (Qing et al., 2010). VLPs can be produced through 
packaging the replicon RNA by structural proteins supplied in trans 
(Harvey et al., 2004; Qing et al., 2010). Besides drug discovery, the 
VLPs could also be used for potential vaccine development. 
In summary, we generated both a transient ZIKV replicon and a Huh-
7 Rep-Neo cell line that stably carries a ZIKV replicon. These replicons 
are useful tools to study ZIKV replication and to develop antiviral thera-
py. These replicons, together with a previously reported infectious clone 
(Shan et al., 2016b), are critical experimental systems that could be used 
to unravel the molecular details of ZIKV replication and pathogenesis, 
and to aid in the development of vaccines and therapeutics. </p>

<p>Funding Sources </p>

<p>X.X. was awarded with a postdoctoral fellowship from Novartis In-
stitutes for BioMedical Research. P.Y.S. was supported by University of 
Texas Medical Branch startup award, University of Texas STARs 
Award, and NIH grant R01AI087856. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest Statement </p>

<p>The authors have no conflict of interest in this study. </p>

<p>Author Contributions </p>

<p>X.X., J.Z., S.C., Y.Y., and D.B.K. performed experiments and data anal-
ysis. X.X, K.D., J.N., and P.Y.S. interpreted the results. X.X., K.D., J.N., and 
P.Y.S. wrote the manuscript. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank our lab members and colleagues at University of Texas 
Medical Branch at Galveston for helpful discussions during the course 
of this study. </p>

<p>Appendix A. Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at http://dx. 
doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2016.09.013. </p>



<p> 
X. Xie et al. / EBioMedicine 12 (2016) 156-160 </p>

</text></tei>