<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5386927" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Pulmonary artery hypertension (PAH) is a progressive 
chronic disease with a high mortality rate [1]. PAH has a 
complex disease mechanism. Its cardinal signs include an el-
evation of pulmonary artery pressure, right ventricular (RV) 
hypertrophy, and arteriolar wall remodeling [2]. Increased 
pul monary vascular resistance and over-proliferation of </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5115/acb.2017.50.1.60 
pISSN 2093-3665 eISSN 2093-3673 </p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Jae Chul Lee 
Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, Seoul National 
University Bundang Hospital, 82 Gumi-ro 173beon-gil, Bundang-gu, 
Seongnam 13620, Korea 
Tel: +82-31-738-0270, Fax: +82-31-738-0271, E-mail: beas100@snu.ac.kr </p>

<p>Therapeutic effect of prostaglandin E1 in 
monocrotaline-induced pulmonary arterial 
hypertension rats </p>

<p>Jae Chul Lee </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>1 Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, Seoul National University Bundang Hospital, Seongnam, 
2 Department of Anatomy, Seoul National 
University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea </p>

<p>Abstract: Pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH) is a severe pulmonary vascular disease characterized by sustained increase 
in pulmonary arterial pressure and excessive thickening and remodeling of distal small pulmonary arteries. During disease 
progression, PAH include increase in mean pulmonary arterial pressure, right ventricular (RV) enlargement, increased 
pulmonary vascular resistance, and smooth muscle hypertrophy in pulmonary arterioles. Several anti-PAH therapies targeting 
various pathways involved in PAH progression have been approved by the Food and Drug Adminstration. However, many 
of the currently available anti-PAH drugs suffer from a number of limitations, including short biological half-life, and poor 
pulmonary selectivity. Prostaglandin E1 (PGE1) is a potent vasodilator with selectivity toward pulmonary circulation when it is 
administered via the pulmonary route. However, PGE1 has a very short half-life of 5-10 minutes. Therefore, we hypothesized 
that long-term effect of PGE1 could reduce mal-adaptive structural remodeling of the lung and heart and prevent ventricular 
arrhythmias in monocrotaline-induced rat model of PAH. Our results revealed that PGE1 reduced ventricular hypertrophy, 
protein expressions of endothelin-1 and endothelin receptor A, and the expression of fibrosis. These results support the notion 
that PGE1 can improve the functional properties of RV, highlighting its potential benefits for heart and lung impairment. </p>

<p>Key words: Heart, Lung, Prostaglandin E1, Pulmonary artery hypertension, Right ventricles </p>

<p>Received January 5, 2017; Revised March 6, 2017; Accepted March 8, 2017 </p>

<p>Therapeutic efficacy of PGE1 in PAH </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5115/acb.2017.50.1.60 </p>

<p>Anat Cell Biol 2017;50:60-68 61 </p>

<p>www.acbjournal.org </p>

<p>utility of PGE1 has been limited due to its chemical instability 
and extremely hydrophobic nature which results in low drug 
absorption and poor bioavailability. Recently, there has been 
renewed interest in the use of PGE1 in cardiac and lung trans-
plantation. Using target organ infusion protocols can circum-
vent the extensive first pass metabolism of PGE1 by the lungs 
and prevent the decreased bioavailability and clinical efficacy 
of PGE1 infused systemically [15-19]. 
It has been demonstrated that PGE1 can improve pulmo-
nary hemodynamics and clinical outcomes of patients with 
PAH [20]. However, the long-term effect of PGE1 on rats with 
monocrotaline (MCT)-induced PAH has not been investigat-
ed. Therefore, the aim of this study was to evaluate the effect 
of continuous intravenous PGE1 on hemodynamics and long-
term outcomes of rats with MCT-induced PAH. To determine 
changes in pulmonary haemodynamics, RV hypertrophy, 
pathology, and protein expressions, we used immunohisto-
chemical staining and western blot analysis to understand 
whether PGE1 treatment could reduce the development of 
PAH in the model. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Six-week-old male Sprague-Dawley rats were used. All rats 
were housed in climate-controlled conditions with a 12-hour 
light/12-hour dark cycle, and had free access to food and wa-
ter. All animal experiments were approved by the appropriate 
Institutional Review Boards of the Seoul National University 
Bundang Hospital (BA1703-219/018-01) and conducted in 
accordance with National Institutes of Health Guide for the 
Care Use of Laboratory Animals (NIH publication No. 86-23,  revised in 1996). </p>

<p>PAH rat model </p>

<p>PAH was induced by subcutaneous injection of 60 mg/kg 
MCT (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) dissolved in 0.5 N 
HCl. Rats were assigned into the following groups: (1) control 
group (C group; 20 rats), vehicle injection with normal diet; 
(2) monocrotaline group (M group; 20 rats), MCT injec-
tion with normal diet; and (3) PGE1 group (20 rats), MCT 
injection+PGE1 injection with normal diet. These animals 
were sacrificed at 7, 14, 21, and 28 days (each group, n=5) 
after MCT administration (Fig. 1). Tissues were removed and 
immediately frozen at -70°C for enzyme analysis. </p>

<p>Drug delivery </p>

<p>Osmotic infusion pump (Alzet Model 2ML-1, ALZA 
Corp., Palo Alto, CA, USA) was utilized as drug delivery 
system as described previously [21]. Alzet 2ML-1 is a fully 
implantable and osmotically driven pump. It can deliver 2 ml 
over a period of 7 days at a constant rate of infusion. PGE1 
(Lot U-10136, Upjohn, Kalamazoo, MI, USA) was dissolved 
in absolute ethanol dried over sodium sulfate and added to 
the pump to yield an infusion rate of 0.1 pg/kg/min. This 
dose was chosen based on previous experiment showing that 
animals receiving it could tolerate high doses of PGE1 [22]. 
Based on pilot studies, PGE1 was found to be stable in the 
pump for 7 days at pH 7.4. </p>

<p>Determination of the organ weights and right 
hypertrophy index </p>

<p>The rats were weighed and observed for general appear-
ance during the study period. The animals were sacrificed at 
the scheduled time. The wet weights of excised RV, left ven-
tricle (LV) plus interventricular septum (IVS) (LV+IVS) were 
measured. The RV to LV+IVS ratio [RV/(LV+IVS)] was used 
to determine the right hypertrophy index (RVI). The standard 
of RV hypertrophy was defined as an RVI &gt;0.33 [23]. </p>

<p>Pulmonary haemodynamics </p>

<p>Rats were anaesthetized by intraperitoneal injection of ure-
thane and secured on a surgical stage. An 8-mm-long right 
internal jugular vein was isolated and ligated at the distal end. 
The vessel was cut at the proximal end of ligation. A catheter 
filled with heparin saline was rapidly inserted along the inci-
sion and slowly advanced for about 5 cm to enter the pulmo-
nary artery. The standard of pulmonary hypertension was de-
fined as systolic pulmonary artery pressure (SPAP) &gt;50 mm 
Hg [23]. Hemodynamic parameters were recorded at baseline 
and at 7, 14, 21, and 28 days. </p>

<p>PGE1 (7 d) </p>

<p>MCT injection </p>

<p>1 d 
7 d 
14 d 
21 d 
28 d </p>

<p>The animals were sacrificed </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Schedule of the experiment. MCT, monocrotaline; PGE1, pro 
staglandin E1. </p>

<p>Anat Cell Biol 2017;50:60-68 </p>

<p>Jae Chul Lee </p>



<p>www.acbjournal.org </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5115/acb.2017.50.1.60 </p>

<p>Histologic findings of pulmonary arteries </p>

<p>Heart and lung tissues were fixed with 10% buffered for-
malin and then embedded in paraffin. Sections were per-
formed by 4-µm-thick hematoxylin-eosin stains to evaluate 
histopathologic changes of pulmonary blood vessels. The 
small pulmonary artery wall thickness was expressed as fol-
lows: % wall thickness. </p>

<p>Masson trichrome staining </p>

<p>Masson trichrome staining was carried out in accordance 
with well-characterized protocols. Briefly, heart and lung tis-
sue sections were deparaffinized and hydrated in distilled 
water prior to a 1-hour treatment in Bouin's fixative (Catalog 
#NC9674780, Richard-Allan Scientific, Carlsbad, CA, USA) 
at 56°C. Sections were washed in running distilled water until 
clear, and then stained in Weigert's iron hematoxylin (Cata-
log #NC9231529, Richard-Allan Scientific) for 10 minutes. 
Following a 10-minute wash in running water, sections were 
stained in Biebrich scarlet-acid fuchsin (Catalog #NC9424144, 
Richard-Allan Scientific) for 2 minutes. Sections were rinsed in 
distilled water followed by a 10-minute differentiation in phos-
phomolybdic-phosphotungstic acid (Catalog #NC9443038, 
Richard-Allan Scientific). Aniline blue (Catalog #NC9684104, 
Richard-Allan Scientific) was used as a counterstain for 10 
minutes, and then sections were differentiated in 1% acetic 
acid for 3 minutes. Sections were dehydrated through a series 
of graded alcohols back to xylene, and then coverslipped and 
sealed using Cytoseal XYL (Richard-Allan Scientific). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Excised lung tissues were incubated overnight in 10% 
buffered formalin. Four-micrometer-thick sections were cut 
from paraffin embedded tissue blocks, deparaffinized in xy-
lene, and rehydrated in graded alcohol solutions (70%-100%). 
Heat antigen retrieval was achieved by boiling the tissue sec-
tions in antigen retrieval solution in pH 6.0 or pH 9.0 (Dako, 
Carpinteria, CA, USA) for 10 minutes in a microwave prior to 
incubation at 4°C overnight with primary antibodies against 
endothelin-1 (ET-1; Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA). After 
incubation with the appropriate biotinylated secondary anti-
bodies for 30 minutes at 4°C and subsequently with streptavi-
din (Dako, Kyoto, Japan), color development was done using 
diaminobenzidine (DAB) as a chromogen and counterstained 
with hematoxylin. </p>

<p>In situ terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase-mediated 
deoxyuridine triphosphate nick-end labeling technique 
assay for lung cell apoptosis </p>

<p>Apoptotic cells in the lung tissue sections were detected by 
the terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase-mediated deoxy-
uridine triphosphate nick-end labeling technique (TUNEL) 
using a commercial apoptosis kit (TACS TdT Kit, R&amp;D Sys-
tems Inc., Minneapolis, MN, USA), according to the supplier's 
instructions. In brief, the lung tissue sections were de-paraf-
finized with xylene and ethanol and rinsed with phosphate 
buffered saline (PBS). The sections were then treated with 
proteinase K in PBS followed by quenching of endogenous 
peroxidase. A biotinylated dNTP mix was added to the 3ʹ-OH 
ends of DNA by terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase (TdT). 
After incubating with streptavidin-horseradish peroxidase, 
the sections were stained with DAB and counterstained with 
methyl green. Finally, the sections were dehydrated in etha-
nol, cleared with xylene, and mounted with coverslips in a 
permanent medium. According to the supplier's instructions, 
experimental controls included for the assay were TACS-
nuclease-treated thyroid tissue sections as the positive control 
and the omission of the TdT reaction step as the negative con-
trol. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>The tissue was homogenized in 10 mM Tris HCl buffer, 
pH 7.4 containing 0.5 mM EDTA, pH 8.0, 0.25 M sucrose, 
1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, 1 mM Na 4 VO 3 and a 
protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche-Boehringer-Mannheim, 
Mannheim, Germany). After centrifugation, the supernatant 
was subjected to sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel 
electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE). Samples equivalent to 25 µg of 
protein content were loaded and size-separated in 8%-12% 
SDS-PAGE. The proteins on the acrylamide gel were trans-
ferred to a polyvinylidene difluoride membrane (Millipore, 
Bedford, MA, USA) at 400 mA in a transfer buffer containing 
25 mM Tris and 192 mM glycine, pH 8.4. The nitrocellulose 
membranes was blocked in Tris-buffered saline with 5% non-
fat dry milk at room temperature for 1 hour in 0.1% Tween 
20 and incubated with the appropriated primary antibodies, 
including anti-ET-1 and anti-endothelin receptor antagonist 
(ERA) (Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA) 
and anti-actin (Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc.), at 4°C over-
night. The membranes were then incubated with horseradish 
peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody (Cell Signaling 
Technology Inc., Danvers, MA, USA) for 1 hour at room tem-</p>

<p>Therapeutic efficacy of PGE1 in PAH </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5115/acb.2017.50.1.60 </p>

<p>Anat Cell Biol 2017;50:60-68 63 </p>

<p>www.acbjournal.org </p>

<p>perature. After washing, the membranes were visualized by 
a chemiluminescent ECL-detection kit from GE-Healthcare 
(Piscataway, NJ, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Results were expressed as the mean±standard deviation. 
Differences between all other parameters for the three groups 
were evaluated by ANOVA followed by multiple-group com-
parisons. An unpaired two-tailed t test and Mann-Whitney 
test were used, and a P-value of &lt;0.05 was considered statisti-
cally significant. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">14.0</rs> for windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA) was used for all statistical analyses. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Organ weight </p>

<p>RV weight of the M group was increased at 21 and 28 
days after MCT administration. Weights of LV+IVS were not 
significantly different among C, M, and PGE1 groups. RV/ 
LV+IVS ratios were significantly increased at 14, 21, and 28 
days in the M group compared to those in the C group. How-
ever, RV/LV+IVS ratios were significantly decreased at 21 and 
28 days in the M group compared to those in the PGE1 group. 
Weights of LV+IVS were significantly lower in the M group 
and the PGE1 group compared to those in the C group at 21 
and 28 days. Heart weights were significantly increased in the 
M group compared to those in the C group at 21 and 28 days. 
However, heart weights were significantly decreased in the </p>

<p>PGE1 group compared to those in the M group at 21 and 28 
days (Table 1). </p>

<p>Changes in SPAP after PGE1 treatment in PAH rats </p>

<p>Mean SPAP values were significantly increased in the M 
group compared to those in the C group at 14, 21, and 28 
days. SPAP values were significantly decreased in the PGE1 
group compared to those in the M group at 21 and 28 days 
(Table 1). </p>

<p>Medial wall thickness of the pulmonary artery </p>

<p>In the M group, the ratio of medial thickening to the ex-
ternal diameter of the pulmonary artery was significantly 
increased from 28 days compared to that in the control group. 
In the PGE1 group, the ratio of medial thickening of the pul-
monary artery was not significantly decreased compared to 
that in the M group (Table 2). </p>

<p>Number of muscular pulmonary arterioles </p>

<p>The number of muscular pulmonary arterioles was sig-
nificantly increased in the M group compared to that in the C 
group. From 21 and 28 days, the number of muscular pulmo-
nary arterioles was significantly decreased in the PGE1 group 
compared to that in the M group (Table 3). </p>

<p>Administration of PGE1 reduces RV and lung collagen 
deposition </p>

<p>To evaluate the effect of PGE1 treatment on the develop-</p>

<p>Table 1. Changes of SPAP and organ weights after PGE1 treatment in PAH rats </p>

<p>Day Group 
SPAP </p>

<p>(mm Hg) </p>

<p>RV </p>

<p>(g) </p>

<p>LV+IVS </p>

<p>(g) </p>

<p>RV/(LV+IVS) </p>

<p>(%) 
7 C 
21.4±1.3 
0.14±0.02 
0.54±0.03 
0.26±0.15 
M 
24.3±2.5 
0.15±0.03 
0.55±0.03 
0.27±0.23 
PGE1 
23.1±2.3 
0.15±0.03 
0.55±0.02 
0.27±0.18 
14 C 
22.4±1.1 
0.15±0.03 
0.66±0.03 
0.22±0.18 
M 
35.2±3.1* 
0.21±0.05 
0.64±0.04 
0.32±0.32* 
PGE1 
31.6±2.4 
0.17±0.04 
0.66±0.05 
0.25±0.24 
21 C 
23.7±1.3 
0.16±0.03 
0.74±0.04 
0.21±0.22 
M 
48.9±6.1* 
0.31±0.05* 
0.64±0.05 
0.48±0.53* 
PGE1 
37.7±4.2 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>0.19±0.03 
0.71±0.05 
0.27±0.35 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>28 C 
24.4±1.2 
0.17±0.04 
0.78±0.05 
0.22±0.24 
M 
55.3±9.3* 
0.37±0.10* 
0.68±0.08 
0.54±0.68* 
PGE1 
39.5±4.3 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>0.21±0.06 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>0.72±0.07 
0.29±0.35 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±SD. SPAP, systolic pulmonary artery pressure; </p>

<p>PGE1, prostaglandin E1; PAH, pulmonary arterial hypertension; RV, right </p>

<p>ventricle; LV, left ventricle; IVS, interventricular septum; C, control; M, </p>

<p>monocrotaline. *P&lt;0.05 compared with the C group, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 compared with the </p>

<p>M group. </p>

<p>Table 2. Ratio of the medial thickening of pulmonary artery in each group (%) </p>

<p>Day 
C 
M 
PGE1 
7 
9.5±0.5 
8.8±0.3 
8.9±0.4 
14 
9.2±1.1 
12.7±1.2 
12.1±1.1 
21 
8.9±0.6 
17.9±2.2* 
16.1±2.8 
28 
8.8±0.7 
21.5±2.8* 
17.9±3.2 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>C, control; M, monocrotaline; PGE1, prostaglandin E1. *P&lt;0.05 vs. the corre-</p>

<p>sponding value in the C group, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. the corresponding value in the M </p>

<p>group. </p>

<p>Table 3. Number of muscular pulmonary arterioles in each group </p>

<p>Day 
C 
M 
PGE1 
7 
2.2±0.1 
2.3±0.1 
2.2±0.4 
14 
2.2±0.1 
2.9±0.1 
2.6±0.1 
21 
2.3±0.2 
3.8±0.2* 
3.1±0.2 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>28 
2.4±0.2 
5.5±0.5* 
4.2±0.4 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>C, control; M, monocrotaline; PGE1, prostaglandin E1. *P&lt;0.05 vs. the corre-</p>

<p>sponding value in the C group, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. the corresponding value in the M </p>

<p>group. </p>

<p>Anat Cell Biol 2017;50:60-68 </p>

<p>Jae Chul Lee </p>



<p>www.acbjournal.org </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5115/acb.2017.50.1.60 </p>

<p>ment of cardiac fibrosis, lung fibrosis, and remodeling, lung 
and RV samples were collected at 28 days after administration 
of MCT to determine histology patterns in the lung and RV. 
Results are shown in Figs. 2 and 3. After staining with Masson 
Trichrome, lung and RV sections showed more pronounced 
collagen deposition from animals with PAH compared to 
those in the control or PGE1 group (P=0.003 vs. C group, P= 
0.01 vs. M group; Fig. 2) (P=0.003 vs. C group, P=0.01 vs. M 
group; Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry analysis of lung samples </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry staining of lung tissues revealed 
that ET-1-positive cells were more prevalent in the PGE1 </p>

<p>group, followed by those in the M group in comparison with 
those in the C group at 28 days (Fig. 4A-F). Three weeks after 
PGE1 treatment, ET-1-positive cells were still observed at 
the lung area in the PGE1 group. The increased level of ET-1 
immunoreactivity observed in the M group was statistically 
significant (P&lt;0.05). The decreased level of ET-1-immunore-
activity was also significant in the PEG1 group compared to 
the M group (Fig. 4G). </p>

<p>TUNEL apoptosis assay </p>

<p>TUNEL staining was performed to detect apoptotic DNA 
in lung tissues. In the C group, there was no positive staining 
(Fig. 5A, D). However, the M group had lung tissues with pos-</p>

<p>C 
M 
PGE </p>

<p>D D 
E E 
F F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>C group 
M group 
PGE1 group </p>

<p>Collagen density (%) </p>

<p>C 
M </p>

<p>0 
PGE1 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>A A 
B 
B 
C 
C </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Representative images of lung stained with Masson Trichrome from C group (A), M group (B), and PGE1 group (C) at 28 days following 
the injection of monocrotaline. Panels (D), (E), and (F) are high power views of panels (A), (B), and (C); fibrosis is colored blue. C group, control 
group; M group, monocrotaline group; PGE1 group, prostaglandin E1 group. *P&lt;0.05 vs. C group, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. M group. Scale bars=150 µm (A-C), 
50 µm (D-F). (G) Collagen content was greatly increased in the M group in comparison with the C group at 28 days. The PGE1 group showed a 
significant decrease in collagen content at 28 days. </p>

<p>Collagen density (%) </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>C 
M </p>

<p>0 
PGE1 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C 
M 
PGE1 </p>

<p>C group 
M group 
group 
PGE1 </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Representative images of right ventricle stained with Masson Trichrome from C group (A), M group (B), and PGE1 group (C) at 28 days 
following the injection of monocrotaline. (D) Collagen content was greatly increased in the M group in comparison with the C group at 28 
days. The PGE1 group showed a significant decrease in collagen content at 28 days. Fibrosis is colored blue. C group, control group; M group, 
monocrotaline group; PGE1 group, prostaglandin E1 group. *P&lt;0.05 vs. C group, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. M group. Scale bar=150 µm (A-C). </p>

<p>Therapeutic efficacy of PGE1 in PAH </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5115/acb.2017.50.1.60 </p>

<p>Anat Cell Biol 2017;50:60-68 65 </p>

<p>www.acbjournal.org </p>

<p>itive TUNEL staining (the presence of dark brown nuclei was 
observed) (Fig. 5B, E). PGE1 group also had cells with brown 
nuclei, indicating apoptotic DNA (Fig. 5C, F). Apoptotic cells 
were significantly more prevalent in the M group than those 
in the C group. However, they were less prevalent in the PGE1 
group than those in the M group (Fig. 5G). These results indi-</p>

<p>cated that PGE1 could attenuate apoptosis in the lung tissues 
of treated PAH rats. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>This experiment was designed to investigate if PGE1 group 
exhibited alterations in expression levels of ET-1 and ERA </p>

<p>C 
M 
PGE1 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>D 
E 
F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>C group 
M group 
PGE1 group </p>

<p>Apoptotic cell (%) </p>

<p>C 
M </p>

<p>0 
PGE1 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Fig. 5. TUNEL assay on lung tissues at 28 days after prostaglandin E1 transfusion (A-F). Immunohistochemical expression revealed that the 
positive cells of apoptosis were significantly higher in the M group than that in the PGE1 group; however, they were lower in the PGE1 group than 
that in the M group (G). Panels (D), (E), and (F) are high power views of panels (A), (B), and (C). *P&lt;0.05 compared with the C group, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 
compared with the M group. TUNEL, terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferasemediated deoxyuridine triphosphate nickend labeling technique; C 
group, control group; M group, monocrotaline group; PGE1 group, prostaglandin E1 group. Scale bars=40 µm (A-C), 20 µm (D-F). </p>

<p>C 
M 
PGE1 </p>

<p>A A 
B B 
C C </p>

<p>D 
D 
E 
E 
F 
F </p>

<p>D 
E E 
F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>C group 
M group 
PGE1 group </p>

<p>Staining density (%) </p>

<p>C 
M </p>

<p>0 
PGE1 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Localization of ET1-immunoreactive cells in the lung tissues at 28 days (A-F). Immunohistochemical expression reveals that the positive 
cells of ET1 is significantly higher in the M group than that in the C group; however, it is lower in the PGE1 group than that in the M group (G). 
Panels (D), (E), and (F) are high power views of panels (A), (B), and (C). ET1, endothelin1; C group, control group; M group, monocrotaline 
group; PGE1 group, prostaglandin E1 group. *P&lt;0.05 vs. C group, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. M group. Scale bars=50 µm (A-C), 25 µm (D-F). </p>

<p>Anat Cell Biol 2017;50:60-68 </p>

<p>Jae Chul Lee </p>



<p>www.acbjournal.org </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5115/acb.2017.50.1.60 </p>

<p>proteins in the lung. Changes in expression levels of ET-1 im-
munoreactivity in the lung were detected in the PGE1 group. 
Expression levels of ET-1 and ERA proteins detected in the 
PGE1 group were significantly decreased compared to those 
in the M group (Fig. 6A, B). Actin bands indicated protein 
loading in the same sample (P&lt;0.001 vs. C group, P&lt;0.001 vs. 
M group) (Fig. 6). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study showed that treatment with PGE1 could 
reduce mal-adaptive structural remodeling of the lung and 
heart and prevent ventricular arrhythmias in MCT-induced 
PAH in rats. The main purpose of this study was to determine 
the effect of PGE1 on PAH using a rat model. Our results 
showed that PGE1 did reduce SPAP in PAH rats. It also im-
proved RV hypertrophy, an indicator of RV pressure overload 
caused by elevated pulmonary artery pressure. In addition, it 
decreased the number of intra-acinar arteries and medial wall 
thickening in pulmonary arterioles, index of vascular remod-
eling. </p>

<p>Endothelins are potent vasoconstricting peptides that have 
proliferative and pro-inflammatory effects. Isoform ET-1 is a 
well-established mediator of pulmonary vascular homeostasis 
[24]. Among other subtypes of PAH, higher levels of ET-1 
are predictive of severity and mortality. ERAs can improve 
clinical and hemodynamic parameters of PAH. Therefore, 
ERAs are mainstays of PAH therapy [25-27]. The following 
is our hypotheses about the mechanisms of how PGE1 de-
creases medial wall thickening. PGE1 has vasodilatory, anti-
inflammatory, anti-aggregatory, and anti-proliferative effects 
through decreasing the expression of ET-1 in lung tissues. 
However, when PGE1 is intravenously administered, it is 
rapidly eliminated by the lungs. The half-life of intravenous 
PGE1 can be as short as 42 seconds. Therefore, the clearance 
of intravenous PGE1 is closely related to respiratory func-
tion and pulmonary blood flow. In animal models of acute or 
chronic pulmonary hypertension, inhaled PGE1 can increase 
ventricular contractility and reduce pulmonary arterial pres-
sure [28]. Inhalation of a single 25 µg dose of aerosolized 
iloprost, a prostanoid analogue, is associated with enhanced 
cardiac index and reduced mean pulmonary arterial pressure 
and pulmonary vascular resistance [29]. In previous studies, 
inhalation of 300 µg/day of PGE1 for 10 days following sur-
gery is associated with reduced pulmonary arterial pressure, 
similar to the effect of intravenous PGE1 infusion [28]. Corti-
cal hyperostosis of long bones is also reversible in neonates 
receiving PGE1 greater than 120 hours [30]. Therefore, the 
aim of this study was to evaluate the effect of continuous in-
travenous PGE1 on hemodynamics and long-term outcomes 
of rats with MCT-induced PAH. In the present study, we 
treated PAH rats with PGE1. We then performed hematoxylin 
and eosin staining, Masson Trichrome staining, immuno-
histochemical staining, and western blot analysis in order to 
investigate changes of ET-1 immunoreactivity in the cardiom-
eter of these rats. A significant increase in pulmonary arterial 
pressure following MCT injection was accompanied by RV 
hypertrophy and increased lung and heart fibrosis when com-
pared to the control group (Figs. 2, 3). In the RV of rats with 
PAH, PGE1 treatment decreased the development of RV hy-
pertrophy and normalized the expression of collagen content 
(Fig. 3). Additionally, in rats with PAH, SPAP of the heart was 
decreased by PGE1 treatment (Table 1). There results suggest 
that PGE1 could decrease pulmonary vessel contraction and 
remodeling, leading to improvement in apoptosis and inhibi-
tion of fibrosis in PAH rats. These findings support our hy-
pothesis that chronic PGE1 administration can improve PAH. </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>24 kDa </p>

<p>69 kDa </p>

<p>44 kDa </p>

<p>ET-1 </p>

<p>ERA </p>

<p>Actin </p>

<p>C 
M 
PGE1 </p>

<p>ERA 
Actin </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
ET-1 
Staining density (%) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>C group 
M group 
PGE1 group </p>

<p>Fig. 6. (A) Western blot analysis of the levels of expression of ET1, 
ERA, and actin immunoreactivity in the RV. (B) The semiquantitative 
analysis confirms that PGE1 group exhibited increased levels of immu 
noreactivity of ET1 and ERA in the RV. ET1, endothelin1; ERA, 
endo thelin receptor antagonist; RV, right ventricle; C group, control 
group; M group, monocrotaline group; PGE1 group, prostaglandin E1 
group (n=4-5 per group). *P&lt;0.05 vs. C group, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. M group. </p>

<p>Therapeutic efficacy of PGE1 in PAH </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.5115/acb.2017.50.1.60 </p>

<p>Anat Cell Biol 2017;50:60-68 67 </p>

<p>www.acbjournal.org </p>

<p>PGE1, a naturally occurring eicosanoid, is synthesized 
from 20-carbon polyunsaturated fatty acid dihomo-gamma-
linolenic acid (DGLA) via cyclooxygenase-1 and -2 pathways 
[31, 32]. PGE1 is a member of series-1 prostaglandin class. It 
can produce a number of physiological effects. It is primarily 
known for its anti-inflammatory and vasodilatory effects. It 
has been reported that PEG1 can inhibit platelet aggregation, 
vascular smooth muscle proliferation, and collagenase activ-
ity [33-35]. In pulmonary circulation, PGE1 is synthesized 
primarily by cells of the vascular endothelium and smooth 
muscle cells. Following intravenous administration, PGE1 is 
distributed and metabolized with an estimated half-life of 5-10 
minutes [36]. Lungs are the primary sites for the metabolism 
of PGE1. They can metabolize as much as 80% of systemically 
absorbed PGE1 in a single pass [36]. Metabolism in pulmo-
nary vascular bed is an oxygen-dependent process [37]. Pros-
taglandins including PGE1 are normally paracrine lipidic me-
diators. They can interact with a distinct family of G-protein 
coupled prostanoids receptors composed of 8 subtypes (EP1-
4, IP, FP, TP, and DP) [38]. Of these eight subtypes, EP2, EP4, 
DP, and IP can induce smooth muscle relaxation and vasodi-
latory effects [39]. This mechanism is different from cardiac 
striated muscles where the troponin complex is responsible 
for the regulation of muscle contractions. PGE1 is also con-
sidered as a potential treatment option for PAH because of its 
high pulmonary clearance (70%-90%) and pulmonary-selec-
tive vasodilating effect [40]. However, intravenous adminis-
tration of PGE1 has side-effects such as systemic hypotension 
and low cardiac output, similar to those produced by other 
short-acting prostacyclin analogues [40]. Recently, Della Roc-
ca et al. [11] have documented the efficacy of inhaled PGE1 
in improving pulmonary hemodynamics and oxygenation in 
a clinical trial enrolling 18 patients undergoing lung trans-
plantation. They reported that PGE1 administered at a low 
dose produced a reduction in pulmonary arterial pressure and 
improved oxygenation without impairing systemic hemody-
namics [11]. Thus, there is compelling evidence showing that 
PGE1 is a pulmonary-selective vasodilator that can be used as 
an alternative to current therapy for PAH. However, no study 
has attempted to develop a long acting PGE1. PGE1 might be 
used to treat cardiovascular disease. It has potential to induce 
vessel relaxation and inhibit excessive proliferation of vascular 
cells. 
In conclusion, PGE1 can suppress PAH. Furthermore, 
PGE1 might be a new medicine for PAH. Further studies are 
needed to determine what pathways are involved in the im-</p>

<p>provement of PAH caused by PGE1. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The Korea Foundation for the Advancement of Science 
and Creativity (KOFAC) grant funded by the Korea govern-
ment (MEST) and supported by a Korea University grant. </p>



<p>Anat Cell Biol 2017;50:60-68 </p>

<p>Jae Chul Lee </p>





</text></tei>