<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5265988" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The proportion of alcohol-induced osteonecrosis of the femoral head (ONFH) in all ONFH patients was 30.7%, with males prevailing 
among the ONFH patients in mainland China (70.1%). Matrix metalloproteinase 2 (MMP2), a member of the MMP gene family, 
encodes the enzyme MMP2, which can promote osteoclast migration, attachment, and bone matrix degradation. In this 
case-control study, we aimed to investigate the association between MMP2 and the alcohol-induced ONFH in Chinese males. 
In total, 299 patients with alcohol-induced ONFH and 396 healthy controls were recruited for a case-control association study. 
Five single-nucleotide polymorphisms within the MMP2 locus were genotyped and examined for their correlation with the risk of 
alcohol-induced ONFH and treatment response using Pearson x 
2 test and unconditional logistic regression analysis. We identified 3 
risk alleles for carriers: the allele "T" of rs243849 increased the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH in the allele model, the log-additive 
model without adjustment, and the log-additive model with adjustment for age. Conversely, the genotypes "CC" in rs7201 and "CC" 
in rs243832 decreased the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH, as revealed by the recessive model. After the Bonferroni multiple 
adjustment, no significant association was found. Furthermore, the haplotype analysis showed that the "TT" haplotype of MMP2 was 
more frequent among patients with alcohol-induced ONFH by unconditional logistic regression analysis adjusted for age. 
In conclusion, there may be an association between MMP2 and the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH in North-Chinese males. 
However, studies on larger populations are needed to confirm this hypothesis; these data may provide a theoretical foundation for 
future studies. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CIs = confidence intervals, HWE = Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium, LD = linkage disequilibrium, MMP = matrix 
metalloproteinase, ONFH = osteonecrosis of the femoral head, OR = odds ratios, SNP = single-nucleotide polymorphism, TIMP = 
tissue inhibitor of matrix metalloproteinases. </p>

<p>Osteonecrosis of the femoral head (ONFH) is an intractable and 
complex orthopedic condition that is characterized by osteocyte </p>

<p>apoptosis and deterioration and collapse of the bone structure of 
the femoral head, which ultimately lead to femoral head ischemia 
and death. 
[1-3] Study has reported that the following revision is 
an outstanding problem in the ONFH treatment procedure. </p>

<p>[4]   Two types of ONFH exist: the traumatic and nontraumatic type. 
Alcohol-induced ONFH is a type of nontraumatic ONFH 
caused by chronic and excessive alcohol consumption. The 
incidence of this condition is increasing in China; data show that 
males dominate with a 70.1% in mainland China, and that the 
proportion of alcohol-induced ONFH among all ONFH patients 
is 30.7%. 
[5] One previous study reported that when alcohol 
intake was higher than 400 mL/wk, there was a clear increase in 
the risk of ONFH. 
[6] Several pathogenic mechanisms associated 
with the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH include environmental 
factors, alcohol intake, dyslipidemia, blood coagulation disor-
ders, and ossification dysfunction of mesenchymal stem cells; 
however, the exact pathogenesis of this condition is still 
controversial and unclear. Genetic researches have offered the 
potential insight into the occurrence and development of alcohol-
induced ONFH. Zhang et al 
[7] confirmed the association between 
ABCB1 polymorphism and increased ONFH risk. In addition, 
the association of ONFH with angiogenesis-and hypoxia-related 
gene polymorphisms, such as IGFBP3, VEGFC, and ACE, has 
been confirmed 
[8] . Recent studies suggest that MMP2 may play a </p>

<p>Editor: Mirko Manchia. </p>

<p>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>a Clinical Laboratory of Hong-Hui Hospital, Xi'an Jiaotong University College of 
Medicine, 
b Key Laboratory of Resource Biology and Biotechnology in Western 
China (Northwest University), Ministry of Education, College of Life Sciences, 
Northwest University, 
c Xi'an Tiangen Precision Medical Institute, 
d Institution of 
Basic Medical Science, Xi'an Medical University, Xi'an, Shaanxi Province, China. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Correspondence: Prof Heping Zhao, Clinical Laboratory of Hong-Hui Hospital, 
Xi'an Jiaotong University College of Medicine, #555 East Youyi Road, Xi'an 
710054, Shaanxi Province, China (e-mail: zhaohpHH@163.com) </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All 
rights reserved. 
This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-
ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is 
properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially 
without permission from the journal. </p>

<p>Medicine (2016) 95:49(e5407) </p>

<p>Received: 6 September 2016 / Received in final form: 25 October 2016 / 
Accepted: 27 October 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000005407 </p>

<p>Observational Study </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>OPEN </p>



<p>key role in the process of bone metabolism and influence the 
proliferation and/or differentiation of bone marrow stem cells in 
bone and joint diseases. </p>

<p>[9,10]   MMP2 is a member of the MMP gene family, which encodes 
zinc-dependent enzymes capable of cleaving components of the 
extracellular matrix and molecules involved in signal transduc-
tion. The MMP/tissue inhibitor of MMP (MMP/TIMP) pathway 
has also been found to impact human bone metabolism, 
[11] while 
polymorphisms of several genes in the pathway have been related 
to orthopedic diseases. 
[12-14] Some single-nucleotide polymor-
phisms (SNPs) in MMP2 have been associated with several 
diseases: for example, rs1053605 is associated with stroke 
outcome, 
[15] but not with abdominal aortic aneurysm 
[16] ; 
rs243849 is related to ischemic stroke outcome 
[15] ; the 
rs243847 variant may increase intracranial aneurysms in 
Japanese male patients 
[17] ; 2 SNPs, rs243832 and rs7201, that 
have a strong linkage disequilibrium (LD), have been associated 
with endometriosis. 
[18] However, whether these 5 MMP2 SNPs 
are associated with alcohol-induced ONFH is still unknown. 
Therefore, in this case-control study, we aimed to investigate 
whether the genetic aspect of MMP2 had a protective or risk-
increasing nature in the context of alcohol-induced ONFH in 
Chinese males. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Ethics committee statement </p>

<p>This case-control study was performed in compliance with the 
principles of the Declaration of Helsinki of the World Medical 
Association and obtained the permission from the Ethics 
Committee of Xi'an Hong-Hui Hospital, Xi'an Jiaotong 
University, and Northwest University. All of the participants </p>

<p>were informed of the case-control study, and their consents were 
obtained. </p>

<p>2.2. Research subjects </p>

<p>This case-control study was conducted in Xi'an Hong-Hui 
Hospital, and a total of 695 males pathologically confirmed 
alcohol-induced ONFH patients were enrolled from September 
2014 to January 2016, including 299 patients and 396 healthy 
controls. ONFH was diagnosed by clinical examination and 
radiographic analysis. Patients underwent anteroposterior and frog 
view X-ray tests; magnetic resonance imaging was needed to further 
confirm the ONFH in cases when the patients had no changes 
observable by X-ray. According to Lee et al </p>

<p>[19]   , alcohol-induced 
ONFH patients were those who consumed more than 400 mL of 
pure ethanol per week. Some patients were excluded from the study 
for reasons such as disagreeing with the study, consumption of 
drugs that have an effect on the patients' liver function and lipid 
metabolism, not meeting the diagnostic criteria of alcohol-induced 
ONFH, and suffering from chronic diseases synchronously. The 
person needing steroid treatment is also excluded from this 
case-control study. All healthy controls had never been diagnosed 
with alcohol-induced ONFH and were interviewed by professional 
interviewers for their age and alcohol exposure. </p>

<p>2.3. Genotyping </p>

<p>MMPs play a key role in the process of bone metabolism. A 
number of studies have revealed that some genes in the MMP/ 
TIMP pathway affect the risk of ONFH. Thus, we selected 
5 SNPs of the MMP2 gene based on the minor allele frequencies 
of more than 5% in the HapMap Chinese Han population: 
rs1053605, rs243849, rs243847, rs243832, and rs7201. </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Characteristics of the male individuals in controls and alcohol-induced ONFH patients. </p>

<p>Group 
N 
Mean 
Std. deviation 
Mean ± SD 
P </p>

<p>Age 
Case 
299 
43.24 
13.07 
43.24 ± 13.07 
P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Control 
396 
47.62 
10.28 
47.62 ± 10.28 </p>

<p>The P value was calculated by Welch t test. 
 *  P &lt; 0.05 indicates statistical significance. </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Summary of the basic information on candidate SNPs examined in the MMP2 gene among the cases and controls, and the odds ratio 
estimates for alcohol-induced ONFH. </p>

<p>Gene 
SNP ID 
Position 
Band 
Alleles A/B </p>

<p>MAF 
Role 
HWE-P </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
P </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Case 
Control </p>

<p>MMP2 
rs1053605 
55519607 
16q12.2 
T/C 
0.12 
0.14 
Coding exon 
0.84 
0.87 (0.63-1.19) 
0.373 
MMP2 
rs243849 
55523705 
16q12.2 
T/C 
0.21 
0.17 
Coding exon 
1.00 
1.33 (1.02-1.75) 
0.037 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>MMP2 
rs243847 
55523998 
16q12.2 
C/T 
0.38 
0.39 
Intron 
0.11 
0.95 (0.76-1.18) 
0.631 
MMP2 
rs243832 
55539191 
16q12.2 
C/G 
0.36 
0.38 
Intron (boundary) 
0.11 
0.92 (0.74-1.15) 
0.482 
MMP2 
rs7201 
55539614 
16q12.2 
C/A 
0.22 
0.25 
30 UTR 
0.22 
0.88 (0.68-1.12) 
0.298 </p>

<p>Bonferroni multiple adjustment was applied to the level of significance, which was set at P &lt; 0.0017 (0.05/30). 
A = minor alleles, B = major alleles, CI = confidence interval, HWE = Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium, MAF = minor allele frequency, MMP2 = matrix metalloproteinase 2, OR = odds ratio, SNPs = single-
nucleotide polymorphisms. 
 *  P values were calculated using the exact test. </p>

<p> † P values were calculated using the x 
2 test. 
 ‡ P &lt; 0.05 indicates statistical significance. </p>

<p>Bold values indicate a significant difference P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Yu et al. Medicine (2016) 95:49 
Medicine </p>



<p>Whole blood samples of each participant were extracted and 
placed in anticoagulant tubes. The extraction kit (GoldMag Co. 
Ltd., Xi'an, China) was used to isolate genomic DNA from the 
whole blood, and the genomic DNA concentration was then 
measured by spectrometry (DU530 UV/VIS spectrophotometer, </p>

<p>Beckman Instruments, Fullerton, CA). The DNA was subse-
quently stored at À20°C until detection. According to the 
manufacturer agreement, the Sequenom MassARRAY 
® RS1000 
system (Agena Bioscience Inc., San Diego, CA) was used to 
perform genotyping, and the Sequence MassARRAY Assay </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Genotypes of rs243849 and the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH were not adjusted for age. </p>

<p>Gene 
SNP_ID 
Model 
Genotype 
Control (%) 
Case (%) 
OR (95% CI) 
P </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>AIC 
BIC </p>

<p>MMP2 
rs243849 
Codominant 
C/C 
275 (69.4%) 
190 (63.5%) 
1 
C/T 
110 (27.8%) 
92 (30.8%) 
1.21 (0.87-1.69) 
0.084 
950.9 
964.6 
T/T 
11 (2.8%) 
17 (5.7%) 
2.24 (1.02-4.88) 
Dominant 
C/C 
275 (69.4%) 
190 (63.5%) 
1 
C/T-T/T 
121 (30.6%) 
109 (36.5%) 
1.30 (0.95-1.79) 
0.1 
951.2 
960.3 
Recessive 
C/C-C/T 
385 (97.2%) 
282 (94.3%) 
1 
T/T 
11 (2.8%) 
17 (5.7%) 
2.11 (0.97-4.57) 
0.055 
950.2 
959.3 
Overdominant 
C/C-T/T 
286 (72.2%) 
207 (69.2%) 
1 
C/T 
110 (27.8%) 
92 (30.8%) 
1.16 (0.83-1.61) 
0.39 
953.2 
962.2 
Log-additive 
-
-
-
1.32 (1.01-1.73) 
0.041 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>949.7 
958.8 </p>

<p>Bonferroni multiple adjustment was applied to the level of significance, which was set at P &lt; 0.0017 (0.05/30). 
AIC = Akaike information criterion, BIC = Bayesian information criterion, CI = confidence interval, MMP2 = matrix metalloproteinase 2, OR = odds ratio, SNPs = single-nucleotide polymorphisms. 
 *  P values were calculated by unconditional logistic regression without adjustment. </p>

<p> † P &lt; 0.05 indicates statistical significance. </p>

<p>Bold values indicate a significant difference P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>Genotypes of dominant SNPs in the MMP2 gene and the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH adjusted for age. </p>

<p>Gene 
SNP_ID 
Model 
Genotype 
Control (%) 
Case (%) 
OR (95% CI) 
P </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>AIC 
BIC </p>

<p>MMP2 
rs243849 
Codominant 
C/C 
275 (69.4%) 
190 (63.5%) 
1 
C/T 
110 (27.8%) 
92 (30.8%) 
1.28 (0.91-1.80) 
0.075 
928.7 
946.9 
T/T 
11 (2.8%) 
17 (5.7%) 
2.17 (0.98-4.80) 
Dominant 
C/C 
275 (69.4%) 
190 (63.5%) 
1 
C/T-T/T 
121 (30.6%) 
109 (36.5%) 
1.37 (0.99-1.89) 
0.059 
928.3 
942 
Recessive 
C/C-C/T 
385 (97.2%) 
282 (94.3%) 
1 
T/T 
11 (2.8%) 
17 (5.7%) 
2.01 (0.92-4.42) 
0.077 
928.8 
942.4 
Overdominant 
C/C-T/T 
286 (72.2%) 
207 (69.2%) 
1 
C/T 
110 (27.8%) 
92 (30.8%) 
1.23 (0.88-1.72) 
0.23 
930.5 
944.1 
Log-additive 
-
-
-
1.36 (1.03-1.79) 
0.027 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>927 
940.7 
MMP2 
rs243832 
Codominant 
G/G 
159 (40.1%) 
116 (38.8%) 
1 
G/C 
172 (43.4%) 
149 (49.8%) 
1.14 (0.82-1.58) 
0.086 
929 
947.2 
C/C 
65 (16.4%) 
34 (11.4%) 
0.67 (0.41-1.09) 
Dominant 
G/G 
159 (40.1%) 
116 (38.8%) 
1 
G/C-C/C 
237 (59.9%) 
183 (61.2%) 
1.01 (0.74-1.38) 
0.97 
931.9 
945.5 
Recessive 
G/G-G/C 
331 (83.6%) 
265 (88.6%) 
1 
C/C 
65 (16.4%) 
34 (11.4%) 
0.62 (0.40-0.98) 
0.037 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>927.5 
941.2 
Overdominant 
G/G-C/C 
224 (56.6%) 
150 (50.2%) 
1 
G/C 
172 (43.4%) 
149 (49.8%) 
1.26 (0.93-1.71) 
0.14 
929.7 
943.3 
Log-additive 
-
-
-
0.89 (0.71-1.11) 
0.31 
930.8 
944.5 
MMP2 
rs7201 
Codominant 
A/A 
228 (57.7%) 
177 (59.2%) 
1 
C/A 
138 (34.9%) 
110 (36.8%) 
1.00 (0.72-1.38) 
0.11 
928.6 
946.7 
C/C 
29 (7.3%) 
12 (4%) 
0.48 (0.24-0.99) 
Dominant 
A/A 
228 (57.7%) 
177 (59.2%) 
1 
C/A-C/C 
167 (42.3%) 
122 (40.8%) 
0.91 (0.67-1.24) 
0.55 
930.6 
944.3 
Recessive 
A/A-C/A 
366 (92.7%) 
287 (96%) 
1 
C/C 
29 (7.3%) 
12 (4%) 
0.48 (0.24-0.98) 
0.035 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>926.6 
940.2 
Overdominant 
A/A-C/C 
257 (65.1%) 
189 (63.2%) 
1 
C/A 
138 (34.9%) 
110 (36.8%) 
1.07 (0.78-1.47) 
0.69 
930.8 
944.5 
Log-additive 
-
-
-
0.85 (0.66-1.09) 
0.19 
929.3 
942.9 </p>

<p>Bonferroni multiple adjustment was applied to the level of significance, which was set at P &lt; 0.0017 (0.05/30). 
AIC = Akaike information criterion, BIC = Bayesian information criterion, CI = confidence interval, MMP2 = matrix metalloproteinase 2, OR = odds ratio, SNPs = single-nucleotide polymorphisms. 
 *  P values were calculated by unconditional logistic regression with adjustment for age. </p>

<p> † P &lt; 0.05 indicates statistical significance. </p>

<p>Bold values indicate a significant difference P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Yu et al. Medicine (2016) 95:49 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>Design 4.0 (Agena Bioscience Inc.) software was used to design a 
Multiplexed SNP mass-EXTEND assay. 
[20] Data analyses and 
management were conducted by <rs id="software-4" type="software">Sequenom Typer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">4.0</rs> Software 
(<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Agena Bioscience Inc</rs>.). </p>

<p>[21]   2.4. Statistical analysis </p>

<p><rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-5" type="software">Excel</rs> and <rs id="software-6" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">16.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">SPSS</rs>, Chicago, IL) were used to 
perform statistical analyses. Throughout the document, P values 
were 2-sided; furthermore, P values less than 0.05 were 
considered statistically significant. The age difference of cases 
and controls was calculated by Welch t tests, and the exact test 
was used to determine whether the SNPs departed from the 
Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE). The association between 
the minor allele and the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH was 
evaluated by Pearson x 
2 test. To assess the association between 
each genotype and the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH, 5 models 
were used, including the codominant, dominant, recessive, 
overdominant, and log-additive model. Finally, the <rs type="software">SHEsis</rs> 
software platform 
[22] and <rs id="software-8" type="software">Haploview</rs> software package (version 
<rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">4.2</rs>) (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">Broad Institute</rs>, Cambridge, MA) were used to analyze the 
patterns of LD, haplotype construction, and the genetic 
association at polymorphic loci. 
[23] Odds ratios (ORs) and 
95% confidence intervals (95% CIs) could show whether the 
frequencies between cases and controls had a significant 
difference. Unconditional logistic regression analysis was 
adjusted for age. In order to eliminate the probability of false-
positive results, Bonferroni multiple adjustment was applied to 
the level of significance, which was set at P &lt; 0.0017 (0.05/30). </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>In this case-control study, all participants were males. The age 
characteristic is presented in Table 1. We selected 695 
individuals, including 299 alcohol-induced ONFH patients 
(age: 43.24 ± 13.07) and 396 healthy controls (age: 47.62 ± 
10.28). A total of 5 SNPs were analyzed in the study. Gene, 
chromosomal position, the minor/major allele frequency, HWE 
test, and Pearson x 
2 test results for all the SNPs are presented in 
Table 2. The HWE test was used to check whether the surveyed 
population approached the genetic equilibrium and whether 
random sampling requirements were achieved. P &gt; 0.05 showed 
that the SNPs met the HWE, so none of the SNPs was excluded. 
The differences in the frequency distribution of alleles between 
cases and controls were compared by Pearson x 
2 test. We found 
that 1 significant SNP of the MMP2 gene was associated with the 
risk of alcohol-induced ONFH at a level of 5% (rs243849 OR = 
1.33, 95% CI = 1.02-1.75, P = 0.037). 
Next, we assumed that the minor allele of each SNP was a risk 
factor and analyzed the association between each variant and the 
risk of alcohol-induced ONFH under 5 genetic models 
(codominant, dominant, recessive, overdominant, and log-
addictive) (Tables 3 and 4). The Akaike information criterion 
and the Bayesian information criterion (BIC) were used to select 
the optimal model among candidate models, as discussed in the 
study by Vrieze. 
[24] The "T" allele of rs243849 was found to 
increase the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH under the log-
addictive model by unconditional logistic regression analysis 
without adjustments (OR = 1.32, 95% CI = 1.01-1.73, P = 
0.041) (Table 3). Moreover, unconditional logistic regression 
analysis adjusted for age was used for further analysis of the 
association of each SNP with the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH 
(Table 4). Similarly, we found that rs243849 was associated with 
increased odds of developing alcohol-induced ONFH in the log-
addictive model in the North-Chinese male population (OR = 
1.36, 95% CI = 1.03-1.79, P = 0.027). Conversely, the recessive 
model revealed that the genotype "CC" in rs243832 and the 
genotype "CC" in rs7201 decreased the risk of alcohol-induced 
ONFH (rs243832 OR = 0.62, 95% CI = 0.40-0.98, P = 0.037; 
rs7201 OR = 0.48, 95% CI = 0.24-0.98, P = 0.035). We did not 
find any statistically significant association between the risk of 
alcohol-induced ONFH and the loci rs1053605 and rs243847 
using the 5 models. However, after Bonferroni multiple 
adjustment was applied to our data, no SNP in our study was 
significantly related to alcohol-induced ONFH. 
Finally, haplotype analysis results showed that 2 blocks have 
the LD, rs243849-rs243847 and rs243832-rs7201, and the D' 
values were 1 and 0.99, respectively (Fig. 1). The haplotype "TT" 
of the rs243849 and rs243847 block was found to be associated 
with an increased risk of alcohol-induced ONFH by Pearson x </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>test (P &lt; 0.05) (Table 5). Furthermore, under unconditional 
logistic regression analysis adjusted for age, the "TT" haplotype 
equally augmented the risk (OR = 1.41, 95% CI = 1.04-1.90, P = 
0.028). However, no significant haplotype was identified in the 
rs243832-rs7201 block. </p>

<p>4. Discussion and conclusion </p>

<p>Epidemiologic studies found that SNPs in several genes might be 
associated with patients' susceptibility to orthopedic dis-
eases, 
[25,26] including alcohol-induced ONFH. 
[27] Investigation 
of the relationship between different genes and diseases can 
improve the treatment, prevention, and prognosis. Furthermore, </p>

<p>Figure 1. Haplotype block map for part of the single-nucleotide polymorph-
isms (SNPs) in the MMP2 gene. Linkage disequilibrium (LD) plots containing 5 
SNPs of 16q12.2. Standard color frame is used to show LD pattern. Two 
blocks in the figure showed higher LD. Darker shades of red indicate higher D' 
and display statistically significant associations between a pair of SNPs. </p>

<p>Yu et al. Medicine (2016) 95:49 
Medicine </p>



<p>several genetic markers for alcohol-induced ONFH had already 
been found. 
[27,28] In our study, we identified the association of 5 
SNPs in the MMP2 gene with the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH 
in the male Chinese Han population from the area of Shanxi. Our 
result showed that MMP2, found on chromosome 16, might be 
associated with the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH. The 
haplotype "TT" was associated with a 1.41-fold increase in 
the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH. 
Alcohol-induced ONFH is a serious and complex condition 
characterized by the apoptosis of osteocytes and an imbalance in 
bone metabolism, caused by a disruption in the dynamic 
equilibrium of bone formation and breakdown and in the 
prosoplasia of bone marrow stromal cells. 
[3,29] Patients present 
with pain and limited hip-joint movement, caused by bone 
trabecula breakage and collapse of the subchondral bone, or with 
abnormal lipid metabolism and intravascular coagulation, which 
result in necrosis of the femoral head. 
[30,31] Some studies report 
that normal repair mechanisms might be disrupted after bone 
death, and the repair process probably takes place in the form of 
bone remodeling coupled with bone resorption and bone 
formation. 
[32] Generally, cellular responses in the physiologic 
cycle of bone remodeling involve a series of highly regulated 
steps, containing "resting," "activation," "resorption," "rever-
sal," and "formation" phases. 
[33] Both osteoblasts and osteo-
clasts are the primary functional cells involved in the process of 
bone remodeling. Osteoclasts attach to the mineralized bone 
surface and initiate bone resorption by secreting hydrogen ions 
and by digesting bone collagen. Afterward, osteoblasts migrate to 
the bone resorption site and secrete bone matrix, which then 
mineralizes and forms new bone. The balance of the bone 
remodeling process plays a key role in maintaining normal bone 
mass. 
MMPs are not only directly involved in bone matrix 
degradation but can also promote osteoclast migration and 
attachment. In fact, it has been demonstrated that osteoblasts 
have the ability to secrete MMPs. 
[34,35] MMPs are maintained at 
a normal level under the regulation of a variety of factors. During 
inflammation, MMPs regulate the differentiation of osteoblasts 
and bone resorption by osteoclasts to complete the repair of the 
necrotic bone. Moreover, it has been suggested that MMP2, 
which is encoded by the MMP2 gene located in 16q12.2, 
contributes to bone remodeling. 
[36] According to Keiichi Inoue, it 
plays a crucial role in forming and maintaining the osteocyte 
canalicular network, whose formation is a determining factor of 
bone remodeling and mineralization. 
[37,38] A report suggested 
that the abnormal expression of MMP2 causes osteolysis. 
[39] The </p>

<p>upregulation of MMP2 induces the MMP/TIMP pathway, which 
in turn activates osteoclast bone resorption and accelerates 
osteoblast apoptosis and bone matrix degradation. The balance 
between bone resorption and bone formation is thus disrupted, 
and this imbalance could be the most important mechanism of 
collapse in ONFH. 
[32] Therefore, MMP2 is an important 
regulatory gene in alcohol-induced ONFH patients. We have 
not found any evidence for the role of heredity between MMP2 
and the risk of alcohol-induced ONFH in Chinese males. In this 
case-control study, carriers of the rs243849 "T" allele exhibited 
a 1.33-, 1.32-, and 1.36-fold, statistically significant increase in 
the susceptibility of alcohol-induced ONFH by the allele model, 
log-additive model without adjustments, and log-additive model 
adjusted for age, respectively. The patients who had the 
genotypes "CC" of rs243832 and "CC" of rs7201 had a 
decreased susceptibility of alcohol-induced ONFH. After 
Bonferroni multiple adjustment was applied, no significant 
association was found. However, the rs243849 risk allele "T" 
and rs243847 wild type allele "T" constituted the haplotype 
"TT", which, compared to the wild type "CT", increased the risk 
of alcohol-induced ONFH. Because Bonferroni correction is the 
most conservative approach, the variability of MMP2 may be a 
risk factor in the Chinese males. 
In summary, we identified 5 SNPs of the MMP2 gene and 
found that the variability of MMP2 could be a biomarker for the 
risk of alcohol-induced ONFH. It is important to note that there 
were several limitations in our case-control study, such as limited 
sample size and lack of corresponding clinical information. Thus, 
further research is needed to verify our results, especially due to 
the lack of previous research on this topic. It is possible that 
MMP2 polymorphisms are related to the risk of alcohol-induced 
ONFH, and these data provide a theoretical foundation for 
future studies of this correlation in the Chinese population or in 
other populations. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank all the patients and individuals for their participation, 
as well as all the physicians and nurses of Xi'an Hong-Hui 
Hospital for offering their blood samples. </p>



<p>Table 5 
MMP2 haplotype frequencies and their association with alcohol-induced ONFH among the cases and controls adjusted for age. </p>

<p>SNPs 
Haplotype 
Freq (case) 
Freq (control) 
P </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
P </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>rs243849jrs243847 
CT 
0.408 
0.439 
-
1.000 
-
CC 
0.381 
0.394 
0.650 
1.06 (0.84-1.35) 
0.600 
TT 
0.211 
0.167 
0.042 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>1.41 (1.04-1.90) 
0.028 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>rs243832jrs7201 
GA 
0.637 
0.618 
-
1.000 
-
CC 
0.224 
0.248 
0.340 
0.85 (0.65-1.10) 
0.210 
CA 
0.139 
0.135 
0.980 
0.97 (0.71-1.34) 
0.870 </p>

<p>CI = confidence interval, OR = odds ratio, SNPs = single-nucleotide polymorphisms. 
 *  P values were calculated by Pearson x 
2 test. 
 † P values were calculated by unconditional logistic regression adjustment for age. 
 ‡ P &lt; 0.05 indicates statistical significance. </p>

<p>Bold values indicate a significant difference P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Yu et al. Medicine (2016) 95:49 
www.md-journal.com </p>







</text></tei>