<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5360432" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Impaired glycogen synthesis and turnover are 
common in insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes. As glycogen 
synthase (GS) is a key enzyme involved in the synthetic 
process, it presents a promising therapeutic target for the 
treatment of type 2 diabetes. In the present study, we identi-
fied a novel, potent and orally available GS activator AJS1669 
{sodium 2-[[5-[[4-(4,5-difluoro-2-methylsulfanyl-phenyl) 
phenoxy] methyl]furan-2-carbonyl]-(2-furylmethyl)amino] 
acetate}. In vitro, we performed a glycogen synthase 1 (GYS1) 
activation assay for screening GS activators and identified that 
the activity of AJS1669 was further potentiated in the pres-
ence of glucose-6-phosphate (G6P). In vivo, we used ob/ob 
mice to evaluate the novel anti-diabetic effects of AJS1669 by 
measuring basal blood glucose levels, glucose tolerance and 
body fat mass index. Repeated administration of AJS1669 over 
4 weeks reduced blood glucose and hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) </p>

<p>levels in ob/ob mice. AJS1669 also improved glucose tolerance 
in a dose-dependent manner, and decreased body fat mass. 
The mRNA levels of genes involved in mitochondrial fatty 
acid oxidation and mitochondrial biogenesis were elevated in 
skeletal muscle tissue following AJS1669 treatment. Hepatic 
tissue of treated mice also exhibited elevated expression 
of genes associated with fatty acid oxidation. In contrast to 
ob/ob mice, in C57Bl/6 mice AJS1669 administration did 
not alter body weight or reduce glucose levels. These results 
demonstrate that pharmacological agents that activate GYS1, 
the main GS subtype found in skeletal muscle, have potential 
for use as novel treatments for diabetes that improve glucose 
metabolism in skeletal muscle. </p>

<p>In 2010, 285 million adults (aged 20 to 79 years) were esti-
mated to have diabetes globally, and this number is expected 
to reach 439 million by 2030 (1). Currently, although several 
types of medications used to treat type 2 diabetes have been 
marketed, pioglitazone and metformin are most commonly 
used as insulin sensitizers (2). 
In humans, skeletal muscle is the major site of glucose 
uptake and glycogen storage, with both processes being 
regulated by insulin. Impaired glycogen synthesis is the 
major abnormality in type 2 diabetes (3,4). For example, 
carbon-13 nuclear magnetic resonance ( 
13 C-NMR) spectros-
copy in subjects undergoing hyperglycemic-hyperinsulinemic 
clamping revealed that patients with diabetes have a 50% or 
greater decrease in glycogen synthesis relative to healthy indi-
viduals (5). In analyses performed at the cellular level, patients 
with type 2 diabetes involving insulin resistance were found 
to have decreased glycogen synthase (GS) activity in skeletal 
muscle (6,7). Insulin sensitivity was found to be enhanced 
by exercise or weight loss associated with exercise (8-10). 
Exercise activates GS and enhances insulin sensitivity (11-13). 
Activation of GS in type 2 diabetes and correction of glucose </p>

<p>AJS1669, a novel small-molecule muscle glycogen 
synthase activator, improves glucose metabolism 
and reduces body fat mass in mice </p>

<p>KAZUHIRO NAKANO </p>

<p>1* </p>

<p>, SEN TAKESHITA 
1* , NORIKO KAWASAKI 
2 , WATARU MIYANAGA 
3 , </p>

<p>YORIKO OKAMATSU </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>, MIZUKI DOHI 
1 and TADAKIYO NAKAGAWA </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Innovation Promotion Department, Research Institute, EA Pharma Co., Ltd., Kawasaki, Kanagawa 210-868; 
2 Nutrition and Health Science Group Frontier Research Laboratories, Institute for Innovation, Ajinomoto Co., Inc., </p>

<p>Kawasaki, Kanagawa 210-8681; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Business Development Department, EA Pharma Co., Ltd., Chuo-ku, Tokyo 104-0042; 
4 Novel Projects Research Group, Institute for Innovation, Ajinomoto Co., Inc., Kawasaki, Kanagawa 210-8681; 
5 Intellectual Property Department, EA Pharma Co., Ltd., Chuo-ku, Tokyo 104-0042, Japan </p>

<p>Received August 9, 2016; Accepted February 16, 2017 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/ijmm.2017.2909 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Dr Kazuhiro Nakano, Innovation Promotion </p>

<p>Department, Research Institute, EA Pharma Co., Ltd., Kawasaki-ku, 
Kangawaga 2108681, Japan 
E-mail: kazuhiro_nakano68@eapharma.co.jp </p>

<p>* Contributed equally </p>

<p>Abbreviations: GS, glycogen synthase; GYS1, glycogen synthase 1; </p>

<p>G6P, glucose-6-phosphate; GPI, glycogen phosphorylase inhibitor; 
HbA1c, hemoglobin A1c; HOMA-IR, homeostatic model for 
assessment of insulin resistance; hGYS1, human GYS1; 
13 C-NMR, 
carbon-13 nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy; OGTT, oral 
glucose tolerance test; PPAR, peroxisome proliferator-activated 
receptor; SGLT2, sodium/glucose co-transporter 2 </p>

<p>Key words: glycogen synthase, AJS1669, glucose tolerance, fat </p>

<p>mass, mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation </p>

<p>NAKANO et al: AJS1669 IMPROVES GLUCOSE METABOLISM IN MICE </p>



<p>metabolism in skeletal muscle have therefore been regarded as 
effective approaches to treating diabetes (14). 
In skeletal muscle, GS is one of the key enzymes in glucose 
metabolism. Glucose-6-phosphate (G6P) is converted to 
UDP-glucose, and GS forms α-1,4-glycosidic linkages, whereas 
branching enzymes create α-1,6-glycosidic linkages (15). 
There are two GS isoforms in mammals, with 69% homology. 
One is encoded by the glycogen synthase 2 (GYS2) gene and 
is expressed only in the liver, whereas the other is encoded by 
GYS1 and is expressed in the skeletal muscle, brain, kidneys, 
pancreas and adipose tissue (16,17). 
Recently, GS activators have been developed by 
Roche (18,19). One of the reported compounds was shown 
to activate GS in the skeletal muscle and liver in a concen-
tration-dependent manner. Repeated administration of this 
compound in ob/ob mice at a dose of 75 mg/kg significantly 
reduced the blood glucose level but did not result in weight 
gain. We identified AJS1669, as a novel allosteric activator 
of GYS1. AJS1669 activates human GYS1 (hGYS1) in a 
concentration-dependent manner. Its activation was found to 
be additive with G6P, an allosteric activator. AJS1669 accel-
erated not only glycogen accumulation, but also glycogen 
degradation in vitro, since the accumulation rate was higher 
with co-administration of a glycogen phosphorylase inhibitor. 
In the present study, we selected ob/ob mice for evaluating the 
effects of this compound on blood glucose level, oral glucose 
tolerance and β-oxidation, since AJS1669 has the potential 
for normalizing blood glucose levels through glycogen 
metabolism, similar to exercise, and ob/ob mice do not have 
exercise capacity. We were thus able to exclude the potential 
effects of exercise and increased skeletal muscle mass in our 
experimental design. Repeated administration of 10 mg/kg of 
AJS1669 over 4 weeks effectively reduced blood glucose level 
and improved glucose tolerance without excessive body weight 
gain. Excessive glycogen accumulation in skeletal muscle was 
not observed, as reflected by in vitro testing. Moreover, fat 
mass was decreased, and we observed upregulation of genes 
related to mitochondrial biogenesis in the skeletal muscle. 
Our results suggest that AJS1669 has potential as a new 
insulin sensitizer, as it reduces fat mass with upregulation of 
β-oxidation through acceleration of glycogen turnover. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Chemicals and materials. Sodium 2-[[5-[[4-(4,5-difluoro-2-meth-
ylsulfanyl-phenyl)phenoxy]methyl]furan-2-carbonyl]-(2-furyl-
methyl)amino] acetate (AJS1669) (Fig. 1A) was synthesized by 
Ajinomoto Pharmaceuticals Co., Ltd. (Kanagawa, Japan). Product 
purity was over 99%, as determined using a Waters BEH C18 
column, 1.7 µM, 2.1x50 mm (Waters, Milford, MA, USA) and a 
Waters Acquity UPLC 
® (ultra-performance liquid chromatog-
raphy) system, with a mobile phase consisting of acetonitrile:H 2 O 
including 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid each. The acetonitrile fraction 
was increased in a linear fashion from 5 to 95% over 2 min and 
kept at 95% over the next 0.5 min, after which the column was 
equilibrated to 5% for 1.5 min. 
Pioglitazone was purchased from Tokyo Chemical 
Industry Co., Ltd. (Tokyo, Japan). Glycogen phosphorylase 
inhibitor (GPI) was purchased from Millipore (Bedford, MA, 
USA). </p>

<p>Animals. Male C57BL/6J and ob/ob mice (both 6-weeks of age) 
were purchased from Charles River Laboratories (Kanagawa, 
Japan). The mice were fed standard laboratory chow (CRF-1; 
Charles River, Tokyo, Japan) and tap water ad libitum for the 
duration of the experiments. All animals were subjected to a 
reverse 12-h light/dark cycle. All procedures involving the care 
and use of animals were approved by the Institutional Animal 
Care and Use Committee of the Pharmaceutical Research 
Laboratories of Ajinomoto Pharmaceuticals Co., Ltd. prior to 
the start of experimentation. </p>

<p>In vitro hGYS1 assay. 293T cells were obtained from 
American Type Culture Collection (Manassas, VA, USA). 
hGYS1 gene cDNA was derived from the muscle cDNA in 
human MTC Panel I (Takara Βio, Shiga, Japan). The pcDNA 
3.1(+) expression vector (Life Technologies Japan, Kanagawa, 
Japan) containing hGYS1 was transiently transfected into 
293T cells. All transfected cells were cultured for 2 days, then 
washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and dissolved 
in lysis buffer consisting of 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 10 mM 
EDTA, 2 mM EGTA, 100 mM NaF, 1 mM PMSF, 1 mM DTT, 
and 1X Complete Protease Inhibitor Cocktail Tablet (Roche 
Diagnostics K.K., Tokyo, Japan). The mixture was homog-
enized and centrifuged at 16,000 x g at 4˚C for 15 min. The 
precipitated fraction was then reconstituted in lysis buffer and 
used as a source of the GS enzyme for evaluation after enzyme 
expression levels were verified by immunoblotting. 
The GS (hGYS1) assay was performed as described previ-
ously (20). In short, a solution containing AJS1669 at various 
concentrations with or without 10 mM G6P was added to a 
polystyrene 96-well half-area plate (12 µl/well). Next, 18 µl 
of a substrate solution containing 21.6 mM UDP-glucose, 
21.6 mM phosphoenolpyruvic acid and 4.05 mM NADH was 
added to each well. An enzyme solution containing GS lysates 
(0.17 mg/ml) and 1.5 µl of a pyruvate kinase/lactate dehydro-
genase solution was added (18 µl/well) to prepare a reaction 
solution. All reagents in the hGYS assay were purchased 
from Sigma-Aldrich Japan (Tokyo, Japan). After the reaction 
solution was incubated at 37˚C for 25 min, the absorbance 
at 340 nm was measured using Benchmark Plus (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories, Tokyo, Japan). 
Test compound activity was calculated according to the 
change in absorbance at 340 nm (ΔA340). The ΔA340 of the 
reaction solutions containing AJS1669 at a final concentration 
of 100 µM (without any G6P present) or 1 µM (with 2.5 mM 
G6P) was taken as a normalization value (100%) to calculate 
the relative activity (%) at various concentrations. The concen-
tration of the compound that elicited a 50% increase in relative 
activity (EC 50 ) was calculated using <rs id="software-0" type="software">XLfit</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IDBS</rs>, Tokyo, 
Japan). </p>

<p>Glucose incorporation into glycogen assay in human muscle 
cells. Human muscle cells were used after differentiation of 
SkGM-2 cells (Lonza, Basel, Switzerland). The assay evalu-
ating glucose incorporation into glycogen was performed using 
previously published methods (21) with slight modification. 
Briefly, after cells were plated onto a collagen-coated 96-well 
plate with SkGM-2 containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) 
for one day, the cells were subsequently differentiated using 
serum-reduced SkGM-2 containing 2% FBS for 3 days. The </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 39: 841-850, 2017 </p>



<p>cells were then starved for 4 h with glucose-free Dulbecco's 
modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) (Life Technologies Japan) 
containing 0.1% bovine serum albumin (BSA). They were then 
incubated for 3 h with DMEM containing 0.1% BSA, 1 g/l 
glucose, and 0.19 µ/l [ 
14 C] glucose (Perkin-Elmer Japan, Tokyo, 
Japan). After washing with ice-cold PBS, cell homogenates 
were dissolved using 1 N NaOH for 10 min at 60˚C and trans-
ferred to 96-well MultiScreen HTS plates (Merck Millipore, 
Billerica, MA, USA). Multiscreen plates were washed 
twice with ice-cold 66% (v/v) ethanol and allowed to dry 
completely. Incorporation of [ 
14 C] UDP-glucose into glycogen 
was measured using a scintillation counter. The decay rate 
(counts/min, cpm) measured in the wells containing AJS1669 
at the final concentration of 100 µM was taken as 100% in the 
calculations of relative activity (%) after subtracting the cpm 
of the background wells, which contained dimethyl sulfoxide 
(DMSO) only. </p>

<p>Assay of GS activity in mouse tissue lysates. Lysates of 
muscle and liver tissues obtained from mice fasted for 16 h 
were homogenized by Microson XL2000 (Qsonica, Newtown, 
CT, USA) in ice-cold buffer containing 50 mM KF (pH 7.0), 
10 mM EDTA (pH 7.0), and 10% glycerol. After centrifuga-
tion (16,000 x g for 10 min), the supernatant was collected 
and used as the enzyme solution. The enzyme was incubated 
3 times with each studied concentration of test compounds 
for 30 min before the GS assay was performed. GS assay was 
performed using previously described methods (22). Briefly, a 
30 µl mixture of enzyme and compounds was added to 60 µl 
of an assay mixture containing 0.5 µCi/ml [ 
14 C] UDP-glucose 
(Perkin-Elmer Japan, Kanagawa, Japan). After incubation for 
20 min at 30˚C, 75 µl of aliquots was immediately spotted onto 
a filter paper. The filter paper, which completely absorbed the 
sample, was placed into a vial, washed twice with 10 ml of 
66% (v/v) ethanol, and completely dried. Incorporation of [ 
14 C] 
UDP-glucose into glycogen was measured using a scintillation 
counter. The decay rate was measured as previously described. </p>

<p>Repeated administration study. Male ob/ob mice (8-weeks 
of age) were divided into 4 groups (n=6-8). Group allocation 
was specifically designed so that no significant differences 
in hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) level, body weight, and blood 
glucose level was observed across groups. Mice were orally 
administered vehicle alone (0.5% methylcellulose), with 
AJS1669 (3 or 10 mg/kg), or with pioglitazone (10 mg/kg) 
twice daily (at 9:00 a.m. and 4:00 p.m.) for 4 weeks. Body 
weight and food intake were monitored every 2 or 3 days. 
Blood samples were taken from unrestrained mice by cutting 
off the tip of the tail. Blood glucose levels were measured every 
2 weeks using a Lifecheck sensor (Gunze, Osaka, Japan), and 
blood HbA1c levels was measured on day 28 (Tosoh, Tokyo, 
Japan). Body composition was analyzed on day 26 using 
EchoMRI (EchoMRI LLC, Houston, TX, USA). EchoMRI 
provides a precise and accurate method for determining the 
fat and lean tissue content of mice without requiring anes-
thesia (23). Change in fat mass and lean mass were analyzed 
by comparing the fat mass before administration and after 
4 weeks of treatment. After 4 weeks of treatment, oral glucose 
tolerance testing (OGTT) was performed following an over-
night fast. After OGTT was performed, the mice were fed for </p>

<p>another 3 days and then sacrificed. Post-mortem blood and 
tissue samples were collected for further analysis. </p>

<p>Oral glucose tolerance test. After 4 weeks of compound 
administration, the mice were fasted overnight. After body 
weight measurement to determine required administration 
volumes, glucose (Otsuka, Tokushima, Japan) was orally 
administered at 1 g/kg. Blood was collected from the tail vein 
1 min prior to and 30, 60 and 120 min after the administration 
of glucose, and blood glucose levels were determined using a 
Lifecheck sensor as described above. </p>

<p>Determination of glycogen content and pancreatic insulin. 
Frozen tissue samples were weighed and hydrolyzed in 
30% (wt/vol) KOH solution in a boiling water bath for 30 min, 
and were agitated vigorously once at 15 min. After cooling 
on ice, 25 µl of 6% Na 2 SO 4 and 750 µl of 100% ethanol 
were added. After overnight storage at -80˚C, samples were 
centrifuged at 10,000 x g for 15 min. The glycogen pellet was 
dried and dissolved in 200 µl of water in a water bath at 55˚C, 
following which 800 µl of water was added for a total volume 
of 1 ml. Aliquots (25 µl) of resulting glycogen solution were 
used for subsequent measurements. Glycogen content was 
determined using a glycogen assay kit (BioVision, Milpitas, 
CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Pancreatic tissue was weighed, homogenized, and extracted 
with 2 ml of 1.5% HCl-75% ethanol buffer overnight with 
shaking in the cold room. For measurements, samples were 
centrifuged at 3,000 x g for 10 min. The insulin level in the 
supernatant was measured using an insulin kit (Morinaga 
Institute of Biological Science, Tokyo, Japan) after a 1:3,000 
dilution. </p>

<p>RNA extraction, real-time PCR, and measurement of mito-
chondrial DNA content. Total RNA was extracted using an 
RNeasy Plus Mini kit (Qiagen, Tokyo, Japan) according to 
the manufacturer's instructions. The concentration and purity 
of total RNA samples were measured using a NanoDrop 
ND-1000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, Kanagawa, 
Japan). cDNA generated via a high capacity cDNA synthesis 
kit (Life Technologies Japan) was analyzed by quantitative 
PCR using Power SYBR Premix (Life Technologies Japan). 
Primer sequences are provided in Table I. Expression data 
were normalized to the geometric mean of β-actin levels to 
control for variability in expression, and were analyzed using 
the 2 
-ΔΔCT method. Mitochondrial DNA content was quantified 
using primers for both NADH dehydrogenase subunit 1 (ND1, 
an index of mitochondrial DNA) and lipoprotein lipase (LPL, 
index of genomic DNA). ND1 levels were normalized to LPL 
DNA content. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. In this study, data are expressed 
as the mean ± SE. Differences among multiple groups 
(vehicle-vs. AJS1669-treated) and between two groups 
(vehicle-vs. pioglitazone-treated) were evaluated using 
step-down Dunnett's multiple comparison test and 
Student's t-test, respectively, with p&lt;0.05 considered to represent 
statistically significant differences. All statistical analyses were 
performed using the EXSUS 8 software package (CAC Exicare 
Corp., Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>NAKANO et al: AJS1669 IMPROVES GLUCOSE METABOLISM IN MICE </p>



<p>Results </p>

<p>AJS1669, a novel GS activator. Since GYS1 is a key enzyme 
involved in glycogen metabolism in skeletal muscle, we 
screened compounds on the basis of their ability to acti-
vate hGYS1 in vitro and identified AJS1669 as a novel 
allosteric activator of hGYS1. AJS1669 activated hGYS1 in 
a concentration-dependent manner when incubated alone 
(EC 50 =5.2 µM) (Fig. 1B). A lower concentration of AJS1669 
was required to elicit an effect on hGYS1 activity when 
compared to the concentration-response relationship without 
G6P (EC 50 = 0.037 µM) (Fig. 1C). AJS1669 did not affect 
hGYS2 in a concentration-dependent manner (data not shown). 
Prior to evaluating its action in vivo, we assessed whether 
AJS1669 has the ability to activate each of the subtypes of 
peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR) using a 
reporter assay system. Each PPAR ligand-binding domain 
was overexpressed in CV-1 kidney fibroblast cells derived 
from African green monkey as a protein fused to the yeast 
GAL4 DNA-binding domain, and the luciferase activity was 
measured. AJS1669 did not exhibit any ability to activate 
PPARα, γ and δ subtypes (data not shown). </p>

<p>GS activation in mouse tissue lysates and glycogen incor-
poration in human muscle cells induced by AJS1669. To 
assess the ability of AJS1669 to activate GS in each organ, 
mouse skeletal muscle and liver tissue were homogenized and 
[ 
14 C] UDP-glucose was used to evaluate GS activity through </p>

<p>measurement of 
14 C-labeled glycogen. Intriguingly, AJS1669 
exhibited a concentration-dependent activation of GS in the 
skeletal muscle lysates (Fig. 2A), which was not observed in 
the liver lysates (Fig. 2B). 
Next, to confirm the stimulation of glycogen production by 
AJS1669 in skeletal muscle tissue, human skeletal muscle cells 
were incubated with [ 
14 C] glucose and AJS1669, and the incor-
poration of [ 
14 C] glucose into cellular glycogen was measured. 
Incubation with AJS1669 alone increased the [ 
14 C] glycogen 
level in a concentration-dependent manner (Fig. 2C). AJS1669 
showed increased stimulation of glycogen production in the 
presence of glycogen phosphorylase inhibitor (GPI) than in the 
absence of GPI, whereas GPI alone did not increase the [ 
14 C] 
glycogen level (Fig. 2C). These results indicate that the ability 
of AJS1669 to increase glycogen level is not a consequence of 
glycogenolysis inhibition, but rather reflects an activation of 
glycogen synthesis, with AJS1669 upregulating the turnover 
of glycogen metabolism in the muscle cells by activating both 
glycogen synthesis and glycogenolysis (Fig. 2C). </p>

<p>Effects of chronic 4-week administration of AJS1669 in 
normal mice and diabetic ob/ob mice. To confirm the 
ability of AJS1669 to act as a GYS1 activator with long-term 
administration, ob/ob mice were administered 3 or 10 mg/kg 
of AJS1669 orally twice daily. As a positive control, mice 
were administered pioglitazone, a PPARγ agonist known to 
significantly reduce blood glucose levels and improve insulin 
resistance. The group receiving 10 mg/kg AJS1669 exhibited a </p>

<p>Table I. List of primers used for real-time PCR. </p>

<p>Forward 5'→3' 
Reverse 5'→3' </p>

<p>Gys1 
TCAGAGCAAAGCACGAATCCAG 
CATAGCGGCCAGCGATAAAGA 
Ucp3 
CTGAAGATGGTGGCTCAGGA 
CCGCAGTACCTGGACTTTCATTA 
Tfam 
CCTTCGATTTTCCACAGAACA 
GCTCACAGCTTCTTTGTATGCTT 
Ppargc1α 
GCGCCGTGTGATTTACGTTG 
CGGTAGGTGATGAAACCATAGCTG 
Cpt1b 
TATCCCAATCATCTGGGTGCTG 
GCGGATGTGGTTCCCAAAG 
Acadl 
CCAAGAAGAAGTGATTCCTCACCAC 
ACCAATGCCGCCATGTTTCT 
Acadm 
CAACACTCGAAAGCGGCTCA 
ACTTGCGGGCAGTTGCTTG 
mt-Nd1 
CCCATTCGCGTTATCTT 
AAGTTGATCGTAACGGAAGC 
Lpl 
GGATGGACGGTAAGAGTGATTC 
ATCCAAGGGTAGCAGACAGGT 
Gys2 
ACTGCTTGGGCGTTATCTCTGTG 
ATGCCCGCTCCATGCAGTA 
Acox1 
CTGTGGCATTGGCATCGTG 
GCAAATCTGATGGCTTTGACTTGA 
Cd36 
GATGGCCTTACTTGGGATTGGA 
GGCTTTACCAAAGATGTAGCCAGTG 
Fabp1 
AAGTACCAATTGCAGAGCCAGGA 
GGTGAACTCATTGCGGACCA 
Cpt1a 
TGTTCAGCTCAGACAGTGGTTTCA 
AGGATCCACCAGGATGCCATA 
Ucp2 
CAGTACCACAGCGCAGGTCA 
TCACTACGTTCCAGGATCCCAAG 
Pck1 
GGTGTCATCCGCAAGCTGAA 
CTGCTCTTGGGTGATGATGACTG 
G6pase 
GTGCAGCTGAACGTCTGTCTGTC 
TCCGGAGGCTGGCATTGTA </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>CATCCGTAAAGACCTCTATGCCAAC 
ATGGAGCCACCGATCCACA </p>

<p>These primers were used to analyze β-oxidation and lipid metabolism, mitochondrial DNA content in skeletal muscle, lipid metabolism 
and glucose metabolism in liver by real-time PCR. Gys1, glycogen synthase 1; Ucp3, uncoupling proteins 3; Tfam, transcription factor A, 
mitochondrial; Ppargc1α, peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor γ, coactivator 1α; Cpt1b, carnitine palmitoyltransferase 1B; Acadl, 
Acyl-CoA dehydrogenase, long chain; Acadm, Acyl-CoA dehydrogenase, medium chain; mt-Nd1, NADH dehydrogenase 1, mitochondrial; 
Lpl, lipoprotein lipase; Gys2, glycogen synthase 2; Acox1, acyl-coenzyme A oxidase 1, palmitoyl; Fabp1, fatty acid binding protein 1; Cpt1a, 
carnitine palmitoyltransferase 1A; Ucp2, uncoupling protein 2; Pck1, phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase 1; G6pase, glucose-6-phosphatase. </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 39: 841-850, 2017 </p>



<p>significant decrease in blood glucose level at day 28 (Fig. 3A). 
Additionally, a reduction in glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) 
was observed at day 28 (Fig. 3B). Weight gain over the 4 week 
administration period was slightly lower in AJS1669-treated 
animals compared to the vehicle-treated group (Fig. 3C). 
No major differences in food consumption amount was 
observed between the treatment groups (Fig. 3D). Next, we 
measured the plasma level of AJS1669 in samples collected 
2 h after the final administration. Plasma levels were shown to 
increase linearly in a concentration-dependent manner, with 
a concentration of 0.92±0.18 µM following administration of 
the 10 mg/kg dose (Fig. 3E). The concentration of AJS1669 
in skeletal muscle at the same time was determined to be 
0.31 µM (data not shown). </p>

<p>Effect of repeated administration of AJS1669 on OGTT in 
ob/ob mice. During the 4th week of AJS1669 administration, </p>

<p>mice were administered 1 g/kg of D-glucose orally following 
a 16-h fast. Blood was collected 0, 30, 60 and 120 min later to 
measure glucose level. Repeated administration of 3 or 10 mg/kg 
AJS1669 induced significant dose-dependent decreases in 
blood glucose level at 30 min after administration (Fig. 4A). As 
a result, AJS1669 was shown to significantly improve glucose 
tolerance in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. 4B). Fasting blood 
glucose and insulin level were measured at the same time, and 
the calculated homeostatic model for the assessment of insulin 
resistance (HOMA-IR) decreased at higher doses relative to 
the vehicle-treated group, although there was no significant 
difference (Fig. 4C). </p>

<p>Chronic effects of AJS1669 on body composition and blood 
parameters in diabetic ob/ob mice. Glycogen levels in both 
the skeletal muscle and liver did not significantly increase after 
4 weeks of repeated administration of AJS1669 or pioglitazone, </p>

<p>Figure 2. Glycogen synthase activity was determined by incorporation of 2-deoxy-D-glucose into glycogen in mouse tissue lysates and in human muscle 
cells. (A) Activation of glycogen synthase (GS) in mouse muscle tissue lysates by AJS1669. (B) Activation of GS in mouse liver tissue lysates by AJS1669. 
(C) Effect of AJS1669 on glycogen accumulation in human muscle cells. Open circles, AJS1669; closed circles, AJS1669 + 10 µM glycogen phosphorylase 
inhibitor (GPI); closed squares, 10 µM GPI. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Identification of a novel glycogen synthase activator AJS1669 and its effect on glycogen synthase activity. (A) Chemical structure of AJS1669. 
(B) Effect of AJS1669 (0.3-100 µM) on human glycogen synthase 1 (hGYS1) activity. (C) Effect of AJS1669 (0.03-1 µM) on hGYS1 activity in the presence 
of 2.5 mM glucose-6-phosphate (G6P). </p>

<p>NAKANO et al: AJS1669 IMPROVES GLUCOSE METABOLISM IN MICE </p>



<p>as compared to the levels measured in the vehicle-treated 
animals (Fig. 5A and B). Insulin content in the pancreas 
showed a tendency to increase at higher doses (Fig. 5C). 
Treatment-induced changes in body composition were assessed 
using EchoMRI, with measurements performed on the day 
before the start of administration and following 4 weeks of 
administration. A significant decrease in Δfat mass was 
observed following administration of 10 mg/kg of AJS1669. 
Conversely, animals treated with pioglitazone exhibited a </p>

<p>significant elevation in Δfat mass (Fig. 5D). No difference in 
Δlean mass was observed between the groups (Fig. 5E). </p>

<p>Effect of repeated administration of AJS1669 on mitochondrial 
biogenesis in skeletal muscle and hepatic fatty acid oxidation 
in ob/ob mice. In the skeletal muscle, treatment with AJS1669 
elicited no change in Gys1 mRNA levels. A trend towards a 
decrease was observed in uncoupling protein 3 (Ucp3) mRNA 
levels. However, a significant increase was observed in mRNA </p>

<p>Figure 3. Evaluation of blood glucose and pancreatic parameters after chronic administration of AJS1669 in ob/ob mice. Vehicle, AJS1669, and piogli-
tazone (Pio) were orally administered twice daily for 4 weeks in wild-type and ob/ob mice (n=6-8). (A) Plasma glucose levels on day 17 and 28. (B) Blood 
glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) levels on day 28. (C) Body weight and (D) cumulative food intake were monitored during treatment. (E) Plasma concentration 
of AJS1669 after 4 weeks of administration. Data are expressed as the mean ± SEM. 
* p&lt;0.05 vs. vehicle-treated group, compared using Dunnett's multiple 
comparison test. 
## p&lt;0.01 and 
### p&lt;0.001 vs. vehicle-treated group, compared using Student's t-test. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Oral glucose tolerance test after chronic administration of AJS1669, pioglitazone and vehicle in ob/ob mice. (A) Changes in blood glucose level in 
oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) performed in mice fasted overnight after the final administration of AJS1669. (B) AUC 0-120min of blood glucose levels and 
(C) homeostatic model for assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) calculated using blood samples collected before starting OGTT. Data are expressed 
as the mean ± SEM (n=6-8). 
* p&lt;0.05 and 
** p&lt;0.01 vs. vehicle-treated group compared using Dunnett's multiple comparison test; 
# p&lt;0.05 and 
## p&lt;0.01 
vs. vehicle-treated group, compared using Student's t-test. </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 39: 841-850, 2017 </p>



<p>encoding mitochondrial transcription factor A (Tfam), which 
is involved in the replication and translation of mitochondrial 
DNA (Fig. 6A). Subsequent evaluation of the mRNA level of 
genes involved in fatty acid oxidation detected a trend towards 
elevated levels of carnitine palmitoyltransferase 1B (Cpt1b), 
long chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase (Acadl), and medium 
chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase (Acadm) following AJS1669 
treatment. Additionally, AJS1669 administration was observed 
to increase mitochondrial DNA content in skeletal muscle 
tissue (Fig. 6B). 
The gene expression in the liver was also evaluated. 
Significant increases in the mRNA levels of genes involved 
in fatty acid oxidation, including Cd36, Fabp1 (which 
encodes fatty acid binding protein 1), Cpt1a and Ucp2, were 
observed (Fig. 6C). No change, however, was observed in 
the transcription of Pck1 and G6pase, which are involved in 
hepatic gluconeogenesis. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, we identified AJS1669 as a novel, 
small-molecule GS activator. In vitro testing showed that this 
compound activated hGYS1 in a concentration-dependent 
manner when administered alone, whereas its action was 
further potentiated in the presence of 2.5 mM of G6P. AJS1669 
also exhibited the ability to activate skeletal muscle GS to 
the same extent as 3 mM G6P in assessment using lysates of 
mouse skeletal muscle. However, the ability of AJS1669 to 
activate liver GS was not stronger than its effect on skeletal 
muscle. AJS1669 acted potently in skeletal muscle and exhib-
ited greater activation with a lower dose in the presence of a 
high G6P concentration. 
To assess the effects at the phenotypic level, skeletal 
muscle cells were incubated with AJS1669. AJS1669 increased 
the glycogen level in a concentration-dependent manner. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Determination of glycogen amount and body composition by EchoMRI measurement after chronic administration of AJS1669. (A) Muscle glycogen 
concentration. (B) Liver glycogen level. (C) Pancreatic insulin level. (D) Δfat mass calculated using EchoMRI. (E) Δlean mass calculated using EchoMRI. 
Data are expressed as the mean ± SEM (n=6-8). 
* p&lt;0.05 and 
** p&lt;0.01 vs. vehicle-treated group, compared using Dunnett's multiple comparison test; 
# p&lt;0.05 
and 
## p&lt;0.01 vs. vehicle-treated group, compared using Student's t-test. V, vehicle; Pio, pioglitazone. </p>

<p>Table II. Effect of AJS1669 on liver weight and hepatic functional parameters in ob/ob mice. </p>

<p>Treatment 
Liver weight (g) 
Plasma ALT (IU/l) 
Plasma AST (IU/l) </p>

<p>Vehicle 
3.89±0.08 
683.29±134.91 
977.57±206.36 
AJS1669 (10 mg/kg) 
3.72±0.71 
471.38±65.39 
544.25±88.32 
Pioglitazone (10 mg/kg) 
4.33±0.84 
621.00±116.99 
978.00±268.51 </p>

<p>ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase. </p>

<p>NAKANO et al: AJS1669 IMPROVES GLUCOSE METABOLISM IN MICE </p>



<p>Intriguingly, incubation with AJS1669 and GPI increased 
glycogen levels to a greater extent than did AJS1669 admin-
istered alone. In contrast, no increase was observed following 
incubation with a GPI alone. 
These observations suggest that in addition to promoting 
glycogen synthesis, AJS1669 caused some glycogen degrada-
tion, apparently enhancing the glycogen metabolism turnover. 
AJS1669 was developed as a hypoglycemic agent for trans-
forming blood glucose into glycogen in both skeletal muscle 
and liver. However, if AJS1669 can ameliorate insulin resis-
tance as a PPAR agonist, then it could be the first in a new 
class of insulin sensitizers. 
Reportedly, PPARγ and PPARδ agonists do not directly 
activate glycogen synthesis, but rather act to enhance glycogen 
formation by stimulation of insulin receptors (24,25). We 
therefore assessed the effect of AJS1669 on the activity of 
each PPAR subtype. AJS1669 did not elicit any increase in 
PPARα, γ or δ activity at a concentration of 100 µM (data not 
shown), which is higher than the physiological level resulting 
from administration of 10 mg/kg AJS1669 (Fig. 3E). 
To evaluate the pharmacological effect of AJS1669, we 
measured the concentration of AJS1669 in both the muscle 
and liver of ob/ob mice. The concentration in the muscle was 
0.31 µM, which was higher than the EC 50 of 0.037 µM with 
G6P (Fig. 1C). Based on the potential of AJS1669 for improving 
glycogen metabolism determined through in vitro tests, we 
selected ob/ob mice, which are hyperinsulinemic, bulimic, and 
do not actively exercise. Diabetic-induced mice (DIO) were 
not used because they are easily affected by food consumption 
and exercise capacity. Additionally, db/db mice were not used </p>

<p>because they may experience body weight loss as a result of 
hyperglycemia. 
Since the AJS1669 concentration of 3 mg/kg observed in 
the muscle in vivo was sufficient to activate GYS1 in vitro, and 
following the 3Rs policy, we decided to use 10 mg/kg as the 
maximum dose for the in vivo experiments. The concentration 
of AJS1669 was much higher in the liver than that noted in 
muscle. As previously reported, the furanyl group of AJS1669 
has high stability with respect to liver metabolism as it is a 
5-membered ring (26). The ability of AJS1669 to reduce blood 
glucose levels, decrease HbA1c levels, and improve glucose 
tolerance was observed following 4 weeks of repeated admin-
istration (Fig. 4). Interestingly, repeated administration of 
AJS1669 did not elicit a major change in food consumption. 
Additionally, 4 weeks of repeated administration of AJS1669 
did not elevate the blood lactic acid level (data not shown). 
No abnormalities were observed in the plasma alanine amino-
transferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) level, 
which reflect the liver safety profile (Table II). Similarly, 
C57BL/6 mice treated for 4 weeks with 30 mg/kg AJS1669 
exhibited no changes in body weight, food intake, blood 
glucose levels, ALT levels, or AST levels (data not shown). 
AJS1669 therefore does not appear to reduce fat mass by any 
toxic mechanism. 
Intriguingly, although muscle glycogen levels in all 
animals in the group treated with 10 mg/kg AJS1669 was 
increased in comparison with the vehicle-treated group 
levels, the change was not significant. The same results were 
observed for pioglitazone-treated animals. Because both 
AJS1669 and pioglitazone improved glucose tolerance (Fig. 4), </p>

<p>Figure 6. Metabolic gene expression determined by qPCR assay after chronic administration of AJS1669 or vehicle in muscle and liver tissue. (A) Gene expres-
sion in mixed gastrocnemius muscle (GC). (B) Mitochondrial DNA content, as assessed by mitochondrial DNA copy number. (C) Gene expression in hepatic 
tissue. Data are expressed as the mean ± SEM (n=7-8). 
* p&lt;0.05 vs. vehicle-treated (Veh) group by Student's t-test. </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 39: 841-850, 2017 </p>



<p>glycogen levels could be increased by administration of these 
compounds. In this study, utilizing ad libitum feeding in 
ob/ob mice, a significant increase in muscle glycogen may not 
have been detected (Fig. 5). However, AJS1669 increased the 
glycogen level in muscle cells, and this level was additively 
increased under treatment with both AJS1669 and GPI (Fig. 2). 
Therefore, AJS1669 increased not only glycogen accumula-
tion but also glycogen degradation, and this machinery could 
improve glycogen metabolism. In exercise, both glycogen 
accumulation and glycogen degradation are involved in energy 
homeostasis and regulation of insulin sensitivity (27). Since 
AJS1669 improves the energy capacity of skeletal muscles, it 
was necessary for us to choose diabetic animals for evaluating 
this compound. Evaluation of these mice showed that piogli-
tazone treatment significantly increased the whole body fat 
mass (a harmful side effect), whereas AJS1669 was observed 
to markedly decrease the fat mass as we hypothesized (Fig. 5). 
AJS1669 thus appears to directly induce both glycogen 
synthesis and glycogen turnover, and therefore may be the first 
in a new class of insulin sensitizers. 
To examine the possibility that the effect of AJS1669 on 
muscle glycogen causes a metabolic response in muscle, 
β-oxidation-related genes were also evaluated (28). Increases 
in the expression of β-oxidation-related genes involved in lipid 
metabolism in the skeletal muscle and liver, as well as in the 
expression of genes involved in mitochondrial biogenesis, were 
observed following 4 weeks of repeated administration of 
AJS1669. Although AJS1669 treatment did not alter the expres-
sion of Gys1 in skeletal muscle tissue, it significantly increased 
the expression of Tfam, a gene involved in the stability and 
transport of mitochondrial gene transcripts. Additionally, a 
trend towards an increase in the expression of genes involved 
in β-oxidation, such as Cpt1b and Acadm, was observed 
following 4 weeks of repeated administration. Regulation 
of genes involved in mitochondrial biogenesis and fatty acid 
oxidation by AJS1669 is likely to be associated with a decrease 
in fat mass. In the liver, no significant modulation of genes 
controlling gluconeogenesis was observed. As evidenced by 
the lack of effect on the liver observed through in vitro experi-
ments, AJS1669 may not alter glucose metabolism by directly 
affecting the liver as excessive liver glycogen accumulation 
would inhibit the fat mass decrease (29) or reduce body fat mass 
by attenuating food intake in high-fat-diet model mice (30). In 
the present study, AJS1669 did not induce accumulation of liver 
glycogen or decrease fat mass. Following the upregulation of 
β-oxidation-related genes involved in lipid metabolism in the 
skeletal muscle, lipid flow may be altered across the entire 
body, thus affecting oxidation in the liver. 
Although AJS1669 improved glucose homeostasis while 
decreasing the fat mass in ob/ob mice, this effect was not 
stronger than the action of pioglitazone. No significant 
glucose-lowering action was observed at day 17 following 
administration, and a longer administration period may be 
required to accurately demonstrate drug efficacy relative to 
pioglitazone. The physiological mechanism underlying this 
difference is currently not known, but a number of factors 
may be involved. AJS1669 could potentially activate GYS1 
at a concentration of &lt;1 µM in vitro (Figs. 1B and C and 2A). 
However, the plasma concentration of AJS1669 at 2 h after 
administration was below 1 µM (Fig. 3E). The dose of </p>

<p>AJS1669 used in our experiments (10 mg/kg) may thus not 
be the optimal dose to elicit the desired pharmacological 
actions. Moreover, 4 weeks of repeated administration may 
result in attainment of a homeostatic phase and thus may not 
be an appropriate term for evaluating the maximum pharma-
cological effect of this compound. Our aim was to determine 
the length of time over which administration of AJS1669 can 
maintain the initial change in glucose metabolism, and we 
found the duration to surpass 4 weeks. Since fat mass was 
reduced in AJS1669-treated animals, glucose tolerance was 
improved, and because the mRNA levels of a number of genes 
were significantly altered in both skeletal muscle and liver, 
long-term administration may elicit stronger pharmacological 
effects. Another factor affecting body composition may be the 
difference in glycogen metabolism between muscle and liver 
tissue. In mice, the basal amount of glycogen in the skeletal 
muscle at satiation is approximately one-tenth of that in the 
liver, and glycogen metabolism is thought to affect glucose 
metabolism more significantly in the liver than in the skeletal 
muscle (31). In humans, however, skeletal muscle accounts 
for ~40% of body composition (32) and plays a central role 
in glucose metabolism (33). In the present study in mouse 
tissue lysates, AJS1669 elicited a stronger effect in the skeletal 
muscle than in the liver (Fig. 2A and B), with intense effects 
not achieved in vivo (Fig. 3). We therefore postulate that the 
pharmacological effect of AJS1669 observed in mice should 
be far more pronounced in humans. 
In skeletal muscle tissue of patients suffering from type 2 
diabetes or obese patients, a decrease in mitochondrial oxidative 
capacity has been reported (34,35), along with lower expression 
of genes related to mitochondrial biogenesis (36,37). Increased 
physical activity and weight loss interventions in these patients 
were the main inducers of improved mitochondrial functional 
capacity, and these changes in the mitochondria were associated 
with improvement of insulin resistance (38,39). Considering 
the association between GS activity and mitochondrial func-
tion, a number of unanswered questions remain regarding the 
molecules that are directly involved. It is, however, conceivable 
that repeated administration of AJS1669 may alter glycogen 
metabolism, and may therefore mimic the effects of exercise 
and weight loss. 
In conclusion, previous studies suggest that beneficial 
alterations of glycogen metabolism, similar to the physiolog-
ical effects of physical exercise, may result from attenuation of 
GS activity in type 2 diabetes. In the present study, AJS1669 
enhanced glycogen metabolism and improved mitochondrial 
biogenesis, and consequently elicited a reduction in body fat 
mass and exhibited anti-diabetic activity. AJS1669 therefore 
exhibits potential for use as a new insulin resistance-improving 
drug with a mechanism of action distinct from that of piogli-
tazone. AJS1669 can be regarded as a promising candidate 
compound for the management of type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We would like to give special thanks to Atsushi Konishi 
and Yukio Iino (Ajinomoto Pharmaceuticals Co., Ltd.) for 
supervising us in this study. Advice given by Yuki Saitoh and 
Tomomi Yoshida (Ajinomoto Pharmaceuticals Co., Ltd.) has 
helped immensely with establishing our in vivo and in vitro </p>

<p>NAKANO et al: AJS1669 IMPROVES GLUCOSE METABOLISM IN MICE </p>



<p>experiments. Kayo Matsumoto and Manami Shuto (Ajinomoto 
Pharmaceuticals Co., Ltd.) who synthesized and analyzed 
other types of GS activators, except for AJS1669, provided 
us with important information. A special note of gratitude is 
owed to Eri Tabuchi (Ajinomoto Pharmaceuticals Co., Ltd.), 
who analyzed the 3D structure of human Gys1 protein using 
information of yeast Gys2 protein and gave us great advice. </p>



</text></tei>