<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5387758" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVES: Chronic hepatitis B (CHB) is caused by infection of hepatitis B virus (HBV) and liver cirrhosis (LC) is its most 
common complication. The accumulated evidence indicates a genetic context of HBV infection phenotypes. Here we determine a 
potential association of CHB/LC with the genetic variant of telomerase reverse transcriptase (TERT), a key player in aging including 
immune-senescence. 
METHODS: The study included 227 Chinese CHB patients and 315 sex/age-matched healthy controls. TERT rs2736098 and 
rs2736100 genotyping was performed using pre-designed TaqMan SNP genotyping assay kits. Leukocyte telomere length (LTL) 
was determined using quantitative PCR. 
RESULTS: The rs2736098_CT/CC genotypes were significantly associated with risk of CHB compared to the TT one (OR 2.265, 95% 
CI 1.202-4.269, P = 0.015). A similar association was also found in CHB patients with cirrhosis (CT/CC vs TT: OR 2.398, 95% CI 
1.168-4.922, P = 0.02). Further analyses showed that the rs2736098_TT genotype difference occurred between male controls and 
patients (P = 0.008) and male CT/CC-carriers exhibited highly increased risk of CHB compared to male controls (CT+CC vs TT, OR 
3.182, 95% CI 1.350-7.500, P = 0.01). There was no difference in the rs2736100 variants between controls and CHB patients. LTL 
was not different between cases and controls. 
CONCLUSIONS: The TERT rs2736098_TT genotype is associated with a lower CHB and LC risk in Chinese males, which may have 
implications in CHB pathogenesis and prevention. 
Close to 400 million individuals are chronically infected with 
hepatitis B virus (HBV) worldwide and approximately one 
million of them die from HBV-related liver diseases including 
chronic hepatitis B (CHB), liver cirrhosis (LC) and hepatocellular 
carcinoma (HCC) annually. 1 The accumulated evidence has 
indicated the host-genetic background of susceptibility to HBV 
infection and CHB. Indeed, early epidemiological studies 
strongly suggested a genetic context of infection phenotypes, 
while recent GWAS and genetic analyses further identified a 
panel of genetic variants associated with HBV infection and 
CHB susceptibility. Because the host immune system respon-
sive for both innate immune and adaptive immunity plays a key 
role in controlling HBV infection and outcomes, 2,3 its associa-
tion with genetic variants of immuno-modulatory factors has 
been extensively explored. So far, variations in genes encoding 
IL-6, IL-1, IL-10, PPARγ, HLAs, TNFα, IFNγ, TIM3, CTLA4 and 
others have been found to significantly influence HBV infection 
and CHB predisposition. 4-19 </p>

<p>Telomerase is a RNA-dependent DNA polymerase that 
elongates telomeric DNA. 20 Most normal human somatic cells 
lack telomerase activity due to the tight transcriptional repression 
of its rate-limiting, catalytic component telomerase reverse 
transcriptase (TERT) gene. 20-22 This, together with the end-
replication problem, leads to progressive telomere shortening 
with each round of cell division or with increased age, and when 
they become too short (dysfunctional) to protect chromosomes, 
the DNA damage response is activated, thereby triggering the 
permanent growth arrest of cells (replicative senescence). 20,22 By 
regulating telomere length and many other biological activities, 
telomerase or TERT plays critical parts in human health. 20 
Importantly, it has been shown that abnormal telomere length is 
associated with chronic liver diseases, and telomerase provides a 
protection against liver fibrosis. 23-26 In addition, shorter telomere 
in immune cells is associated with a lower activity against viral 
infection. 27 These findings suggest that TERTor telomerase may 
be involved in HBV infection-related CHB and LC. 
There are multiple single-nucleotide polymorphisms in the 
TERT gene, among which rs2736100 and rs2736098 are most </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Central Research Laboratory, The Second Hospital of Shandong University, Jinan, PR China; 2 Department of Medicine, Division of Hematology and Center for Molecular 
Medicine, Karolinska University Institutet and Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden; 3 Clinical Laboratory, The Second Hospital of Shandong University, Jinan, 
PR China and 4 School of Nursing, Shandong University, Jinan, PR China 
Correspondence: Feng Kong, MD, The Second Hospital of Shandong University, Jinan 250033, PR China or D Xu, MD, PhD, Center for Molecular Medicine, Karolinska 
University Institutet, Stockholm 17176, Sweden. 
E-mail: kongfeng@sdu.edu.cn or Dawei.Xu@ki.se </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Received 3 September 2016; accepted 30 January 2017 </p>

<p>Citation: Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology (2017) 8, e79; doi:10.1038/ctg.2017.9 </p>

<p>&amp; 2017 the American College of Gastroenterology 2155-384X/17 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ctg </p>

<p>studied. These variants have been shown to be associated 
with cancer, atherosclerosis, depression and other health 
problems. 28-40 Given the findings documented above, we 
sought to ask whether the rs2736100 and rs2736098 
genotypes modify susceptibility to CHB and its LC complica-
tion. Our results reveal a significant association between the 
TERT rs2736098_TT genotype and reduced risk of CHB and 
LC in Chinese males. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study populations. The case-control individuals include 
542 unrelated Chinese adults consisting of 227 CHB patients 
and 315 healthy controls. All 227 patients were active CHB 
and recruited from Infectious Diseases Inpatient, the Shan-
dong University Second Hospital, between January 2014 and 
October 2015. Three hundred and fifteen healthy adults who 
were age-and sex-matched to cases were recruited as 
controls, from Physical Examination Center of the Shandong 
University Second Hospital. The study was approved by the 
Ethics Review Committee of Shandong University Second 
Hospital and written informed consent was obtained from the 
participants. All experiments were performed in accordance 
with relevant guidelines and regulations. </p>

<p>DNA extraction and genotyping of the TERT rs2736100 
and rs2736098 variants. Genomic DNA was extracted 
from peripheral blood cells using QIAGEN DNA extraction 
kits. The TERT rs2736100 (AC) and rs2736098 (T/C) 
genotyping was carried out using pre-designed TaqMan 
SNP genotyping assay kits on an ABI PRISM 7900 HT 
Sequence Detection System (Applied Biosystems, Foster 
City, CA), as described. 30,39 Both positive and negative 
controls were included in all assays and the running condition 
was as followed: 95 °C for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles of 
92 °C for 15 s and 60 °C for 1 min. </p>

<p>Leukocyte telomere length assay. Genomic DNA was 
isolated from peripheral blood cells as above and leukocyte 
telomere length (LTL) was assessed using real-time PCR as 
previously described. 41,42 Briefly, 2 ng of DNA were used for 
each PCR reaction. The primer sequences for human 
telomere (Tel 1b and Tel 2b) and β-globin (HBG3 and 
HBG4) were: Tel1b: 5′-CGGTTTGTTTGGGTTTGGGT-TTGG 
GTTTGGGTTTGGGTT-3′; Tel2b: 5′-GGCTTGCCTTACCCT 
TACCCTTACCC-TTACCCTTACCCT-3′; HBG3: 5′-TGTGC 
TGGCCCATCACTTTG-3′, and HBG4: 5′-ACCAGCCA-CCA 
CTTTCTGATAGG-3′. T/HBG values were determined using 
the formula T/S = 2 -ΔCt , where ΔCt = average Ct telomere − 
average Ct β-globin . The T/S ratio was arbitrarily expressed 
as LTL. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses. Required sample size for association 
studies was calculated using <rs id="software-0" type="software">QUANTO</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 1.2</rs>, Uni-
versity of Southern California) and a power 40.80 is 
acceptable. The evaluation of distribution differences of 
selected variables and alleles of the TERT rs2736100 and 
rs2736098 between CHB patients and healthy controls were 
done using χ 2 test. Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium of the 
genotype distribution among the controls was tested by a 
goodness-of-fit χ 2 test. Unconditional univariate and multi-
variate logistic regression analyses were used to estimate 
ORs for risk of CHB or LC and their 95% CIs. The LTL 
difference between patients and healthy controls was 
assessed using the Mann-Whitney U-tests. All the tests 
were computed using <rs type="software">SigmaStat3.1 software</rs> (Systat Soft-
ware, Inc., Richmond, CA, USA). For comparison of 
rs2736098 and rs2736100 genotypes between healthy 
controls and CHB patients, P values were adjusted by 
Bonferroni correction and a statistical significance should be 
o0.025. P values of o0.05 were considered as statistically 
significant for all other comparisons. </p>

<p>Table 1 TERT rs2736098 and 2736100 genotyping in healthy adults and CHB patients </p>

<p>HA 
CHB 
Odds ratio (95% CI) 
P value a </p>

<p>N 
315 
227 </p>

<p>Sex 
M 
210 
153 
F 
105 
74 
M/F Ratio 
2.0 
2.0 </p>

<p>Age (years) 
44 ± 15 
43 ± 13 </p>

<p>Genotypes 
rs2736098 (N) 
304 (100%) 
219 (100%) 
TT 
41 (13.4) 
14 (6.4) 
1.0 (ref.) 
CT 
146 (47.7) 
111 (50.7) 
2.227 (1.157-4.286) 
0.022 
CC 
119 (38.9) 
94 (42.9) 
2.313 (1.191-4.495) 
0.018 
CT+CC 
265 
205 
2.265 (1.202-4.269) 
0.015 
rs2736100 (N) 
306 (100%) 
227 (100%) 
AA 
115 (37.3) 
94 (41.4) 
1.0 (ref.) 
CA 
139 (45.5) 
101 (44.5) 
0.889 (0.612 to 1.292) 
0.602 
CC 
52 (17.2) 
32 (14.1) 
0.753 (0.449-1.264) 
0.344 
CA+CC 
191 
133 
0.852 (0.600-1.210) 
0.421 </p>

<p>CHB, chronic hepatitis B; CI, confidence interval; HA, Healthy adults; ref., reference. 
a Po0.025 as statistically significant according to Bonferroni correction. </p>

<p>Association of TERT rs2736098 Genotype With Hepatitis B 
Cheng et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Demographic and/or clinical characteristics of study 
subjects. A total of 227 patients with CHB were genotyped 
for TERT rs2736100 and rs2736098 variants. A total of 165 
CHB patients had LC complication. Active CHB diagnosis was 
made according to abnormal levels of alanine aminotransfer-
ase and/or aspartate transaminase, higher amounts of HBV 
DNA quantification and positive HBSeAg. The presence of LC 
complication was diagnosed based on liver Ultrasound B and 
Computer Tomography examination. None of the patients 
developed HCC. Patient age and sex are summarized in 
Table 1. In total, 315 healthy adults used as controls were 
age-and sex-matched (Table 1), and all of them were negative 
for HBV surface antigen and had normal levels of alanine 
aminotransferase and aspartate transaminase. The power for 
the number of cases and controls in this study, as made using 
QUANTO, was 0.968 (40.80 acceptable). </p>

<p>The TERT rs2736100 variant and CHB risk. The TERT 
rs2736100 genotyping was successfully performed on DNA 
from 306 of 315 healthy adults and all 227 CHB patients, and 
the frequency was summarized in Table 1. The genotype 
distributions were 37.3, 45.5, and 17.2% for AA, AC, and CC, 
respectively, in healthy adults, while 41.4, 44.5, and 14.1% for 
AA, AC, and CC, respectively, in CHB patients (Table 1). 
There was no significant difference in the rs2736100 
genotype frequency between healthy controls and CHB 
patients, which indicates the lack of rs2736100 association 
with CHB susceptibility (Table 1). </p>

<p>The TERT rs2736098 variant and CHB risk. The TERT 
rs2736098 genotyping was performed on DNA from those 
same individuals, and the analysis was successfully in 304 of 
315 healthy adults and 219 of 227 CHB patients. As shown in 
Table 1, 41 of 304 controls had TT (13.4%), 146 CT (47.7%), 
and 119 CC genotype (38.9%), while there were 14 TT (6.4%), 
111 CT (50.7%), and 94 CC genotype (42.9%) among 219 
cases. The TT genotype was presented at a significantly 
higher frequency in the healthy controls compared to that in 
the CHB patients (P = 0.015). The CT and CC genotypes 
exhibited significantly increased risk of CHB (TT vs CT: OR, 
2.227, 95% CI, 1.157-4.286, P = 0.022; TT vs CC: OR, 2.313, 
95% CI, 1.195-4.495, P = 0.018). These results remained 
same even when P value o0.025 was considered as 
statistically significant after Bonferroni correction. 
We further compared the rs2736098 allele distribution in male 
and female individuals separately. The highly significant lower 
TT genotype was observed in male cases (4.8%) compared to 
that in male controls (13.7%; Table 2, TT vs CT: OR, 4.0, 95% 
CI, 1.646-9.720, P = 0.002; TT vs CC: OR, 2.574, 95% CI, 
1.063-6.237, P = 0.018). In contrast, a slight difference in the TT 
genotype was seen between female controls (12.7%) and 
patients (9.7%), which was not significant (controls vs cases in 
female, P40.05 in all the comparisons; Table 2). </p>

<p>The TERT rs2736098 variant and LC risk in CHB patients. 
Telomerase is known to protect liver from non-HBV-related 
cirrhosis, 25 and we are thus interested in the relationship of 
rs2736098 variants with CHB-mediated LC. Among 165 CHB 
patients with the LC complication, 155 of them were available 
for the rs2736098 genotyping. Compared with healthy 
controls, patients with LC exhibited a significantly lower </p>

<p>Table 2 Sex difference in the association of rs2736098 with CHB </p>

<p>HA 
CHB 
Odds ratio (95% CI) 
P value </p>

<p>Male 
Genotypes (N) 
204 (100%) 
147 (100%) 
TT 
28 (13.7) 
7 (4.8) 
1.0 (ref.) 
CT 
75 (36.8) 
75 (51.0) 
4.000 (1.646-9.720) 
0.002 
CC 
101 (49.5) 
65 (44.2) 
2.574 (1.063-6.237) 
0.051 
CT+CC 
176 
140 
3.182 (1.350-7.500) 
0.010 </p>

<p>Female 
Genotypes (N) 
102 (100%) 
72 (100%) 
TT 
13 (12.7) 
7 (9.7) 
1.0 (ref.) 
CT 
48 (47.1) 
36 (50.0) 
1.122 (0.401-3.137) 
0.968 
CC 
41 (40.2) 
29 (40.3) 
1.631 (0.587-4.532) 
0.490 
CT+CC 
89 
65 
1.356 (0.513-3.588) 
0.708 </p>

<p>CHB, chronic hepatitis B; CI, confidence interval; HA, healthy adults; ref., reference. </p>

<p>Table 3 The association of rs2736098 with cirrhosis in CHB </p>

<p>HA 
CHB with cirrhosis 
Odds ratio (95% CI) 
P value </p>

<p>Genotypes (N) 
304 (100%) 
165 (100%) 
TT 
41 (13.4) 
10 (6.1) 
1.0 (ref.) 
CT 
146 (47.7) 
88 (53.3) 
2.471 (1.179-5.180) 
0.020 
CC 
119 (38.9) 
67 (40.6) 
2.308 (1.087-4.908) 
0.041 
CT+CC 
265 
155 
2.398 (1.168-4.922) 
0.020 </p>

<p>CHB, chronic hepatitis B; CI, confidence interval; HA, healthy adults; ref., reference. </p>

<p>Association of TERT rs2736098 Genotype With Hepatitis B 
Cheng et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>

<p>frequency of the TT type (Tables 3, 13.4 vs 6.1%). Both CT 
and CC genotypes were significantly associated with a higher 
risk of LC development in CHB patients (Table 3, TT vs CT: 
OR, 2.471, 95% CI, 1.179-5.180, P = 0.02; TT vs CC: OR, 
2.309, 95% CI, 1.087-4.908, P = 0.041). </p>

<p>Leukocyte telomere length in CHB patients. Finally, we 
determined telomere length in leukocytes from healthy adults 
and CHB patients, and then compared its difference between 
two groups. LTL was 1.01 ± 0.47 and 0.94 ± 0. 60 for HA and 
CHB, respectively (Figure 1a), and there was no significant 
difference (P = 0.182). Because the rs2376098 variants were 
previously shown to be correlated with LTL, 32,43 we further 
made a comparison among individuals with different 
rs2736098 alleles. In healthy controls, TT-, CT-, and CC-
carriers had LTL 0.85 ± 0.36, 0.89 ± 0.36, and 1.00 ± 0.44, 
respectively (age-corrected values; Figure 1b). LTL in CHB 
patients was: TT: 0.83 ± 0.40, CT: 0.89 ± 0.49, and CC: 
1.03 ± 0.689 (Figure 1). There was a trend of LTL increase 
from TT-, CT-to CC-carriers in both healthy controls and CHB 
patients, however, none of these differences were significant 
(Figure 1b). LTL between controls and patients bearing the 
same genotype did not differ significantly either (Figure 1b). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The variants of the TERT gene have been observed to be 
associated with a significantly higher susceptibility to cancer and 
aging-related disorders, 29,33 however, their relationship with 
chronic virus infection is unclear. In the present study, we 
investigated the influence of the TERT genetic variants on risk of 
CHB and LC. Our results reveal significantly higher frequencies 
of the rs2736098_TT in healthy controls than in CHB patients, 
which suggest that the TERT rs2736098_TT genotype exerts a 
protective effect on susceptibility to CHB and LC. To our 
knowledge, this is the first report demonstrating an association 
between the rs2736098 variant and CHB or its complications. 
During HBV infection, complete HBV clearance occurs in 
more than 90% of infected adults, while 5-10% of them has viral 
persistence, thereby leading to CHB, and then further devel-
opment of cirrhosis or even HCC. 1 Cell-mediated immune 
response is believed to contribute to variable clinical outcomes 
of HBV infection. Telomerase or TERTand telomeres have long 
been recognized to play pivotal parts in regulating immunolo-
gical activity. 44,45 Activation of telomerase via induction of TERT 
expression occurs in activated lymphocytes for their expansion 
in response to infectious challenge. 44,45 Shorter LTL was 
associated with increased susceptibility to experimentally 
induced acute upper respiratory infection and clinical illness in 
adults. 27 Mechanistically, shorter telomeres limit proliferation 
potentials of immune cells and compromise immune response 
to pathogens, thereby lowering host resistance to infection. 44,45 
It is thus likely that TERT variants modify risk of CHB by 
influencing host immune function. 
However, the LTL comparison between healthy controls and 
CHB patients did not reveal a significant difference, which 
indicates that telomere homeostasis is not significantly impaired 
in CHB patients. In addition, the rs2736098 TT and CC 
genotype-carriers were previously shown to harbor shortest 
and longest LTL, respectively, while the CT variant was </p>

<p>correlated with medium levels of LTL. 32 Consistently, Atzmon 
et al. found a significant association between rs2736098 and 
LTL. 43 However, we did not find this scenario in both healthy 
controls and CHB patients, indicating that the association 
between rs2736098_TT allele and a lower CHB risk is unlikely 
attributable to telomere length regulation. However, the sample 
size in the present study is relatively small, which might 
be a potential reason behind the dissociation between the 
rs2736098 genotype and phenotype (LTL). On the other hand, 
telomere lengthening is the canonical function of telomerase or 
TERT, but recent studies have demonstrated its multiple 
properties independently of telomere homeostasis. 46-51 Ecto-
pic expression of TERT was shown to promote mobilization of 
stem cells and proliferation of many types of cells via 
upregulation of stem cell factors, growth factors or their receptor 
expression; 52-54 telomerase and TERT is capable of protecting 
cells from apoptosis mediated by various insults. 49,50,55,56 
Mechanistically, TERT can act as co-factors to stimulate gene 
transcription. 48 It is thus likely that the rs2736098_TT allele 
boosts host immune response for HBV clearance via a telomere 
lengthening-independent manner. However, the exact under-
lying mechanism calls for further investigations. 
Telomere and telomerase or TERT have been shown to be 
involved in the pathogenesis of chronic liver diseases including 
LC. 23-25 Telomerase-deficient mice at late generations exhibit 
shortened telomeres and diminished capacity for liver regen-
eration, and undergo accelerated development of cirrhosis 
after liver injury, whereas re-expression of telomerase activity is 
shown to improve liver function and protect mice from 
development of hepatic steatosis and fibrosis. 25 Similar 
pathological alterations including accelerated telomere attrition 
and regenerative exhaustion of liver cells were observed in 
patients with loss-of-function of telomerase genes. 23,24 On the 
other hand, telomere over-erosion also occurs in CHB-related 
cirrhosis due to a higher turn-over of hepatocytes to compen-
sate for liver damage. Conceivably, HBV infection and shorter 
telomeres cooperate to accelerate the development of LC. 
However, it is currently unclear whether this mechanism is 
involved in the rs2736098_CT/CC-related risk of LC. 
Intriguingly, we only observed the effect of rs2736098 
variants on risk of male CHB patients. It is well-known that 
estrogen protects females from HBV infection and CHB by </p>

<p>Figure 1 Leukocyte telomere length (LTL) in healthy adults (HA) and patients with 
chronic hepatitis B (CHB) and relation with the rs2736098 genotyping. Genomic DNA 
from HA and CHB peripheral leukocytes analyzed for telomere length using qPCR, 
and relative LTL was calculated as described in Methods. (a) Comparison of LTL 
between HA and CHB patients. (b) LTL in HA and CHB patients bearing different 
rs2736098 genotypes. The LTL values shown were age-corrected. </p>

<p>Association of TERT rs2736098 Genotype With Hepatitis B 
Cheng et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>

<p>directly inhibiting HBV replication. 57 On the other hand, 
however, estrogen is also a strong activator of TERT transcrip-
tion and telomerase. 58,59 There may thus be a possibility that a 
potent controlling of TERT expression by estrogen masks the 
effect of the rs2736098 genotypes in female CHB patients. 
Further studies are required to elucidate this issue. 
In summary, the finding presented here demonstrates that the 
TERTrs2736098 variants significantly contribute to the suscept-
ibility of CHB and its cirrhosis complication in Chinese males, 
providing new insights into telomerase biology and etiology of 
CHB and LC. These results also raise a number of intriguing 
questions: How those different TERT genotypes modify the risk 
of CHB and LC, and why their influence only occurs in males. In 
addition, because CHB is a key factor that drives development of 
HCC, while telomerase and TERTare essential in oncogenesis, 
it is important to further dissect the relationship between 
rs22736098 variants and CHB or HBV-related HCC. Elucidation 
of all these issues will certainly contribute to the management 
and prevention of CHB and its complications. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>Guarantor of the article: Feng Kong, MD. 
Specific author contributions: Planning the study: Guanghui 
Cheng, Xiaotian Yuan, Feng Kong, Dawei Xu. Conducting the 
study: Guanghui Cheng, Xiaotian Yuan, Fang Wang, Qing Sun, 
Qian Xin, Kailin Li, Chao Sun, Zhaomin Lin, Yun Luan, Yiteng 
Xu, Ping Li. Collecting and/or interpreting data: Guanghui 
Cheng, Xiaotian Yuan, Fang Wang. Drafting the manuscript: 
Guanghui Cheng, Xiaotian Yuan, Yiteng Xu, Feng Kong, Dawei 
Xu. All the authors have approved the final draft submitted. 
Financial support: This study was supported by grants from 
the National Basic Research Program of China (Grant No. 
2012CB911202), Shandong Provincial Natural Science 
Foundation, China (No: 2016ZDJS07A09), Swedish Cancer 
Society, the Swedish Research Council, Cancer Society in 
Stockholm. The study sponsors have no any roles in the study 
design, collection, analysis, and interpretation of the data and in 
the writing of the report. 
Potential competing interests: None. </p>

<p>Study Highlights </p>

<p>WHAT IS CURRENT KNOWLEDGE </p>

<p>✓ The accumulated evidence has indicated the host-genetic 
background of susceptibility to chronic hepatitis B (CHB). 
✓ Telomerase is involved in liver inflammation and cirrhosis. </p>

<p>WHAT IS NEW HERE </p>

<p>✓ The telomerase (TERT) rs2736098_TT genotype is 
associated with a lower risk of CHB in Chinese males. 
✓ The TERT rs2736098_TT genotype may reduce the onset 
of cirrhosis resulting from CHB. </p>

<p>TRANSLATIONAL IMPACT </p>

<p>✓ The TERT rs2736098 genotyping may identify individuals 
with increased susceptibility to CHB, thereby allowing 
precision prevention of CHB. </p>



<p>Association of TERT rs2736098 Genotype With Hepatitis B 
Cheng et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>



<p>Association of TERT rs2736098 Genotype With Hepatitis B 
Cheng et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>

</text></tei>