<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5098051" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Pre-cooling is known to enhance exercise performance in soccer players. However, little information currently exists 
regarding precooling effects in Iranian young soccer players. </p>

<p>Objectives: The aim of this study was to assess the effect of precooling (water immersion) on exhaustive performance in the heat ( 
temperature = 32 -34°C, humidity = 50%). </p>

<p>Patients and Methods: Sixteen young male soccer players from the provincial competitive teams were divided into two equal </p>

<p>groups and were randomly assigned to precooling (age = 16.5 ± 1.1 year, height = 171.7 ± 6.4 cm, BMI = 21.5 ± 3.3, VO2max = 50.6 ± 6.9 
mL/kg/min) and non-precooling (age = 16.1 ± 1.1 year, height = 170.0 ± 4.7 cm, BMI = 21.3 ± 3.6, VO2max = 50.6 ± 6.8 mL/kg/min) groups. </p>

<p>An exhaustive treadmill run test was conducted after warm-up (non-precooling) or warm-up + water immersion (temperature = 22 
-24°C). Oral temperature, plasma lactate and plasma volume were measured at the baseline (fasting state), mid test (immediately 
after warm up or warm -up + water immersion) and post test (immediately after exhaustive test). Mixed repeated measures analysis 
of variance and independent t test were used for data analyzing. P &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>Results: There were no significant differences between two groups at baseline, mid test and post test regarding oral temperature 
and plasma lactate. The time to exhaustion was considerably higher in the precooling group compared with the non-precooling 
group, but the difference was not statistically significant. No significant differences were found between the two groups on mea-
sures of the baseline and mid test plasma volume, but post test plasma volume was significantly higher in the precooling group 
compared to the non-precooling group (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Conclusions: These results show that precooling effectively attenuates dehydration, but has no positive effect on exhaustion time 
in the hot environment. </p>

<p>Keywords: Heat Temperature, Exercise, Plasma Volume </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>The function of all organs and health status are depen-
dent on the body water and electrolyte balance (1, 2). Water 
facilitates biochemical reactions within cells and tissues 
and is critical for maintaining the blood volume (3). Body 
water compartments contain electrolytes, which are essen-
tial for moving fluid between extracellular and intracellu-
lar space and for producing cell membrane potentials (4). 
One hour of moderate physical activity produces 0.5 to 1.5 L 
of sweat and considerable water loss occurs during several 
hours of vigorous exercise in a hot environment (4), which 
can lead to the loss of electrolytes such as sodium (5, 6). The 
loss of body fluid impairs thermoregulation, circulatory 
system and athletic performance (7, 8). Soccer is the most 
popular sport among the Iranian high school students. 
Hundreds of high school students in Iran participate in </p>

<p>soccer training programs during summer holidays which 
last for three months. Soccer is a combination of aerobic 
and anaerobic activities, leading to high rates of metabolic 
heat production and may cause dehydration during hot 
summer days (9). We are unaware of any studies about 
dehydration in the Iranian young soccer players, but a re-
cent study by Da Silva et al showed that mean sweat losses 
were approximately 2.5 L in young soccer players during a </p>

<p>match played in the heat (31.0 ± 2.0°C) and the players re-</p>

<p>placed less than 50% of their sweat loss (10). Recent data 
indicated significant water deficit in young soccer players, 
when water or sport drinks were available, an indication 
of involuntary dehydration (11). It is well documented that 
dehydration reduces plasma volume (12) which in turn will 
lead to active muscles blood flow restrictions and core tem-
perature rising, both of which compromise athletic perfor-
mance and thermal regulation during physical activity un-</p>

<p>Copyright © 2016, Sports Medicine Research Center. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 
International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial usages, provided the 
original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Azad A et al. </p>

<p>der hot conditions (13). In general, water and electrolytes 
replenishment before, during and after exercise and pre-
cooling are approaches which have been used to prevent 
the athletic performance impairment and heat related in-
juries in a high ambient temperature. Water-immersion, 
cool water showering, the wearing of ice-cooling garments 
and cold air exposure are different methods of pre-cooling. 
Reduction of body temperature prior to a subsequent exer-
cise bout under high temperature condition is the under-
lying rationale for all the methods. 
In a study conducted by Cotter et al. it was shown that 
an ice vest with and without thigh cooling + cold air can in-
crease endurance performance during 35 minutes cycling 
under warm conditions (33°C) (14). Booth et al. reported 
increased distance ran in 30 minutes by 304 m (+ 4%) in a 
warm humid environment (31.6°C, 60% rh) after water im-
mersion (24°C) (15). Gonzalez-Alonso et al. demonstrated 
that, compared to the exercise capacity in the control trial, 
exercise capacity could be enhanced (~37%) by pre-cooling </p>

<p>to an esophageal temperature of 35.9 ± 0.2°C and reduced 
(39%) by warming to a temperature of 38.2 ± 0.1°C (16). </p>

<p>In another study, Schmidt and Bruck using an exhaustive 
cycling test found that precooling (cold air exposure) im-
proved the exhaustion time (17). Generally, a number of 
studies have shown precooling to increase time to exhaus-
tion and improve performance in running or cycling. 
To date no studies have assessed the effects of precool-
ing in Iranian young soccer players. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>Therefore the aim of this study was to examine the ef-
fect of precooling (cold water immersion) on exhaustion 
time, oral temperature and plasma volume in young soc-
cer players during an incremental exhaustive test in warm 
conditions. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>3.1. Subjects </p>

<p>Sixteen young male soccer players from two competi-
tive teams volunteered to participate in this study. G power 
analysis for repeated measure revealed this sample size 
was adequate to detect a moderate effect size (18). All the 
subjects were informed of the procedures and signed an 
informed consent. The study was approved by the ethics 
committee of the university of Zanjan. 
As shown in Figure 1, three days before the main trial 
subjects arrived at exercise physiology laboratory (room 
temperature) for baseline assessments. Height and weight 
were measured using stadiometer and electronic scale, </p>

<p>respectively. Multistage maximal exercise test was con-
ducted on a motorized treadmill (Cosmed, Italy) using 
Bruce protocol (19) and the following formula was used to 
estimate the VO 2max (T = total time on treadmill in min-
utes): </p>

<p>VO 2 max = 14.8 -(1.379 × T) + (0.451 × T 
2 ) -(0.012 × T </p>

<p>3 ) 
Then the subjects were divided into two equal groups 
based on age, height, weight and VO 2max and were ran-
domly assigned to precooling and non-precooling groups 
(Table 1). Three days after baseline assessments, subjects re-
ported to the laboratory (tem = 32 -34°C, humidity = 50%) 
following a 10 hour overnight fasting. The temperature in 
the laboratory was maintained at 32 -34°C throughout the 
experiments. </p>

<p>3.2. Blood Samples Collection, Lactate and Plasma Volume As-
sessments </p>

<p>Blood samples were collected from the left antecubital 
vein as follows: 
1) Pretest Fasting blood sample-7 a.m. 
2) Mid test sample-Both groups consumed standard 
breakfast at 8 a.m. Blood samples were drawn after 10 min-
utes of warm up( non-precooling group) or 10 minutes 
warm up + 10 minutes precooling (Precoling group) at 10 
a.m. 
3) Post test sample-immediately after exhaustive test. 
The system K-4500 automated hematology analyzer 
was used to determine hemoglobin (mg/dL) and hema-
tocrit (%) concentrations in the blood samples. Plasma 
lactate concentrations were measured using Kobas auto-
analyzer and kits manufactured by Randox company of 
England. 
In each of the subjects, the following equations were 
used to calculate the baseline, mid test and post test 
Plasma volume from the values of hematocrit (Hct%) 
hemoglobin (Hb mg/dL) (20). 
BV A = BV B (Hb B /Hb A ) 
CV A = BV A (Hct A ) 
PV A = BV A -CV A 
PV B = BV B -CV B 
PV A = BVA -CV A 
Subscribes A and B refer to baseline and post treatment 
values, respectively and BVA is taken as 100. BV, CV and PV 
stand for the blood volume, red cells volume and plasma 
volume, respectively. Plasma lactate values were corrected 
based on plasma volume changes. </p>

<p>3.3. Oral Temperature </p>

<p>Oral temperatures were recorded pre (Baseline), mid 
(non-precooing group, at the end of warm-up; precooling 
group, at the end of warm up + precooling) and post test </p>

<p>2 
Asian J Sports Med. 2016; 7(3):e33125. </p>

<p>Azad A et al. </p>

<p>1th Day 
(Room Temperature) 
1. Participants, Weight, Height and 
BMI Measurements 
2. VO2 Maax Test 
3. Group Assignment </p>

<p>Non -Precooling 
Group </p>

<p>Precooling 
Group </p>

<p>4thDay 
(Baseline Assessment) </p>

<p>(TEM = 32-34 C, Humidity = 5o%) 
1. Fasting Blood Samples (7 am) 
2.Oral Temperature </p>

<p>3. Standard breakfast (8 am) </p>

<p>4thDay 
(Baseline Assessment) </p>

<p>(TEM = 32-34 C, Humidity = 5o%) 
1. Fasting Blood Samples (7 am) 
2.Oral Temperature </p>

<p>3. Standard breakfast (8 am) </p>

<p>4thDay 
Mid Test Assessment) </p>

<p>(TEM = 32 -34 C, Humidity = 5o%) </p>

<p>1. 10 min Warm Up (10 am) 
2. Blood Samples, Oral Temperatures 
(Immediately after Step 1) </p>

<p>4thDay 
Mid Test Assessment) 
(TEM = 32 -34 C, Humidity = 5o%) </p>

<p>1. 10 min Warm Up + 10 min Water 
Immersion (10 am) 
2. Blood Samples, Oral Temperatures </p>

<p>(Immediately after Step 1) </p>

<p>4th Day 
(Post Test Assessment) </p>

<p>(TEM = 32 -34 C, Humidity = 50%) </p>

<p>1. Exhaustive Test 
2. Blood Samples, Oral Temperatures </p>

<p>(Immediately after Step 1) </p>

<p>4th Day </p>

<p>(Post Test Assessment) </p>

<p>(TEM = 32 -34 C, Humidity = 50%) 
1. Exhaustive Test </p>

<p>2. Blood Samples, Oral Temperatures </p>

<p>(Immediately after Step 1) </p>

<p>Figure 1. Flow Chart </p>

<p>(immediately after exhaustive test) by Beurer FT 09 Digital 
Clinical Thermometer (Germany). </p>

<p>Non-precooling group conducted an exhaustive tread-
mill run test after a 10 minutes of warm up consist of light </p>

<p>exercise and stretch training, while the same exhaustive 
test was done by precooling group after 10 minutes warm 
up + 10 minutes cold water immersion. </p>

<p>Asian J Sports Med. 2016; 7(3):e33125. </p>

<p>
Azad A et al. </p>

<p>Table 1. Subjects Characteristics </p>

<p>Variable 
Group (N = 8) </p>

<p>Non-Precooling 
Precooling </p>

<p>Age, y </p>

<p>16.1 ± 1.9 
16.1 ± 1.1 </p>

<p>Height, cm </p>

<p>170 ± 4.7 
171.7 ± 6.4 </p>

<p>Weight, kg </p>

<p>61.9 ± 12.3 
63.56 ± 10.23 </p>

<p>VO2max, mL/kg/min </p>

<p>50.69 ± 5.6 
50.62 ± 6.9 </p>

<p>BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>21.33 ± 3.6 
21.52 ± 3.3 </p>

<p>3.4. Precooling Maneuver 
A small pool filled with water of 24°C and the water 
temperature was maintained between 22 -24°C through-
out immersion test. Participants in the precooling group 
were immersed up to the neck for 10 minutes. All the ex-
periments were conducted at the laboratory temperature 
and humidity of 32 -34°C and 50%, respectively. </p>

<p>3.5. Exhaustive Test 
During exhaustive test, treadmill started at 7 km/h, the 
speed was increased by 1 km/h every 2 minutes until 10 
km/h, and then the constant speed was maintained until 
volitional exhaustion. </p>

<p>3.6. Statistical Analysis 
The Shapiro-Wilk test verified normal distributions of 
the data for exhaustive performance, plasma volume. If as-
sumptions for normality were not met (oral temperature 
and plasma lactate), data were log-transformed before sta-
tistical analysis. The untransformed values are shown in 
the text, tables and figures. Precooling and non-precooling 
groups were as between subjects' factor, and time (base-
line, mid test and post test) was regarded as within sub-
jects' factor. A mixed repeated measures analysis of vari-
ance was used to assess the main effects and interaction ef-
fect of these factors on the dependent variables. If the sig-</p>

<p>nificant time effect or group × time interaction effect were </p>

<p>observed, then one way repeated measures with Bonfer-
roni as post-hoc and independent samples t test were con-
ducted for further analysis. Independent t test was used to 
compare the subjects' characteristics and exhaustive per-
formance. Research data were analyzed by <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs>-<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">19</rs>. Partial 
eta-squared was used to assess the effect size and signifi-</p>

<p>cant level was set P ≤ 0.05. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>Both the study groups showed similar change in oral 
temperature from the pre to the post test [F (2, 28) = 11.87, </p>

<p>P = 0.001, Partial Eta Squared = 0.4]. After exhaustive test 
oral temperature (post test) was significantly (P &lt; 0.05) 
higher than the baseline and mid test in the precooling 
and non-precooling groups. There were no significant dif-
ferences between precooling and non-precooling groups 
in the oral temperature measures [F (1, 14) = 1.63; P = 0.22, 
Partial Eta Squared =0.19; Table 2]. A significant time effect 
was observed for plasma lactate [F (2, 28) = 11.87, P = 0.001, 
Partial Eta Squared = 0.4]. In the both groups, plasma lac-
tate increased form baseline to post test, but it was only in 
the non-precooling group that the post test plasma lactate 
was found significantly (P &lt; 0.05) higher than the base-
line and mid test (Table 2). No significant differences were 
observed between groups regarding plasma lactate [F (1, 
14) = 0.05; P = 0.99; Partial Eta Squared = 0.025; Table 2]. 
Based on these findings, we can conclude that oral tem-
perature and plasma lactate changes from baseline to post 
test showed a similar pattern in the precooling and non-
precooling groups. 
The plasma volume change, from the pre to the post 
test, was not similar in the precooling and non-precooling 
groups [F (2, 28) = 1.25; P = 0.3; Partial Eta Squared = 0.082; 
Table 2]. There was significant between groups difference 
in plasma volume measure [F (1, 14) = 3.74; P = 0.007; Par-
tial Eta Squared = 0.41; Table 2]. Subsequent independent 
t test analysis revealed higher post test plasma volume in 
the precooling than in non-precooling group (P = 0.03; Ta-
ble 2). This evidence suggesting that precooling can atten-
uate plasma volume decrement during exhaustive activity 
in the hot. 
The exhaustion time was considerably higher in the </p>

<p>precooling group (40.87 ± 12 minutes) than in the non-
precooling group (34.87 ± 5.9 minutes), but did not reach </p>

<p>a significant level (P = 0.24; Table 2). </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to assess the effect of pre-
cooling ( water immersion) on exhaustive performance at </p>

<p>4 
Asian J Sports Med. 2016; 7(3):e33125. </p>

<p>Azad A et al. </p>

<p>Table 2. Effect of Precooling and Warm Up on Oral Temperature, Plasma Lactate, Plasma Volume and Exhaustive Performance in the Hot Environment (Temperature = 32 -34°C, 
Humidity = 50%) </p>

<p>a , b </p>

<p>Variable 
Group (N = 8) </p>

<p>Precooling 
Non-Precooling </p>

<p>Oral Temperature, ºC </p>

<p>Baseline </p>

<p>36.16 ± 0.5 
36.52 ± 0.23 </p>

<p>Mid test </p>

<p>36.17 ± 0.5 
36.71 ± 0.72 </p>

<p>Post test </p>

<p>37.23 ± 0.6 </p>

<p>A,B </p>

<p>37.07 ± 0.44 </p>

<p>A,B </p>

<p>Plasma lactate, mg/dL </p>

<p>Baseline </p>

<p>15.88 ± 3.2 
15.7 ± 2.1 </p>

<p>Mid test </p>

<p>17.3 ± 6.5 
14.81 ± 6.7 </p>

<p>Post test </p>

<p>23.98 ± 10.20 
23.25 ± 7.1 </p>

<p>A,B </p>

<p>Plasma volume, mL/100 mL </p>

<p>Baseline </p>

<p>56.02 ± 4.2 
56.62 ± 2.2 </p>

<p>Mid test </p>

<p>57.83 ± 1.3 
56.05 ± 2.7 </p>

<p>Post test </p>

<p>58.80 ± 1.3 
54.04 ± 2.2 </p>

<p>B, c </p>

<p>Exhaustion time, min </p>

<p>40.87 ± 12.9 
34.87 ± 5.9 </p>

<p>a Baseline (fasting state); mid test, immediately after warm up (non-precooling group) or warm up + precooling (precooling group); Post test, immediately after an </p>

<p>exhaustive test. 
b Different capital letters in superscript shows significant differences compared with baseline and mid test, respectively. 
c Significant difference compared with the post test in the precooling. </p>

<p>environmental temperature of 32 -34°C and humidity of 
50%. Two groups of the young soccer players performed an 
exhaustive treadmill run test after warm up or warm up + 
precooling. No significant difference was found in the ex-
haustion time between the precooling and non-precooling 
groups. In contrast to our result, previous studies had 
reported endurance performance improvement after pre-
cooling in hot condition. Booth et al. and Marino et al. 
reported endurance performance ( distance run or cycle) 
improvement after water immersion (15, 21). Cold air ex-
posure (as a precooling maneuver) was found to increase 
the work output during an exhaustive or endurance type 
test (21). The authors interpreted the results in light of re-
duced thermoregulatory strain (21), decreased reliance on 
anaerobic energy production (22) and attenuated plasma 
volume reduction (16) in precooled condition. Greater 
heat storage rate has been reported in precooling trail 
than in control trail (23), which allows greater margin for 
metabolic heat production. Booth et al observed deep 
body temperature increment immediately after precool-
ing which significantly decreased at the commencement 
of the exercise (15). We found no significant change in the 
oral temperature immediately after precooling, and there 
was no significant between group difference in mid test 
oral temperature (Table 2). Based on these results, it can 
be said that the lack of significant difference in exhaus-</p>

<p>tive performance between precooling and control trails 
might be due to the fact that precooling did not create 
any heat storage capacity prior to the exhaustive test. Ten 
minutes of water immersion was conducted in this study, 
compared with the 60 minutes in the other studies (24). It 
seems that the immersing duration was not high enough 
to create thermal gradient for heat dissipation. </p>

<p>In the present study, precooling attenuated the plasma 
volume decrement during exhaustive test in the heat con-
dition. At the same time, non precooling group showed 
reduction in plasma volume, which lead to the significant 
between group differences following exhaustive test (Table 
2). Given this result, it can be said that the amount of fluid 
loss as sweat was higher in the non-precooling than that 
of in the precooling. Reduced plasma volume in the non-
precooling group following exercise in hot condition, that 
is characterized as hypovolemia (decrease in the volume 
of blood plasma) (25), is in line with similar other studies 
which found a decrease in plasma volume (26, 27). During 
exercise in the heat, active muscles' blood flow must be 
maintained at a high level to supply oxygen and substrates, 
On the other hand, high blood flow to the skin must also be 
maintained to convert heat to the body surface, but hypo-
volumia can restrict these tissues blood flow (28, 29). It is 
well established that acute anemia induces increased lac-
tate concentrations in animals during exercise (22), and </p>

<p>Asian J Sports Med. 2016; 7(3):e33125. 
5 </p>

<p>Azad A et al. </p>

<p>there is strong evidence that the hypovolumia is responsi-
ble for the increase in heat storage and a decrease in heat 
loss during exercise (3). These effects can limit the exer-
cise performance in the heat (1). Compared with the non-
precooling trail, our precooling maneuver attenuated the 
plasma volume reduction, but could not induce any posi-
tive effects on plasma lactate and exhaustive performance, 
since no significant differences were found in the post test 
plasma lactate and exhaustive performance between the 
two groups (Table 2). In an earlier study, blood lactate was 
decreased despite an increase in endurance performance 
following precooling (30). It was speculated that decreased 
blood lactate following precooling might in part be associ-
ated with altered muscle metabolism due to the marked 
reduction in tissue temperature (30). We did not find any 
difference in the oral temperature between two groups 
following precooling. Oral cavity temperature is consid-
ered as a reliable index of core temperature when the ther-
mometer is placed into the sublingual pocket, because 
the sublingual pocket is close to the sublingual artery and 
tracks changes in core body temperature (31). In this study, 
oral temperatures were recorded in the sublingual pocket. 
Therefore, we can probably say that the similar exhaustion 
time in two study groups was because of the fact that cold 
water immersing did not affect the core body temperature 
to induce positive metabolic change. 
Significant difference in the plasma volume but sim-
ilar body temperature and exhaustion time in the two 
study groups seems somewhat paradoxical. It is well 
documented that a body water deficit of greater than 2% 
of body weight marks the level of dehydration that can 
adversely affect thermoregulation and performance (32). 
Non-precooling group showed a body water loss of about 
1% of body weight (data not presented) immediately after 
exhaustive test. It seems that the level of dehydration was 
not high enough to cause an adverse effect on exhaustive 
performance in the non-precooling group. 
Compared to the non-precooling trail, the exhaustion 
time was not significantly but considerably higher in the </p>

<p>precooling group (40.87 ± 12.9 minutes vs. 34.87 ± 5.9 </p>

<p>minutes). Precooling elicited the similar thermoregula-
tory and metabolic responses as the non-precooling dur-
ing exhaustive test. The limitation of this study was the 
fact that this research was not conducted with crossover 
design, therefore several confounders, as heat tolerance, 
heat acclimatization and running economy, independent 
of precooling could affect exhaustive performance. 
Cold water immersion before an exhaustive test atten-
uates plasma volume decrement and cannot induce any er-
gogenic effect on exhaustive performance in the hot condi-
tion. The findings need to be verified in a crossover study 
using a soccer specific test and monitoring the true core </p>

<p>temperature. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Paper extracted from the thesis entitled: The effect of 
cold water immersion (Pre-cooling) on core temperature, 
endurance performance, heart rate, plasma lactate and 
electrolyte levels in youth soccer players in the heat. </p>

<p>Footnote </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution: Ahmad Azad: conceptualized 
and designed the study, drafted the initial manuscript; 
Mansour Mousavi: conducted the protocol and collected 
the data; Ali Gorzi: critically reviewed the manuscript, 
and approved the final manuscript as submitted; Aghaali 
Ghasemnian: analized the data. </p>



<p> 
Asian J Sports Med. 2016; 7(3):e33125. </p>

<p>Azad A et al. </p>



</text></tei>