<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5091065" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.2</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>Panissa VLG, et al. • Lipoprotein profile and high-intensity exercise </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The main findings of the present study were that HIIE-F exercise 
seems to decrease TG when compared with HIIE-AO, and both 
exercises protocols induced similar responses for VLDL (increase 
postexercise). However, no other statistical significant improvement 
of lipoprotein profile was found in both exercise protocols. 
These findings are in agreement with a recent study, which 
showed that a session composed by 20 all-out sprint lasting 6 sec 
of effort interspersed with 24-sec recovery did not change post-
prandial triacylglycerol, glucose and insulin in healthy men (Allen 
et al., 2014). The authors suggested that the lack of improvement 
for postprandial triacylglycerol was due the low energy expendi-
ture of the exercise session (120 kcal approximately). In line with 
this results, the two modes of HIIE of the present study showed 
slight higher energy expenditure (162 to 202 kcal approximately) 
than the previous study (Allen et al., 2014), which may be one 
explanation for the lack of positive results in lipid profile. </p>

<p>However, a study showed that to achieve the positive effects of 
HIIE upon lipoprotein profile, especially in VLDL-TG secretion, 
the exercise should be performed for, at least, 2 months (Tsekouras 
et al., 2008), showing the importance of regular exercise in these 
outcomes. In addition, Lira et al. (2009) showed that high-inten-
sity exercise (90% VO2max) performed continuously, with low en-
ergy expenditure (~124 kcal), decreased total cholesterol and 
LDL-c levels in young males. 
Recently, Bellou et al. (2013) reported that HIIE (4 times of 4 
min at 90% of V 
. O2peak interspersed with 4 min at 60% of V 
. O2peak </p>

<p>for a total of 32 min; gross energy expenditure ~500 kcal) reduced 
fasting plasma VLDL concentrations in nonobese men the next 
day (14 hr after exercise bout) by augmenting VLDL clearance, 
just like a single bout of continuous endurance exercise. Therefore, 
further studies are clearly needed to identify the mechanisms un-
derlying the beneficial effects of HIIE to help in the designing of 
optimal exercise protocols. 
Alongside, energy expenditure seems to be a determinant in the </p>

<p>LDL (mg/dL) </p>

<p>This study was supported by FAPESP (2011/22862-9). Ursula 
Ferreira Julio is supported by FAPESP (2011/22105-3), Fabio 
Santos Lira thanks Fapesp for their support (2013/25310-2). </p>



<p>https://doi.org/10.12965/jer.1632666.333 </p>

<p>Panissa VLG, et al. • Lipoprotein profile and high-intensity exercise </p>



<p>van Loon LJ, Greenhaff PL, Constantin-Teodosiu D, Saris WH, Wagen-</p>

<p>makers AJ. The effects of increasing exercise intensity on muscle fuel </p>

<p>utilisation in humans. J Physiol 2001;536(Pt 1):295-304. </p>

</text></tei>