<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5066091" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-28T23:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In recent years, there has been a growing interest in the 
development of quantitative spectral optoacoustic (OA) imaging 
for medical diagnostics [1]. This technique exploits the wave-
length-dependent optical absorption properties of specific chro-
mophores in tissue (e.g. hemoglobin), to provide quantitative 
estimates of their spatially varying concentrations [2-7]. A 
physiologically important example is the determination of local 
blood oxygen saturation, based on the distinct absorption spectra 
of oxy-and deoxyhemoglobin in the near-infrared range [8,9]. This 
is of particular relevance for the study of oxygenation heterogene-
ity in tumors, the early detection and monitoring of cerebral 
ischemia in brain, and of other abnormalities characterized by a 
change in tissue oxygenation or perfusion status [10]. 
Quantitative spectroscopic OA imaging, however, faces impor-
tant challenges, as well-described by Cox et al. [11]; and among 
them is the spectral distortion due to wavelength-dependent 
fluence attenuation. The retrieval of accurate functional informa-
tion will only be possible if this wavelength-dependency of the 
optical attenuation in the tissue is taken into account (which we </p>

<p>shall refer to as ''spectral correction'') [12,13]. Many groups have 
been working on this problem, proposing a number of different 
correction approaches, each of which has certain advantages and 
disadvantages [4,13-18]. An ideal method to estimate the fluence 
distribution would be non-invasive, not rely on any additional 
modality, or any a priori knowledge. 
In this study, we present a technique that aims at fulfilling all 
the aforementioned criteria. Our approach ties in with the concept 
introduced by Zemp et al. [19,20], which employs multiple 
irradiation positions to estimate optical properties of highly 
scattering media, a concept similar to optical tomography. 
However, as opposed to superficial optical detection, it employs 
optically absorbing structures inside the tissue as intrinsic ''fluence 
detectors''. The practical feasibility of this concept was shown in 
the context of OA microscopy, demonstrating for a single-
wavelength a depth-dependent correction for the optical attenua-
tion [21,22]. The work described in the present study constitutes a 
natural continuation of the aforesaid study, in that the multiple-
irradiation technique is extended to a spectral correction, which is 
essential to retrieve quantitative functional information. Further, 
to emphasize the suitability of this technique for clinical OA 
imaging with a handheld probe, we make use of a linear array 
transducer for 2D image acquisition. 
We conducted phantom experiments with a tissue-mimicking 
bulk material showing a spectrally varying optical attenuation in </p>

<p>Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>

<p>A R T I C L E I N F O </p>

<p>Article history: 
Received 21 December 2015 
Received in revised form 2 May 2016 
Accepted 26 May 2016 
Available online 4 June 2016 </p>

<p>Keywords: 
Optoacoustic 
Quantitative optoacoustic imaging 
Fluence compensation 
Spectral correction 
Multiple irradiation sensing 
Light diffusion 
Blood oxygenation saturation </p>

<p>A B S T R A C T </p>

<p>Spectral optoacoustic (OA) imaging enables spatially-resolved measurement of blood oxygenation 
levels, based on the distinct optical absorption spectra of oxygenated and de-oxygenated blood. 
Wavelength-dependent optical attenuation in the bulk tissue, however, distorts the acquired OA 
spectrum and thus makes quantitative oxygenation measurements challenging. We demonstrate a 
correction for this spectral distortion without requiring a priori knowledge of the tissue optical 
properties, using the concept of multiple irradiation sensing: recording the OA signal amplitude of an 
absorbing structure (e.g. blood vessel), which serves as an intrinsic fluence detector, as function of 
irradiation position. This permits the reconstruction of the bulk effective optical attenuation coefficient </p>

<p>m eff,l . If performed at various irradiation wavelengths, a correction for the wavelength-dependent </p>

<p>fluence attenuation is achieved, revealing accurate spectral information on the absorbing structures. 
Phantom studies were performed to show the potential of this technique for handheld clinical combined 
OA and ultrasound imaging. 
ß 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND 
license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>* Corresponding author. 
E-mail address: Martin.Frenz@iap.unibe.ch (M. Frenz). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>Photoacoustics </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / p a c s </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pacs.2016.05.004 
2213-5979/ß 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/ 
4.0/). </p>

<p>which vessel-like cylindrical absorbers characterized by a distinct 
absorption peak were embedded. Our results demonstrate that the 
multiple optical irradiation approach allows a successful correc-
tion of the measured OA spectrum of the absorbers, which was 
initially distorted by the spectral attenuation of the surrounding 
medium. </p>

<p>2. Theory </p>

<p>2.1. Spectral optoacoustic signal amplitude </p>

<p>The initial pressure, p l (r, t = 0) = p 0,l (r), generated at position r 
after tissue irradiation, acts as a source of acoustic energy emitting 
a broadband transient wavefield (OA signal). The initial pressure 
can be described by </p>

<p>p 0;l ðrÞ ¼ GðrÞÁm a;l ðrÞÁF l ðrÞ </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>where the Grueneisen parameter G(r) characterizes the thermo-
elastic expansion of the tissue, m a (r) is the wavelength-dependent 
absorption coefficient of the chromophore of interest and F l (r) </p>

<p>refers to the fluence at a position r. Under ideal conditions (i.e., full 
information, thus no detection bandwidth limitation, sample-
encompassing detection area), p 0,l (r) can be reconstructed from 
the OA signal p(r 0 , t) measured at detection points r 0 , by solving an 
acoustic inverse problem. The reconstructed signal, S l (r), can be 
expressed as </p>

<p>S l ðrÞ ¼ p 0;l ðrÞ </p>

<p>/ a d;l ðrÞ ¼ m a;l ðrÞÁF l ðrÞ </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>Eq. (2) highlights the proportionality between the recon-
structed signal, S l (r), at any point r = (x, y, z) inside the investigated </p>

<p>tissue and the absorbed energy density, a d,l (r), which corresponds 
to the product of m a,l (r) and the fluence F l (r). This holds true if the 
product of m a,l (r) and diameter of the absorbers is significantly </p>

<p>smaller than 1 (see [23]). For quantitative spectroscopic OA 
imaging it is therefore inevitable to have knowledge on the light </p>

<p>fluence distribution F l (r), which itself is not self-evident to </p>

<p>formulate, as it depends in a complex way on the tissue geometry </p>

<p>and composition. To describe F l (r) in a simplified situation, the </p>

<p>following significant assumptions were made: 
First, we presume that the tissue can be modeled as an optically 
homogeneous bulk material, which is strongly scattering and 
weakly absorbing. In the diffusion approximation for light 
propagation in a semi-infinite 3D geometry (infinite along x À y 
plane and with a boundary at z = 0, infinite along z &gt; 0 -see next </p>

<p>section for more details) 1 the fluence F 0,l (r j |m eff ) at a virtual </p>

<p>intrinsic detection point r j = (x j , y j , z j ) inside the bulk material is 
fully determined by the optical effective attenuation coefficient </p>

<p>m eff,l . For a point-like irradiation, it can be analytically expressed </p>

<p>as: </p>

<p>F 0;l ðd; z j ; m eff Þ / z j 
d 3 Á½1 þ m eff Ád e Àm eff Ád </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>where z j denotes the depth of the virtual detection point, and d the 
distance, from the said point to the source position. 
Secondly, we presume that absorbing structures (e.g., blood </p>

<p>vessels containing specific chromophores, m chr </p>

<p>a;l ðr j Þ) which are 
optically more absorbing than the background, are sparsely 
distributed within the bulk medium. The assumption is made 
that these absorbing structures do not affect the light propagation, 
so that the actual fluence inside the tissue is undisturbed and can </p>

<p>be taken equal to F 0,l (r j |m eff ) (This zero-order assumption is akin </p>

<p>to the first Born approximation commonly used in light scattering 
problems). As such, S l (r j ) can be written as: </p>

<p>S l ðr j Þ / m chr </p>

<p>a;l ðr j ÞÁF 0;l ðr j jm eff ;l Þ 
(4) </p>

<p>2.2. Optically absorbing structures as intrinsic fluence detectors </p>

<p>If F 0,l (r j |m eff ) is known for all wavelengths of interest, the </p>

<p>undistorted absorption spectrum of the absorbing structures can 
be retrieved by inverting Eq. (4): </p>

<p>S l ðr j Þ </p>

<p>F 0;l ðr j jm eff ;l Þ / m chr </p>

<p>a;l ðr j Þ 
(5) </p>

<p>As F 0,l (r j |m eff ) is fully determined by m eff,l , the bulk effective </p>

<p>attenuation coefficient can be derived by ''measuring'' the 
fluence for various source-detection distances d and fitting 
Eq. (3) to the outcome. A conventional way to measure the 
fluence would be to use an external optical detector (e.g., a 
photodiode) [25], but this requires additional equipment and 
can be rather cumbersome in a clinical environment. Instead, we 
make use of the judicious approach proposed in [19], which 
suggests using the investigated absorbing structures themselves 
as point-like ''intrinsic fluence detectors''. As the OA signal </p>

<p>amplitude is proportional to F 0,l (r j |m eff ), the idea is that 
successively acquired OA images at different l and with varying </p>

<p>irradiation positions effectively sample the fluence for different 
source-detection distances d. </p>

<p>3. Materials and methods </p>

<p>3.1. Experimental model </p>

<p>To demonstrate the feasibility of the proposed method, we have 
conducted phantom experiments in a well-defined and controlla-
ble setting, where the phantom was chosen to fulfill the 
assumptions made so far. A liquid fat emulsion was taken as a 
homogeneous and spectrally attenuating bulk medium because (i) 
it is commonly considered as a fairly realistic model for optical 
tissue properties [26], (ii) it is strongly scattering and weakly 
absorbing, and (iii) it is well-studied, easy to manipulate and 
perfectly reproducible. The fat emulsion was placed in a large 
cuboid container, so that boundary effects can be neglected. To 
mimic sparsely distributed absorbing structures (e.g. blood 
vessels), cylindrical tubings were embedded in the liquid bulk 
medium, aligned on top of each other, in parallel to the y-axis (see 
Fig. 1). The total number of absorbers was limited to three, to avoid 
excessive reverberations of OA transients between the different 
absorbers. The tubings were filled with a dye solution, whose 
absorption spectrum displays a significant wavelength dependen-
cy. The tubings were chosen thin to minimize the influence on </p>

<p>F 0,l (r|m eff,l ), while still providing a good signal-to-noise ratio of </p>

<p>the OA signal. 
Fig. 1a and c shows a sketch of the experimental model, 
illustrating the position and orientation of the absorbers inside the 
bulk medium, the irradiation optics and the linear transducer 
array, which is placed on top of the phantom surface for OA signal 
detection. The x-z plane underneath the transducer, represented 
by a red-dashed rectangle in Fig. 1c, defines the so-called 
''imaging-plane'', i.e., the plane of maximum sensitivity of the 
linear US transducer. 
To fulfill the requirements needed for the validity of Eq. (3) in 
terms of irradiation geometry, an optical fiber was used to 
approximate a point-like irradiation. The irradiation spot was 
translated along the phantom surface, parallel to the linear </p>

<p>1 We prefer to use here a simplified version of the stationary solution of the </p>

<p>diffusion model, which can be found in, e.g. Arridge et al. [24]. This version holds 
true for source-detection distances d used in our applications. </p>

<p>K.G. Held et al. / Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>

<p>
transducer in the x-direction, leading to different distances d ij 
between the irradiation spot and the virtual fluence detection 
point r j , i.e., the intersection of the cylindrical tubings with the 
imaging plane (Fig. 1a). The ith irradiation spot position is 
described by x i , the depth of the jth dye-filled tubing of interest 
by z j and the fixed spacing distance between the transducer 
imaging plane and the fiber translation axis by y. This distance 
was set to 16 mm, dictated by the finite width of the linear 
transducer array. The orientation of the linear transducer array, 
aligned perpendicularly to the embedded absorbers, enabled a 2D 
reconstruction that represents a cross-sectional view of the dye-
filled tubings within the imaging plane. Fig. 1d exemplarily shows 
an OA image acquired with one irradiation spot position x i at one </p>

<p>irradiation wavelength l. It displays the spatially-resolved OA </p>

<p>signal, S l (r), of the embedded absorbers at various depths z j . 
In Section 2.1 we made the assumption of a calibrated OA 
detection system providing full information. Yet in practice, a 
typical linear array transducer has a limited aperture and detection 
bandwidth, thus not strictly fulfilling the made assumption. 
Despite that, S l (r) can be regarded as an entity, which is, in case of a 
moderate optical absorption, proportional to the absorbed energy </p>

<p>density a d,l (r), at the cross-sectional position r j of the absorbers in </p>

<p>the imaging plane and is thus proportional to the fluence, </p>

<p>F 0,l (r j |m eff,l ), ''detected'' at those positions. The cross-section </p>

<p>points of the imaging plane with the vessels act in this manner as 
intrinsic fluence detectors. </p>

<p>3.2. Phantom preparation </p>

<p>The background medium was prepared by diluting an optically 
scattering stock fat emulsion (SMOFlipid 20%, Fresenius Kabi, 
Switzerland) with de-ionized water. 2 To produce a total volume of 
4100 ml, 6 wt% of the stock fat emulsion was mixed with de-
ionized water, resulting in a total fat concentration of 1.2 wt%. 
Optical reference measurements of the fat emulsion were 
performed in the spectral range from 700 nm to 830 nm, using 
various optical characterization techniques (see supplementary 
material). The spectrally-absorbing dye Indocyanine green (ICG) 
(IR-125, Laser Grade, ACROS Organics, NJ, USA), diluted in ethanol 
(Ethanol, p.a., Sigma-Aldrich), was used to fill the embedded 
cylindrical tubings. The absorption coefficient of the ICG-ethanol 
solution was assessed from extinction measurements using a 
transmission photo-spectrometer. The measured absorption spec-
trum agrees with literature values [27]. The peak absorption 
coefficient value (m chr 
a;l ¼ 0.35 mm À1 at 785 nm) has the same order 
of magnitude as the absorption of hemoglobin for the spectral 
range of interest (see Section 5). </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 1 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 1. (a) Experimental model including a spectrally-attenuating bulk medium and three embedded dye-filled tubings; the light propagation distance d ij is defined as the 
distance between the ith irradiation spot position and the intersection of the jth cylindrical absorber with the transducer imaging plane. (b) Experimental setup, showing the 
mounting of the linear transducer and the multimode fiber attached to the translation stage. (c) 2D cross-section of the experimental model, indicating the locations of the 
three absorbers at depths z j=1,. . .,3 laterally centered in the imaging plane. (d) 2D reconstructed OA image showing the vertical alignment of the absorbers inside the spectral 
attenuating bulk medium. (For interpretation of the references to color in text, the reader is referred to the web version of the article.) </p>

<p>2 1000 g of the homogeneous stock emulsion consisted of 60 g soybean oil, 60 g </p>

<p>medium-chain triglyceride, 50 g olive oil, 30 g fish oil, leading to a total fat 
concentration of 20% by mass (wt%), assuming a density of 1 g/cm 3 . </p>

<p>K.G. Held et al. / Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>

<p>
3.3. Measurement setup </p>

<p>An overview of the experimental setup is given in Fig. 1b. The 
cuboid container for the bulk medium was made of polymethyl-
methacrylate (PMMA) and had geometrical dimensions of 23 cm 
(length), 17 cm (width) and 14 cm (height). Cylindrical polyure-
thane (PU) tubings (Harvard Apparatus GmbH, Germany), with an 
inner-diameter of 0.28 mm and an outer-diameter of 0.6 mm, 
were used as embedded absorbers filled with the dye solution. The 
tubings were placed at depths of 14.8 mm, 25.4 mm and 28 mm, 
respectively. For OA signal generation, a diode-pumped Q-
switched Nd:YAG laser (Spitlight DPSS OPO, InnoLas Laser GmbH, 
Germany) with an integrated optical parametric oscillator (OPO) 
was used, delivering laser pulses with a tuneable wavelength in 
the range of 680-900 nm, a pulse duration of 10 ns and a 
repetition rate of 100 Hz. The laser light was coupled into a </p>

<p>1000 mm core, multimode fiber (Thorlabs Inc., NJ, USA), delivering </p>

<p>a wavelength-dependent average output pulse energy at the fiber 
tip of around 4 mJ. The energy of each single pulse was measured 
before the fiber coupling with a pyroelectric energy sensor. The 
fiber terminal was fixed on a motorized translation stage (T-series, 
Zaber Inc., Canada), allowing an automated, stepwise translation 
of the irradiation spot parallel to the x-axis. The OA pressure 
transients, generated from the absorbing inclusions, were 
detected by a linear array transducer (ATL L7-4, Philips N.V., 
NL) containing 128 elements at a pitch of 0.298 mm with a center 
frequency of 5 MHz and fractional bandwidth of 80%. OA signal 
acquisition and reconstruction was carried out with an ultrasound 
research system (V 1-64, Verasonics Inc., Redmond, WA), which 
allowed parallel signal readout of 64 channels and continuous 
data transfer for real-time processing on a host PC. This system 
facilitates the acquisition and reconstruction of a full OA image 
with each single laser pulse, at a frame rate corresponding to the 
laser pulse repetition rate. The software of the ultrasound 
research system was programmed in order to alternately acquire 
US and OA images, which offer a direct one-to-one comparison 
between the two modalities. 
For image acquisition, the transducer was mounted with its 
imaging plane perpendicular to the cylindrical PU tubings, 
permitting a cross-sectional image with a high signal-to-noise 
ratio (SNR) [28]. The fiber tip was dipped into the liquid at a 
distance of 16 mm from the imaging plane (y-direction). The fiber 
tip and the transducer aperture were aligned to be at the same 
depth z relative to the liquid surface. The initial irradiation 
location x 0 corresponded to the minimal light propagation 
distance to all absorbers. The fiber tip was then laterally translated 
over a total distance of 25 mm, with a step size of 0.5 mm. For each 
irradiation position an OA image was acquired. To reduce any 
non-systematic background, such as thermal noise, 100 OA 
images were averaged for each irradiation position. The OA 
images (Fig. 1c) were reconstructed using a frequency domain 
algorithm [29]. </p>

<p>3.4. Correction procedure </p>

<p>The implementation of the proposed method for the spectral 
correction can be summarized in the following steps: </p>

<p>(i) Positioning of the transducer array, as described in the 
previous section. </p>

<p>(ii) Acquiring N * M OA images for N irradiation wavelengths, l, </p>

<p>and M different irradiation spot positions, x i . 
(iii) Determining the OA signal amplitudes, S l (r j , x i ), of the jth </p>

<p>detection point for each l and each x i by fitting a 2D Gaussian </p>

<p>profile to the reconstructed OA signal envelope and taking the 
resulting prefactor as a measure for the amplitudes. </p>

<p>(iv) Estimating m eff,l separately for each detection point and each l </p>

<p>by fitting the diffusion model to the OA amplitude values (as 
function of d ij , instead of r j as in Eq. (3)), fS l ðd ij Þg i¼1;...;M;j¼1;...;3 , 
where d ij denotes the distance between the ith irradiation spot 
position and the jth detection point. 
(v) Calculating the undisturbed fluence, {F 0,l (r j=1,. . .,3 )|m eff,l }, for </p>

<p>each l in the tissue, using the previously estimated m eff,l </p>

<p>coefficient values as input to Eq. (3), which is now taken as a 
forward model. </p>

<p>(vi) Finally, knowing F 0 (r j |m eff,l ), the correction of the spectral </p>

<p>optical attenuation in the tissue is possible, according to Eq. (5). </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>4.1. Estimation of the optical effective attenuation </p>

<p>In Fig. 2, the OA signal amplitude, S l (r j ), is exemplarily shown </p>

<p>for one wavelength, l = 760 nm, as function of source-detection </p>

<p>distance, d ij . For visualization purposes, the signals yielded by the 
three absorbers are represented by different symbols and 
normalized to the maximum amplitude for each absorber. The </p>

<p>fluence model F 0,l (r j=1,. . .,3 |m eff,l ) (dotted lines) was fitted to S l (r j ), </p>

<p>to retrieve the bulk medium's effective attenuation coefficient </p>

<p>m eff,l . It is apparent that the fit accurately describes the decay of the </p>

<p>measurements for all three absorbers. </p>

<p>The estimated m eff,l values, using the different absorbers as </p>

<p>fluence detectors, are in good agreement with the results of the 
independently performed optical characterization described in the 
supplementary material. Table 1 summarizes the results with an </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 2 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 2. OA signal amplitudes of the three absorbers as function of source-detection </p>

<p>distances at l = 760 nm. For better visual comparison, all amplitude values were </p>

<p>normalized to the maximum values of the respective absorber and plotted on a 
logarithmic scale. The dotted lines are the result of the fit of the diffusion model to the 
measured amplitude values, whereas the solid lines show the results of MC </p>

<p>simulations based on the m eff,l values determined by the reference optical </p>

<p>measurements. </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Estimated m eff,l values of the bulk medium for one exemplarily </p>

<p>selected wavelength (l = 760 nm), together with the results obtained 
from the independently performed reference measurements using 
frequency-domain diffuse optical spectroscopy (Imagent TM ). </p>

<p>jth absorber </p>

<p>m eff,l=760 nm </p>

<p>j = 1 
0.092 mm À1 AE 0.0041 
j = 2 
0.089 mm À1 AE 0.0072 
j = 3 
0.071 mm À1 AE 0.01 </p>

<p>Reference 
Imagent TM (760 nm) 
0.099 mm À1 AE 0.009 </p>

<p>K.G. Held et al. / Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>

<p>
error estimation based on the 95% confidence interval (CI) of the </p>

<p>least-square fit. The estimated m eff,l values based on the first and </p>

<p>second absorber lie within the range of the reference measure-</p>

<p>ments. Yet, using the third absorber, m eff,l shows an underestima-</p>

<p>tion relative to the reference by around À0.02 mm À1 : This is visible 
in Fig. 2, where the fitted slope for the third absorber differs from 
those obtained with the first and second absorbers. This is further 
discussed in Section 5. 
To validate the applicability of the diffusion approximation to 
our experimental model, we performed Monte Carlo (MC) 
simulations by thoroughly reproducing the phantom and irradia-
tion geometry. All simulations were conducted by generating 
1.5 Â 10 9 photon paths with our general purpose MC software </p>

<p>''<rs type="software">jaMCp 3</rs> '' [30-33]. The input optical parameters (m a,l (r), m s,l (r), </p>

<p>and g l (r)) were taken from the reference measurements. The MC 
simulations of the OA amplitudes agree very well with the decay of 
the experimental data and the diffusion model, supporting the 
assumption that the applied model accurately describes the light 
propagation in the considered experimental situation, where 
boundaries other than the surface could be neglected. </p>

<p>Fig. 3 presents the estimated m eff,l values retrieved from a </p>

<p>single experiment over the full investigated spectral range, from 
700 nm to 830 nm. These values are based on fitting the fluence </p>

<p>model F 0,l (r j=1,. . .,3 |m eff,l ) to N = 27 sets of measurements, one for 
each l. A single set is in turn composed of M = 50 measurements </p>

<p>(each obtained by averaging 100 OA signal acquisitions) corre-
sponding to different irradiation spot positions, x i . The error 
estimation for each set is based on the 95% CI of the single least-
square fit. (Note that this entire experiment was repeated five 
times in total, with a reproducibility error 6%, which lies within 
these 95% CI values.) 
For comparison, the results obtained from each absorber are </p>

<p>separately plotted along with the reference m eff,l values. The </p>

<p>experimental results based on the first and second absorber (Fig. 3a 
and b) show a very good quantitative agreement with the reference 
values, except for the slight overestimation between 700 and 
720 nm. In contrast, the results obtained with the third absorber 
show a good agreement with the reference values between 700 </p>

<p>and 730 nm, but a strong underestimation of m eff,l for l &gt; 730 nm. </p>

<p>4.2. Spectral correction </p>

<p>The results in Fig. 3 underline the spectrally varying attenuation 
of the fluence within the bulk medium. This leads to a distorted OA 
spectrum with respect to the actual absorption spectrum of the 
investigated ICG solution, as shown in Fig. 4a, c and e. The observed 
distortion is getting more pronounced for deeper absorber 
positions. It is particularly accentuated at the spectral range from </p>

<p>700 nm to 790 nm, where m eff,l of the bulk medium strongly </p>

<p>changes from around 0.04 mm À1 to 0.09 mm À1 (see Fig. 3). 
To verify the reliability of our measurements, the expected OA 
amplitude values were calculated according to Eq. (4), using the </p>

<p>m eff,l values retrieved from the optical reference measurements </p>

<p>and plotted over the actual measurements: see Fig. 4a, c and e. The 
expected values coincide well with the measured amplitudes, with </p>

<p>a slight underestimation for l 720 nm. In this range, the OA 
measurements provide a better estimation of m eff,l than the optical </p>

<p>reference measurements, which is apparent in the excellent </p>

<p>spectral correction for l 720 nm in Fig. 4b, d and f. The 
underestimation of the m eff,l values in the reference measurements </p>

<p>(see Fig. 3) is due to the higher scattering, that reduces the accuracy 
of the spectrometric analysis presented in the supplementary 
material. 
Our goal is to correct for this distortion, using the relation given </p>

<p>in Eq. (5). Having determined m eff,l at all wavelengths, we calculate 
the corresponding fluence F 0 (r j=1,. . .,3 |m eff,l ), following the steps </p>

<p>(v-vi) described in Section 3.4. The corrected OA spectra are shown 
in Fig. 4b, d and f for all three absorbers, respectively. The shapes of 
the corrected spectra of the first and second absorbers (Fig. 4b and 
d) show a very good agreement with the reference absorption </p>

<p>spectrum m chr </p>

<p>a;l ðr j Þ of the dye-solution. As for the third absorber, 
despite the observed systematic underestimation of the bulk </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 3 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 3. m eff,l values of the background medium as determined using the different </p>

<p>absorbers, displayed separately for each absorber (a) j = 1, (b) j = 2, (c) j = 3, over the 
spectral range of interest (700-830 nm). The results of the independent optical 
characterization, are presented as reference (gray dashed line, black circles, orange 
squares). (For interpretation of the references to color in this legend, the reader is 
referred to the web version of the article.) </p>

<p>K.G. Held et al. / Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>

<p>
effective attenuation (see Fig. 3c), the spectral correction is still 
apparent. 
In practical applications such as the determination of local 
blood oxygen saturation levels, we are interested in the ratio of OA 
amplitudes at different wavelengths [13,6], rather than in absolute </p>

<p>values of m chr </p>

<p>a;l ðr j Þ. The reason is the incapability to measure 
absolute pressure amplitudes owing to the a priori unknown 
influence of the limitations of the imaging system (e.g. bandwidth 
limitation, restricted detection aperture) on the OA signal 
amplitude [28]. Even though these system inherent parameters 
are not known a priori, they can be considered to be independent of 
the irradiation wavelength. 
Therefore, to provide quantitative evidence of the efficiency 
of our spectral correction, we are interested in the ratio </p>

<p>R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ). R OA ðr j Þ ¼ S l 1 ðr j Þ=S l 2 ðr j Þ is the OA signal amplitude </p>

<p>ratio and R ref ðr j Þ ¼ m chr </p>

<p>a;l 1 ðr j Þ=m chr 
a;l 2 ðr j Þ is the absorption coefficient </p>

<p>ratio, both calculated for different wavelength pairs l 1 ; l 2 </p>

<p>f 
g . The 
amplitude ratios are affected by two types of error: (i) the 
distortion of R OA relative to the reference spectrum, caused by the 
wavelength-dependent attenuation (akin to a systematic error) 
and (ii) a random error owing to measurement noise, which leads 
to an uncertainty in the experimental data. R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ) can be 
considered as a random variable, which, in the case of an ideal 
spectral correction, would be uniformly distributed, whereby </p>

<p>each l 1 ; l 2 </p>

<p>f 
g pair yields a ratio equal to 1. To illustrate our 
purpose, Fig. 5 displays the histogram of realizations of the ratio 
R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ) obtained from our experimental data at r j=2 , 
before and after spectral correction. These histograms are </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 4 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 4. OA signal spectra of the 3 embedded absorbers as function of wavelength, {S l (r j=1,. . .,3 )} and the reference absorption spectrum, m chr </p>

<p>a;l ðr j Þ (red solid line). For each 
absorber, (a), (c) and (e) show the amplitude values before correction. Additionally, the expected OA amplitude values (dashed line), calculated according to Eq. (4) and using </p>

<p>the m eff,l values retrieved from the optical reference measurements, are plotted to verify the reliability of our measurements. (b), (d) and (f) present the amplitude spectra </p>

<p>after spectral correction. All spectra were normalized to their respective mean value for better comparability with the reference. (For interpretation of the references to color 
in this legend, the reader is referred to the web version of the article.) </p>

<p>K.G. Held et al. / Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>

<p>
restricted to spectral regions where the distortion is noteworthy, </p>

<p>e.g., 700 nm l 1 725 nm and 740 nm l 2 810 nm. Before </p>

<p>spectral correction, the R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ) values are significantly 
larger than 1 and the realizations are strongly scattered, as a 
result of the systematic error, which prevails over the random 
error. Yet, after spectral correction, the systematic error vanishes 
and the random error becomes dominant. The ensuing histogram 
follows a normal distribution with a mean equal to 1 and a 
standard deviation of 0.15. This, together with the fact that the 
two histograms do not show any overlap, underlines the 
relevance of the spectral correction. For our following analysis 
in the next section, we consider the ratio R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ) for one </p>

<p>particular wavelength pair l 1 ¼ 800 nm; l 2 ¼ 715 nm </p>

<p>f 
g . The 
corresponding ratios are shown for all three absorbers in Table 2. </p>

<p>5. Discussion and conclusion </p>

<p>5.1. Validity of the tissue model </p>

<p>Overall, our results demonstrate that we have successfully 
applied the concept of multiple optical irradiations to correct for 
the spectral attenuation of the bulk medium. The optoacoustically </p>

<p>determined m eff,l values, based on the first and second absorbers, </p>

<p>agree very well with the reference measurements, showing a </p>

<p>variation in m eff,l from 0.04 mm À1 at 700 nm to 0.11 mm À1 at </p>

<p>830 nm. These values lay within the physiological range of 
superficial human tissue, such as breast tissue ($0.1 mm À1 ) or </p>

<p>muscle tissue ($0.2 mm À1 ) [34], which are at the site of potential 
target applications. 3 </p>

<p>Yet, for l&gt; 730 nm, the m eff,l values obtained from the third </p>

<p>absorber are consistently underestimated with deviations reach-
ing À0.02 mm À1 with respect to the reference measurements. An 
explanation for this underestimation is the small spacing in the z-
direction ($2.5 mm) between the second and third absorbers. This 
geometry was purposefully chosen to demonstrate the fact that the 
fluence at the location of deeper absorbers is perturbed by the 
presence of absorbing structures located above (this models an in 
vivo setting, where, for instance, the trajectories of two or more 
blood vessels/arteries are bound to intertwine): see preliminary 
studies reported in [35]. In other terms, the absorbers do disturb to </p>

<p>some extent the fluence F 0,l (r j=1,. . .,3 |m eff,l ), on the contrary to </p>

<p>what has been assumed in Section 2. This influence can be seen in 
the different slopes of the OA amplitudes of the three absorbers in 
Fig. 2. For the exemplarily chosen wavelength, the slope of the 
third absorber is less steep than that of the first and second 
absorbers. Thus, the fitting of the diffusion model to the OA </p>

<p>amplitudes generated by the third absorber yields m eff,l values, </p>

<p>which differ from the expected ones. We have further validated 
this explanation with additional MC simulations: see Fig. 6, 
showing a ''close-up'' of Fig. 2. It is apparent that the light diffusion 
model based on the optical reference measurements is appropriate 
to describe the fluence at the depth of the third absorber (z j = 
28 mm), in case of a single embedded absorber. Yet, in the presence 
of two additional absorbers located at z j &lt; 28 mm, the fluence is </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Quantitative comparison of R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ) of each individual absorber at one wavelength pair, l 1 ¼ 800 nm; l 2 ¼ 715 nm </p>

<p>f 
g , before and after spectral correction. </p>

<p>jth absorber 
Correction [before/after] 
R OA (r j ) [S 800 (r j )/S 715 (r j )] 
R ref ðr j Þ½m chr 
a;800 ðr j Þ=m chr 
a;715 ðr j Þ 
R OA ðr j Þ </p>

<p>R ref ðr j Þ AE s </p>

<p>j = 1 
Before 
1.73 AE 0.15 
2.65 AE 0.03 
0.65 AE 0.06 
After 
2.51 AE 0.27 
0.94 AE 0.1 </p>

<p>j = 2 
Before 
1.52 AE 0.18 
2.65 AE 0.03 
0.57 AE 0.07 
After 
2.57 AE 0.57 
0.97 AE 0.19 </p>

<p>j = 3 
Before 
1.55 AE 0.38 
2.65 AE 0.03 
0.58 AE 0.14 
After 
2.2 AE 0.88 
0.84 AE 0.33 </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 5 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Histogram of realizations of the ratio of R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ) for various wavelength </p>

<p>pairs l 1 ; l 2 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>g , before (blue) and after (red) spectral correction; l 1 ; l 2 </p>

<p>f 
g were 
restricted to a spectral region with significant spectral distortion, e.g., </p>

<p>700 nm l 1 725 nm and 740 nm l 2 810 nm; after spectral correction, the </p>

<p>histogram is dominated by the random error and can be approximated by a normal 
distribution with a mean value of 1 and a standard deviation of 0.15. (For 
interpretation of the references to color in this legend, the reader is referred to the 
web version of the article.) </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 6 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 6. MC simulations were performed at 760 nm to demonstrate the effect of the 
presence of additional absorbers on the fluence at the position of the third absorber 
r j=3 . It can be seen that the light diffusion model (solid red line) based on the optical 
reference measurements is inappropriate to describe the fluence at r j=3 . (For 
interpretation of the references to color in this legend, the reader is referred to the 
web version of the article.) </p>

<p>3 It should be noted that the proposed technique can also be applied on tissue </p>

<p>types with a higher effective attenuation coefficient. </p>

<p>K.G. Held et al. / Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>

<p>
significantly reduced at r j=3 , depending on the number of absorbers 
present. This effect is particularly pronounced for 32 mm 
d ij 35 mm (see Fig. 6, squares and dots), when the irradiation 
location is positioned close to the center, i.e. when the source-
detector distance is the shortest. Under such conditions, the 
proposed diffusion model fails at correctly describing the fluence at 
the position r j=3 . 
Ultimately, a few more general remarks can be made regarding 
the quality of the proposed method to optically characterize the 
bulk medium. We have quantitatively assessed the accuracy of our 
results by comparison to independently performed reference </p>

<p>measurements of the absorption coefficient m a,l (r), the scattering 
coefficient m s,l (r) and the anisotropy factor g l (r), needed to 
express m eff,l . Naturally, these reference values are to be </p>

<p>considered with precaution, insofar as the factor g l (r) was not 
directly measured but estimated based on indirect measurements 
and different literature sources. Nonetheless, we have noticed that 
all estimations agree on the spectral trend of g l (r). This means that </p>

<p>the spectral behavior of m eff,l remains unaffected by the absolute </p>

<p>value of g l (r), as the latter simply adds a systematic offset, which 
was taken into account in our error propagation calculations. In 
comparison, the source-detection distance d ij is of higher influence </p>

<p>on the accuracy of the m eff,l determination. For instance, a change </p>

<p>in d ij by 2 mm results in a variation in the optoacoustically </p>

<p>determined m eff,l of up to 20%. This error, however, can be avoided </p>

<p>with an appropriate geometrical calibration of the position of the 
optical fiber relative to the imaging plane. In conclusion, the </p>

<p>retrieved m eff,l values show a very good agreement with the </p>

<p>independently performed optical reference measurements and 
thus, underline the general ability of the proposed technique to </p>

<p>determine absolute m eff,l values of strongly scattering bulk </p>

<p>materials. </p>

<p>5.2. Influence of the number of irradiation spot positions and number 
of acquisitions on the estimation of the optical effective attenuation </p>

<p>The high number (M = 50) of irradiation spot positions, x i , for 
this proof-of-principle study was chosen so as to fully understand 
the behavior of the light fluence for a large number of d ij and over a 
broad spectral range. To provide a good SNR, particularly for x i far 
off the absorbers, 100 OA acquisitions per x i were used for 
averaging. The resulting measurement time per x i of around 3 s 
(including 100 OA acquisitions, image reconstruction and me-
chanical translation of the irradiation spot position) led to long 
acquisition times for a single experiment. 
With the aim of shortening the acquisition time, we investigat-</p>

<p>ed how the accuracy of the estimated m eff,l values is affected by </p>

<p>reducing (i) the number of x i and (ii) the number of acquisitions per 
x i . Exemplarily, for one absorber (j = 2) and one set of measure-</p>

<p>ments (l = 760 nm), we estimated m eff,l based on smaller subsets </p>

<p>with n number of x i values, randomly sampled (Â100) out of M. The 
number of acquisitions for each x i was kept constant. The resulting </p>

<p>mean and 95% CI of m eff,l for different n values are summarized in </p>

<p>Fig. 7a. The results show that for this specific absorber and </p>

<p>wavelength, the estimated m eff,l values converge to the reference </p>

<p>value for n ! 10, accompanied by a decrease in the fit uncertainty. 
For the same absorber (j = 2) and set of measurements </p>

<p>(l = 760 nm), we subsequently estimated m eff,l by averaging k </p>

<p>acquisitions for M irradiation spot positions. The resulting mean </p>

<p>and 95% CI of m eff,l for different k are presented in Fig. 7b. The </p>

<p>results show that for the specific absorber and wavelength, the </p>

<p>estimated m eff,l values converge to the reference value for k ! 15, </p>

<p>accompanied by a slightly decreasing fit uncertainty. The 
underestimation for small k results from the noise contribution 
to the fit, observed for x i positions far off the absorbers. Excluding 
those noise dominated measurements (i.e., effectively reducing the </p>

<p>number of x i values) from the fit improves the m eff,l estimation, </p>

<p>even for k 15. 
Certainly, these results suggest that n ! 10 positions and k ! 15 </p>

<p>acquisitions would suffice to accurately determine m eff,l , leading in </p>

<p>practice to a significant reduction in acquisition time. Yet, it is 
difficult to draw a universal conclusion with respect to clinical 
applications, since the slope will be perturbed in an in vivo setting, 
where not only geometrical boundaries, but also optical hetero-
geneities play an influential role. Actually, the effect of the optical 
heterogeneities can already be observed here in the case of the 
third absorber: see Fig. 6. As such, we can only claim that there is 
trade-off between the number of irradiation spot positions and the 
number of acquisitions, and that this needs to be further 
investigated with in vivo studies. </p>

<p>5.3. Accuracy of the spectral correction and ensuing blood oxygen 
saturation level calculations </p>

<p>We shall recall that the main purpose of this ''proof-of-
principle'' study was to correct for the spectral distortion of the </p>

<p>measured OA spectra. The key point was to calculate F 0,l (r j |m eff,l ), 
based on the spectrally determined m eff,l using multiple-irradia-</p>

<p>tion sensing, and to subsequently assess the accuracy of the 
spectral correction. The latter is of particular relevance if 
quantitative OA imaging is applied to measure physiological 
parameters such as the blood oxygen saturation level [1]. 
Compared to the distorted OA spectra, the corrected ones 
presented in Fig. 4(b), (d), and (f), indicate a significantly better </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 7 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 7. (a) Mean and 95% CI of m eff,l , estimated based on (a) randomly sampled subsets of irradiation spot positions with size n out of M, (b) by averaging over k acquisitions for 
M irradiation spot positions; all results are based on the second absorber (j = 2) acquired at l = 760 nm. </p>

<p>K.G. Held et al. / Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>

<p>
agreement with the reference absorption spectrum of the ICG 
solution. This qualitative observation can be quantitatively 
judged by the ratio of R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ) at 800 nm and 715 nm given 
in Table 2. After spectral correction, R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ) of the first 
(0.93 AE 0.11) and second (0.94 AE 0.2) absorbers agree, within the 
standard deviation, with the target value (i.e. R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ) = 1). 
Yet, the correction of the third absorber (0.84 AE 0.4) does not yield 
the intended ratio, despite a significant correction compared to the 
initial value (0.58 AE 0.087). This is related to the observed </p>

<p>systematic underestimation of m eff,l , as thoroughly explained </p>

<p>above. 
The choice of R OA (r j )/R ref (r j ) was motivated by the target 
application example, i.e. quantification of the relative concentra-
tions of deoxyhemoglobin (HHb) and oxyhemoglobin (HbO 2 ) 
based on the distinct optical absorption ratios of HHb and HbO 2 at 
two different wavelengths. Assuming HHb and HbO 2 to be the 
main optically absorbing blood constituents, their relative con-
centrations at r j can be retrieved using the following relation 
between the known molar absorption coefficient and the resulting 
OA amplitudes at two different wavelengths: </p>

<p>S l1 </p>

<p>S l2 </p>

<p>¼ </p>

<p>k l 
m a;l1 
m a;l2 </p>

<p>" 
# </p>

<p>¼ k l1 0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>k l2 </p>

<p>e HbO 2 </p>

<p>l1 </p>

<p>e HHb </p>

<p>l1 </p>

<p>e HbO 2 </p>

<p>l2 </p>

<p>e HHb </p>

<p>l2 </p>

<p>" 
# 
c HbO 2 </p>

<p>c HHb </p>

<p>" 
# </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>where the product of the total hemoglobin (Hb) concentration 
($150 g Hb/L) and the wavelength-dependent molar extinction </p>

<p>coefficient is given as e. The relative concentrations of HHb and 
HbO 2 is denoted by c HHb and c HbO2 , respectively and the factors k l </p>

<p>depend on the wavelength-dependent fluence, as well as on </p>

<p>various system parameters. (Although, S l , m a,l , c HbO2 , and c HHb are </p>

<p>all a function of r j , this dependency is omitted in Eqs. (6)-(8), for 
sake of simplicity.) The inversion of Eq. (6) yields </p>

<p>c HbO 2 
c HHb </p>

<p>" 
# </p>

<p>¼ 1 
det e </p>

<p>S l1 </p>

<p>k l1 
Á e HHb </p>

<p>l2 Àe HHb </p>

<p>l1 Á k l1 
k l2 </p>

<p>ÁR OA </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>l1 </p>

<p>k l1 </p>

<p>Á Àe HbO 2 </p>

<p>l2 </p>

<p>þ e HbO 2 
l1 Á k l1 
k l2 </p>

<p>ÁR OA </p>

<p>2 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
5 
(7) </p>

<p>in which det e is the determinant of the molar extinction coefficient 
matrix and R OA ðr j Þ ¼ S l 2 ðr j Þ=S l 1 ðr j Þ refers to the ratio between OA 
signal amplitudes at two different wavelengths. The resulting 
blood oxygen saturation (SO 2 ) level can be expressed as a function 
of the relative concentrations of HHb and HbO 2 [36], where the </p>

<p>ratio between k l1 and k l2 accounts for the wavelength-depen-</p>

<p>dency of the fluence at the two wavelengths of interest. The 
accuracy of the SO 2 level quantification depends on the accurate </p>

<p>determination of this ratio, i.e. the spectral correction of the 
amplitude ratio R OA (r j ): </p>

<p>SO 2 ¼ 
c HbO 2 
c HHb þ c HbO 2 </p>

<p>¼ </p>

<p>e HHb </p>

<p>l2 Àe HHb </p>

<p>l1 Á k l1 
k l2 </p>

<p>R OA </p>

<p>e HHb </p>

<p>l2 Àe HbO 2 
l2 À½e HHb 
l1 Àe HbO 2 </p>

<p>l1 </p>

<p>Á k l1 
k l2 </p>

<p>R OA </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>To discuss the accuracy of the achieved spectral correction in 
the context of SO 2 level quantification, we extrapolate the 
measured OA spectra (see Fig. 4) to a literature-based blood 
absorption spectrum, corresponding to a nominal SO 2 level of 90%, 
which is reasonable for a healthy adult [36] (black solid line in 
Fig. 8). The extrapolated spectra were obtained by multiplying the 
ratios S l ðr j Þ=m chr 
a;l ðr j Þ of the measured OA spectra (see Fig. 4) with 
the said nominal blood spectrum. Fig. 8 shows the extrapolated 
spectra for the second absorber (blue dots), before and after 
spectral correction, together with the literature-based nominal 
blood absorption spectrum. The SO 2 levels were quantified for the </p>

<p>particular wavelength pair l 1 ¼ 800 nm; l 2 ¼ 715 nm </p>

<p>f 
g using 
Eq. (8). It should be noted that this wavelength pair, which was 
already considered in Section 4, was chosen so that the efficiency of 
our approach could be assessed in the case of a strong initial 
distortion of the OA spectrum. To underline the sensitivity of the 
SO 2 level determination to small deviations from the extrapolated 
spectrum, the absorption spectra corresponding to the two 
''extreme'' blood oxygenation states (1% O 2 and 99% O 2 saturation) 
are added in Fig. 8. 
Table 3 presents the nominal and the estimated SO 2 levels, 
before and after spectral correction, together with the experimen-
tally obtained 95% CI values. The estimated SO 2 values before </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 8 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 8. OA spectrum of the second absorber (blue dots), before (a) and after (b) spectral correction, extrapolated to a literature-based nominal blood absorption spectrum of </p>

<p>90% SO 2 (black solid line); the SO 2 level estimation is based on the extrapolated OA spectra at the two wavelengths, l 1 = 800 nm and l 2 = 715 nm; the absorption spectra of </p>

<p>oxygenated (99% SO 2 ) and deoxygenated (1% SO 2 ) blood illustrate the full possible absorption range. (For interpretation of the references to color in this legend and in the text, 
the reader is referred to the web version of the article.) </p>

<p>Table 3 
The nominal and estimated SO 2 levels based on all three absorbers, before and after 
spectral correction, together with the corresponding 95% CI. </p>

<p>jth 
absorber </p>

<p>Correction 
[before/after] </p>

<p>Estimated 
SO 2 [%] </p>

<p>95% CI 
[%] </p>

<p>Nominal SO 2 [%] </p>

<p>j=1 
Before 
69.5 
AE6.4 
90 
After 
87.2 
AE 7.3 </p>

<p>j=2 
Before 
62.1 
AE8.6 
90 
After 
88.9 
AE 16.4 </p>

<p>j=3 
Before 
62.8 
AE18.9 
90 
After 
82.2 
AE 26.8 </p>

<p>K.G. Held et al. / Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>

<p>
spectral correction show for all three absorbers a significant 
deviation from the reference value, which leads in practical 
applications to an erroneous diagnostic outcome. Yet, after spectral 
correction, the estimated SO 2 values approach the nominal value. 
The corresponding CI values increase after spectral correction, as a </p>

<p>consequence of the error in the experimental m eff,l determination. </p>

<p>It is apparent that despite the increased CI values, the improve-
ment in SO 2 level determination is significant, underlining the 
power of this technique. Even in the case of a strong initial 
distortion of the OA spectrum, the accuracy of our results with the 
first absorber lies within the CI, which is comparable not only to 
other OA based methods [6], but also to commercially available 
pulse oximeters (95% CI &lt;AE6%) [37,38]. Moreover, our approach 
does not require any a priori knowledge about the tissue geometrical 
properties, unlike the study of Laufer et al. [6], and provides spatially 
resolved information, not possible with pulse oximetry. Furthermore, 
we would like to point out that the accuracy of our results could 
further be increased when using a larger wavelength range. 
In conclusion, we presented a method to correct for the 
wavelength-dependent optical attenuation in highly scattering 
media such as biological tissues, which is of great relevance in the 
frame of quantitative OA imaging. The method is based on the 
concept of multiple irradiation sensing which was implemented on 
a system designed for handheld, clinical combined OA and US 
imaging. The fact that the proposed technique is non-invasive, 
does not require a priori knowledge or any other additional 
detection modalities and has low computational cost, makes it 
promising for real-time clinical application. The results of this 
feasibility study emphasize its applicability also for deep 
optoacoustic imaging. Its benefit for the estimation of blood 
oxygen saturation levels was underlined. More importantly, this 
proof-of-principle study helped identifying the challenges and the 
limitations of this approach. These include the applicability limits 
of the tissue model in the presence of several strong optical 
absorbers, as well as the influence of the noise on the fit of the 
diffusion model. Future steps will involve more realistic situations, 
i.e., simulation and experimental work on strongly heterogeneous 
phantoms (multi-layered, non-trivial vasculature model, etc.) with 
influential boundaries, and the corresponding adaptation of the 
light propagation model. This will pave the way to quantitative OA 
imaging in a clinical settings. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest 
The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>We would like to thank on the one hand René Nyffenegger for 
his valuable contribution to the experimental work and on the 
other hand, Salvador Sanchez Majos and Jingjing Jiang from the 
University Hospital Zurich for their help in validating our results, 
through an independent analysis of our measurements. This 
research was funded in part by the European Community 
Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) under grant agreement 
no. 31806, the Swiss TransMed platform 'ONIRIUS' and the Swiss 
Science Foundation (grant no. 205320-144443). The Imagent TM 
measurements could not be realized without the financial support 
of the Swiss Science Foundation 'R'EQUIP' (grant no. 139238). 
Michael Jaeger acknowledges support from the career develop-
ment scheme 'Ambizione' (grant no. PZ00P3-142585) and K. Gerrit 
Held from the Hans-Sigrist Foundation. </p>

<p>Appendix A. Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data associated with this article can be found, in 
the online version, at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pacs.2016.05.004. </p>



<p>K.G. Held et al. / Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>



<p>
K. Gerrit Held received his BSc in Biomedical Technol-
ogy, in 2010, and his MSc degree in Biomedical 
Engineering, in 2013, both from the University of 
Twente, The Netherlands. He is currently working 
towards a PhD degree at the Institute of Applied Physics 
(IAP) of the University of Bern, Switzerland. His current 
research focuses on real-time quantitative optoacoustic 
imaging implemented on a handheld, clinical combined 
OA and US system. </p>

<p>Michael Jaeger received the Dipl. Phil. Nat. degree in 
physics from the University of Bern, Switzerland, in 
2002, and the PhD in physics from the same university 
in 2007. In 2010/2011 he joined the Institute of Cancer 
Research and the Royal Marsden Hospital, Sutton, UK. 
In 2012 he won a grant for a three-year project under 
the career development scheme Ambizione and is since 
them group leader of the Optoacoustic Imaging Team at 
the Institute of Applied Physics, University of Bern. His 
research includes optoacoustic imaging with focus on 
clinical imaging, as well as novel ultrasound techniques 
such as speed-of-sound imaging using echo ultrasound. </p>

<p>Jaro Rička received his Doctorate degrees from the 
University of Bern, Switzerland. After completing a 
PostDoc at MIT in Boston he returned back to the 
Institute of Applied Physics of the University of Bern for 
heading the research group, time correlated photon-
counting and complex liquids. In 2001 he became a 
professor at the University of Bern where he retired in 
2014. His research interests are in optical measurement 
techniques and their applications in physics, biology 
and chemistry. </p>

<p>Martin Frenz received the Master degree in physics 
from the Albert-Ludwig University of Freiburg, 
Germany, in 1985, and the PhD in physics from the 
University of Bern, Switzerland in 1990. In 1995 he 
joined the University of Texas at Austin, USA. In 2002 he 
became a professor and head of the biomedical 
photonics department of the Institute of Applied 
Physics at the University of Bern, Switzerland. Since 
2008 he is director of the Institute of Applied Physics. 
His most recent work has explored new imaging 
modalities in biomedicine, including quantitative 
optoacoustic imaging and sensing, in vivo microscopy, 
optoacoustic contrast agents for imaging and therapy, 
light propagation in tissue as well as biomedical laser 
applications for medical diagnostics and therapy. </p>

<p>H. Gü nhan Akarçay completed his MSc at the Ecole 
Nationale Superieure de Physique de Strasbourg before 
joining the Institute of Applied Physics (IAP) of the 
University of Bern to work on his PhD. He then carried 
out postdoctoral research in Montreal and Ulm. His 
work focuses on the numerical modeling of light 
propagation in condensed soft matter and his interests 
cover radiative transfer, electromagnetism, statistical 
physics and biophysics. He currently pursues his work 
as a postdoctoral fellow at the IAP. </p>

<p>K.G. Held et al. / Photoacoustics 4 (2016) 70-80 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>