<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5407455" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Many patients suffering from trichotillomania (TTM) have never undergone 
treatment. Without treatment, TTM often presents with a chronic course. Characteristics of TTM 
individuals who have never been treated (untreated) remain largely unknown. Whether treat-
ment history impacts Internet-based interventions has not yet been investigated. We aimed 
to answer whether Internet-based interventions can reach untreated individuals and whether 
treatment history is associated with certain characteristics and impacts on the outcome of an 
Internet-based intervention. 
Methods: We provided Internet-based interventions. Subjects were characterized at three time 
points using the Massachusetts General Hospital Hairpulling Scale, Hamilton Depression Rating 
Scale, and the World Health Organization Quality of Life questionnaire. 
Results: Of 105 individuals, 34 were untreated. Health-related quality of life (HRQoL) was 
markedly impaired in untreated and treated individuals. Symptom severity did not differ 
between untreated and treated individuals. Nontreatment was associated with fewer depressive 
symptoms (P=0.002). Treatment history demonstrated no impact on the outcome of Internet-
based interventions. 
Conclusion: Results demonstrate that Internet-based interventions can reach untreated TTM 
individuals. They show that untreated individuals benefit as much as treated individuals from 
such interventions. Future Internet-based interventions should focus on how to best reach/ 
support untreated individuals with TTM. Additionally, future studies may examine whether 
Internet-based interventions can reach and help untreated individuals suffering from other 
psychiatric disorders. 
Approximately 1%-2% of the general population are affected by trichotillomania 
(TTM). 
1 TTM is characterized by repetitive hairpulling (criterion A, Diagnostic and 
Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition [DSM 5] 
2 ). TTM is associated 
with significant distress and functional impairment (criterion C, DSM 5), and patients' 
attempts of reducing hairpulling are usually unsuccessful (criterion B, DSM 5). Most 
frequent locations of hairpulling are the scalp, eyebrows, and eyelashes. 
3 Affected 
individuals tend to avoid group activities because they are worried about their appear-
ance and that others may uncover their problem. 
4,5 Approximately 86% of TTM 
individuals report a reduced quality of close friendships. 
6 Additionally, TTM often 
interferes with work performance and health-related quality of life (HRQoL), 
3,7 and it 
is frequently comorbid with other psychiatric disorders such as anxiety, mood, eating, </p>

<p>8,9   and personality disorders. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Steffi Weidt 
Department of Psychiatry and 
Psychotherapy, University hospital 
Zurich, University of Zurich, 
culmannstrasse 8, ch-8091 
Zurich, switzerland 
Tel +41 44 255 5280 
Fax +41 44 255 4408 
email steffi.weidt@usz.ch </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 
21 April 2017 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1154 </p>

<p>Weidt et al </p>

<p>Cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT), including habit 
reversal training (HRT), 
11 progressive muscle relaxation 
(PMR), 
12 acceptance and commitment therapy (ACT), 
13 and 
decoupling (DC), 
14,15 are effective treatments for TTM. How-
ever, individuals with TTM often report feelings of embar-
rassment and shame that have been shown to be significant 
barriers for them to access and seek treatment. 
3,7,8,16 Therefore, 
in adult individuals with TTM, the estimated prevalence of 
treatment is only ∼50%. 
3 Treatment often begins ∼9 years 
after the onset of hairpulling. 
17 In addition to embarrassment 
and shamefulness, further possible reasons for nontreatment 
may include failure to recognize symptoms as a treatable 
problem and not knowing where to seek professional help. </p>

<p>18   Without proper treatment, TTM almost always leads to a 
chronic and often debilitating course. </p>

<p>19   Very few studies have investigated individual or illness-
specific characteristics, differentiating between individu-
als with and without previous treatment. In patients with 
obsessive compulsive disorder, studies have found no signifi-
cant associations between gender and treatment history. </p>

<p>20-22   Results on age and treatment history in obsessive compulsive 
disorder studies have been inconsistent. </p>

<p>23-25   Whether individual characteristics (eg, age), illness 
characteristics (eg, severity of hairpulling), and/or impair-
ment of HRQoL are associated with treatment history of 
TTM individuals is not yet known. Thus, learning more 
about the similarities and differences in the characteris-
tics of treated and untreated TTM individuals may guide 
researchers and clinicians to find individualized approaches 
to access and support those who have never been treated 
or identified through the conventional therapeutic network. 
One approach to support untreated individuals may be via 
Internet/mobile-based interventions. 
26,27 However, whether 
such interventions can access and benefit untreated individu-
als compared to previously treated individuals has never yet 
been investigated. Thus, the present study has mainly focused 
on the following hypotheses: 
• Untreated individuals with TTM can be accessed via 
Internet-based interventions. 
• Individual (eg, age) and specific TTM characteristics 
(eg, severity of symptoms) do not differ between 
untreated and treated individuals, but more severe depres-
sive symptoms, as in the case of OCD individuals, are 
associated with previous treatment. 
• Previously untreated individuals benefit from the pro-
vided Internet-based interventions and do not have a 
higher dropout rate than previously treated individuals. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Our TTM sample was recruited from an Internet-based 
interventional, double-blind randomized controlled trial 
(NCT02044237), which was published previously. 
15 The 
study was approved by the local ethics committee of the 
Canton of Zurich in Switzerland and was conducted accord-
ing to the Declaration of Helsinki. All participants gave their 
written (electronic) informed consent. </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>A total of 141 individuals signed the electronic informed 
consent form. The inclusion criteria were adult individu-
als who met the diagnostic criteria for TTM according to 
DSM-IV-TR. 
28 Exclusion criteria were current suicidal 
ideations, dependency of alcohol or drugs, and/or current 
psychotic episodes. Other comorbid AXIS I disorders were 
assessed but were not considered as exclusion criteria 
due to the known high rate of psychiatric comorbidity in 
TTM. Individuals were excluded if they discontinued the 
pretreatment assessment (n=20). An additional 16 indi-
viduals were excluded because they were interested in the 
study but did not meet criteria for TTM (n=4), they could 
not be contacted for the telephone interview (n=6), they 
decided not to take part in the interview (n=1), and they 
met the exclusion criteria (four individuals with current 
suicidal ideations, one with current alcohol dependency; 
flow chart, Figure 1). 
With regard to treatment history, individuals were asked 
if they have ever received professional help (such as psy-
chiatric, psychotherapeutic, and/or psychopharmacological 
treatment) and/or if they were currently treated for any 
mental health problem. This assessment did not refer to the 
specific and targeted treatment for TTM since we aimed to 
also include additional TTM-related mental health problems 
(such as depressive symptoms) in the study. Individuals 
who answered "no" for both questions were assigned to the 
"never-treated/untreated" group (N=34). If one or both ques-
tions were answered affirmatively, individuals were assigned 
to the "previously treated/treated" group (N=71). </p>

<p>Procedures </p>

<p>A web link directed potential participants to the pretreatment 
assessment (UNIPARK, QuestBack™). After the pretreat-
ment assessment, individuals were contacted for a telephone 
interview in order to assess for the diagnostic criteria of TTM, 
depressive symptoms, and psychiatric comorbidity. Partici-
pants were then randomly allocated to one of two intervention </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1155 </p>

<p>Trichotillomania: treatment history and internet-based self-help </p>

<p>groups (decoupling or PMR). 
15 After the 4-week interven-
tion period and the 6-month follow-up, subjects completed 
questionnaires and were interviewed by phone. </p>

<p>interventions </p>

<p>Detailed information is given in the study of Weidt et al. </p>

<p>15   In short, both methods (decoupling and PMR) were mailed 
to the participants in PDF files, which included written and 
illustrated instructions. Decoupling instructed the participants 
to redirect their movement from the hair to a different target 
close to the pulling side or into the room (= decouple). 
14 PMR 
followed standard instructions. 
29 During the online self-help 
intervention participants in both groups received weekly 
identically worded email support. </p>

<p>Measures </p>

<p>The Massachusetts General Hospital Hairpulling Scale 
(MGH-HPS, German version) was administered to capture 
the severity of hairpulling. 
30,31 The total score is the sum of </p>

<p>seven self-report items (range: 0-28, higher scores indicating 
worse pulling). The instrument's internal consistency (0.89) 
and retest reliability (r=0.97) are excellent. </p>

<p>30,32   The World Health Organization Quality of Life ques-
tionnaire (WHOQOL-BREF, German version) was used 
to assess HRQoL. 
33,34 The scale contains 26 items that are 
coded on a five-point scale. The items can be summarized in 
four composite scores (WHO-physical, WHO-psychological, 
WHO-social relationships, and WHO-environment) and one 
global score (WHO-global) with higher scores indicating 
better HRQoL. Reference values of the German general 
population are available. </p>

<p>34   To assess general psychopathology, a short form (SCL-
K-9, German version) 
35 of the Symptom Checklist SCL-90-R </p>

<p>36   was applied. The SCL-K-9 results in the Global Severity 
Index (GSI). The GSI represents the mean score of nine items 
(range 0-4, higher scores indicating more severe general 
psychopathology). 
Comorbid psychiatric disorders were assessed with the 
Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview (M.I.N.I., 
German version). </p>

<p>37,38   For clinician-rated depressive symptoms, the Hamilton 
Depression Rating Scale (HDRS-17, 17-item German version) 
was used. 
39,40 Ratings were determined during semistructured 
telephone interviews. The sum-score ranges between 0 and 
52 (higher scores indicating worse symptoms). 
All interviewers were clinically experienced psychologists/ 
psychiatrists and trained in the administration of M.I.N.I. and 
HDRS-17. 
Sociodemographic and clinical data were obtained 
through structured questions regarding treatment experience, 
duration of illness, age, gender, and education. </p>

<p>analysis </p>

<p>Group differences (untreated vs previously treated) at baseline 
were calculated using the Student's t-test for continuous vari-
ables and Pearson χ 
2 test for nominal variables (eg, pulling 
site). WHOQOL-bref scores of the two groups were com-
pared between untreated and treated TTM individuals in addi-
tion to the German general population 
34 using the Student's 
t-test. To test whether treatment history potentially affects 
the outcome of Internet-based intervention, an intention-to-
treat analysis (ITT) with first observations carried forward 
(FOCF) and a completer's analysis were conducted. In both 
analyses, a general linear model with repeated measures 
(GLM-RM) and repeated contrasts was conducted for the 
dependent variables (MGH-HPS, HDRS-17, WHOQOL-bref </p>

<p>Figure 1 consort diagram of never-treated and previously treated subjects from 
baseline to follow-up. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1156 </p>

<p>Weidt et al </p>

<p>subscores [not WHO environment], and SCL-K-9). Group 
(treatment history: untreated vs previously treated) served as 
the between-subject variable, and time (pre, post, follow-up) 
as the within-subject factor. A significant impact of treatment 
history can be seen in a significant interaction between group 
and time. Variables (baseline HDRS-17 and baseline WHO-
global) that had demonstrated baseline differences between 
both groups (untreated/previously treated) were included as 
covariates into the analyses, also the variable intervention 
group (decoupling/PMR). Assumptions for all analyses with 
GLM-RM were checked in terms of Box's test of equality 
of covariance matrices, Mauchly's test of sphericity, and 
Levene's test of equality of error variances. All assumptions 
were met, with the exception of a significant Box's test for 
the HDRS-17 and a significant Mauchly's test for the GSI 
(ITT and completers' analysis), which was considered with 
a Greenhouse-Geisser correction. Effect sizes (partial η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
were calculated (0.01 small effect, 0.06 medium effect, 
and 0.14 large effect size). </p>

<p>41   All statistical calculations were performed using the 
software package <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> (Version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">22.0</rs>). The level of signifi-
cance was set at P0.05 (two-sided). </p>

<p>Results 
Baseline characteristics of individuals 
without previous treatment compared to 
those with previous treatment </p>

<p>Table 1 presents the results of the comparisons between 
untreated (n=34, 32.4%) and previously treated individuals 
(n=71, 67.6%). Individuals in the untreated group were sig-
nificantly less likely to pull hair from their own scalp and 
showed lower HDRS-17 scores and higher global HRQoL 
(WHO-global). They did not differ in duration of symptoms 
and severity of hairpulling. </p>

<p>Baseline hrQol of the two groups and 
compared to the german population </p>

<p>Figure 2 depicts the mean scores on the WHOQOL-bref 
subscales for both groups separately and compared to the 
German population (age matched, range 18-65 years). In 
both groups (untreated and previously treated), the mean 
scores on the subscales physical, psychological, and social 
relationships of the WHOQOL-bref were significantly lower 
than those of the general population. Environmental HRQoL </p>

<p>Table 1 characteristics and illness symptoms of previously treated subjects with TTM (T) and untreated subjects with TTM (NT) at 
baseline </p>

<p>Variable 
NT (n=34) 
T (n=71) 
Test statistics 
df 
P-value </p>

<p>gender: male 
N=4 (11.8%) 
N=1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-
-
age, years 
31.35 
32.42 
−0.52 
103 
0.60 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>age at onset, years 
13.65 
13.73 
−0.06 
103 
0.96 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Diagnostic delay, years 
9.74 
9.90 
−0.10 
103 
0.93 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Dos, years 
18.71 
19.69 
−0.46 
103 
0.65 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>comorbid disorders -yes 
N=15 (44.1%) 
N=40 (56.3%) 
1.34 
1 
0.24 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>higher education 
N=28 (82.4%) 
N=50 (70.4%) 
1.79 
1 
0.18 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>employed 
N=17 (50%) 
N=32 (45.1%) 
0.22 
1 
0.64 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mgh-hPs 
17.12 
18.27 
−1.11 
103 
0.27 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Number of pulling sites 
1.53 
1.83 
−1.36 
103 
0.18 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Pulling site -scalp 
N=22 (64.7%) 
N=62 (87.3%) 
6.95 
1 
0.008 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Pulling site -eyebrow 
N=15 (44.1%) 
N=20 (28.1%) 
2.58 
1 
0.11 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Pulling site -eyelashes 
N=8 (23.5%) 
N=21 (29.6%) 
0.43 
1 
0.51 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Pulling site -not visible 
N=6 (17.6%) 
N=18 (25.4%) 
0.8 
1 
0.31 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>gsi 
1.54 
1.59 
−0.33 
103 
0.74 </p>

<p>hDrs-17 
5.68 
9.85 
−3.19 
103 
0.002 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>WhOQOl-bref subscale 
global 
64.34 
54.58 
2.28 
103 
0.024 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Physical 
73.32 
68.85 
1.70 
103 
0.09 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Psychological 
56.37 
49.59 
1.72 
103 
0.09 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>social relationships 
56.13 
52.11 
0.89 
103 
0.38 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>environment 
71.42 
72.71 
−0.41 
103 
0.68 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Notes: Values are mean values unless specified otherwise. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>χ 
2 test. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t-test; significant P-values are shown in bold; </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>not calculated due to very small numbers. 
Abbreviations: TTM, trichotillomania; Dos, duration of symptoms; Mgh-hPs, Massachusetts general hospital hairpulling scale; gsi, global severity index; hDrs-17, 
hamilton Depression rating scale, 17-item version; WhO, World health Organization; WhOQOl-bref, WhO Quality of life questionnaire short form. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1157 </p>

<p>Trichotillomania: treatment history and internet-based self-help </p>

<p>was similar to that of the general population for both groups. 
Global HRQoL was significantly impaired in the previously 
treated group but not in the untreated group. The compari-
son of the two groups demonstrated no significant differ-
ences in the WHOQOL-bref subscales, except for global 
HRQoL, which was lower in the treated group (Table 1 and 
Figure 2). </p>

<p>effect of treatment history on hairpulling 
severity, depressive symptoms, hrQol, 
and global severity outcome </p>

<p>iTT (N=105) </p>

<p>Effects over time were significant for all dependent variables 
(P0.001, except: WHO-social relationships, P=0.06; 
Table 2). We observed no significant effect for any of the 
group × time interactions (P from 0.08 to 0.72), indicating 
that treatment history did not affect the outcome of the 
Internet-based intervention. Group × time interaction did not 
change significantly after including the covariates 1) baseline 
HRDS-17, 2) baseline WHO-global, and 3) intervention 
group (decoupling/PMR) into the GLM of the ITT analyses 
(Table 2, P from 0.053 to 0.71). </p>

<p>completer analysis (N=81) </p>

<p>Number of dropouts from baseline to follow-up did not differ 
between the two groups (untreated =6; 17.6%, previously 
treated =18; 25.4%; Pearson χ 
2 =0.38). Completer analyses 
demonstrated significant effects over time for all dependent 
variables (Table 3, P from 0.05 to 0.001). We observed 
the same lack of significant group × time interactions as in 
the intention-to-treat analyses (P from 0.1 to 0.75). Including 
covariates (as mentioned earlier) did not change group × time 
interaction significantly (Table 3, P from 0.14 to 0.93). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study compar-
ing clinical characteristics between untreated and previously 
treated individuals suffering from TTM and examining the 
potential effect of treatment history on the outcome of an 
Internet-based intervention. Both untreated and previously 
treated individuals with TTM demonstrated marked impair-
ment in HRQoL compared with the general population. TTM 
individuals who have never received any previous treatment 
had significantly lower depressive symptoms, in addition to 
having significantly more hairpulling from other body areas </p>

<p>Figure 2 health-related quality of life of previously treated TTM subjects (T) vs never treated TTM subjects (NT) and in comparison with the general german population (Norm). 
Notes: **P0.001, *P0.05, higher scores indicate better health-related quality of life. 
Abbreviations: TTM, trichotillomania; WhO, World health Organization; WhOQOl-bref, WhO Quality of life questionnaire short form. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1158 </p>

<p>Weidt et al </p>

<p>Table 2 results of the general linear models (repeated measures) for hairpulling severity, depressive symptoms, hrQol, and global severity on intent-to-treat analyses between 
previously treated TTM subjects (T) and never-treated TTM subjects (NT), N=105 </p>

<p>Scale/questionnaire </p>

<p>Baseline </p>

<p>Posttreatment </p>

<p>Follow-up </p>

<p>Group </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Time </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Group × </p>

<p>time </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Group × </p>

<p>time </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>NT, M (SD) T, M (SD) NT, M (SD) T, M (SD) NT, M (SD) T, M (SD) F </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>(η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>(η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>(η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>(η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Mgh-hPs 
17.12 (5.17) 18.27 (4.88) 13.09 (5.57) 14.38 (6.18) 14.65 (6.23) 14.93 (6.12) 0.85 </p>

<p>=0.36 (0.01) </p>

<p>24.40 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.19) 0.43 </p>

<p>=0.65 (0.00) </p>

<p>0.34 
=0.71 (0.00) </p>

<p>hDrs-17 </p>

<p>5.68 (3.76) </p>

<p>9.85 (7.15) </p>

<p>4.71 (3.48) </p>

<p>8.30 (5.64) </p>

<p>4.29 (4.24) </p>

<p>6.86 (5.83) </p>

<p>11.37 0.001 
(0.10) 10.13 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.09) 1.39 </p>

<p>=0.25 (0.01) </p>

<p>0.53 
=0.57 (0.01) </p>

<p>WhOQOl-bref subscale </p>

<p>global 
64.34 (19.00) 54.58 (21.15) 70.96 (19.64) 58.45 (20.57) 71.32 (19.10) 60.74 (21.05) 8.30 0.01 </p>

<p>(0.08) 8.80 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.08) 0.36 </p>

<p>=0.70 (0.00) </p>

<p>0.74 
=0.48 (0.01) </p>

<p>Physical 
73.32 (17.01) 66.85 (18.75) 77.00 (14.53) 67.05 (20.46) 68.49 (12.79) 63.18 (17.03) 4.47 0.05 </p>

<p>(0.04) 14.95 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.13) 2.17 </p>

<p>=0.12 (0.02) </p>

<p>0.77 
=0.47 (0.01) </p>

<p>Psychological 
56.37 (18.53) 49.59 (19.06) 63.73 (15.06) 51.70 (21.52) 62.62 (18.56) 53.87 (19.14) 5.94 0.05 </p>

<p>(0.06) 12.42 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.11) 2.59 </p>

<p>=0.08 (0.03) </p>

<p>2.04 
=0.13 (0.02) </p>

<p>social relationships 
56.13 (22.78) 52.11 (21.21) 58.09 (20.56) 51.53 (23.16) 60.05 (22.45) 55.40 (22.19) 1.45 </p>

<p>=0.23 (0.01) </p>

<p>2.80 
=0.06 (0.03) </p>

<p>0.34 
=0.72 (0.00) </p>

<p>0.61 
=0.55 (0.01) </p>

<p>gsi </p>

<p>1.56 (0.91) </p>

<p>1.59 (0.76) </p>

<p>1.07 (0.74) </p>

<p>1.45 (0.85) </p>

<p>1.15 (0.89) </p>

<p>1.26 (0.75) </p>

<p>1.61 
=0.21 (0.02) </p>

<p>13.77 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.12) 2.68 </p>

<p>=0.08 (0.03) </p>

<p>3.07 
=0.053 (0.03) </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>results for general linear models without covariates; </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>general linear models with baseline HDRS-17, baseline WHO-global, and intervention group covariates. For WHOQOL-bref, higher scores indicate better HRQoL. Significant </p>

<p>P-values 
are shown in bold. 
Abbreviations: Mgh-hPs, Massachusetts general hospital hair-Pulling scale; hDrs-17, hamilton Depression rating scale, 17 item version; WhO, World health Organization; WhOQOl-bref, WhO Quality of life questionnaire </p>

<p>short form; TTM, trichotillomania; hrQol, health-related quality of life; gsi, global severity index; </p>

<p>η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, partial eta square. </p>

<p>Table 3 results of the general linear models (repeated measures) for hairpulling severity, depressive symptoms, hrQol, and global severity on completer analyses between previously 
treated TTM subjects (T) and never-treated TTM subjects (NT), N=81 </p>

<p>Scale/questionnaire </p>

<p>Baseline </p>

<p>Posttreatment </p>

<p>Follow-up </p>

<p>Group </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Time </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Group × </p>

<p>time </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Group × </p>

<p>time </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>NT, M (SD) T, M (SD) NT, M (SD) T, M (SD) NT, M (SD) T, M (SD) F </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>(η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>(η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>(η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>(η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Mgh-hPs 
16.75 (5.44) 18.13 (4.88) 12.79 (5.21) 13.28 (5.99) 13.75 (6.36) 13.66 (5.98) 0.30 </p>

<p>=0.58 (0.00) </p>

<p>26.13 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.25) 0.64 </p>

<p>=0.53 (0.01) </p>

<p>0.07 
=0.93 (0.00) </p>

<p>hDrs-17 </p>

<p>5.11 (3.13) 
10.38 (7.26) 4.32 (3.35) </p>

<p>8.38 (5.42) </p>

<p>3.43 (3.47) </p>

<p>6.38 (5.46) </p>

<p>15.53 0.001 
(0.16) 11.46 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.13) 1.92 </p>

<p>=0.15 (0.02) </p>

<p>0.71 
=0.49 (0.01) </p>

<p>WhOQOl-bref subscale </p>

<p>global 
62.50 (19.23) 52.12 (20.32) 70.98 (20.14) 56.60 (19.86) 70.98 (19.85) 60.38 (20.76) 8.46 0.01 </p>

<p>(0.10) 9.05 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.10) 0.59 </p>

<p>=0.55 (0.01) </p>

<p>0.66 
=0.52 (0.01) </p>

<p>Physical 
73.09 (17.29) 64.56 (18.81) 77.68 (14.95) 64.35 (20.94) 67.22 (11.67) 59.64 (15.55) 6.96 0.01 </p>

<p>(0.08) 15.39 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.16) 2.39 </p>

<p>=0.10 (0.03) </p>

<p>1.31 
=0.27 (0.02) </p>

<p>Psychological 
55.80 (19.12) 48.43 (16.55) 64.14 (15.73) 51.10 (20.22) 63.39 (19.12) 54.17 (16.83) 6.54 0.05 </p>

<p>(0.08) 12.41 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.14) 2.04 </p>

<p>=0.13 (0.03) </p>

<p>1.69 
=0.19 (0.02) </p>

<p>social relationships 
58.63 (22.51) 50.79 (21.26) 61.31 (18.87) 50.79 (23.19) 63.39 (21.44) 55.19 (22.71) 3.66 </p>

<p>=0.06 (0.04) </p>

<p>3.06 0.05 </p>

<p>(0.04) 0.29 </p>

<p>=0.75 (0.00) </p>

<p>0.53 
=0.59 (0.01) </p>

<p>gsi </p>

<p>1.48 (0.88) </p>

<p>1.69 (0.73) </p>

<p>0.96 (0.64) </p>

<p>1.46 (0.85) </p>

<p>1.01 (0.80) </p>

<p>1.26 (0.74) </p>

<p>4.51 0.05 
(0.05) 14.58 0.001 </p>

<p>(0.16) 1.45 </p>

<p>=0.24 (0.02) </p>

<p>2.04 
=0.14 (0.03) </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>results for general linear models without covariates; </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>general linear models with baseline HDRS-17, baseline WHO-global, and intervention group covariates. For WHOQOL-bref, higher scores indicate better HRQoL. Significant </p>

<p>P-values 
are shown in bold. 
Abbreviations: NT, never-treated subjects; T, previously treated subjects; Mgh-hPs, Massachusetts general hospital hairpulling scale; hDrs-17, hamilton Depression rating scale, 17 item version; WhO, World health Organization; 
WhOQOl-bref, WhO Quality of life questionnaire short form; TTM, trichotillomania; hrQol, health-related quality of life; gsi, global severity index; </p>

<p>η </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, partial eta square. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1159 </p>

<p>Trichotillomania: treatment history and internet-based self-help </p>

<p>except from the scalp. Interestingly, treatment history did 
not affect the outcome of the Internet-based intervention and 
dropout rates did not differ between untreated and previously 
treated individuals. 
Before a detailed discussion of the present study, we 
would like to acknowledge several limitations. One of the 
main limitations of our study is that the majority of indi-
viduals were female. Therefore, it would be imprudent to 
apply our current results to males. However, previous TTM 
online studies have reported similar female predominance in 
their study sample. 
3,16 Whether this reflects TTM as having 
a higher prevalence in females 
1,42 or females with greater 
information-or help-seeking behavior 
43 remains an important 
but yet unsolved question. </p>

<p>11,44   Although 32.4% of participants of the current sample were 
untreated individuals, this number appears to be considerably 
lower than the number of individuals not receiving treatment 
in the community and in other published epidemiological 
studies (∼50%, eg, the study of Woods et al </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>). One reason 
for this discrepancy might be due to the assessment history. 
We inquired about the general psychiatric treatment history 
and did not explicitly seek treatment history specific to TTM. 
We also did not ask the participants about their reasons for 
not receiving any treatment. For those who have received 
treatment, we also did not inquire whether their treatment 
was perceived as helpful. In addition, we cannot exclude 
recall bias by participants who might have had difficulties to 
accurately recall therapy experiences from the past. 
To reduce potential interrater disagreement all three raters 
were trained and interviews followed clearly stated guidelines 
for M.I.N.I. and HDRS-17. 
One of the strengths of the present study in contrast to 
many other online studies was the external validation of 
the diagnosis of TTM. Furthermore, we used a longitudinal 
study design in order to assess differences between individu-
als with and without previous treatment history and also to 
investigate whether these differences affect the outcome of 
an Internet-based intervention. 
As the probability of treatment often correlates with 
disorder severity, 
45 a crucial step when interpreting findings 
in untreated individuals is to consider whether they have 
clinically relevant symptoms. If, for example, such individu-
als had only minor hairpulling symptoms and good HRQoL, 
this alone might explain their nontreatment. Overall, both 
patient groups reported longstanding symptoms and consid-
erable impairment of HRQoL. Nevertheless, global HRQoL 
and depressive symptoms were less severe in untreated 
individuals compared to those who have previously sought </p>

<p>treatment. While these results implied that certain untreated 
individuals might not have sought treatment before due to a 
relatively lower functional impairment, severity of hairpull-
ing, duration of hairpulling symptoms, and global severity 
did not differ between the groups. Furthermore, there was no 
significant difference in the number of psychiatric comorbid 
disorders, and all participants were motivated enough to seek 
help in the current intervention study, indicating substantial 
amount of suffering in both groups of TTM participants 
(treated and untreated). 
Three potential explanations can be discussed for the 
association of depressive symptoms and treatment history. 
1) Because of the feeling of shamefulness 
5 and fear of nega-
tive reactions from others, 
20 the attempt to conceal hairpull-
ing symptoms often delays treatment seeking in individuals 
with TTM. 
3,7 However, due to effective health education 
and global awareness on depressive symptoms over the last 
decade, the shame and stigma to disclose depressive symp-
toms have slowly reduced. 
46 Therefore, individuals may feel 
more comfortable to disclose depressive than hairpulling 
symptoms. 2) The association between nontreatment and rel-
atively low depression scores is further supported by findings 
in other psychiatric patient populations. For instance, lower 
depression scores have been reported in patients with social 
phobia who sought treatment for the first time compared 
to those with prior treatment history. 
47 Among psychiatric 
patients, interference with daily living due to depressive 
symptoms is one of the major motivations for individuals to 
seek professional treatment. 
20,23,48,49 3) Physicians are often 
more familiar and knowledgeable to manage depressive 
symptoms 
50,51 than hairpulling symptoms, 
44,52 this in turn 
may allow individuals to disclose their depressive symp-
toms more willingly to their physicians. Thus, individuals 
with more severe depressive symptoms may be identified 
and provided treatment more often than those who have 
fewer depressive symptoms. Taken together, 1) feeling less 
shameful to disclose depressive symptoms than hairpulling 
symptoms, 2) the negative impact of depressive symptoms 
as a significant motivation for individuals to disclose their 
symptoms and seek help, and 3) the higher rate of identifying 
individuals with more severe depressive symptoms might 
explain the association between depressive symptoms and 
previous treatment history. 
We demonstrated that individuals without a previous 
treatment history benefited to the same extent from the 
provided intervention compared to individuals with a prior 
treatment history. Additionally, dropout rates did not differ 
between the untreated and treated groups. These findings </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Weidt et al </p>

<p>were encouraging because they suggested that Internet-based 
interventions may be effective in treating TTM individuals, 
independent of their treatment history. 
In the following section, we would like to discuss pos-
sible reasons that may explain the present findings. 1) Even 
though TTM individuals with a previous treatment history 
might have benefited from their previous treatment, they 
did not report less hairpulling severity but instead reported 
more severe depressive symptoms at baseline than individu-
als without any prior treatment. Depressive symptoms have 
been shown consistently to be associated with cognitive 
impairments, 
53 and these symptoms could impair learning 
and the application of new adaptive behaviors. However, the 
severity level of depression in both samples was relatively 
low and did not reach diagnostic thresholds for a current 
depressive episode in most individuals. 
54 This might explain 
why potential cognitive effects of depression did not affect 
treatment outcome in this study. 2) While some studies 
reported that individuals with previous treatment are more 
likely to dropout from current therapies, 
55 the dropout rates 
did not differ between our studied groups. This finding is 
supported by the abovementioned study in patients suffering 
from social phobia 
47 -prior treatment was not associated with 
a change in dropout rates. A potential reason might be that 
prior treatment was less successful and/or less specific for 
TTM symptoms, and therefore, individuals attempting our 
new Internet-based intervention might be more motivated 
and desperate to complete the whole treatment program in 
order to learn new skills for reducing their TTM symptoms. 
3) One might assume that individuals without previous treat-
ment might, due to limited skills of reducing TTM symptoms 
compared with individuals with prior treatment, benefit to a 
lesser extent. However, previous treatment(s) might not be 
as comprehensive or successful, which might not have pro-
vided an additive improvement to our current Internet-based 
intervention(s). When interpreting our findings, it is impor-
tant to keep in mind that the data were gathered and assessed 
via the Internet. Participants without previous treatment 
indeed sought help in our Internet-based intervention study. 
These individuals were actively searching for information 
and help related to TTM online; therefore, they might have at 
least some insights into their problems. Overall, the present 
study provided encouraging results and demonstrated that it 
is possible to access at least some of the "hidden" untreated 
individuals and that professional online information/ 
intervention might be important to successfully close the 
gap between being ill, having insight into symptoms and/or </p>

<p>mental illness, seeking professional help, 
56 and benefiting 
from the provided Internet-based intervention(s). </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Current results suggested that both TTM individuals with 
and without previous treatments suffer from clinically sig-
nificant symptoms with substantial impairment in HRQoL. 
The severity of depressive symptoms was correlated with 
initiating treatment in TTM. Furthermore, the present study 
demonstrated that the Internet-based intervention reached 
out to certain "hidden" untreated TTM individuals, and TTM 
individuals benefited from such intervention independent of 
their treatment history. The dropout rates were comparable 
between the previously treated and untreated groups. 
Future Internet-based interventions should especially 
be focused to reduce barriers for and to support "hidden" 
untreated TTM individuals in order to gain access to 
evidence-based online interventions that are tailored for 
them. The present study may be a stepping stone for future 
studies to examine whether "hidden" untreated individuals 
who suffer from different chronic and debilitating psychi-
atric disorders can be accessed online and can benefit from 
Internet-based interventions. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>Potential conflicts of interest and support and financial 
involvement over the previous 3 years, regardless of their 
potential relevance to the paper are reported. The authors 
would like to acknowledge funding support from the 
Gottfried and Julia Bangerter-Rhyner Foundation and from 
the Novartis Foundation for medical-biological research. 
The authors advise that no granting or other outside parties 
had any role in the study's design or orchestration, includ-
ing data collection and analysis, their decision to publish, 
or preparation of the manuscript. SW reports grants from 
Gottfried and Julia Bangerter-Rhyner Foundation, Novartis 
Foundation for medical-biological research, and University 
of Zurich -career development grant Filling the gap. ABB 
reports fellowship from the Swiss Foundation for Grants in 
Biology and Medicine (SFGBM) and the Swiss National 
Science Foundation (SNSF). AD reports grants from the 
University of Zurich Matching Fund and from the Johnson 
Foundation. GZ reports Canadian Institutes of Health 
Research (CIHR) Postdoctoral Fellowship and W Garfield 
Weston Doctoral Fellowship. AK reports no conflicts of 
interest in this work. MR reports speaker honoraria from 
AstraZeneca and Lundbeck Institute; research grants from </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1161 </p>

<p>Trichotillomania: treatment history and internet-based self-help </p>

<p>the Gottfried and Julia Bangerter-Rhyner Foundation and the 
Novartis Foundation for medical-biological research. The 
authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/neuropsychiatric-disease-and-treatment-journal </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment is an international, peer-
reviewed journal of clinical therapeutics and pharmacology focusing 
on concise rapid reporting of clinical or pre-clinical studies on a 
range of neuropsychiatric and neurological disorders. This journal 
is indexed on PubMed Central, the 'PsycINFO' database and CAS, </p>

<p>and is the official journal of The International Neuropsychiatric 
Association (INA). The manuscript management system is completely 
online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review system, which 
is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to 
read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2017:13 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1162 </p>

<p>Weidt et al </p>



</text></tei>