<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5436526" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: By targeting the prostate-specific membrane antigen (PSMA) on prostate cancer (PCa) cells 
PSMA-PET/CT shows great potential in locating the site of biochemical recurrence even at low PSA 
(Prostate-specific antigen)-levels. Accurate imaging of PCa recurrent lymph node metastases (LNM) is crucial 
for metastases directed therapies such as salvage-lymph node dissection (salvage-LND). 
Objective: To evaluate the diagnostic accuracy of PSMA-PET/CT for detection of affected lymph-node 
regions at salvage-LND for nodal recurrence of PCa. 
Design, setting and participants: 30 patients with the suspicion of exclusively nodal PCa-relapse after 
primary therapy underwent a template pelvic and/or retroperitoneal salvage-LND after whole body 
68-Ga-PSMA-PET/CT. The diagnostic accuracy of PET/CT was evaluated in comparison to the histopathology 
of 965 resected lymph nodes (LN) dissected from 68 main regions (pelvic left/right, retroperitoneal) and 289 
subregions (common iliac, external iliac, obturator, internal iliac, presacral, aortic-bifurcation, aortal, caval). 
LNM and tumor deposits in LNM were measured bidimensionally in the histopathology. PSMA-expression 
was analyzed by immunohistochemistry in LNM. 
Results: LNM were present in 11.4% of the resected LN (110/965) resulting in 45 positive main regions and 
85 positive subregions. PET/CT was true positive in 41 main regions and 69 subregions. Three PET-negative 
main regions and 16 PET-negative subregions finally contained LNM, the majority of these false negative 
subregions (13/16) were in neighboring regions of true-positive subregions. Sensitivity, specificity, positive 
predictive value, negative predictive value and accuracy were: main region-based 93.2%, 100%, 100%, 88.9% 
and 95.6%, subregion-based 81.2%, 99.5%, 98.6%, 92.7 and 94.1%. Median short diameters of tumor deposits 
in LNM resected from false-negative subregions (1.3 mm) were significantly smaller than in LNM removed 
from true-positive subregions (5.5 mm, p&lt;0.0001). Based on anatomical subregions containing just one LNM, 
the necessary short diameter of tumor deposits in LNM required to reach a detection rate of 50% and 90% 
was estimated to be ≥ 2.3 mm and ≥ 4.5 mm, respectively. 
Conclusion: In men with biochemical PCa-relapse and positive PSMA-PET/CT, PET/CT detects metastatic 
affected anatomical regions with high accuracy at a main region and at a subregion-level. If the decision for 
salvage-LND is prompted by a positive PSMA-PET/CT, the size of metastases is crucial for accurate detection 
of affected regions. All LNM showed a clear PSMA-expression in the immunohistochemistry. Further studies 
need to investigate how to translate the high anatomical correlation observed between PET/CT and surgical 
findings into optimal approaches for target salvage-LND. </p>

<p>Key words: prostate cancer, lymph node metastases; PSMA-PET/CT; salvage lymph node dissection; salvage 
lymphadenectomy. </p>

<p>Ivyspring </p>

<p>International Publisher </p>

<p>Theranostics 2017, Vol. 7, Issue 6 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Accurate preoperative imaging of prostate 
cancer (PCa) metastases, predominantly lymph node 
metastases (LNM), at primary therapy or at salvage 
lymph node dissection (salvage-LND) in patients with 
biochemical PCa recurrence enables physicians to 
plan accurate extended lymph node dissection and to 
identify those who most likely will not benefit from 
surgery because of high metastatic or non-lymphatic 
tumor burden [1, 2]. At the stage of biochemical 
relapse (after having a PSA-Nadir &lt; 0.03 ng/ml 
following primary therapy) or biochemical 
progression after primary therapy (lacking a 
PSA-Nadir &lt; 0.03ng/ml) a positron emission 
tomography (PET/CT) with choline analogues such 
as 18 F-fluoroethylcholine or 11 C-choline represented 
an option to locate PCa-relapse for many years [1, 3, 
4]. PET-CT with 11 C-or 18 F-labeled choline derivatives 
is superior to MRI and CT for recurrent PCa [3, 5], but 
the efficiency of choline-PET/CT for detecting sites of 
tumor strongly depends on the PSA (Prostate specific 
antigen) value at the time of imaging, Gleason score, and 
other clinical factors [3]. The value of choline-PET/CT 
was still limited due to a lack of sufficient sensitivity 
(lesion-based pooled sensitivity 66%) [6]. 
Targeting the prostate-specific membrane 
antigen (PSMA) on the surface of PCa cells enables 
powerful imaging of PCa lesions [7-9]. Meanwhile, in 
many countries around the world PSMA-PET/CT is 
rapidly gaining acceptance as a very valuable tool for 
restaging PCa patients with biochemical recurrence 
[10-13] and is reimbursed in several countries. 
Recently PSMA-PET/CT has found its way into the 
German prostate cancer S3-guidelines for patients 
with biochemical relapse [14]. With the aim of locating 
the site of PCa recurrence in general, the lesion-based 
sensitivity, specificity, negative predictive value and 
positive predictive value were reported by Afshar et 
al. to be of 76.6 %, 100 %, 91.4 % and 100 %, 
respectively [15]. Few reports on identification of 
LNM by PSMA-PET/CT with subsequent surgical 
resection and histopathological evaluation are 
available from different groups [16-21]. 
For those patients with biochemical recurrence 
and the suspicion of nodal relapse only, a complete 
surgical resection of pelvic and retroperitoneal lymph 
node metastases (LNM) could represent a therapeutic 
approach to avoid less well tolerated and palliative 
systemic treatments such as antihormonal deprivation 
therapy. Especially, the detection of small LNM is 
challenging in recurrent PCa. Furthermore, the extent 
of salvage-LND (e.g. the decision whether to include 
the contralateral pelvic site for surgery when a 
unilateral PET-positive lesion is present) is still a </p>

<p>matter of controversy. The number of diagnosed 
lymph node metastases correlates with the number of 
removed lymph nodes overall at lymphadenectomy 
[14]. To the best of our knowledge data about limited 
(e.g. target lymphadenectomy) versus extended 
salvage-LND after PSMA-PET/CT do not exist yet. 
Adverse effects and morbidity of extended lymph 
node dissection should be considered before extended 
lymphadenectomy. </p>

<p>Material and Methods </p>

<p>Patients and salvage lymph node dissection </p>

<p>From 04/2014 to 11/2015, 30 consecutive 
patients at the stage of biochemical relapse (PSA &gt; 0.2 
ng/ml after radical prostatectomy and PSA &gt; 2n/ml 
above the nadir after primary radiotherapy) after 
primary therapy and the suspicion of LNM 
exclusively (without detectable bone or visceral 
metastases) on a PSMA-PET/CT underwent 
salvage-LND. Salvage-LND was performed on a 
compassionate-use basis in order to avoid systemic 
treatment. At least one pelvic or retroperitoneal 
suspected lymph node metastases had to be present 
on PSMA-PET/CT. Exclusion criteria were presence 
of bone or visceral metastases and continuation of 
adjuvant antihormonal therapy if administered after 
primary therapy. According to the presence of 
PET-positive lesions (pelvic, retroperitoneal or both), 
a bilateral template pelvic (common iliac vessels, 
external iliac vessels, obturator vessels, internal iliac 
vessels, presacral region), retroperitoneal (aortic 
bifurcation, aortal, caval, interaortocaval) or 
combined pelvic and retroperitoneal salvage-LND 
was performed (Supplementary Figure 1). Whenever 
intraoperative circumstances permitted, we adhered 
to this template and removed the nodal-fibro-fatty 
tissue. In some cases with additional atypical 
questionable suspected lesions on PET/CT (n=7 
patients) a salvage-LND was not denied. 
Consequently tumor tissue (nodal and non-nodal 
tumor tissue from atypical regions (one lesion each), 
positive on PET/CT (n=1 each: inguinal, piriformis 
muscle, duodenum region, seminal-vesicle, pillar of 
urinary bladder, n=2 mesorectal) were also resected at 
surgery. LNs from each subregion were collected 
separately at surgery. Follow-up after salvage-LND 
was mean 13.3 months (± SD 4.6) and median 12.1 
months. 
Of note, about 45-50 patients per year within the 
stage of biochemical relapse after primary therapy are 
considered for salvage lymph node dissection at our 
center. Salvage-LND is performed on half of those 
patients each year. The remaining patients are treated 
with target radiotherapy, antihormonal therapy or </p>

<p>Theranostics 2017, Vol. 7, Issue 6 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>active surveillance. The local ethics committee 
approved this retrospective data analysis (N°562/15). </p>

<p>PSMA-HBED-CC-PET/CT and imaging 
analysis </p>

<p>Glu-NH-CO-NH-Lys(Ahx)-HBED-CC 
was 
labeled with 68 GaCl 3 by using a fully automated 
synthesis module according to Good Laboratory 
Practice in combination with sterile single-use 
cassettes (Eckert &amp; Ziegler, Germany). The 
radiochemical purity of the final product was ≥97% 
and the decay-corrected yield was &gt;95%. The patients 
fasted for at least 4 hours before the intravenous 
injection of the radiopharmaceutical and were asked 
to void before starting the PET scan. Injected activity 
of 68 Ga-PSMA was mean / ± SD / median: 188.5 / 
34.6 / 198 MBq. At 1 hour post injection, underwent a 
whole body PET scan. Scans were either performed 
with a 64-slice GEMINI TF PET/CT or a 16-slice 
GEMINI TF BIG BORE PET/CT (both Philips 
Healthcare, USA), which provide virtually identical 
image 
characteristics. 
To 
further 
optimize 
comparability of the quantitative measurements both 
scanners were cross-calibrated. The spatial resolution 
of the reconstructed PET scan is about 7 mm (full 
width half maximum, FWHM) for both scanners. A 
contrast-enhanced diagnostic CT (120 kVp, 100 -400 
mAs, dose modulation) or a low-dose CT (120 kVp, 25 
mAs) for attenuation correction (depending on 
previous CT scans and contraindications) was 
performed. A PSMA-positive lesion was defined as 
focal tracer accumulation greater than normal or 
physiological local background activity. Two 
experienced nuclear medicine physicians (HCR, TB) 
evaluated all the PET/CT studies in consensus by 
side-by-side review of the co-registered PET and CT 
datasets using predefined PET window settings 
(inverted grey scale, SUV range: 0 to 5 g/ml). </p>

<p>Histopathology and immunohistochemistry 
(IHC) </p>

<p>All resected LNs (i.e., the entire LN in case of 
small LNs, one central slice in case of LNs &gt; 4 mm) 
were formalin-fixed and paraffin-embedded. The 
pathologist was not aware of the PET-findings and 
did not know the clinical estimation of the tissue from 
the surgeon. Histopathologic evaluation was 
performed by one pathologist on hematoxylin and 
eosin (H&amp;E) stained tissue slides. Maximum size 
(diameter) of each lymph node (whole lymph node) 
and metastatic deposits (tumor deposits in the lymph 
node) were measured (mm) in two dimensions. 
Anti-PSMA IHC was performed for each LNM: 
Heat-induced antigen retrieval 95°C for a period of 30 
min. in pH 6.1 using Dako antigen retrieval buffer </p>

<p>S1699 was followed by incubation with mouse 
anti-PSMA antibody (PSMA 3E6, IR089, Lot: 
10096665, Dako, USA) at room temperature for 60 
minutes and staining with EnVision TM Flex 
Visualization system (DAKO K8000) using the 
AutostainerPlus (DAKO, Hamburg, Germany). After 
washing using PBS and water, all slides were 
counterstained with hematoxylin, dehydrated in 
ascending alcohol concentrations and covered with 
TissueTek 4770 Cover slipping Film on TissueTek 
SCA. 
IHC for anti-PSMA in tumor deposits in LNM 
was evaluated as followed: percent of tumor-area 
positive for PSMA (regardless of the intensity of 
staining) and PSMA-intensity-staining: percent tumor 
area with score a: faint, barely staining (e.g. 
incomplete membrane staining), percent tumor area 
with score b: weak to moderate staining, percent 
tumor area with score c: strong -complete staining. 
For overall 110 LNM percent of tumor area positive 
for IHC-PSMA (regardless of the intensity score) and 
an area-weighted score (%score a*1 + %score b*2 + 
%score c*3) / 100)) was calculated in order to quantify 
the PSMA-expression. LNM (n=45) were identified 
for which we could establish a direct link from 
histopathology to PET (i.e. the LNMs from 
PET-positive subregions with a single LNM) such that 
we know that this LNM was detected. For those LNM 
a correlation of SUVmax with the area-weighted 
PSMA-score and a correlation of SUV max with the 
maximal diameter of the tumor deposits in the LNM 
were performed. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>All 
tumor 
tissue detected 
either 
by 
histopathology (n=110 LNM) or by clinical follow up 
(n=7 lesions) were included in the analysis (Table 1, 
Supplementary Table 1). In a few instances, it was 
impossible to resect a suspected LNM indicated by a 
positive PET finding. In these cases, a verification of 
the 
lesions 
was 
conducted 
by 
follow-up 
PSMA-PET/CT or by target radiotherapy to the 
lesions with PSA-decline respectively. In case of 
verification of a lesion by follow-up PSMA-PET/CT 
(progression of size/SUVmax [&gt;30%]) or therapy 
response (PSA-decline: at least 90% PSA reduction 
compared to PSA-level prior to radiotherapy) after 
target radiotherapy those lesions were assessed as 
true positive. Sensitivity, specificity, positive 
predictive value, negative predictive value and 
accuracy were analyzed at a main-region level (pelvic 
right/left, retroperitoneal) and per subregion 
(Supplementary Figure 1). At main-region and 
subregion levels, PET findings were compared with 
the presence of one or more LNM detected in the </p>

<p>Theranostics 2017, Vol. 7, Issue 6 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>histopathological work-up. Descriptive statistics were 
obtained by calculating means, standard deviations 
(SD) medians, interquartile ranges (IQR; 25%-75% 
percentile) and ranges. Continuous variables were 
compared with a two-sided unpaired Mann-Whitney 
test. 
In order to investigate the dependence of the 
detection of LNM on the size of tumor deposits in 
LNM, we selected LNM for which we could establish 
a direct link: the LNM from PET-positive subregions 
with a single LNM (LNM was detected), and the LNM 
from PET-negative subregions (LNM were not 
detected). 
However, 
to 
ensure 
sufficient 
comparability, we restricted the latter to subregions 
with maximally two LNMs. For these LNMs we 
determined longitudinal and short diameters of LNM 
and tumor deposits. We then modeled the detection of 
the LNM by PET as a function of the diameter using a 
logistic regression model in <rs id="software-1" type="software">STATA</rs> ® <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 14.1</rs>, 
which allows estimating thresholds corresponding to 
50% and 90% detection rates. The remaining statistics 
were obtained with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v19</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corp</rs>. Armonk, 
NY, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Patient characteristics and salvage lymph node 
dissection </p>

<p>30 patients underwent template salvage-LND 
because of nodal PCa-relapse. 19/30 (63%) were in the 
high-risk group at primary diagnosis according to the 
D`Amico-classification. Based on the results of 
PSMA-PET/CT, all patients had the suspicion of at 
least one LNM. Complications arising from 
salvage-LND according to Clavien-Dindo were 
noticed in 16/30 cases (53.3%): 62% grade I (10/16), 
0% grad II (0/16), 25% grade IIIa (4/16: lymphocele 
required secondary drainage) and 2% grade IIIb 
(2/16: renal congestion with ureter catheter insertion). 
No 
grade 
IV-V 
complications 
occurred. 
Representative maximum intensity projection (MIP) 
of two PSMA-PET/CTs and the corresponding PET 
and CT images prior to surgery are shown in Figure 
1A-1F. 
Detailed 
clinical 
information 
from 
30 
salvage-LNDs from 30 patients is listed in Table 1. 
Median PSA at salvage-LND was 1.7 ng/ml (IQR 0.8 -
2.9 ng/ml). Overall 965 LN have been resected, 
median 33.0 (IQR 25.5 -41.5) were removed per 
patient, whereof median 1.0 (IQR 1 -6.5) per patient 
turned out to be metastases (Table 1). 87/110 (79%) 
LNM were removed from true-positive subregions, 
23/110 (21%) LNM originated from false-negative 
subregions. </p>

<p>Table 1. Data from salvage lymph node dissections in 30 patients </p>

<p>Variable 
Value 
Patients with salvage-LNDs overall (n) 
30 
Primary therapy n (%) 
Radical prostatectomy 
29 (96.7%) 
Radiotherapy + LA 
1 (3.3%) 
Gleason-Score at primary PCa n (%) 
Gl 7 
12 (40%) 
Gl 8-10 
18 (60%) 
Initial PSA at primary therapy (ng/ml) 
Median / IQR / range 
9.6 / 6.1 -14.3 / 3.2 -40 
Time from primary therapy to first PSA-relapse 
(months) 
Median / IQR / range 
21.3 / 7.5 -46.7 / 2.9 -67.1 
Time from primary therapy to salvage-LND 
(years) 
Median / IQR / range 
5.2 / 3.4 -8.0 / 0.9 -13.7 
Time from PSMA-PET/CT to salvage-LND 
(months) 
Median / IQR / range 
2.3 / 1.6 -3.6 / 0.6 -9.6 
LN removed overall n (%) 
965 
LN free of tumor 
855 (88.6%) 
LNM 
110 (11.4%) 
Age at salvage-LND (years) 
Median / IQR / range 
65.7 / 61.6 -70.0 / 52.4 -70 
PSA at salvage-LND (ng/ml) 
Median / IQR / range 
1.7 / 0.8 -2.9 / 0.11 -12.16 
LN removed per patient 
Median / IQR / range 
33.0 / 25.5 -41.5 / 4 -61 
LNM removed per patient 
Median / IQR / range 
1.0 / 1 -6.5 / 0 -15 
Topography of salvage-LNDs with respect to 
main regions n / n (%) 
Pelvic LA R 
28 / 68 (41%) 
Pelvic LA L 
26 / 68 (38%) 
Retroperitoneal LA 
14 / 68 (21%) 
Regions of salvage-LNDs (in n = 30 men) (%) 
Pelvic L + R 
11 / 30 (37%) 
Pelvic L + R + retroperitoneal 
13 / 30 (43%) 
Pelvic L only 
2 / 30 (7%) 
Pelvic R only 
3 / 30 (10%) 
Pelvic R + retroperitoneal 
1 / 30 (3%) 
Main regions overall 
68 
With LNM n (%) 
36 (53%) 
Subregions overall 
289 
With LNM n (%) 
85 (29.4%) 
Number of LN removed per subregion 
Median / IQR / range 
3.0 / 2.0 -5.0 / 0 -11 
Number of LNM removed per subregion 
Median / IQR / range 
0.0 / 0.0 -0.0 / 0 -9 
Patients with histopathology confirmed LNM n 
(%) 
28 (93.3%) </p>

<p>Confirmation of true positive subregions n (%) 
Histopathology 
62 (90%) 
PET/CT follow-up 
4 (6%) 
PSA-decline after RT of lesion 
3 (4%) 
Patients with (additional) non-nodal PCa relapse 
n (%) 
6 / 30 (20%) </p>

<p>Subregions with (additional) non-nodal 2 PCa 
relapse n (%) 
9 / 289 (3.1%) </p>

<p>PSA-Nadir after salvage-LND (n/ml) (mean / ±SD 
/ median) 
0.59 / 1.0 / 0.1 </p>

<p>Median time to PSA-Nadir (months) 
3.2 
PSA-reduction at end of follow up (%) (mean / 
±SD / median) 
46.7 / 118.2 / 87.7 </p>

<p>1 aortic bifurcation, aortal, caval 
2 seminal vesicle (n=7), solid PCa-tissue in the region of the M. piriformis (n=1) and 
in a left obturator fossa (n=1). 
LN = lymph node, LNM = Lymph node metastases, R = right, L = left, LA = 
Lymphadenectomy, PSA = Prostate specific antigen 
Salvage-LND = salvage-lymph node dissection, PCa = Prostate cancer, RT = 
Radiotherapy, IQR = Interquartile range </p>

<p>Theranostics 2017, Vol. 7, Issue 6 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>For all 30 men with suspected LNM on PET/CT 
the presence of tumor could be confirmed, resulting in 
100% positive predictive value in a subject-based 
analysis. In 28/30 patients the presence of suspected 
nodal recurrence on PET/CT had been confirmed by 
histopathology. For 7/289 subregions from 5 patients 
the resection of the suspected LNM was not possible 
because 
of 
intraoperative 
difficulties 
and 
inaccessibility 
of 
the 
region 
of 
interest 
(Supplementary Table 1). For these 7 PET-positive 
lesions without histopathology, a verification by 
follow-up PSMA-PET/CT showed either clear 
progression (n = 4), or a PSA-remission after target 
radiotherapy of the lesion (n = 3) (Supplementary 
Table 1). Two representative cases of intraoperatively 
missed PET-positive LNM and their progression at 
follow-up PSMA-PET/CT are displayed in 
Supplementary Figure 2A, 2B. 
The distribution of the number of removed LN 
and histopathologically confirmed LNM is plotted 
according to the topography in supplemental Figure 
1A, 1B. Median 3.0 LN (IQR 2.0 -5.0) have been 
resected per subregion. In 6/30 patients (20%), 
respectively, 9/289 subregions (3.1%) non-nodal-
tissue has been resected: seminal vesicle (n = 7), solid 
PCa-tissue in the region of the piriformis muscle (n=1) 
and in a left obturator fossa (n = 1). </p>

<p>Diagnostic accuracy </p>

<p>Diagnostic accuracy of PSMA-PET/CT for 
detection of affected regions based on 68 main regions 
and 289 subregions in 30 patients is shown in Table 2. 
Only 3 PET-negative main regions and 16 
PET-negative subregions finally contained LNM (i.e., 
false-negative PET-findings). The majority of these 
false negative subregions (13/16) were in neighboring 
regions of true-positive subregions. 
On the main-region level, no false-positive 
PET-findings occurred. On subregion level, one case 
of a false-positive PET-scan was observed. The 
PSA-level of patients with additionally false-negative 
subregions (mean 4.3 ± 4.1, median 2.0 ng/ml, IQR 1.5 
-8.0) tended to be higher compared to the PSA level 
of men with true-positive subregions only (mean 1.8 
±1.6, median 1.4 ng/ml, IQR 0.7 -2.0, p = 0.07). </p>

<p>Effect of size and PSMA-expression in tumor 
deposits in LNM on PSMA-PET/CT results </p>

<p>Sizes of LNM and tumor deposits in LNM 
removed from true-positive or false-negative 
subregions are summarized in Table 3 and Figure 2A, 
2B. Median longitudinal diameters of whole LNM 
from true-positive or false-negative subregion were 
8.5 mm each (p = 0.565) (Figure 2A). In contrast, the 
median short axis diameter of whole LNM from 
false-negative subregions (3.8 mm) was significantly 
smaller than the median short axis diameter of whole 
LNM removed from true-positive subregions (5.8 
mm; p = 0.0075) (Table 3 and Figure 2A). For both, 
longitudinal and short axis diameters of tumor 
deposits in LNM, the median sizes (8.0 mm and 5.5 
mm, respectively) from true-positive subregion were 
significantly larger compared to tumor deposits in 
LNM removed from false-negative subregions (2.5 
mm and 1.3 mm, respectively; p &lt; 0.0001) (Table 3 and 
Figure 2B). Typically enlarged affected lymph nodes 
were almost fully penetrated with tumor tissue, 
sometimes with extracapsular growth, explaining the 
almost similar size of "whole lymph node metastases" 
and "tumor deposits". 
All 110 LNM visible on HE-staining were clearly 
positive at IHC for PSMA, meaning that no LNM had 
been missed due to a lack of PSMA-expression. 
Representative IHC for PSMA in 2 LNM removed 
from a true-positive and a false-negative subregion 
are shown in Figure 3A-3B. 
Data about the percent of tumor area in LNM 
positive for PSMA and information about the 
intensity of PSMA-expression in tumor deposits 
(area-weighted score) are shown in Table 4. 
Area-weighted score of PSMA-expression in LNM 
removed from true-positive and false-negative 
subregions is demonstrated in Table 4. For those LNM 
with a direct link from PET/CT to histopathology a 
correlation of SUVmax with the area-weighted 
PSMA-score and a correlation of SUV max with the 
maximal diameter of the tumor deposits in the LNM 
was performed (Table 4). </p>

<p>Table 2. Diagnostic accuracy of PSMA-PET/CT for detection of lymph node metastases </p>

<p>Sensitivity % 
Specificity % 
PPV % 
NPV % 
Accuracy % 
Main region-based 1 (n=68) 
93.2 (41/44) 
100 (24/24) 
100 (41/41) 
88.9 (24/27) 
95.6 (65/68) 
Subregion-based 2 (n=289) 
81.2 (69/85) 
99.5 (203/204) 
98.6 (69/70) 
92.7 (203/219) 
94.1 (272/289) </p>

<p>1 pelvic left/right, retroperitoneal 
2 common iliac, external iliac, obturator, internal iliac, presacral, aortic-bifurcation, aortal, caval </p>

<p>Theranostics 2017, Vol. 7, Issue 6 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>Figure 1. (A, B) Maximum intensity projections (MIP) of PSMA-PET/CT and the transversal PET (E, F) with the corresponding CT (C, D) images from patient N°1 with a single 
lymph node metastasis (initial PSA 7.43 ng/ml, Gleason-score 3+4 at radical prostatectomy in history, PSA 1.72 ng/ml at salvage-lymphadenectomy) and patient N°2 with multiple 
lymph node metastases (initial PSA 4.11 ng/ml, Gleason-score 4+5 at radical prostatectomy in history, PSA 1.78 ng/ml at salvage-lymphadenectomy). Red arrows indicate lymph 
node metastases. </p>

<p>Theranostics 2017, Vol. 7, Issue 6 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>Figure 2. Boxplots showing the sizes of whole lymph node metastases (A) and tumor deposits in lymph nodes (B) either removed from true-positive or false-negative 
subregions at surgery. Sizes are shown in two dimensions: median longitudinal and short-axis diameters (mm) of (A) lymph node metastases and (B) tumor deposits in lymph 
node metastases. Thick horizontal lines represent medians, crosses represent means, boxes show the 25 th and 75 th percentiles, whiskers represent the minimum and maximum 
values. n.s. p &gt; 0.05, ** p ≤ 0.01, *** p ≤ 0.001. (C) Detection rates of LNMs in dependence on the longitudinal diameter of tumor deposits in lymph node metastases (LNM). The 
estimated threshold to reach a detection rate of 90% (d90) is 6.0 mm. (D) Detection rates of LNMs in dependence on the short axis diameters of tumor deposits in lymph node 
metastases (LNM). The estimated threshold to reach a detection rate of 90% (d90) is 4.5 mm. </p>

<p>Table 3. Longitudinal and short diameter of 110 lymph node metastases and tumor deposits in LNM according to true-positive and 
false-negative subregions </p>

<p>Diameter (mm) 
LNM (n=87) out of 69 true-positive 
subregions 
LNM (n=23) out of 16 false-
negative subregions 
Mann-Whitney-test 
p-value 
Longitudinal diameter of LNM 
Mean ±SD / median / IQR 
11.8 ±11.2 / 8.5 / 6.0 -13.0 
9.7 ±6.8 / 8.5 / 4.0 -15.0 
0.565 
Short diameter of LNM 
Mean ±SD / median / IQR 
7.5 ±6.8 / 5.8 / 3.5 -8.4 
4.2 ±2.9 / 3.8 / 2.0 -6.0 
0.0075 
Longitudinal diameter of tumor deposits in LNM 
Mean ±SD / median / IQR 
10.8 ±11.5 / 8.0 / 5.0 -13.0 
4.6 ±5.2 / 2.5 / 1.1 -5.0 
&lt; 0.0001 
Short diameter of tumor deposits in LNM 
Mean ±SD / median / IQR 
7.2 ±7.0 / 5.5 / 3.0 -8.0 
2.5 ±2.9 / 1.3 / 0.6 -2.9 
&lt; 0.0001 
LNM = Lymph node metastases, IQR = Interquartile range </p>

<p>Theranostics 2017, Vol. 7, Issue 6 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>Figure 3. (A) Representative immunohistochemistry (IHC) for prostate-specific membrane antigen (PSMA) in lymph node metastases removed from a true-positive subregions 
(dark brown). (B) IHC for PSMA in small tumor deposits in lymph node metastases removed from false-negative subregions. </p>

<p>Table 4. Immunohistochemistry anti-PSMA in lymph node metastases </p>

<p>Overall n=110 LNM 
Percent of tumor area positive for PSMA-IHC in LNM 
Mean ±SD / median / IQR 
99.8 ±2.3 / 100 / 100 -100 
Area-weighted score* 
Mean ±SD / median / IQR 
2.4 ± 0.51 / 2.5 / 2.0 -3.0 
Area-weighted score* 
LNM (n=87) out of 69 true-positive 
subregions 
LNM (n=23) out of 16 false-
negative subregions 
Mann-Whitney-test 
p-value 
Mean ±SD / median / IQR 
2.4 ± 0.51 / 2.4 / 2.0 -2.9 
2.55 ± 0.46 / 2.6 / 2.1 -3.0 
0.2303 
Spearman correlation 
LNM with direct link from PET to histopathology (n=45)** 
SUVmax versus area-weighted-score PSMA-IHC 
r = 0.1536 
p = 0.3136 95%CI (-01.55 -0.435) 
Max. diameter tumor deposits (mm) versus SUVmax 
r = 0.6720 
p &lt; 0.0001 95%CI (0.464 -0.809) </p>

<p>LNM = lymph node metastases 
PMSA-IHC in tumor deposits in LNM: score a (faint / barely staining), score b (weak to moderate staining), score c (strong -complete staining). 
*Area-weighted-score = (a*1 + b*2 + c*3) / 100 
** LNMs from PET-positive subregions with a single LNM </p>

<p>Detection rates </p>

<p>For estimating the necessary tumor size to reach 
a detection rate of 50% and 90% we could include 45 
true-positive LNM from 45 PET-positive subregions 
and 23 false-negative LNM from 16 PET-negative 
subregions. The estimated longitudinal diameters of 
tumor deposits in LNM to reach a detection rate of 
50% and 90% are 3.7 mm and 6.0 mm, respectively 
(Figure 2C). The respective estimates for the short axis 
diameters of tumor deposits are 2.3 mm and 4.5 mm, 
respectively (Figure 2D). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Here we show that in men with biochemical 
PCa-relapse and a positive PSMA-PET/CT, PET/CT 
detects metastatic affected anatomical regions with 
excellent accuracy at a main region and at a 
subregion-level. Furthermore we were able to 
describe a necessary short diameter of tumor deposits 
in LNM to reach a detection rate of 50% and 90%. Our 
analysis was completed by the investigation of the 
size and the quantitative PSMA-expression (IHC) of 
tumor deposits in removed LNM. 
Compared to our subregion-based analysis, </p>

<p>Maurer et al. described a somewhat lower 
template-based sensitivity (68.3%), while specificity 
(99.1%) and overall accuracy (95.2%) were comparable 
[16]. The lower template-based sensitivity in that 
study can be explained by the fact that Maurer et al. 
included patients who were at primary stage and 
underwent radical prostatectomy and template pelvic 
lymph node dissection irrespective of the 
PSMA-PET/CT result. In contrast, a PSMA-PET/CT 
suspicious for LNM prompted salvage-LND in our 
patients, which explains the higher sensitivity 
observed in our study, as patients with biochemical 
recurrence but negative PSMA-PET/CT (i.e., 
false-negative) were excluded. Herlemann et al. 
reported a region-based (pelvic left, right, presacral, 
para-aortic) sensitivity and specificity of 84% and 
82%, respectively, for the detection of LNM in a 
summary analysis of 20 primary lymphadenectomies 
and 14 salvage-LNDs (in patients with positive 
PSMA-PET/CT) [17]. Again, the sensitivity can 
hardly be compared to the aforementioned studies. 
However, the reported lower specificity is clearly at 
variance to and not supported by the study of Maurer 
et al. and our group. E.g. lacking a PSMA-PET/CT 
follow-up is a clear difference between our and </p>

<p>Theranostics 2017, Vol. 7, Issue 6 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>previous published studies and might contribute to a 
reported lower specificity [17]. 
The very small number of false-positive cases in 
our analysis (no false-positive main region, one 
false-positive subregion) is outstanding. In the patient 
with the false-positive subregion the PSA level 
remained &lt; 0.03 ng/ml for 5.8 months after 
salvage-LND suggesting that it is unlikely that the 
false positive PET-finding was due to a LNM that was 
missed intraoperatively. The finding was located on 
the left presacral region. Thus, it is unlikely that it was 
caused by urinary retention (ureter), e.g. it may have 
been caused by a ganglion. The small number may be 
explained by the fact that we conducted a 
follow-up-PSMA-PET/CT 
and, 
or 
a 
target 
radiotherapy to the 7 subregions (from 5 patients) 
with a missing LNM yield but suspected LNM. Those 
7 lesions showed either a clear progression on 
PSMA-PET/CT or a clear remission (PSA-response) 
after target radiotherapy has been conducted. 
In case of any pelvic PET-positive LN (i.e., 
suspected LNM) a bilateral template pelvic-LND was 
sought, although this was, due to intraoperative 
difficulties or due to individual consideration of the 
surgical risk, only achieved for 24/30 patients. Of 
note, contralateral LNM would have been missed in 
3/24 of these patients by restriction to a unilateral, 
PET-guided salvage-LND as 3 PET-negative 
contralateral main regions finally contained LNM. 
Although this number (12.5%) might be low, from a 
surgeon's point of view a bilateral lymph node 
dissection is indispensable in order to remove all 
possible tumor bearing lymphatic tissue whenever 
possible. Based on sensitivities from PSMA-PET/CT 
for LNM-detection demonstrated in literature e.g. 
Maurer et al or Herlemann et al. (63.3% % and 84%) 
[16, 17] a unilateral salvage-LND seems to be 
questionable when it comes to achieving a maximum 
of tumor reduction. 
However, in order to minimize side effects of 
radical extended lymphadenectomy there may still be 
a request for target-lymphadenectomy based on 
subregions. In a subregion-based analysis 16 
PET-negative subregions from 11 patients contained 
finally 23 LNM. The majority of these subregions 
(13/16) were in neighboring regions of true-positive 
subregions. This data support the recommendation 
for an accurate salvage-LND not only in all 
PET-positive subregions but also in neighboring 
LN-subregions. Following this strategy, target 
PET-guided salvage-LND may still be a valuable 
option in patients with increased risk for surgical 
complications. However controlled randomized trials 
may clarify the role of and PSMA-PET/CT before 
extended or limited salvage-LND in patients with </p>

<p>removed pelvic and/or retroperitoneal metastases by 
investigating outcomes e.g. such as PSA-response or 
time to clinical progression. 
The estimates of diagnostic accuracy presented 
in this paper are biased by the fact that positive 
PET-findings were used to decide on whether the 
pelvic and/or retroperitoneal regions were covered. 
This implies that some false-negative (sub)-regions 
could not be identified as such. The impact on the 
sensitivity can be judged, if we assume that the 
observed negative predictive values apply also to the 
(sub)regions not covered. Consequently, among the 
22 main regions, which were not covered, we have to 
expect about 2.4 with a LNM, according the negative 
predictive value of 88.9 at the main region level. This 
would decrease sensitivity to 41/46.4 = 88.4%. Among 
the 420-289 = 131 subregions not covered, we have to 
expect about 9.5 with a LNM, according to the 
negative predictive value of 92.7%. This would 
decrease sensitivity to 69/94.5 = 73.0%. Our corrected 
sensitivity values come very close to findings from 
Herlemann et al. (for main regions) and Maurer et al. 
(for subregions). 
Men with additional false-negative subregions 
tended to show a higher PSA-value compared to those 
patients with true-positive subregions exclusively. 
Whether a high PSA-value may be a predictor of 
lower diagnostic performance of PSMA-PET/CT for 
detection of affected LN-regions (e.g., due to a higher 
likelihood 
of 
microscopic 
spread), 
once 
PSMA-PET/CT produced at least one positive finding 
remains speculative. 
Although in some series using choline-PET for 
detection of LNM the identification of even small 
lesions was possible [3, 4], to the best of our 
knowledge no established criteria exist to identify 
lymph node metastases smaller than e.g. 5mm on CT 
or MRT. We were able to show that the size of 
correctly identified LNM and tumor deposits in these 
LNM from PSMA-PET-positive subregions was 
significantly larger compared to the size of those that 
were missed by PET. Against the background that all 
LNM exhibited a very robust staining for PSMA at 
IHC, this indicates that tumor heterogeneity in our 
cohort of patients with biochemical recurrence and 
positive PSMA-PET/CT appears to be very low and 
that the tumor size seems to be the most important 
predictor for the detection of LNM by PSMA-PET/CT 
in this situation. By investigating only subregions 
with a single LNM, aforementioned observation 
allowed us to estimate the necessary short-axis tumor 
sizes to reach detection rates of 90% and 50% to be 
only ≥4.5 mm and 2.3 mm, respectively. This 
impressively underlines the fact that lesions of small 
size (i.e., well below the scanner spatial resolution of </p>

<p>Theranostics 2017, Vol. 7, Issue 6 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>about 6-7 mm) can nevertheless be detected with high 
sensitivity if target expression is high. 
It is obvious that intraoperative locating of very 
small lymph nodes by the surgeon using optical and 
manual (palpation) control is very challenging. 
Hence, 
further 
developments 
to 
improve 
intraoperative LNM detection are needed. In line with 
the findings of the present study, the development of 
intraoperative probes that target PSMA-expression on 
PCa manifestations may be particularly promising 
(e.g. using gamma-emitters or fluorescent peptides). 
The introduction of "PSMA-radioguided surgery" 
might improve the capability of removing all affected 
nodal tissue [22, 23]. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>Since only patients with known biochemical 
recurrence and suspicious foci on PSMA-PET/CT 
have been included into the present study, a 
patient-based analysis of PSMA-PET sensitivity, 
specificity and accuracy is not possible. Likewise, it is 
important to note that the results of the present study 
only apply to the selected population of patients with 
biochemical 
recurrence 
and 
PSMA-PET/CT 
suggestive of LNM. The performance will be different 
if salvage-LND is performed on patients with a 
negative PSMA-PET/CT, which, however, is not in 
line with clinical practice. Because of intraoperative 
difficulties reaching the region of interest (LNM), a 
deviation from the template was unavoidable in a few 
cases. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In men with biochemical PCa-relapse and 
positive PSMA-PET/CT, PET/CT detects metastatic 
affected anatomical regions with high accuracy at a 
main-region and at a subregion-level. If the decision 
for salvage-LND is prompted by a positive 
PSMA-PET/CT, the size of metastases is crucial for 
accurate detection of affected regions. All LNM 
showed 
a 
clear 
PSMA-expression 
in 
the 
immunohistochemistry. Further studies need to 
investigate how to translate the high anatomical 
correlation observed between PET/CT and surgical 
findings into optimal approaches to target 
salvage-LND. If a target salvage-LND is intended the 
neighboring LN-subregions of positive subregions -
potentially harboring small false-negative LNM -
should also be considered. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Supplementary figures and tables. 
http://www.thno.org/v07p1770s1.pdf </p>

<p>Competing Interests </p>

<p>PTM received financial support for on-going 
research by GE and Piramal Imaging unrelated to the 
present study. CAJ, VD, TB, KS, WSS, UW, HCR, WV 
have no financial disclosures. </p>



<p>Theranostics 2017, Vol. 7, Issue 6 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>





</text></tei>