<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5001609" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Cotranslational degradation of polypeptide nascent 
chains plays a critical role in quality control of pro-
tein synthesis and the rescue of stalled ribosomes. 
In eukaryotes, ribosome stalling triggers release of 
60S subunits with attached nascent polypeptides, 
which undergo ubiquitination by the E3 ligase Ltn1 
and proteasomal degradation facilitated by the AT-
Pase Cdc48. However, the identity of factors acting 
upstream in this process is less clear. Here, we exam-
ined how the canonical release factors Sup45-Sup35 
(eRF1-eRF3) and their paralogs Dom34-Hbs1 affect 
the total population of ubiquitinated nascent chains 
associated with yeast ribosomes. We found that 
the availability of the functional release factor com-
plex Sup45-Sup35 strongly influences the amount 
of ubiquitinated polypeptides associated with 60S ri-
bosomal subunits, while Dom34-Hbs1 generate 60S-
associated peptidyl-tRNAs that constitute a relatively 
minor fraction of Ltn1 substrates. These results un-
cover two separate pathways that target nascent 
polypeptides for Ltn1-Cdc48-mediated degradation 
and suggest that in addition to canonical termina-
tion on stop codons, eukaryotic release factors con-
tribute to cotranslational protein quality control. </p>

<p>Protein quality control (QC) is essential for the production 
of a functional proteome. Inefficient or dysfunctional QC 
may cause accumulation of aberrant and aggregation-prone 
polypeptides, a condition implicated in a wide range of 
human disorders including neurodegenerative diseases and 
cancer (reviewed in (1)). Recent studies in eukaryotic cells 
have demonstrated that aberrant and misfolded polypeptide 
nascent chains (NCs) can undergo modification with ubiq-
uitin while still attached to the ribosome, thereby initiating </p>

<p>the degradation of the aberrant polypeptides by the pro-
teasome (2-5). Given that as much as 6-15% of all newly 
generated polypeptides in eukaryotic cells fail to fold or as-
semble properly (3,5), the systems responsible for cotrans-
lational QC are clearly important for maintaining protein 
homeostasis. 
Currently, cotranslational degradation of NCs is best un-
derstood in the situations when ribosomes stall during elon-
gation. Previous studies indicated that a complex of the 
release-like factors Dom34-Hbs1 (also known as Pelota-
Hbs1 in mammalian cells) acts in concert with the recycling 
factor Rli1 (ABCE1 in mammals) to split stalled ribosomes 
into subunits (6-9). After dissociation from 40S, 60S sub-
units with associated NCs (60S·NC complexes) are recog-
nized by the ribosome quality control (RQC) complex con-
sisting of Ltn1, Rqc1 and Rqc2 (also known as Tae2) (2,10). 
Rqc2 binds to the intersubunit surface, prevents reassocia-
tion of the ribosomal subunits (11-13), signals translation 
stress to the heat shock factor Hsf1 (10,13), and promotes 
activity of the E3 ligase Ltn1 (12). Ltn1 (also known as Rkr1 
in yeast and Listerin in mammals) modifies NCs in 60S·NC 
complexes with polyubiquitin chains, leading to the recruit-
ment of the ubiquitin-selective chaperone complex Cdc48-
Npl4-Ufd1 (2,4,10,14,15). It is currently believed that be-
cause of a steric clash with the 40S subunit, Ltn1 cannot 
bind to translating ribosomes, which likely serves to prevent 
ubiquitination of NCs by Ltn1 during elongation (11,12). 
The AAA family ATPase Cdc48 assists the clearance of the 
60S-associated polypeptides, presumably by supplying me-
chanical force for the extraction of NCs and their presenta-
tion to the proteasome. 
The RQC system is conserved in all eukaryotes and de-
fects in its components have been linked to neurodegener-
ation in mice (16,17). The nature of the RQC substrates in 
the cell, however, remains an open question (18). The pio-
neering work by the Inada laboratory (19,20) demonstrated 
ubiquitin-proteasome-mediated degradation of NCs utiliz-
ing poly(Lys)-and poly(Arg)-containing model substrates, 
which were later investigated in conjunction with the RQC 
system (2,4,10,14). However, ribosomal stalling can occur in </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 856 566 6907; Fax: +1 856 566 2881; Email: shcherna@rowan.edu </p>

<p>C The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 14 6841 </p>

<p>many other situations, including impaired cotranslational 
protein folding, the presence of rare codons and stable sec-
ondary structures within mRNA (3,5,21,22). Recent evi-
dence indeed points to additional types of translational 
stalling contributing endogenous substrates to the RQC 
pathway (23,24). Additionally, the translation factors that 
generate RQC substrates are not completely understood. 
Dom34-Hbs1 play a pivotal role in splitting non-translating 
80S ribosomes containing Stm1 in place of the mRNA (25) 
and have been shown to operate efficiently on ribosomal 
complexes with a short mRNA length relative to the ribo-
some's P-site, such as ribosomes stalled at the 3 end of trun-
cated mRNA and some nonstop messages (7,8,26). More-
over, aberrant nonstop polypeptides were observed to be 
stabilized by an ltn1Δ deletion in the absence of Dom34 
(27). Thus, the contribution of Dom34-Hbs1 to cotransla-
tional QC on a global scale remains unclear. Intriguingly, 
canonical release factors were recently reported to medi-
ate release of ribosomes on polylysine-encoding segments 
of mRNA (28), although whether this contributes to degra-
dation of other aberrant translation products is currently 
unknown. Here, we addressed the role of factors that oper-
ate upstream of Ltn1 ubiquitination in ribosome-associated 
degradation by investigating the global pattern of modifica-
tion of distinct ribosomal species with ubiquitin. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Yeast strains and media </p>

<p>We used standard recipes for YPDA (1% yeast extract, 2% 
peptone, 2% dextrose, 10 mg/l adenine), rich media without 
dextrose (1% yeast extract, 2% peptone, 10 mg/l adenine) 
and synthetic glucose or galactose-containing media. All 
strains used in this study are listed in Supplemental Table 
S1. To generate deletion strains, his5+ or LEU2 disruption 
cassettes were integrated via homologous recombination at 
the targeted genomic loci using standard PCR-based tech-
niques (29). Genomic integration of the disruption cassettes 
was verified by PCR using two sets of primers. One set in-
cluded a forward primer annealing ∼100 bp upstream of the 
integration site and a reverse primer annealing within the 
LEU2 or his5+ cassettes. The second set included primers 
annealing upstream and downstream of the integration site 
to discriminate between intact genes and the disruption cas-
settes. Sequences of all primers used in this study are avail-
able upon request. 
All strains used in this study carry the prion form of the 
Rnq1 protein, [PIN 
+ ], which promotes formation of Sup35 
aggregates. The [psi 
− PIN 
+ ] strain 74-D694 (30), also des-
ignated as OT60 (31), contains a UGA allele of the ADE1 
gene, ade1-14. The strain GT181 was selected as a sponta-
neous Ade 
+ derivative of OT60 on -Ade medium and de-
termined to bear a mutant allele of the SUP35 gene (desig-
nated sup35-R15) in a test for allelism using tester strains 66-
8A-P3532 (MATα ade1-14 his7-1 met13-A1 sup45 [rho 
− ]) 
and 68-8A-P3532 (MATα ade1-14 his7-1 met13-A1 sup35), 
kindly provided by S.G. Inge-Vechtomov (St. Petersburg 
State University, Russia). PCR amplification and sequenc-
ing of the sup35-R15 allele showed a single G-to-T substitu-
tion at nucleotide position 1615 (relative to the start of the 
Sup35 coding sequence), which created a premature stop </p>

<p>codon instead of codon 535 in the SUP35 ORF. The sup35-
R15 allele in the strain GT181 causes temperature sensitiv-
ity of growth on complete medium, with the permissive tem-
perature of 25 
• C and non-permissive temperature of 30 
• C 
and above. Growth defects observed at 30 
• C were rescued 
by ectopic expression of the Sup35-N protein, which lacks 
the QN-rich N-terminal prion domain but retains the trans-
lation termination activity. </p>

<p>Antibodies and chemicals </p>

<p>The polyclonal anti-FLAG antibodies were purchased 
from Sigma (F7425); the anti-ubiquitin antibodies (clone 
P4G7-H11) were from Stressgen (SPA-203); the anti-Rpl3 
(ScRPL3) and anti-␣-tubulin (12G10) antibodies were from 
the Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, University of 
Iowa; anti-Rps14 antibodies were kindly provided by John 
Woolford, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh; anti-
Sup35C antibodies were kindly provided by D. Bedwell, 
University of Alabama, Birmingham. Doxycycline (Fron-
tier Scientific, cat. # D10056) was used at a final concen-
tration of 10 g/ml. Cycloheximide (CHX) was purchased 
from Sigma (cat. # 01810) and used at 100 g/ml, hy-
gromycin B (Calbiochem cat. # 400053) was used at 100 
g/ml. </p>

<p>Plasmids </p>

<p>Full-length SUP35 was amplified by PCR from genomic 
yeast DNA with primers complementary to the 5 and 3 
ends of the SUP35 coding sequence. To generate the N 
truncation mutant (lacking the first 154 amino acids), the 
forward (5 ) primer was chosen to anneal 462 bp down-
stream of the start codon of SUP35. To generate FLAG-
tagged constructs of Sup35, we used a reverse (3 ) primer 
containing a sequence that encoded the FLAG tag. PCR 
products were digested with BamHI and XbaI and cloned 
into BamHI and XbaI sites of the pLA1 vector (32). </p>

<p>Sucrose gradient analysis </p>

<p>Polysomes were prepared essentially as described previously 
(33). Cells were treated with CHX prior to harvesting, pel-
leted by centrifugation, washed twice in ice-cold lysis buffer 
A (100 mM NaCl, 3 mM MgCl 2 , 10 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.4, 
100 g/ml CHX, 200 g/ml heparin and 100 M PMSF). 
Cells were lysed in the lysis buffer by 8-10 cycles of 30 s 
vortexing followed by 30 sec incubation on ice in the pres-
ence of glass beads at 4 
• C. An aliquot corresponding to 
50 OD 260 units of the clarified lysate was loaded onto 15-
45% (w/v) or 15-42% (w/v) sucrose gradients prepared in 
70 mM NH 4 Cl, 4 mM MgCl 2 and 10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 
7.4). The volume of each gradient was 11 ml. Gradients were 
centrifuged at 188 000 × g at 4 
• C for 4 h 15 min (Beckman 
SW41Ti rotor, 36,000 rpm) and fractionated into 14 frac-
tions (∼0.78 ml each) for 15-45% gradients or into 28 frac-
tions (∼0.39 ml each) for 15-42% gradients using a Beck-
man fraction recovery system connected to an EM-1 UV 
monitor (Bio-Rad). </p>



<p>Protein analysis </p>

<p>To analyze proteins co-sedimented with various fractions of 
the sucrose gradients, each fraction was incubated with 0.1 
mg/ml BSA and 10% TCA on ice for 30 min. Proteins were 
pelleted by centrifugation at 4 
• C for 20 min, pellets were 
washed once with ethanol and once with acetone, air-dried 
and resuspended in 1× SDS-PAGE loading buffer. Proteins 
were resolved in 10% SDS-polyacrylamide gels, transferred 
onto nitrocellulose membranes, and stained with Ponceau 
S prior to immunodetection. Each membrane used for de-
tection of ubiquitinated species was cut at ∼60 kDa and the 
lower part incubated with anti-Rpl3 antibodies to monitor 
60S subunit distribution on the gradients. All gradient anal-
yses shown in this paper were repeated a minimum of three 
times. </p>

<p>RNA analysis </p>

<p>To analyze RNA present in sucrose gradient fractions, each 
fraction was treated with 100 g/ml proteinase K (Roche) 
in the presence of 1% SDS and 10 mM EDTA for 30 
min at 42 
• C, followed by phenol/chloroform extraction 
and ethanol precipitation. RNA pellets were resuspended 
in formamide and separated on 1.5% agarose gels contain-
ing 1.3% formaldehyde (34). RNA was transferred to ny-
lon membranes (Hybond N, GE Biosciences) and RNA 
was visualized by methylene blue staining. Individual RNA 
species were detected by Northern hybridizations using 
32 P-
labeled oligonucleotide probes as described (35). Sequences 
of hybridization probes used in this study are listed in Sup-
plemental Table S2. Hybridizations were analyzed using a 
Typhoon 9200 PhosphorImager and <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GE Biosciences)</rs>). </p>

<p>Peptidyl-tRNA analysis </p>

<p>The presence of peptidyl-tRNA on 60S subunits was an-
alyzed by acid-urea gel electrophoresis as described previ-
ously (36). First, the 60S fraction separated on a 15-45% 
sucrose gradient was subjected to ultracentrifugation at 67 
000 × g for 90 min at 4 
• C (Beckman TLA-55 rotor, 55 000 
rpm). The pelleted subunits were resuspended in 8 M urea, 
10 mM sodium acetate (pH 5.0), 1 mM EDTA, 0.02% bro-
mophenol blue and 0.03% xylene cyanol and loaded onto 
0.75 mm, 10 × 10 cm 8% polyacrylamide gels containing 8 
M urea. Gels were run at 4 
• C for 5 h at 100 V in 100 mM 
sodium acetate (pH 5.0) and 1 mM EDTA. RNA was trans-
ferred to nylon membranes in 0.5× TBE for 20 min at 10 V 
using a Trans-blot SD semi-dry apparatus (Bio-Rad), with 
subsequent staining and hybridizations done as described 
above. </p>

<p>SDD-AGE (semi-denaturating detergent agarose gel elec-
trophoresis) </p>

<p>The distribution of the Sup35 prion polymers by size was 
determined by using SDD-AGE, as described previously 
(37) with some modifications (38). Crude cell extracts were 
prepared by vortexing cells with glass beads. Total lysates 
were cleared from cell debris by centrifugation at 3000 rpm </p>

<p>for 2 min, 50 g of total protein was incubated in the sam-
ple buffer (0.5× TAE, 2% SDS, 5% glycerol, 0.025% bro-
mophenol blue) for 5 min at 37 
• C, and resolved on a 1.8% 
agarose gel in 1× TAE, 0.1% SDS, followed by wet transfer 
to a nitrocellulose membrane. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Gradient analysis of ubiquitinated polypeptides associated 
with ribosomes in Cdc48-depleted cells </p>

<p>To examine how endogenous targets of cotranslational pro-
tein QC are distributed among different subpopulations of 
ribosomes in yeast cells, we fractionated cytoplasmic lysates 
by sedimentation through sucrose gradients. We observed 
a smear of ubiquitinated translation products in fractions 
containing polysomes and 80S monosomes in wild-type 
cells (Figure 1A, Supplementary Figure S1A), consistent 
with the previously described ubiquitination of ribosome-
associated NCs (3,4). Previous studies have shown that loss 
of Cdc48 function increases accumulation of ubiquitinated 
NCs associated with ribosomes (2-4). To better define this 
effect, we analyzed yeast strains in which CDC48 is placed 
under the control of a tetracycline-regulatable promoter 
(P TET-O7 -CDC48) (39). Depletion of Cdc48 by addition of 
doxycycline (Dox) to growing yeast cultures significantly in-
creased the intensity of the ubiquitin signal in these cells 
(Figure 1B, Supplementary Figure S1A-D), as expected 
from stabilization of ubiquitinated NCs that normally un-
dergo Cdc48-assisted degradation by the proteasome (4). 
The ubiquitin signal in Cdc48-depleted cells was mainly 
concentrated in fractions 3-5 (Figure 1B), corresponding to 
the peaks of 60S subunits (fractions 3 and 4) and 80S mono-
somes (fractions 4 and 5). In this and other experiments, the 
equivalent separation of ribosomal fractions on gradients 
was controlled by comparing alignment of A 260 traces of the 
gradients, gel analysis of rRNA from the same fractions that 
were used for protein isolation, Ponceau S staining to con-
trol protein transfer, and probing with antibodies against ri-
bosomal protein Rpl3 (Supplementary Figure S1A). When 
it was necessary to compare absolute levels of ubiquitinated 
species between different strains, we analyzed fractions side 
by side on the same gel to rule out variations between pro-
cessing of individual membranes (Supplementary Figure 
S1D). Notably, the increase in ubiquitination of the 80S 
fraction was not due to redistribution of ribosomes from 
polysomes to the 80S monosome form in Cdc48-depleted 
cells, as shift of wild-type cells to medium lacking glucose (a 
condition known to inhibit translation initiation) resulted 
in elevated 80S levels comparable to those in Dox-treated 
P TET-O7 -CDC48 cells, but did not cause accumulation of 
polyubiquitinated peptides in the 60S-80S fractions (Sup-
plementary Figure S1E). Thus, Cdc48 depletion leads to in-
creased accumulation of ubiquitinated polypeptides associ-
ated predominantly with 60S and 80S ribosomes. 
We next examined the distribution of ubiquitin-
conjugated species in the 60S-80S fractions of P TET-O7 -
CDC48 strains containing additional deletions in genes 
of E3 ligases implicated in cotranslational QC. Consistent 
with previous findings obtained with model substrates 
(4,14,15,40), an ltn1Δ deletion completely abrogated the 
accumulation of ubiquitin-modified NCs in fractions that </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 14 6843 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Cdc48 and ubiquitin ligases affect the distribution pattern of ribosome-associated ubiquitinated species. Sucrose gradient sedimentation analysis 
of ribosomes extracted from the wild-type RS1158 strain (A) and its derivative strain harboring a tetracycline-repressible P TET-O7 -CDC48 allele (B). Cells 
were grown in the presence of doxycycline (Dox) for 20 h. Cell lysates were centrifuged through 15%-45% sucrose gradients and fractionated with the 
continuous measurement of absorbance at 254 nm to visualize ribosomal peaks. Proteins isolated from individual fractions were separated on 10% SDS-
acrylamide gels and the same membrane was probed with anti-ubiquitin (top) and anti-Rpl3 (bottom) antibodies. (C) and (D) The same analysis performed 
in P TET-O7 -CDC48 cells lacking either LTN1 or NOT4. All gradients were run at least five times, representative blots are shown; see Supplemental Figure 
S1 for additional controls. (E) Hygromycin B (HygB) treatment induces accumulation of Ltn1-ubiquitinated 60S products. Where indicated, cells were 
treated with 100 g/mL hygromycin for 2 h. Gradient fractions 2-6 were separated on the same gel for a better comparison of total ubiqutination levels. 
(F) Lack of LTN1 makes cells hypersensitive to hygromycin. Five-fold dilutions of wild-type B4741 (WT) and ltn1Δ strains were grown on plates without 
antibiotic or with 100 g/ml hygromycin for 3 days at 30 • C. </p>



<p>contained free 60S subunits, but not in the 80S fraction 
(Figure 1C). In contrast, a Cdc48-depleted strain lacking 
Not4, part of the Ccr4-Not deadenylase complex reported 
to ubiquitinate polypeptides associated with stalled ri-
bosomes (19,27), showed a diminished intensity of the 
ubiquitin signal in the 80S fraction, whereas accumulation 
of ubiquitinated products in the 60S fraction remained 
constitutively high (Figure 1D). These results support the 
notion (2,10,14,15) that Ltn1 is a primary, and possibly 
unique, E3 ligase responsible for ubiquitin tagging of 
the 60S-associated NCs, a process necessary for Cdc48 
recruitment and polypeptide degradation. 
To further investigate whether the observed accumulation 
of 60S-associated products ubiquitinated by Ltn1 is related 
to aberrant polypeptide synthesis during translation, we 
treated cells for 2 h with hygromycin B, an aminoglycoside 
that causes decoding errors, stop codon readthrough and 
ribosomal stalling (41-43). In wild-type cells, hygromycin 
treatment significantly increased the amount of polyubiq-
uitinated products present in the 60S-80S fractions (Fig-
ure 1E). Similarly to P TET-O7 -CDC48 ltn1Δ cells, deletion of 
LTN1 abrogated the accumulation of ubiquitinated prod-
ucts in the 60S, but not 80S fraction in the hygromycin-
treated cells (Figure 1E). Consistent with a role of Ltn1 
in resolving translation errors caused by hygromycin, ltn1Δ 
cells are hypersensitive to this antibiotic (Figure 1F). These 
results support the idea that the Ltn1-Cdc48-mediated QC 
mechanism can capture a variety of defective translational 
products that remain associated with the large ribosomal 
subunit after splitting of the ribosome. </p>

<p>Dom34 has little impact on the levels of ubiquitinated NCs </p>

<p>Having found that gradient analysis can differentiate Ltn1-
modified NCs from those ubiquitinated through Ltn1-
independent mechanisms, we sought to probe the upstream 
events that generate Ltn1 substrates. Splitting of ribosomal 
subunits during ribosome-associated QC in previous stud-
ies was attributed to the complex of the proteins Dom34 
and Hbs1. Specifically, Dom34-Hbs1 was shown to pro-
mote separation of ribosomal subunits and drop-off of 
short peptidyl-tRNAs in an in vitro yeast translation sys-
tem (6). Efficient splitting of ribosomes stalled on trun-
cated mRNA sequences has been also demonstrated for 
the mammalian homologs of Dom34-Hbs1, Pelota-Hbs1 
(7,40). However, the extent to which Dom34-Hbs1 con-
tribute to the total pool of ubiquitinated NCs in cells, and 
specifically to Ltn1 substrates, is not known. To address this, 
we made a P TET-O7 -CDC48 dom34Δ strain and analyzed the 
distribution of ubiquitinated NCs in ribosomal fractions af-
ter Cdc48 depletion. Surprisingly, deletion of DOM34 had 
only a modest effect on the relative level and distribution of 
ubiquitin conjugates, with significant accumulation still ob-
served in the 60S fraction (Figure 2, middle; Supplementary 
Figure S2A). Introduction of an additional ltn1Δ deletion 
into the P TET-O7 -CDC48 dom34Δ strain abolished accumu-
lation of the ubiquitin signal in the 60S fraction, confirm-
ing that ubiquitination of the 60S·NC complexes in these 
cells was still dependent on Ltn1 (Figure 2, right; Supple-
mentary Figure S2A). The unexpectedly minor impact of 
Dom34 on the accumulation of ubiquitinated 60S·NC com-</p>

<p>plexes raised the possibility that additional factors may ex-
ist in cells to effect the splitting of ribosomes and generate 
substrates for the Ltn1-Cdc48 pathway. </p>

<p>Canonical release factors are responsible for generating a ma-
jor fraction of Ltn1-modified NCs </p>

<p>Dom34 and Hbs1 are structurally related to the canonical 
release factors Sup45 and Sup35 (termed eRF1 and eRF3 
in other species). Recently, the Sup45-Sup35 complex has 
been shown to mediate premature translation termination 
on polylysine-containing luciferase reporters (28), prompt-
ing us to test the role of these factors in the generation of 
substrates for Ltn1 and Cdc48. We had to use partial de-
pletion strategies since both SUP35 and SUP45 are essen-
tial. First, we used an established approach based on the 
partial inactivation of the endogenous Sup45-Sup35 com-
plex via sequestration into prion-like aggregates of Sup35. 
These aggregates are formed with high efficiency when full-
sized Sup35 is overproduced in cells bearing a prion form 
of another protein, Rnq1 (44-48). To generate Sup35 ag-
gregates, we first overexpressed full-length Sup35 from the 
GAL1 promoter in P TET-O7 -CDC48 cells. As a control, we 
used overexpression of Sup35-N that lacks the N-terminal 
prion-domain responsible for aggregate formation but re-
tains the ability to interact with Sup45 and act as a trans-
lation termination factor (49,50). As expected, galactose-
induced expression of the full-length Sup35 led to the ef-
ficient formation of the high molecular weight aggregates 
of Sup35 (Figure 3A). Analysis of the ribosomal fractions 
in these cells (Figure 3B, middle; Supplementary Figure 
S2B) revealed a significant drop in the level of ubiquitinated 
products in the 60S fraction 3 and an altered accumula-
tion pattern in the 60/80S fraction 4 and 80S fraction 5. 
In the control cells expressing Sup35-N, aggregates failed 
to form (Figure 3A) and the distribution of the ubiquiti-
nated species between the 60S and 80S fractions was sim-
ilar to the empty-vector control (Figure 3B, right and left; 
Supplementary Figure S2B). To better understand the pat-
tern of ubiquitination in the intermediate fraction 4, which 
contains both 60S and 80S ribosomes, we lowered concen-
tration of sucrose in gradients and collected fractions of a 
smaller volume (Figure 3C). The improved separation of 
the 60S and 80S fractions confirmed a significantly low-
ered amount of 60S-associated ubiquitinated polypeptides 
in cells with aggregated Sup35 (compare fractions 4 and 5 
between different panels in Figure 3C). 
To exclude the possibility that the release factors are 
involved in the generation of ubiquitinated NCs only in 
cells with deficient Cdc48 function, we overexpressed full-
length Sup35 in a strain carrying wild-type CDC48 (Sup-
plementary Figure S2C). Detection of ubiquitinated species 
in these cells required a much longer exposure of the blots 
compared to the P TET-O7 -CDC48 cells used above, consis-
tent with a lower overall abundance of ubiquitinated NCs 
in cells with normal Cdc48 function. Nonetheless, we ob-
served a similar pattern of the specific reduction in the 60S-
associated ubiquitin signal (Supplementary Figure S2D). 
To test the role of the release factors in the generation 
of Ltn1-Cdc48 substrates through a different approach, we 
next created a strain carrying a hypomorphic sup35 allele </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 14 6845 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Deficiency in Dom34 does not significantly affect levels of ubiquitinated 60S·NCs. Lysates prepared from the indicated strains grown in the 
presence of Dox for 20 h to deplete Cdc48 were separated on 15-45% sucrose gradients and analyzed as described in Figure 1. Representative blots are 
shown. Experiment was repeated four times, see Supplemental Figure S2A for another experimental repeat with samples separated on one gel. </p>

<p>(see Materials and Methods for details). Reduced activity of 
Sup35 in the newly generated sup35-R15 strain resulted in 
a temperature sensitive growth phenotype (Supplementary 
Figure S3) that was rescued by expression of the translation-
ally active Sup35-N (Figure 4A). We examined the distri-
bution of ubiquitinated NCs across ribosomal fractions in 
the sup35-R15 strain and its parental wild-type strain after 
shifting these cells from 25 
• C to a semi-permissive temper-
ature (30 
• C) for 4 h (Figure 4B). We found that the ubiqui-
tin signal in the 60S fraction was greatly reduced compared 
to wild-type cells, although these cells continued to display 
the robust accumulation of ubiquitinated 80S complexes, re-
sembling the effect of the ltn1Δ deletion (compare Figure 
4B, right with Figure 1C). The accumulation of ubiquiti-
nated products in the 60S fraction was restored when the 
translationally competent Sup35-N was supplied by ex-
pression from a plasmid (Figure 4C). Taken together, these 
results suggest that the translational activity of the canoni-
cal release factors gives rise to a substantial portion of Ltn1-
modified NCs. </p>

<p>Accumulation of ubiquitinated 60S-NCs in a tRNA-free form </p>

<p>During canonical translation termination, the release fac-
tor complex Sup45-Sup35 promotes the cleavage of tRNAs 
from NCs (51,52). In contrast, the splitting of ribosomal 
subunits by the release-like factors Dom34-Hbs1 occurs 
without accompanying peptidyl-tRNA hydrolysis (6) since 
Dom34 lacks the GGQ motif required for catalysis (53,54). 
Previous biochemical and cryo-electron microscopy stud-
ies obtained with model substrates revealed the presence of 
peptidyl-tRNA in 60S subunits in cells harboring either a 
temperature-sensitive cdc48-3 allele (4) or catalytically in-
active Ltn1 (11,13). Recent studies have shown that the ex-
posed tRNA moiety in tRNA-linked 60S·NC species can 
interact with Rqc2 (11,13), which, along with Ltn1, is part 
of the RQC complex (2,10). Considering the possibility that 
Sup45-Sup35 can also generate Ltn1 substrates (Figures 3 
and 4), we wondered to what extent peptidyl-tRNAs con-
tribute to the total pool of the ubiquitinated species asso-
ciating with 60S ribosomal complexes. To address this, we 
examined sedimentation profiles of tRNAs after treating in-
dividual ribosome-containing gradient fractions with pro-</p>

<p>teinase K, which hydrolyzes the ester bond between tRNAs 
and the conjugated peptides (55). We determined the rela-
tive amounts of four different elongator tRNAs (tRNA 
Glu , 
tRNA 
Leu , tRNA 
Val , tRNA 
Thr ) in each gradient fraction by 
quantitative northern hybridizations. By comparing tRNA 
distributions in different strains (Figure 5A-B, Supplemen-
tary Figure S4), we were able to observe a decrease in elon-
gator tRNA amounts associated with polysomes (fractions 
6-10) after Cdc48 depletion, expected from partially re-
pressed translation in these cells, and increase in polysome-
associated tRNAs in dom34Δ cells, as was previously de-
scribed (56). Remarkably, the tRNA distribution data in-
dicated a significant increase in the amount of elongator 
tRNAs in the 60S fraction 3 in Cdc48-depleted cells rela-
tive to wild-type cells (Figure 5B, Wilcoxon rank sum test, 
P = 2 × 10 
−4 ) and in fraction 4 containing 60S and 80S 
(Wilcoxon rank sum test, P = 4 × 10 
−4 ). In contrast to the 
elongator tRNA species, we did not observe a similar en-
richment in the parallel analysis of the initiator tRNA 
Met i , 
which is not present in peptidyl-tRNAs (Figure 5A and B, 
Supplementary Figure S4A). We also observed enrichment 
in elongator tRNAs in the 60S fraction 3 in ltn1Δ cells (Sup-
plementary Figure S4B; Wilcoxon rank sum test, P = 4 
× 10 
−3 ), although this effect was less pronounced than in 
Cdc48-depleted cells. 
To confirm that the observed increase in elongator 
tRNAs in the 60S fraction of Cdc48-depleted cells reflects 
accumulation of peptidyl-tRNA species (11-13), we precipi-
tated 60S-containing complexes from P TET-O7 -CDC48 cells 
and wild-type control cells by ultracentrifugation and re-
solved them by electrophoresis on acid-urea polyacrylamide 
gels. Hybridization with a radioactively labeled tRNA 
probe revealed the increased quantities of peptidyl-tRNAs 
in the 60S complexes isolated from Cdc48-depleted, but 
not wild-type cells (Figure 5C). Treatment of the peptidyl-
tRNAs with a phenol-containing reagent prior to elec-
trophoresis selectively removed the top part of the smear 
of peptidyl-tRNAs (Figure 5C), consistent with the prop-
erty of tRNAs conjugated to peptide chains longer then 80 
residues to partition to the organic phase (36). Together 
with the gradient tRNA distribution analysis (Figure 5A 
and B, Supplementary Figure S4), these results support the </p>



<p>Figure 3. Translational activity of conventional release factors promotes ubiquitination of 60S·NCs. (A) Induction of high molecular weight (HMW) 
aggregates of Sup35 in P TET-O7 -CDC48 cells by overexpression (OE) of P GAL1 -driven Sup35 FLAG (full length, FL). Cells were shifted to galactose medium 
for 28 h to induce Sup35 FLAG and Dox was added to cultures for an additional 20 h. Cellular lysates were resolved by electrophoresis on a 10% SDS-
acrylamide gel to assess expression of Sup35 FLAG (SDS-PAGE, bottom) and on a 1.8% SDS-agarose gel to detect its aggregates (SDD-AGE, top) by 
western blotting. Expression of Sup35-N or empty vector (V) was used as controls. (Band C) Ribosomal species present in cellular lysates from the same 
cultures as analyzed in (A) were subjected to sedimentation through 15-45% (B) or 15-42% (C) sucrose gradients. Proteins isolated from individual fractions 
were separated on 10% SDS-acrylamide gels and probed with anti-ubiquitin, anti-Rpl3 and anti-Rps14 antibodies. Representative blots are shown; see 
Supplemental Figure S2B for another experimental repeat with samples separated on one gel. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 14 6847 </p>

<p>Figure 4. Reduced ubiquitination level of 60S·NCs in the GT181 strain harboring the hypomorphic sup35-R15 allele. (A) GT181 (sup35-R15) and isogenic 
wild-type control strain OT60 were transformed with an empty vector (V) or an expression construct for the translationally active N-terminally truncated 
Sup35-N under the control of a galactose-inducible promoter (P GAL1 -Sup35-N). Serial 5-fold dilutions were spotted on dextrose-and galactose-
containing synthetic media plates and incubated at 30 • C for 3 days. (B) Wild-type and sup35-R15 strains were grown in YPDA at 25 • C to mid-log phase 
and shifted to 30 • C for 4 h. Cell lysates were centrifuged through sucrose gradients and analyzed as in Figure 1. (C) sup35-R15 cells were transformed with 
an empty vector (V) or P GAL1 -Sup35-N expression construct. Sup35-N was induced by growth in galactose-containing medium for 16 h followed by 
shift to 30 • in YPDA for 4 h. Polyubiquitinated NCs present in ribosomal fractions were analyzed as in Figure 1. Each strain was analyzed a minimum of 
three times; representative blots are shown. </p>



<p>Figure 5. Enrichment of elongator tRNAs in 60S fractions in Cdc48-depleted cells depends on Dom34. We treated individual ribosome-containing sucrose 
gradient fractions with proteinase K to separate tRNAs from the conjugated peptides. Next, the extracted RNAs were sequentially analyzed by northern 
hybridization of the same membrane with probes that detect tRNA Met i , tRNA Glu , tRNA Leu , tRNA Val , tRNA Thr . The 18S and 25S rRNAs were analyzed 
on all membranes to verify alignment of the gradient fractions. (A) A representative example of the distribution of rRNA and tRNAs in gradient fractions 
is shown; see Supplementary Figure S4 for full hybridization sets. (B) The percentage of tRNAs in each fraction relative to the total was determined using 
phosphorimager quantification of the hybridization signals. The floating bars represent the full range of values obtained in each fraction (min to max) and 
the crossing lines indicate the mean. Four elongator tRNAs (top) or tRNA Met i (bottom) were quantified in gradients prepared from 2 biological replicates 
of wild-type cells, 3 replicates of P TET-O7 -CDC48 and three replicates of dom34Δ P TET-O7 -CDC48 cells. (C) RNA in ribosomes pelleted from the 60S 
gradient fractions of the indicated strains was resolved on an acid-urea polyacrilamide gel and analyzed by northern hybridization using a radioactively 
labeled probe against tRNA Leu . Treatment with phenol ('+') was used to selectively remove long peptidyl-tRNAs. Prior to hybridization, the membrane 
was stained with methylene blue (MB) to control loading by visualizing 5S and 5.8S rRNAs in the 60S subunits. XC, the xylene cyanol band. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 14 6849 </p>

<p>Figure 6. Accumulation of 60S-associated ubiquitinated products does not require Hbs1, Dom34 or Rqc2. The indicated strains were grown in the presence 
of Dox for 20 h, lysed and ribosomes were separated by centrifugation through a sucrose gradient. Proteins were extracted from each fraction and analyzed 
as in Figure 1. Gradients were repeated three times with hbs1Δ P TET-O7 -CDC48 and dom34Δ hbs1Δ P TET-O7 -CDC48 cells, and three times with rqc2Δ 
P TET-O7 -CDC48 and ltn1Δ rqc2Δ P TET-O7 -CDC48 cells. Representative blots are shown. </p>

<p>notion that tRNA-linked NCs accumulate in the 60S sub-
units in Cdc48-depleted cells, in agreement with the current 
models of RQC (18). 
If Dom34 is responsible for the generation of tRNA-
linked NCs, as suggested by previous studies (6,7), its lack 
in the cell should abolish accumulation of elongator tRNAs 
in the 60S fraction. As predicted, introducing a dom34Δ 
deletion into P TET-O7 -CDC48 cells prevented the increase 
in elongator tRNAs in fractions 3 and 4 after Cdc48 deple-
tion (Figure 5A-B, Supplementary Figure S4A; Wilcoxon 
rank sum test, P &lt; 1 × 10 
−4 ). However, as shown above, 
the western blot analysis of the gradient fractions indicates 
that large amounts of ubiquitin conjugates continue to ac-
cumulate in the 60S fraction in dom34Δ cells (Figure 2). 
We confirmed that accumulation of 60S-associated ubiq-
uitinated species also occurred in hbs1Δ cells after Cdc48 
depletion (Figure 6A), even though like in dom34Δ cells, 
elongator tRNAs did not accumulate in the 60S fraction 
in hbs1Δ cells (Supplementary Figure S4C). These data are 
consistent with the idea that many 60S·NC complexes tar-
geted for Ltn1-Cdc48-mediated degradation do not contain 
tRNA. To further substantiate this result, we evaluated how 
much the total ubiquitination of the 60S·NC complexes 
depends on Rqc2, which binds to the tRNA in 60S·NC-
tRNA complexes (12,13). We reasoned that if most Ltn1 
substrates in the cell are derived from Sup45-Sup35 activ-</p>

<p>ities, Rqc2 would be expected to impact a relatively minor 
pool of 60S·NC-tRNA species that are products of Dom34-
Hbs1. Indeed, the distribution of ubiquitinated NCs in the 
rqc2Δ P TET-O7 -CDC48 strain was virtually unaffected rela-
tive to the parental P TET-O7 -CDC48 strain (Figure 6B, left), 
whereas the ltn1Δ rqc2Δ double deletion abolished the for-
mation of ubiquitinated 60S species (Figure 6B, right). 
Based on these data, we conclude that only a small frac-
tion of ubiquitinated 60S·NC complexes accumulating in 
Cdc48-depleted cells contain peptidyl-tRNA and are conti-
gent on Dom34/Hbs1-mediated release. These results sup-
port a model in which faulty translation products can be tar-
geted for Ltn1-mediated ubiquitination and Cdc48-assisted 
degradation through canonical release mechanisms that in-
volve tRNA hydrolysis. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Much information on ribosome-associated QC has been 
obtained through analysis of translation products derived 
from model mRNA substrates that either lack a stop codon 
or encode sequences (e.g. polylysine) that induce ribosome 
stalling. In this work, we took a different approach by exam-
ining the total population of ubiquitinated nascent polypep-
tide chains associated with different ribosomal complexes. 
We made use of the observation that deficiency of Cdc48 re-
sults in the accumulation of the ubiquitin-labeled proteome </p>



<p>Figure 7. Two alternative pathways generate substrates for Ltn1-Cdc48. 
Our data are consistent with a model for Ltn1-Cdc48-mediated transla-
tional surveillance in which one upstream pathway utilizes release factors 
Sup45-Sup35 and captures ribosomes stalled at any position on mRNA, 
giving rise to 60S·NC complexes polyubiquitinated by Ltn1 (left). Another 
upstream pathway requires release-like factors Dom34-Hbs1 and oper-
ates on ribosomes stalled at the 3 end of non-stop and truncated mes-
sages (right). The Dom34-Hbs1-generated complex, 60S·NC-tRNA, is rec-
ognized by the tRNA-binding protein Rqc2 and Ltn1. Prior to Cdc48-
mediated release of the ubiquitinated NC, tRNA undergoes hydrolysis to 
allow NC passage through the exit tunnel of 60S. </p>

<p>in cells (57), including polypeptides that are modified co-
translationally (4), to assess upstream steps in ribosome-
associated degradation. In agreement with prior work uti-
lizing translation reporters, our data indicate that the E3 
ligase Ltn1 carries out most, if not all 60S-associated sub-
strate ubiquitination in yeast cells. Importantly, our results 
establish that Dom34-Hbs1 are not the only factors respon-
sible for generating Ltn1-Cdc48 substrates. Rather, our data 
point to the canonical release factors Sup45-Sup35 as the 
important mediators in ribosome-associated degradation 
that supply the bulk of 60S·NC substrates for Ltn1 (Figure 
7). 
The existence of more than one pathway leading to 
Cdc48-mediated clearance of NCs could reflect the need to 
target different types of arrested ribosomes. Recent stud-
ies of model stalling substrates have suggested that Sup35-
Sup45 can terminate translation at internal polylysine seg-
ments (28). By contrast, Dom34 targets ribosomes arrested 
on truncated mRNAs and near the ends of 3 UTRs, but 
does not appear to facilitate the splitting of ribosomes on 
several types of coding sequences known to cause stalling 
(26,58). Consistently, recent in vitro studies (7,8), supported </p>

<p>by structural data (59), revealed that subunit dissociation 
by Dom34-Hbs1 requires a short length of the mRNA's 3 
extension relative to the codon in the P-site, 23 and 9 nu-
cleotides for yeast and human Dom34-Hbs1, respectively. 
Thus, one possibility is that Dom34-Hbs1 evolved to recog-
nize a specific type of substrates that cannot be efficiently re-
solved through canonical release factors, such as ribosomes 
reaching the 3 end of nonstop messages or inactive 80S ri-
bosomes (60,25). The existence of alternative mechanisms 
to resolve translational stalls may explain why DOM34 and 
HBS1 are nonessential in yeast, unlike the key components 
of the translation rescue systems in bacteria (61). 
Another specialized function of Dom34-Hbs1 may be 
to generate tRNA-linked 60S·NC complexes ((6), Figure 
5A, B). It was recently shown that tRNA in these com-
plexes recruits Rqc2, which promotes synthesis of non-
templated C-terminal extensions of NCs (CAT tails), re-
quired for the transmission of the translation-stress signal 
to Hsf1 (10,13). Because cotranslational clearance of mis-
folded peptides and rescue of stalled ribosomes is a process 
that must take place in cells at all times, some way to avoid 
continuous translation-stress signaling in clearly needed. A 
plausible scenario consistent with our data is that most of 
the 'routine' clearance of aberrant NCs is performed by 
the release factors and accompanied by peptidyl-tRNA hy-
drolysis, thereby carrying no intrinsic proteotoxic signaling 
function. This could also explain why mutations in tRNA-
interacting residues of Rqc2 (13) or rqc2Δ deletion only 
weakly affect the clearance of model reporters (10) and re-
cruitment of Cdc48 to 60S·NC complexes (2). 
Considering that the canonical release factors are capable 
of efficiently discriminating against sense codons under nor-
mal circumstances (6,62), an important question for the fu-
ture studies is whether these factors function in QC by medi-
ating detection of aberrant translation events such as ribo-
some slippage, which could lead to termination on prema-
ture stop codons, or their function involves a previously un-
characterized type of interactions with ribosomes, distinct 
from conventional termination. Intriguingly, there is prior 
evidence that Sup45-Sup35 may be capable of binding to 
stalled ribosomal complexes that contain a sense codon in 
the A site (63,64,28). Another interesting question concerns 
the activity of Ltn1 on 60S·NC substrates in the absence 
of tRNA or Rqc2. Given the highly flexible structure of 
Ltn1 (65), this ubiquitin ligase could have additional modes 
of interaction with ribosomal complexes in addition to the 
previously observed conformation in cryo-EM structures in 
which its N-terminus contacts Rqc2 at the subunit interface 
(11-13). Indeed, previous in vitro studies of these proteins' 
mammalian homologs suggest that Ltn1-mediated ubiqui-
tination of aberrant translation products may occur, albeit 
with reduced efficiency, without Rqc2 (40). 
An unconventional activity of Sup45-Sup35 on stalled 
ribosomes may also have ramifications for gene expres-
sion. The switches between soluble and aggregated [PSI 
+ ] 
prion states of Sup35 impart complex phenotypes, which 
have been attributed mainly to altered read-through of stop 
codons, but it is clear now that the full spectrum of the ob-
served effects cannot be fully accounted for by this mech-
anism (66-68). We suggest that deficiency in functional 
Sup45-Sup35 conferred by [PSI 
+ ] elements or conditions </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 14 6851 </p>

<p>that affect Sup35 aggregation such as aging and heat stress 
(69,70) may lead to changes in the proteome via increased 
synthesis of proteins with built-in elongation stalling sites. 
This could serve as a regulatory mechanism contributing to 
survival under unfavorable conditions. Additionally, envi-
ronmental insults that induce ribosome stalling might elicit 
differential responses depending on whether the release fac-
tors are available to trigger premature termination on se-
lected mRNAs, with the subsequent destruction of the par-
tially synthesized polypeptides via the Ltn1-Cdc48 path-
way. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We are thankful to S.G. Inge-Vechtomov (St. Petersburg 
State University, St. Petersburg, Russia) for the sup35/45 
tester strains, to D. Bedwell (University of Alabama, Birm-
ingham, USA) for anti-Sup35C antibodies and to John 
Woolford (Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, USA) 
for anti-Rps14 antibodies. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>UMDNJ Foundation (to N.S.); National Institutes of 
Health [GM093294 to T.A.C. and GM074091 to D.G.P.]; 
National Science Foundation [MCB-1516872 to Y.O.C.]. 
Funding for open access charge: Rowan University intra-
mural support funds (to N.S.). 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







</text></tei>