<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5210542" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>R-loopDB (http://rloop.bii.a-star.edu.sg) was origi-
nally constructed as a collection of computationally 
predicted R-loop forming sequences (RLFSs) in the 
human genic regions. The renewed R-loopDB pro-
vides updates, improvements and new options, in-
cluding access to recent experimental data. It in-
cludes genome-scale prediction of RLFSs for hu-
mans, six other animals and yeast. Using the ex-
tended quantitative model of RLFSs (QmRLFS), we 
significantly increased the number of RLFSs pre-
dicted in the human genes and identified RLFSs in 
other organism genomes. R-loopDB allows search-
ing of RLFSs in the genes and in the 2 kb up-
stream and downstream flanking sequences of any 
gene. R-loopDB exploits the <rs type="software">Ensembl</rs> gene annota-
tion system, providing users with chromosome co-
ordinates, sequences, gene and genomic data of 
the 1 565 795 RLFSs distributed in 121 056 genic 
or proximal gene regions of the covered organisms. 
It provides a comprehensive annotation of Ensembl 
RLFS-positive genes including 93 454 protein coding 
genes, 12 480 long non-coding RNA and 7 568 small 
non-coding RNA genes and 7 554 pseudogenes. Us-
ing new interface and genome viewers of R-loopDB, 
users can search the gene(s) in multiple species with 
keywords in a single query. R-loopDB provides tools 
to carry out comparative evolution and genome-scale 
analyses in R-loop biology. </p>

<p>An R-loop is a three-stranded nucleic acid structure com-
prising nascent RNA hybridized with its corresponding </p>

<p>DNA template strand while leaving the non-template DNA 
single-stranded. R-loops are often formed during transcrip-
tion. Both in vitro and in vivo, a few short guanine clusters 
and further G-rich DNA segment in non-template DNA 
strand, as well as its sequence length, can provide impor-
tant determinants of the initiation of R-loop formation and 
its stabilization (1-4). R-loop formation has been observed 
from bacteria to mammalian species (5,6). In cells these 
structures have long been considered to result from rare or 
accidental RNA with DNA hybrids detected in a few spe-
cific loci. However, their functional importance was poor 
understood. 
For the last several years, the roles of R-loops in the as-
sociation of transcription, splicing, chromatin remodeling, 
telomere maintenance, genome instability, mutagenesis, cell 
proliferation, differentiation, epigenetic regulation and si-
lencing as well as disease involvement have been demon-
strated (7-17). RNA:DNA hybrids as the component of 
R-loops are being increasingly associated with human dis-
eases, with a major concern that their presence predisposes 
the locus to chromosomal instability, mutation and break-
age (7,8,18). 
In 2011, using the first version of our quantitative R-loop 
forming sequence (RLFS) prediction model (QmRLFS), R-
loopDB was originally constructed as a collection of the 
RLFSs, identified computationally in the genes of the hu-
man genome (18). R-loop models collected in R-loopDB 
had a number of important features, including genic strand 
RLFS directionality, CpG island abundance, preferential 
location of the RLFSs in the open chromatin and highly 
regulated genic regions (e.g. in the vicinity of alternative 
transcription start sites, RNA polymerase II pause sites, 
splicing regions, the first exon and first intron), activation-
induced cytidine deaminase target sequences, fragile regions 
and disease critical loci (18). In silico analysis of the hu-
man genome identified a high number of RLFS (245 181) 
in 59% well-annotated genes (18). Consistent with these </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +656478 8288; Fax: +65 6478 9047; Email: vladimirk@bii.a-star.edu.sg </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>D120 Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, Database issue </p>

<p>predictions, several recent genome-wide experimental stud-
ies mapped thousands of RNA:DNA hybridization signals 
distributed along human and mouse genomes and demon-
strated that R-loops can be formed not only in the gene 
body but also in the upstream promoter regions (9-11) and 
transcription pause sites located downstream of the poly(A) 
signal (9,10,12,13,19). Formation of these R-loops in prox-
imal promoter regions was shown to be involved in tran-
scription initiation or elongation (9) and the recruitment of 
key pluripotency regulators (11). R-loops forming in tran-
scription termination sites could promote termination by 
slowing down the advance of the RNA polymerase II and 
allowing the recruitment of termination factors (13). Inter-
estingly, such co-localization of R-loops with key regula-
tory regions was not limited to humans but also found or 
predicted in many other species (7,20,21). 
Previously, we have presented <rs type="software">QmRLFS-finder</rs>, a tool us-
ing an updated quantitative model of RLFS (QmRLFS) 
model that has predicted the RLFS locations in ∼75% 
of the human genes (22). This tool allowed a higher ac-
curacy, precision and strand specificity of the QmRLFS-
based predictions of the R-loops in the proximal pro-
moter and downstream transcription termination site re-
gions (7,20). Soon after the publication of the R-loopDB, 
the DNA:RNA immune-precipitation coupled to high-
throughput sequencing (DRIP-seq) data became available 
(9,23). Ginno et al. (9) have improved the initial DRIP-seq 
method (23) and reported detection of 4181 RNA:DNA hy-
brid regions. In (22), we reported that RLFS predicted by 
<rs type="software">QmRLFS-finder</rs> overlapped with 79.2% of DRIP-seq re-
gions defined by Ginno et al. (9). In a comparison of the 
frequencies of experimentally defined R-loops with those 
RLFSs predicted by QmRLFS-finder, our tool showed 91% 
accuracy, 94% sensitivity and 75% specificity (22). 
Recently, new high-throughput technologies for detec-
tion of RNA:DNA hybrid formation and new data sets 
became available, which provide an opportunity to specify 
prevalence, strand specificity and chromosome distribution 
of R-loops in the human and mouse genomes, their conser-
vation across cell types and species, their mechanisms of for-
mation and turnover and specify their functions (12,14,24). 
The new version of R-loopDB, based on the predic-
tions by <rs type="software">QmRLFS-finder</rs> (22), includes several key im-
provements and extensions that facilitate exploration of the 
RLFS analysis. We updated the identification of RLFSs 
in the human genome and provided for the first time the 
genome-scale prediction of RLFSs in seven additional or-
ganisms. The updated R-loopDB allows the user to search 
for gene(s) containing RLFSs not only in genic regions but 
also in 2 kb upstream and downstream flanking sequence of 
the gene, termed 'RLFS-positive genes'. Compared to the 
previous R-loopDB version, we now use Ensembl gene an-
notation system that contains information on protein cod-
ing genes, pseudogenes, long noncoding RNA genes and 
short noncoding RNA genes (25). Mapping of RLFSs and 
other genomic regulatory sequences is graphically visual-
ized in <rs type="software">Gbrowse2</rs> (26) and <rs type="software">UCSC genome browser</rs> (27). 
In the case of the human and mouse genomes, the exper-
imentally detected RNA:DNA hybrid data (9,12,14,24) on 
the genome scale were integrated into the genomics view-
ers. That allows users to carry out comprehensive compar-</p>

<p>ative analyses of the predicted and experimentally detected 
RLFSs. Based on the provided results, users can narrow 
down their target and pick the most plausible sequence of 
the R-loop forming region. </p>

<p>Data sources </p>

<p>We collected all genome assembly data from the <rs id="software-21" type="software">UCSC 
genome browser</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-21" type="url">https://genome.ucsc.edu/</rs>/) (27). The hu-
man genome hg19 (NCBI build GRCh37) was used as the 
reference genome in this database. We also analyzed ge-
nomic data of selected model organisms including Mus 
musculus (mm10), Rattus norvegicus (rn5), Pan troglodytes 
(panTro4), Gallus gallus (galGal4), Xenopus tropicalis (xen-
Tro3), Drosophila melanogaster (dm5) and Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae (saccer3). Only the reference chromosomes were 
used in this study. Therefore, we excluded other sequence 
regions such as unlocalized and unplaced scaffolds, su-
percontigs, assembly patches and alternate loci (haplo-
types). Gene annotation data for these organisms was re-
trieved directly from <rs type="software">MySQL</rs> server of BioMart database 
build 75 (ensembl mart 75; http://www.ensembl.org/info/ 
data/mysql.html) (25). Genomic information of the gene 
structures for these organisms (GTF format) was down-
loaded from <rs id="software-30" type="software">Ensembl</rs> <rs corresp="#software-30" type="version-number">Release 75</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-30" type="url">http://feb2014.archive.ensembl.org/info/data/ftp/</rs>/; accessed 1 April 2016). </p>

<p>Identification of R-loop structures </p>

<p>We predicted R-loop structures on both strands of genomic 
DNA using <rs type="software">QmRLFS-finder</rs> (22). After obtaining RLFSs, 
we collected RLFSs located in the genic region and 2 kb up-
stream and downstream flanking regions of each gene using 
<rs type="software">BEDTools</rs> (28). RLFSs that overlapped by at least one nu-
cleotide were merged into unique RLFS clusters. When no 
further RLFSs overlapped the long merged sequence, then 
this sequence, called an RLFS-merged region, has reached 
its maximum length. Such regions were reported, counted 
and made visible in the updated R-loopDB. 
RLFSs that are located in any genic region were con-
sidered gene-associated RLFS. We determined locations of 
RLFSs on the 2 kb upstream, genic (gene body) and 2 
kb downstream regions. RLFSs that are located simultane-
ously in any genic combination of these three regions were 
also identified and counted. </p>

<p>GC skew calculation </p>

<p>The GC skew could favor the thermodynamic stability of 
R-loop formation (21,24). GC skew values, reflecting the 
asymmetric distribution of G and C between the leading 
strand and the lagging strand were calculated according to 
the following equation </p>

<p>GC skew = (#G − #C)/(#G + #C), 
(1) </p>

<p>using the numbers of G and C in 200 bp sliding window and 
a step size of 10 bp. The GC skew profiles of each organism 
were stored in BigWig file format. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, Database issue D121 </p>

<p>RLFS, RLFS-merged regions and RLFS-positive genes </p>

<p>R-loopDB currently covers eight organisms, including hu-
man, mouse, rat, chimpanzee, chicken, frog, fruit fly and 
yeast. Supplementary Table S1 provides information on 
the genome assemblies of these species. Using <rs type="software">QmRLFS-
finder</rs> (22), we significantly extended the list of RLFSs and 
RLFS-positive genes in the human genome compared to 
the previous version (18). The summary statistics of RLFSs, 
RLFS-merged regions and RLFS-positive genes presented 
in the previous and updated R-loopDBs are shown in Ta-
ble 1. For instance, 511 651 RLFSs (or 169 222 RLFS-
merged regions) were computationally predicted in genic 
regions and 2 kb upstream and downstream flanking re-
gions of the genes, whereas, in the previous R-loopDB, 245 
181 RLFSs (or 140 106 RLFS-merged regions) were found 
in the UCSC-defined gene regions. In total, R-loopDB 
provides chromosome coordinates, sequences and genomic 
data of 1565 795 RLFSs distributed across 121 056 genes 
and 2 kb upstream and downstream flanking region of the 
genes of eight organisms. 
Using the <rs type="software">Ensembl</rs> gene annotation system (25) in R-
loopDB, RLFS-positive genes can be classified into 93 454 
protein-coding genes, 7 554 pseudogenes, 12 480 long non-
coding RNA genes and 7 568 short non-coding RNA genes 
(Table 2). </p>

<p>Search for RLFS-positive genes and visualization tools </p>

<p>Visual tools for RLFS search could be used for locating pu-
tative R-loops in a specific region of genic or gene-proximal 
regions for further experimental design and validation of 
the computational prediction(s). Here, we redesigned the in-
terface of R-loopDB to search genes containing RLFS in 
multiple organisms with a single search. The genes contain-
ing RLFS can be retrieved from the database using several 
search options, e.g. keywords, <rs type="software">Ensembl</rs> gene ID or <rs type="software">Ensembl</rs> 
transcript ID, gene symbol, gene description, Entrez ID, 
Refseq ID, gene biotype and synonyms (Figure 1A). Note 
that the keywords option will search the query input string 
against all terms in the database. The gene search query re-
turns RLFS-positive genes (Figure 1B). Each Ensembl gene 
ID of the search result is linked to the result gene page that 
provides information in two parts 'Gene Overview' (Figure 
1C) and 'Genomic Location' (Figure 2). 
The 'Gene Overview' provides detailed information of 
the Ensembl gene (Figure 1C.i) and RLFS-merged regions 
within proximal gene regions (Figure 1C.ii). Here, NEAT1 
gene encodes a nuclear long non-coding RNA. Accord-
ing to its annotation, NEAT1 RNA is essential for the 
formation and maintenance of nuclear structures called 
paraspeckles and is involved in cell malignancy. The gene 
information panel (Figure 1C.i) shows the gene annotation 
of a given <rs type="software">Ensembl</rs> gene ID retrieved from the BioMart 
database (build 75), i.e. gene description, gene biotype, 
chromosome location, Ensembl transcript ID, Entrez ID 
and RefSeq ID, while gene synonyms were retrieved from 
the Ensembl database (build 84). In RLFS-merged region 
information (Figure 1C.ii; also see Figure 2a), this table pro-
vides a list of RLFS-merged regions located in the genic re-
gion and 2 kb upstream and downstream flanking regions </p>

<p>of the particular gene. Each RLFS-merged region has use-
ful information for supporting the R-loop forming poten-
tial, such as (i) the number of RLFSs, and (ii) strand and 
(iii) statistics of the GC skew value. To find RLFS candi-
dates for experimental validation, we recommend that users 
consider the information in the RLFS-merged region table 
(Figure 1C.ii). The first one is the 'number of RLFSs'. A 
higher number of RLFSs in the RLFS-merged region im-
plies a higher propensity of R-loop initiation and forma-
tion in a given locus. The second one is 'strand'. According 
to the R-loop definition where a nascent RNA is hybridized 
with a DNA template, predicted RLFS are located on the 
same strand as the transcribed gene (Supplementary Fig-
ure S1). The third one is 'statistics of GC skew value'. GC 
skew value was calculated at the whole genomic scale, as 
shown in Figure 2c. The 'statistics of GC skew value' show 
statistics of GC skew value in each RLFS-merged region in-
cluding minimum, maximum, mean and median. GC skew 
maximum values &gt; 0.1 (for plus strand) or GC skew min-
imum values &lt; −0.1 (for minus strand) are considered G-
rich regions (21). The more G-rich an RLFS-merged region 
is, the more likely it is to increase the thermodynamic stabil-
ity of R-loop formation (24). In the case of the human and 
mouse genomes, 'DRIP/RDIP support' and 'DRIPc sup-
port' columns, which indicate the number of RNA:DNA 
hybrid detection experiments for each RLFS-merged re-
gion, are provided. There are at least nine RNA:DNA hy-
brid detection experiments including four DRIP-seq stud-
ies in Ntera2, one DRIP-seq in K562, one DRIP-seq in 
primary fibroblast cells (9,12,14), two RDIP-seq studies in 
IMR-90 and HEK293T cells (24) and one DRIPc-seq in 
Ntera2. Individually, these experiments showed variations 
in the sequence overlap region boundaries, their locations 
and the sequence cluster overlap peak heights, however, 
collectively they often demonstrate the patterns converged 
on the theoretical predictions. A combination of computa-
tional predictions and biological data sets suggests a role 
of NEAT1-associated R-loops in an aberrant NEAT1 tran-
scription initiation and/or 3-end elongation isoform syn-
theses, leading to modulation of the paraspeckle formation 
and cell malignancy. 
The RLFS or RLFS-merged region results can be down-
loaded into text file, BED file and FASTA file (Figure 
1C.iii). 
The top panel of the 'Genomic Location' result shows 
gene name, gene location, strand and cytoband information 
of the particular gene (see in Figure 2). New genomics visu-
alization has been integrated into R-loopDB using embed-
ded Gbrowse2. The genomics viewer provides visualization 
of RLFS-merged, RLFS, CpG Island, GC skew profile, En-
sembl genes, <rs type="software">Ensembl</rs> transcripts, DRIP-seq profile, RDIP-
seq profile and DRIPc-seq profile in a particular genic re-
gion as well as in 2 kb upstream and downstream flanking 
regions of the gene. In Figure 2a-d, the light blue and pink 
colors indicate the orientation of the sense-and antisense-
strand of the annotations, respectively. Clicking on an in-
dividual RLFS-merged (Figure 2a) or RLFS (Figure 2b) 
will link to the detailed information of RLFS-merged (Sup-
plementary Figure S2A) or RLFS (Supplementary Figure 
S2B), respectively. GC skew profile (Figure 2c) indicates the 
boundaries between the bias distributions of G-rich regions </p>

<p>D122 Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, Database issue </p>

<p>Figure 1. Screenshots of R-loopDB and search results. (A) R-loopDB main search page where a user can perform a search based on keywords or specific 
gene ID and the resulting page is shown in (B). R-loop forming sequence (RLFS) and other regulatory sequences and their characteristics for NEAT1 
(nuclear noncoding RNA gene) are visualized. (C) The user can view the gene result page with RLFS information by clicking on the Ensembl gene ID 
linked from (B). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, Database issue D123 </p>

<p>Table 1. The growth of data hosted by the R-loopDB since the initial release </p>

<p>Initial release in 2012 
Up-to-date in 2016 </p>

<p>Gene annotation system 
UCSC known genes 
Ensembl build 75 
No. of organisms 
1 species 
8 species 
No. of transcript IDs 
39 720 
286 584 
No. of gene IDs 
14 954 
121 056 
No. of RLFSs in the human genes 
245 181 
511 651 
No. of RLFS-merged regions in the human genes 
140 106 
169 222 
No. of RLFSs in genes 
245 181 
1 565 795 
No. of RLFS-merged regions in genes 
140 106 
565 789 </p>

<p>Remark: the initial release database provides RLFSs only in genic regions, where the updated database provides RLFSs in genic regions and 2 kb 
up/downstream region of genes. </p>

<p>Table 2. Statistics of RLFS-positive genes according to the Ensembl gene annotation system and ratio of RLFS-positive gene to total number of gene for 
each gene category in each organism </p>

<p>No. of protein coding genes * 
No. of pseudogenes * </p>

<p>No. of long noncoding RNA 
genes * </p>

<p>No. of short noncoding RNA 
genes * </p>

<p>Organism 
Total </p>

<p>RLFS 
positive Ratio 
Total </p>

<p>RLFS 
positive Ratio 
Total </p>

<p>RLFS 
positive Ratio 
Total </p>

<p>RLFS 
positive Ratio </p>

<p>human 
23 431 
17 798 
0.76 
15 934 
4 433 
0.28 
14 966 
9 028 
0.60 
9 771 
2 296 
0.23 
mouse 
22 835 
18 201 
0.80 
6 129 
2 161 
0.35 
4 291 
3 283 
0.77 
5 924 
1 950 
0.33 
rat 
22 771 
17 529 
0.77 
1 840 
662 
0.36 
79 
65 
0.82 
1 714 
608 
0.35 
chimpanzee 
18 759 
15 462 
0.82 
572 
213 
0.37 
0 
0 
n/a 
8 681 
1 870 
0.22 
chicken 
15 508 
12 007 
0.77 
42 
26 
0.62 
0 
0 
n/a 
1 558 
546 
0.35 
frog 
18 442 
9 932 
0.54 
173 
44 
0.25 
0 
0 
n/a 
1 306 
268 
0.21 
fruit fly 
13 863 
2 423 
0.17 
200 
11 
0.06 
830 
104 
0.13 
789 
30 
0.04 
yeast 
6 692 
102 
0.02 
21 
4 
0.19 
15 
0 
n/a 
398 
0 
n/a 
All organisms 
142 301 93 454 
0.66 
24 911 
7 554 
0.30 
20 181 
12 480 
0.62 
30 141 
7 568 
0.25 </p>

<p>* The Ensemble gene biotypes were grouped into protein coding genes, pseudogenes, long non-coding RNA genes and short non-coding RNA genes 
(available at http://asia.ensembl.org/Help/Faq?id=468). Examples of gene biotypes in each group are as follows: 
-Protein coding genes: IGC gene, IGD gene, IG gene, IGJ gene, IGLV gene, IGM gene, IGV gene, IGZ gene, nonsense mediated decay, non-translating 
CDS, non-stop decay, polymorphic pseudogene, TRC gene, TRD gene, TRJ gene. 
-Pseudogenes: disrupted domain, IGC pseudogene, IGJ pseudogene, IG pseudogene, IGV pseudogene, processed pseudogene, transcribed processed pseu-
dogene, transcribed unitary pseudogene, transcribed unprocessed pseudogene, translated processed pseudogene, TRJ pseudogene, unprocessed pseudogene 
-Long non-coding RNA genes: 3-prime overlapping ncRNA, ambiguous ORF, antisense, antisense RNA, lincRNA, ncRNA host, processed transcript, 
sense intronic, sense overlapping 
-Short non-coding RNA genes: miRNA, miRNA pseudogene, miscRNA, miscRNA pseudogene, Mt rRNA, Mt tRNA, rRNA, scRNA, snlRNA, 
snoRNA, snRNA, tRNA, tRNA pseudogene. </p>

<p>in a sense-or antisense-strand of the chromosome. Clicking 
on an individual Ensembl gene or Ensembl transcript (Fig-
ure 2d) will result in a close-up view of the particular gene 
or transcript. In Figure 2e and f, DRIP-seq, RDIP-seq and 
DRIPc-seq peak regions indicate significant enrichment of 
DRIP-seq, RDIP-seq and DRIPc-seq signals, respectively, 
from different studies of experimental RNA:DNA hybrid 
detection. R-loopDB also provides external browser but-
tons which are linked to interactive genomics viewers such 
as UCSC Genome Browser (27) and <rs type="software">GBrowse2</rs> (26) (Sup-
plementary Figure S3). Furthermore, users can directly in-
put the gene coordinate or gene symbol on UCSC Genome 
Browser for searching. Users have the option to turn on/off 
or re-order the tracks that are displayed on the genome 
browser. </p>

<p>Comparative analysis of RLFS in genic and proximal gene 
regions </p>

<p>According to the updated R-loopDB, the largest number 
of RLFSs is observed in the human genome (664 791 se-
quences) and the smallest number of RLFSs is found in 
the yeast genome (78 sequences). Mammalian genomes </p>

<p>are highly abundant in RLFSs and RLFS-merged clusters 
(Supplementary Table S2). The RLFSs are preferentially lo-
cated in genic and proximal gene regions. 
The most abundant are yeast (95%), human (77%), fruit 
fly (77%) and chicken (68%) gene body and 2 kb proximal 
genic regions. The fraction of RLFS-positive genes and 2 
kb proximal genic regions is relatively lower in chimpanzee 
(57%), mouse (53%), rat (42%) and frog (33%) genomes. 
The numbers and the proportions of RLFSs within genic 
and proximal gene regions also differ across the organisms. 
Detailed information is presented in Supplementary Table 
S2. According to the updated R-loopDB, the upstream and 
downstream proximal gene regions are highly enriched with 
unique RLFSs, the boundaries of which can either overlap 
or not overlap with gene starts (or transcription start sites), 
gene body and the gene ends. Such data could provide the 
targets for detailed characterization in future experimental 
studies. The Venn diagrams of Supplementary Figure S4A 
and S4B shows these values for the RLFS overlapped with 
the human genes and transcripts, respectively. </p>

<p>D124 Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, Database issue </p>

<p>Figure 2. Screenshots of mapping of RLFS, genes, GC skew profile and other annotation data. The genomic mapping can be viewed in the bottom panel 
of the gene result page. </p>

<p>RLFS positions within a gene of different organisms </p>

<p>R-loopDB allows users to search and analyze the RLFS 
in a gene and in the proximal up-stream and down-stream 
gene body regions in multiple organisms (Supplementary 
Figure S5A). For illustration purposes, glycine dehydroge-
nase (GLDC) gene was used as a query. GLDC protein is a 
member of the multiple-enzyme glycine cleavage system in-
volved in the degradation of glycine. The deletion in GLDC 
is a major cause of nonketotic hyperglycinemia, an inborn 
error of metabolism characterized by the accumulation of 
glycine in body fluids and various neurological symptoms 
(29). In the previous paper, we have shown that RLFSs are </p>

<p>located at the deleted regions of the human GLDC and may 
contribute to recombination of this gene (18). In this work, 
the updated R-loopDB result page shows that five of the 
eight organisms, including human, chimpanzee, mouse, rat 
and chicken, contain at least one RLFS in GLDC gene. Sup-
plementary Figure S5B shows the search result of GLDC 
containing RLFS in five analyzed organisms. Figure 3 illus-
trates the relative RLFS positions in GLDC gene of the or-
ganisms. Interestingly, RLFSs have relative positions within 
the first exon of GLDC gene between all five organisms 
(green color box in Figure 3). In addition, there are several 
other RLFSs showing relative positions within an intron of </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, Database issue D125 </p>

<p>Figure 3. RLFS in different genic and the proximal gene regions and across different organisms. Positions of RLFSs predicted in the GLDC gene in five 
organisms. Screenshot from Gbrowse2 shows relative positions of RLFSs in the GLDC gene for human, chimpanzee, mouse, rat and chicken. The green 
color box indicates relatively similar positions of the RLFSs within exon 1 of GLDC across all five organisms. Blue color boxes indicate the relationship of 
the positions of RLFSs within an intron of GLDC gene between human and chimpanzee. </p>

<p>the GLDC gene, which may characterize the commonness 
and uniqueness of the human and chimpanzee intron se-
quences (blue color boxes in Figure 3). These RLFS clusters 
(in blue color boxes in Figure 3) are not computationally 
identified in other (non-primate) organisms. This example 
allows users to investigate several hypotheses regarding the 
functional roles of the sequence structure and genome loca-
tion of the predicted RLFSs. Many aspects of comparative 
evolution and evolutional conservation of RLFSs and the 
disease-associated functions of the R-loops in GLDC and 
other genic regions annotated in the R-loopDB may be in-
vestigated using the R-loopDB. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION AND FUTURE DIRECTIONS </p>

<p>Here, we present a comprehensive database of RLFSs in 
eight organisms, i.e. human, chimp, mouse, rat, chicken, 
frog, fruit fly and yeast, that offers benefits for the re-
searchers who study R-loop related human diseases us-
ing these species. The combination of several other data 
resources, such as RLFS strand, GC skew value and ex-
perimental R-loop detection data, could provide more in-
formation for advanced analyses and predictions. For in-
stance, predicted RLFS and other R-loop formation fea-
tures with DRIP-seq data and Global-Run-On sequencing 
was demonstrated as a fruitful strategy in identification of 
the specific transcriptional features, namely convergence of 
transcription and polymerase II stalling, as important fac-</p>

<p>D126 Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, Database issue </p>

<p>tors underlying secondary genetic lesions frequently seen in 
precursor B leukemia (30). RNA:DNA hybrids are being 
increasingly associated with human diseases, with a major 
concern that their presence predisposes a locus to chromo-
somal breakage (7,8). 
The updated R-loopDB could be utilized not only as a 
predictive model resource but also as an analytical tool to 
predict and validate many RLFS-positive genes (as coding 
and non-coding for proteins), pseudogenes to test the spe-
cific hypotheses in R-loop biology, to improve the existing 
methods, to design new experimental studies and to provide 
an adequate interpretation of the experimental and theoret-
ical results. In those contexts, a combination of R-loopDB 
and <rs type="software">QmRLFS-finder</rs> web server (identifying RLFSs in non-
annotated and artificial targeting sequences) might be use-
ful. 
Further development of R-loopDB will be focused on 
classification of RLFS and R-loops, evolutionary conser-
vation and de novo RLFSs and the RLFS-positive genes in 
different gene families and subsets, cell types and organisms. 
We plan to develop and integrate the options to retrieve 
evolutionarily conserved and unique RLFS-positive genes, 
searching across several mammalian and non-mammalian 
genomes in the R-loopDB. As more experimental R-loop 
data sets are generated, in the next update, R-loopDB 
should offer a more comprehensive collection of experimen-
tally supported data and further development of the inte-
grative and predictive tools. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Tan Xuanru Mavis for the discussion 
and data processing. The collaboration between the co-
authors would not have been possible without the travel 
grants from the School of Bioresources and Biotechnol-
ogy, King Mongkut's University of Technology, Thonburi, 
Thailand. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>The Biomedical Research Council of the Agency for 
Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR), Singa-
pore. Funding for open access charge: Bioinformatics 
Institute/A*STAR core budget. 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



</text></tei>