<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5109890" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>on age, race, PSA, digital rectal examination (DRE), family history, 
and history of a previous negative prostate biopsy. It was reported that 
use of the PCPT risk calculator can avoid 1% and 2% of unnecessary 
biopsies if a threshold probability of 20% and 30% is used for patients 
with PSA from 0.5 to 50 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>, respectively. ERSPC risk calculator 
included PSA, DRE, transrectal ultrasound (TRUS) findings, and 
prostate volume (PV). It was reported that use of ERSPC risk calculator 
can avoid 9% and 23% of unnecessary biopsies if a threshold probability 
of 20% and 30% is used for patients with PSA from 0.5 to 50 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>, 
respectively. 
5 The utility of these risk calculators had been externally 
validated in Western populations and observed to outperform PSA 
and %fPSA for predicting PCa. </p>

<p>6-8 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Prostate-specific antigen (PSA) is the most widely used biomarker 
for prostate cancer screening and early detection of PCa. However, its 
relatively low specificity has resulted in large number of unnecessary 
biopsies. 
3 To solve this problem, several independent factors have been 
considered for predicting PCa, for example, age, results from digital 
rectal exam (DRE), and several PSA derivatives such as ratio of free to 
total PSA (%fPSA), PSA density (PSAD), and PSA velocity (PSAV). 
4 In 
some studies, prediction tools (such as nomograms and risk calculators) 
were based on these factors, which might provide added value to PSA 
testing for predicting PCa or high-grade PCa. Among those prediction 
tools, the Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial (PCPT) risk calculator 
and the European Randomized Study of Screening for Prostate 
Cancer (ERSPC) risk calculator were most widely used in Western 
populations. The PCPT reported a risk calculator that was built based </p>

<p>ORIGINAL ARTICLE </p>

<p>The Huashan risk calculators performed better in 
prediction of prostate cancer in Chinese population: 
a training study followed by a validation study </p>

<p>Yi-Shuo Wu 
1,2,* , Ning Zhang 
1,2,* , Sheng-Hua Liu </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Jian-Feng Xu </p>

<p>1,2,4 </p>

<p>, Shi-Jun Tong </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Ye-Hua Cai 
3 , 
Li-Min Zhang </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Pei-De Bai </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Meng-Bo Hu </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Hao-Wen Jiang </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Rong Na </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Qiang Ding </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Ying-Hao Sun </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>The performances of the Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial (PCPT) risk calculator and other risk calculators for prostate cancer (PCa) 
prediction in Chinese populations were poorly understood. We performed this study to build risk calculators (Huashan risk calculators) 
based on Chinese population and validated the performance of prostate-specific antigen (PSA), PCPT risk calculator, and Huashan 
risk calculators in a validation cohort. We built Huashan risk calculators based on data from 1059 men who underwent initial 
prostate biopsy from January 2006 to December 2010 in a training cohort. Then, we validated the performance of PSA, PCPT risk 
calculator, and Huashan risk calculators in an observational validation study from January 2011 to December 2014. All necessary 
clinical information were collected before the biopsy. The results showed that Huashan risk calculators 1 and 2 outperformed 
the PCPT risk calculator for predicting PCa in both entire training cohort and stratified population (with PSA from 2.0 ng ml 
−1 to 
20.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>). In the validation study, Huashan risk calculator 1 still outperformed the PCPT risk calculator in the entire validation 
cohort (0.849 vs 0.779 in area under the receiver operating characteristic curve [AUC]) and stratified population. A considerable 
reduction of unnecessary biopsies (approximately 30%) was also observed when the Huashan risk calculators were used. Thus, 
we believe that the Huashan risk calculators (especially Huashan risk calculator 1) may have added value for predicting PCa in 
Chinese population. However, these results still needed further evaluation in larger populations. 
Asian Journal of Andrology (2016) 18, 925-929; doi: 10.4103/1008-682X.181192; published online: 20 May 2016 </p>

<p>Keywords: biopsy; China; prostate cancer; prostate-specific antigen; risk calculator </p>

<p>1 Department of Urology, Huashan Hospital, Fudan University, Shanghai, China; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Urology Research Center, Fudan University, Shanghai, China; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Ultrasonic, 
Huashan Hospital, Fudan University, Shanghai, China; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>NorthShore University HealthSystem, Evanston, IL, USA; </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Department of Urology, Changhai Hospital, The Second 
Military Medical University, Shanghai, China. 
* These authors contributed equally to the work. 
Correspondence: Dr. Q Ding (qiangd_urology@126.com) or Dr. R Na (narong.hs@gmail.com) 
Received: 09 September 2015; Revised: 19 November 2015; Accepted: 29 March 2016 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Prostate Cancer </p>

<p>Asian Journal of Andrology </p>

<p>Risk calculators for prostate cancer 
YS Wu et al </p>



<p>decades) and different ancestry (Han race in China vs Caucasian 
or African-American in Western countries) could also limit the 
effectiveness of those risk calculators. In this study, we used a training 
cohort to build risk calculators (Huashan risk calculators) based on 
the Chinese population, followed by a prospective observational study 
to validate the performance of our risk calculators. We also compared 
the performance of PSA, PCPT risk calculator, and Huashan risk 
calculators in both substudies. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
The complete study design is shown in Figure 1. </p>

<p>Population of the training study 
All men (n = 1059) who underwent initial prostate biopsy from January 
2006 to December 2010 in Huashan Hospital were recruited in the 
training cohort. All the clinical information were collected before 
biopsy. The patients were excluded if any essential clinical data on 
age, PSA, %fPSA, PV, DRE result, or TRUS result were missing. The 
characteristics of tertiary health institutes in China were described in 
our previous study. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Population of the validation study 
Patients (n = 828) who underwent initial prostate biopsy from January 
2011 to December 2014 were consecutively enrolled in our prospective, 
observational validation study. Participants who completed all the 
examinations (PSA, fPSA, DRE, and TRUS) before biopsy were 
included in the final analysis. All the clinical data were collected and 
entered into the Huashan Risk calculators to generate the Huashan 
Risk Index. In the validation study, the Huashan Risk index did not 
influence the decision-making of prostate biopsy. In both training 
and validation studies, all men underwent an ultrasound-guided 
transperineal needle prostate biopsy with 6-core before October 2007 
or 10-core thereafter. The indications for prostate biopsy at our institute 
were the following: (1) tPSA &gt;4.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>, (2) tPSA &lt;4.0 ng ml 
−1 with 
suspicious fPSA/tPSA &lt;0.16 or PSA density &gt;0.15 (PSAD = tPSA/PV, 
PV (ml) = height (cm) × length (cm) × width (cm) × 0.52), (3) positive 
findings from a digital rectal exam (DRE) with any level of tPSA, </p>

<p>and (4) positive findings from imaging techniques such as transrectal 
ultrasound (TRUS) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) with any 
level of tPSA. </p>

<p>Sample collection 
All specimens were diagnosed by the same group of pathologists from 
the Pathology Department of Huashan Hospital. All blood samples 
were collected before biopsy and were measured by the Department 
of Clinical Laboratory for tPSA and fPSA. The protocol of the current 
study was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Review Board 
of Huashan Hospital, Fudan University, Shanghai, China. Both written 
and verbal informed consent were obtained from patients for their 
participation in the study. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Based on our former studies, we built two risk calculators in the training 
cohort (n = 1059) from 2006 to 2010. 
11 Risk calculator 1 (RC1) was 
built according to the rules of a logistic regression model based on age, 
result of DRE, PV, logPSA (logarithm of PSA), %fPSA, and TRUS result. 
Risk calculator 2 (RC2) was built according to the rules of a logistic 
regression model based on age, result of DRE, logPSA (logarithm 
of PSA), and %fPSA. The dichotomous variables (TRUS and DRE 
results) were considered as 1 for positive and 0 for negative in the 
risk calculators. Then, we evaluated the performances of PSA, PCPT 
risk calculator, and Huashan RC1 and RC2 for predicting PCa and 
high-grade PCa in the training cohort, the validation cohort and 
their subgroups (e.g., population with PSA ranging from 2.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>to 20.0 ng ml 
−1 and population with PSA ranging from 2.0 ng ml 
−1 to 
10.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>). 
In the current study, the PCPT risk calculation was performed using 
the available formula. 
9 PSA was also used as a reference prediction tool 
in our analysis. The high-grade PCa was defined as PCa with a Gleason 
Score ≥8 according to the Chinese Urological Association (CUA) 
guideline. 
12 Evaluation of the PCPT risk calculator was excluded 
in high-grade PCa in the criteria for high-grade PCa in the CUA 
guidelines 
12 and EAU (European Association of Urology) guidelines. 
Since the epidemiological database was not well established in China, the 
risk factor of family history in PCPT risk calculator was ignored in the 
analysis. The baseline characteristics (age, prostate volume, logPSA, and 
%fPSA) between two cohorts were compared using t-test for continuous 
variables or Chi-squared test for categorical variables (DRE result, 
TRUS result, and PCa detection rate under 6-or 10-core). Z-test was 
performed to evaluate the differences among area under the receiver 
operating characteristic curves (AUCs) of the two risk calculators, 
PCPT risk calculator and PSA. Two-sided test with P = 0.05 was used. 
Statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">19.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Statistical Product and Service Solutions, IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
A total of 1059 patients were included in the training study and 
828 patients were included in the validation study. </p>

<p>Training study 
The characteristics of the study population and the stratified 
subgroups (PSA ranging from 2.0 ng ml 
−1 to 20.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>) are shown in 
Supplementary Table 1. In the training cohort and its subgroup with 
PSA ranging from 2.0 ng ml 
−1 to 20.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>, the mean age, logPSA, and 
positive rates of DRE result and TRUS result were statistically higher 
in men diagnosed with PCa than in men without PCa whereas the 
mean PV and %fPSA were lower in PCa group (all P &lt; 0.05). When the 
patients were categorized by Gleason Score ≥8 as high-grade PCa and </p>

<p>Figure 1: Flowchart of the study population and study design. </p>

<p>Asian Journal of Andrology </p>

<p>Risk calculators for prostate cancer 
YS Wu et al </p>



<p>others, the differences in age, PV, and %fPSA became less significant 
or nonsignificant in two groups, whereas the differences in logPSA, 
positive rates of DRE results and TRUS results remained significant. 
Multivariate logistic regression analyses were performed to evaluate 
each factor in the training cohort. We observed that age, DRE result, 
TRUS result, PV, PSA, and %fPSA were still associated with PCa and 
high-grade PCa (all had P &lt; 0.05). On the basis of the results from the 
logistic regression analysis and the consensus risk factors (e.g., age, 
DRE result, TRUS result, PV, PSA, and %fPSA), we constructed the 
Huashan risk calculators as follows: 
(i) Huashan risk calculator I (RC 1) for PCa: risk points = −7.552 + 
0.05 × age + 1.636 × DRE − 0.035 × PV + 3.675 × logPSA − 0.02× 
%fPSA + 1.137 × TRUS 
(ii) Huashan risk calculator I (RC 1) for high-grade PCa: risk points 
= −4.041 − 0.006 × age + 0.455 × DRE + 1.325 × logPSA + 0.008× 
%fPSA − 0.013 × PV + 1.513 × TRUS 
(iii) Huashan risk calculator II (RC 2) for PCa: risk points = −7.983 
+ 0.051 × age + 2.333 × DRE + 3.146 × logPSA − 0.047× %fPSA 
(iv) Huashan risk calculator II (RC 2) for high-grade PCa: risk points 
= −4.417 + 0.004 × age + 1.055 × DRE + 1.252 × logPSA + 0.009× 
%fPSA. 
In further analysis, the prediction accuracy of PSA, PCPT risk 
calculator, and Huashan risk calculators were evaluated in the training 
cohort. The area under the receiver operating curves (AUCs) of the 
different PCa risk calculators in the training cohorts and its subgroup 
are shown in Supplementary Table 2. In the training cohort and its 
subgroup, when predicting PCa, the AUCs of RC 1 and RC 2 were 
0.926 and 0.901, respectively, which indicated that both performed 
better than the PCPT risk calculator (AUC = 0.860) (P &lt; 0.05). 
Similar results were also observed in patients with PSA ranging from 
2.0 to 10.0 ng ml 
−1 in the training cohort (Supplementary Table 3). 
When predicting high-grade PCa (a Gleason score ≥8), there was 
no significant difference among the AUCs of PSA (AUC = 0.781), 
RC 1 (AUC = 0.838), and RC 2 (AUC = 0.814) in the training cohort. </p>

<p>Validation study 
In the subsequent validation study, we evaluated the performance of the 
Huashan risk calculators in a prospective cohort. The characteristics of 
the validation cohort and its subgroup (PSA ranging from 2.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>to 20.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>) are shown in Supplementary Table 4. In this cohort 
and its subgroup, the baseline characteristics were consistent with 
those of the training group. 
When we evaluated the prediction abilities of the risk calculators 
in the validation cohort and its subgroup, RC 1 outperformed 
the PCPT risk calculator (0.849 vs 0.779 in the whole validation 
cohort and 0.765 vs 0.663 in its subgroup) whereas no significant 
difference in the AUCs was observed between the PCPT risk 
calculator and RC 2 in predicting PCa. Similar results were also 
observed in patients with PSA that ranged from 2.0 to 10.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>in the validation cohort (Supplementary Table 3). When predicting 
high-grade PCa, there was no significant difference among the AUCs 
of PSA (AUC = 0.879), RC 1 (AUC = 0.855), and RC 2 (AUC = 0.886) 
in the entire validation cohort. 
The receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves of PSA, PCPT 
risk calculator, RC 1, and RC 2 in predicting PCa in two cohorts are 
shown in Figures 2 and 3. The ROC curves of the RCs in predicting 
PCa in the subgroups with PSA ranged from 2.0 ng ml 
−1 to 20.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>are provided in Supplementary Figures 1 and 2. 
We also evaluated the reduction of biopsy cases using different 
PCa risk calculators compared with using PSA only (Supplementary </p>

<p>Table 5). For instance, with a sensitivity of 80%, the PCPT risk 
calculator, RC 1, and RC 2 could spare 6.67%, 22.74%, and 18.60%, 
respectively, of the patients in the training cohort who did not have 
PCa from undergoing unnecessary procedures. For patients in the 
validation cohort, the PCPT risk calculator, RC 1, and RC 2 at a 
sensitivity of 80% could spare 25.60%, 29.67%, and 16.94%, respectively, 
of unnecessary biopsies. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to build a risk 
calculator based on Chinese patients who underwent prostate 
biopsy. First, we performed univariate and multivariate analyses in a 
retrospective training cohort and built the Huashan risk calculators 
(RC 1 and RC 2). We found that the Huashan risk calculators (especially 
RC 1) performed better than the PCPT risk calculator and PSA alone 
for predicting PCa. Second, we validated the Huashan risk calculators 
in a prospective, observational study. We found that RC 1 performed 
better than the PCPT risk calculator in the validation cohort as well. 
Finally, we evaluated the reduction rate of biopsy using risk calculators 
and found that RC 1 still had added value on avoiding unnecessary 
biopsies. 
The goal of PCa screening is to identify the presence of curable 
disease while minimizing unnecessary biopsies. Using PSA and other 
clinical information at the time of screening, it is possible to predict 
the risk of PCa more precisely than using PSA alone. Thus, several PCa 
risk calculators had been developed in several studies and validated 
in a variety of populations (e.g., non-Hispanic whites, Hispanics, and 
African Americans). 
The two most widely used risk calculators are the PCPT risk 
calculator and ERSPC risk calculator 3. A recent meta-analysis 
showed that the summary AUC of the PCPT risk calculator was 
0.66 (95% CI: 0.62-0.70) and the AUC of the ERSPC RC 3 was 0.79 
(95% CI: 0.77-0.81). In the initial screening, the PCPT risk calculator 
was slightly better than PSA at predicting PCa whereas ERSPC was 
much better. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>In the current study, our risk calculators were based on available 
information without any further invasive procedures. The PCPT risk 
calculator included the variables of PSA, family history of prostate 
cancer, DRE, a prior negative prostate biopsy, race, and age. It had 
been previously evaluated in Western populations and a Chinese 
population, and it was widely recognized. The AUCs of the PCPT risk 
calculator in the Western populations ranged from 0.57 to 0.69, and 
the AUC was higher (0.78) in the Chinese population. 
6-8,14 However, 
the incompleteness of epidemiologic data in China was incomplete 
in the past decades due to ineffective health-care policies might have 
weakened the utility of the PCPT risk calculator (which uses race 
and family history) for predicting PCa in the Chinese population. 
Thus, we attempted to improve the PCa risk calculator for Chinese 
population. For the ERSPC risk calculator 3, the variable of age was 
not included. While age is considered an important risk factor for PCa 
and has been evaluated in several studies in both Western and Chinese 
populations, 
15-18 we included age in our risk calculators. Moreover, 
the characteristics of the cohorts in the current study were different 
from the PCPT risk calculator cohort, particularly with respect to the 
inclusion in the initial study cohort (all the participants in this study 
had indications for prostate biopsy, whereas the participants in PCPT 
had PSA ≤3.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>) and biopsy cores (most of the participants in this 
study underwent the 10-core biopsy whereas 80% of the participants in 
PCPT underwent the 6-core biopsy). Since there is no PSA screening in 
the Chinese population due to the large population and social burden, </p>

<p>Asian Journal of Andrology </p>

<p>Risk calculators for prostate cancer 
YS Wu et al </p>



<p>Figure 3: The ROC curves of PSA, PCPT risk calculator, RC 1, and RC 2 in 
predicting PCa in the validation cohort. ROC: receiver operating characteristic; 
PCa: prostate cancer. </p>

<p>we decided that the PCa risk calculator should be tailored more to a 
biopsy population than to a screening population. 
Overall, in both training cohort and validation cohort, the overall 
positive detection rate of PCa was approximately 45%, which was 
higher than that in Western screening populations. 
5,6 The AUCs of 
PSA in the training and validation cohorts were 0.827 and 0.757, 
respectively, which were relatively high compared with Western 
studies (slightly above 0.5). This finding might be attributable to the 
fact that the current study was based on a biopsy population at higher 
risk for PCa. For example, some of the patients came to the urology 
department because of elevated PSA while others seeking help for 
their urinary symptoms. 
Our results showed that RC 1, which included age, result of DRE, 
PV, PSA (logarithm of PSA), %fPSA, and TRUS result, performed best 
among three risk calculators. This may be due to the fact that RC 1 
considered both prostate volume and TRUS results. Thus, our results 
implied that TRUS might be a useful diagnostic tool in predicting PCa 
in the Chinese population and that it had its value in helping both 
patients and urologists make the decision as to whether to perform a 
prostate biopsy in China. 
In the stratification analysis, the positive rate of PCa in the patients 
with PSA ranged from 2.0 to 20.0 ng ml 
−1 was approximately 23%-31%, 
which was comparable to the positive rate in Caucasian populations 
with PSA ranged from 2.0 to 10.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>. 
19,20 Other studies have also 
shown that the PCa positive rate in the Chinese biopsy population with 
PSA ranging from 4.0 to 10.0 ng ml 
−1 was approximately 20%, which 
was lower than the percentage reported in the Western population. </p>

<p>11,21,22 </p>

<p>Therefore, in this study, we performed subgroup analysis in patients 
with PSA in the range of 2.0-20.0 ng ml 
−1 to determine whether the 
PCPT risk calculator and our risk calculators could improve the PCa 
prediction ability. The results showed that RC 1 outperformed the 
PCPT risk calculator in the subgroup analysis whereas RC 2 did not. 
In addition, we evaluated the AUCs of different PCa risk calculators in 
the subgroups with PSA in the range of 2.0-10.0 ng ml 
−1 (the Western 
gray zone), and the result remained the same. </p>

<p>In addition, compared with using PSA alone, we demonstrated that 
using RC 1 led to a reduction in the number of unnecessary biopsies by 
at least 20% while maintaining a sensitivity of 80%. While maintaining 
a sensitivity of 90%, the reduction was as much as 50% and 38% in the 
training and validation cohorts, respectively. This finding indicated that 
urologists could reduce a proportion of unnecessary biopsies by adding 
the needed clinical variables into their consideration. This approach 
could both relieve the socioeconomic burden and avoid unnecessary 
invasive procedures. 
In our study, the Huashan risk calculator 1 provided an index that 
ranked from−3 to 4. According to our data, if a patient with Huashan 
risk calculator index of ≤−2 undergoes a prostate biopsy, the positive 
rate will be &lt;10%. When a patient has Huashan risk calculator index 
of ≥2, the risk of PCa is 80%-90%. For high-grade PCa risk calculator, 
if a patient with a Huashan risk calculator index of ≤−4 undergoes 
prostate biopsy, the positive rate of the high-grade PCa will be &lt;10%. 
When a patient has Huashan risk calculator index of ≥−1, the risk of 
high-grade PCa will be 70%-90% (Data were not shown in the results). 
These estimates indicated that our risk calculators could provide an 
intuitive means of using the data to help patients. 
The current study had several strengths: (i) we built two logistical 
models based on a biopsy population, and we validated two RCs and the 
PCPT risk calculator in a subsequent biopsy population; this approach 
implied that this was a retrospective and prospective study; (ii) a 
contemporary standard 10-core biopsy was used in most of the training 
cohort and the whole validation cohort; (iii) indications for prostate 
biopsy were based on the current Chinese guidelines without research 
inclusion criteria; and (iv) because TRUS is widely used in China to 
help urologists make the decision as to whether to biopsy, we included 
the PV and TRUS results in RC 1 to determine whether TRUS really 
works. However, there were several limitations in our study. First, the 
study population was from a single tertiary health institute which could 
lead to selection bias. Nevertheless, as we mentioned above, tertiary 
health institutes in China, receive patients from all over the country. 
Therefore, our study population could be partially representative of the </p>

<p>Figure 2: The ROC curves of PSA, PCPT risk calculator, RC 1, and RC 2 in 
predicting PCa in the training cohort. ROC: receiver operating characteristic; 
PCa: prostate cancer. </p>

<p>Asian Journal of Andrology </p>

<p>Risk calculators for prostate cancer 
YS Wu et al </p>



<p>Chinese population. Second, the study population was at relatively high 
risk for PCa as we noted above, and thus the risk calculator might be 
more applicable to other biopsy populations rather than to screening 
populations. Third, the use of a different definition of high-grade PCa 
in the Chinese guidelines might restrict the application of the risk 
calculators for predicting high-grade PCa in other populations. Fourth, 
the performance of ERSPC RC 3 was not tested in the current study 
for lack of formulae. Since ERSPC risk calculator is also a logistic 
regression based risk calculator and is known to perform better than 
PCPT risk calculator, it might perform equivalent to the Huashan risk 
calculators. Although the Huashan risk calculators were more tailored 
to a Chinese biopsy population with relatively high risk, it still required 
further refinement and validation. 
In future study, we first intend to enlarge the sample size of the cohort 
and conduct a multicenter study. Second, we will modify the formulas 
of our risk calculators in the enlarged training population to make it 
more accurate and stable. Third, we will validate the risk calculators 
in other populations from the joint center and community. If the risk 
calculators truly work, we will build a website or an app and recommend 
that urologists use it to assess their patients before prostate biopsy. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
The Huashan risk calculators might have added value for predicting 
PCa in the Chinese population; it also resulted in a considerable 
reduction in unnecessary biopsies for PCa while missing only a few 
cases. However, it requires further evaluation in larger populations. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS 
YSW, RN, QD, JFX, and YHS conceived and designed the study. YSW, 
SHL, NZ, YHC, and HWJ performed the experiments. YSW, RN 
analyzed the data. PDB, SJT, LMZ, and MBH contributed materials and 
analysis tools. YSW, NZ, and SHL wrote the manuscript. All authors 
read and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>COMPETING INTERESTS 
All authors declared no competing interests. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank all the people who took part in this study. 
This study was sponsored by the National Natural Science Foundation 
of China (No. 81272835 and No. 81402339) and the Clinical Science and 
Technology Innovation Project of Shanghai Shen Kang Hospital Development 
Center (No. SHDC12015105). </p>

<p>Supplementary information is linked to the online version of the study on 
the Asian Journal of Andrology website. </p>



<p>Supplementary Figure 1: The ROC curves of PSA, PCPT risk calculator, RC 1, and RC 2 in predicting PCa in the subgroups of training cohort with PSA ranged 
from 2.0 ng ml 
−1 to 20.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>. ROC: receiver operating characteristic; PCa: prostate cancer. </p>

<p>Supplementary Figure 2: The ROC curves of PSA, PCPT risk calculator, RC 1, and RC 2 in predicting PCa in the subgroups of the validation cohort with PSA 
ranged from 2.0 ng ml 
−1 to 20.0 ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>. ROC: receiver operating characteristic; PCa: prostate cancer. </p>

<p>Supplementary Table 1: Clinical characteristics of the training cohort </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Supplementary Table 2: Evaluation of the area under the receiver operating curves (AUCs) of different PCa risk calculators </p>

<p>Supplementary Table 3: Evaluation of the area under the curves (AUCs) 
of different PCa risk calculators </p>

<p>Supplementary Table 4: Clinical characteristics of the validation cohort </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Supplementary Table 5: Number of biopsies reduced by different PCa 
risk calculators comparing with PSA </p>

</text></tei>