<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5435914" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p27 
Kip1 (p27) 
also behaves as a transcriptional repressor. Data 
showing that the p300/CBP-associated factor 
(PCAF) acetylates p27 inducing its degradation sug-
gested that PCAF and p27 could collaborate in the 
regulation of transcription. However, this possibility 
remained to be explored. We analyzed here the tran-
scriptional programs regulated by PCAF and p27 in 
the colon cancer cell line HCT116 by chromatin im-
munoprecipitation sequencing (ChIP-seq). We iden-
tified 269 protein-encoding genes that contain both 
p27 and PCAF binding sites being the majority of 
these sites different for PCAF and p27. PCAF or p27 
knock down revealed that both regulate the expres-
sion of these genes, PCAF as an activator and p27 
as a repressor. The double knock down of PCAF and 
p27 strongly reduced their expression indicating that 
the activating role of PCAF overrides the repressive 
effect of p27. We also observed that the transcrip-
tion factor Pax5 interacts with both p27 and PCAF 
and that the knock down of Pax5 induces the ex-
pression of p27/PCAF target genes indicating that 
it also participates in the transcriptional regulation 
mediated by p27/PCAF. In summary, we report here 
a previously unknown mechanism of transcriptional 
regulation mediated by p27, Pax5 and PCAF. </p>

<p>The protein p27 
Kip1 (p27) is a member of the Cip/Kip fam-
ily of cyclin dependent kinase (Cdk) inhibitors that also in-
cludes p21 
Cip1 and p57 
Kip2 (1). Its classical role is to inhibit </p>

<p>the activity of most cyclin-Cdk complexes involved in cell 
cycle progression. It interacts with both cyclin and Cdk sub-
units by the KID domain sited on its amino moiety (2). 
The KID consists of three subdomains: the cyclin-binding 
subdomain (D1), the Cdk-binding subdomain (D2) and a 
linker subdomain that joins D1 and D2 (3). Phosphoryla-
tion of specific tyrosine residues in the D2 subdomain (Y74 
and Y88), by members of the Src family of kinases, allows 
the partial activation of the Cdk in the trimeric complexes 
formed by cyclin, Cdk and p27 (4, 5). Thus, p27 behaves as a 
dual regulator of cyclin-Cdk complexes by inhibiting their 
activities in the non-tyrosine phosphorylated form and al-
lowing Cdk to be active when phosphorylated at these spe-
cific tyrosine residues. 
p27 directly interacts with the acetyltransferase and 
transcriptional co-activator p300/CBP associated factor 
(PCAF) by a region (aa 91-120) containing a proline rich 
domain (PRD, aa 91-96) included in the D2 subdomain 
of p27 (6). PCAF interacts with p27 by its catalytic do-
main and acetylates p27 at Lysine 100, very close to the 
PRD. This acetylation induces its ubiquitylation and the 
subsequent degradation via proteasome (6). Thus, Src ki-
nases and PCAF regulate cell cycle progression by generat-
ing post-translational modifications of p27 that lead to the 
activation of cyclin-Cdk complexes. 
p27 also plays a role as a transcriptional regulator (7-
9). It associates with a number of gene promoters through 
E2F4/p130 complexes behaving as a transcriptional repres-
sor of these genes (9). The specific role of p27 on these re-
pressor complexes is to recruit cyclin D2/D3-Cdk4 com-
plexes needed for p130 phosphorylation at early-mid G1 
phase (10). This possibility is supported by the fact that 
the interaction of p27 with E2F4 and p130 is through its 
carboxyl-moiety (9) indicating that the KID subdomain in 
the NH2 region will be free to associate with cyclin-Cdk </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +934035386; Fax: +934021907; Email: obachs@ub.edu </p>

<p>C The Author(s) 2017. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 9 5087 </p>

<p>complexes when they appear at early G1. The role of p27 as 
a transcriptional repressor mediated by E2F4/p130 com-
plexes has been confirmed by a recent work showing that 
p27 represses transcription of SOX2 through this mecha-
nism (11). 
p27 deficiency is associated with tumorigenesis and re-
duced p27 levels are frequently observed in human cancers 
in association with tumor aggressiveness and poor clini-
cal outcome (12-14). In most of the cases, low p27 levels 
are due to post-transcriptional mechanisms that induce its 
proteasome-dependent degradation (15, 16). Interestingly, 
the over-expression of p27-target genes (p27-TGs) in hu-
man tumors correlates with poor clinical outcome suggest-
ing that the transcriptional regulatory function of p27 plays 
an important role in tumor development (9). Thus, to un-
derstand how p27 regulates transcription is an important 
goal to be achieved not only to better define the mechanisms 
involved in cell cycle regulation but also the role of p27 in 
tumorigenesis. 
The evidence that the transcriptional co-activator PCAF 
acetylates the repressor p27 inducing its degradation (6) 
led us to investigate whether these two proteins collaborate 
in the regulation of gene expression. We performed chro-
matin immunoprecipitation sequencing (ChIP-seq) analysis 
to identify the putative transcriptional programs regulated 
by these two proteins. We selected a number of targets com-
mon to both proteins and analyzed the mechanism by which 
p27 and PCAF regulate the transcription of these genes. In-
terestingly, we found that the transcription factor PAX5 in-
teracts with both p27 and PCAF and also participates in 
the transcriptional regulation of p27/PCAF target genes. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Antibodies </p>

<p>Antibodies against p27 (ChIP and IP) (sc-528), PAX-5 
(WB) (sc-13146), PAX-5 (WB) (sc-1974), UNC5D (WB) 
(anti-UNC5H4, sc-135262), PCAF (WB) (sc-13124), SPAG 
9 (WB) (anti-JIP-4, sc-134972) and ROBO1 (WB) (sc-
25672) were from Santa Cruz. p27 antibody (WB) (610242) 
was from BD Transduction Laboratories. Antibodies 
against PCAF (WB) (P7493) and tubulin (WB) (T9026) 
were from Sigma. Antibodies against PCAF (ChIP/IP) 
(ab12188) and PAX-5 (ChIP/IP, WB) (ab15164) were from 
Abcam. GRIN3A antibodies (WB) (MA1-10881) were 
from Thermo Fisher Scientific and actin antibody (WB) 
(0869100) was obtained from MP Biomedicals. </p>

<p>Cell cultures </p>

<p>HCT116 cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Ea-
gle's medium (DMEM)-HAM F12 (1:1). MCF-7 cells and 
mice embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs) WT and p27 
−/− were 
cultured in DMEM supplemented with 10% fetal bovine 
serum, 2 mM glutamine, 1% non-essential amino acids, 1 
mM pyruvic acid and 5% penicillin/streptomycin. Cultures 
were maintained at 37 
• C and 5% CO 2 . </p>

<p>Determination of generation time </p>

<p>Generation time was determined in HCT116 Control, p27 
and PCAF cells transfected with the CRISPR plasmid as </p>

<p>described in CRISPR/Cas9 transfection section. Cells were 
seeded at a density of 300 000 cells per 60 mm dish to deter-
mine their proliferation. We calculated the rate of growth of 
each cell line by counting the total number of viable cells in 
duplicate dishes for 24, 48, 72 and 96 h with the Scepter™ 
2.0 Cell Counter (Millipore). </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>Asynchronously growing HCT116 cells were scraped and 
washed twice with PBS. Pellets were lysed in 1 ml of im-
munoprecipitation (IP) buffer (PBS containing 0.5% Tri-
ton X-100, 1 mM EDTA, 100 M sodium orthovanadate, 
0.25 mM PMSF, 20 mM ␤ glycerol phosphate, complete 
protease inhibitor mixture by Roche Applied Science, and 
1/25 vol of DNAse I) (Sigma). Cell lysates were incubated 
for 15 min rotating at RT and 15 min on ice. Then, they 
were centrifuged at 3000 rpm at 4 
• C for 5 min. After cen-
trifugation, samples were subsequently quantified using the 
Lowry method (17). 1 mg of total protein was incubated 
overnight at 4 
• C with 2-4 g of antibodies (PAX5, p27 or 
PCAF). Proteins and antibody were incubated with pro-
tein A-Dynabeads (Invitrogen) for 1 h and the immunocom-
plexes were extensively washed with IP buffer. Subsequently 
they were eluted by boiling at 100 
• C in Laemmli buffer for 
western blot (WB) analysis. As a control, lysates were incu-
bated with irrelevant rabbit IgG. </p>

<p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) </p>

<p>HCT116 cells were asynchronously grown till achieve an 
80% confluence. ChIP assays were then performed as previ-
ously described (18). Briefly, cells were lysed and chromatin 
from cross-linked cells was sonicated. Chromatin was in-
cubated with 5 g of anti-p27, anti-PCAF or anti-PAX5 
antibodies in RIPA buffer (50 mM Tris−HCl pH 7.5, 150 
mM NaCl, 1% NP-40, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 0.1% 
SDS, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT, 1 mM PMSF, 0.1 mM 
Na 3 VO 4 , 0.5 g/l aprotinin, 10 g/l leupeptin) adding 
20 l of Magna ChIP Protein A magnetic beads (Milli-
pore). Samples were incubated in rotation overnight at 4 
• C. 
Beads were washed with low salt buffer, high salt buffer, 
LiCl buffer and TE buffer. Subsequent elution and purifi-
cation of the immunoprecipitated DNA-proteins complexes 
was performed using the IPure kit (Diagenode) according to 
manufacturer's protocol. Samples were analyzed by qPCR. 
The association of p27 and PCAF to their respective bind-
ing sites of the gene Grin3A, SPAG9, ROBO1 and UNC5D 
was performed by RT-PCR using the primers listed in Sup-
plementary Table S1. </p>

<p>ChIP-seq </p>

<p>HCT116 cells were grown to confluence and made quies-
cent by serum starvation during 48 h for doing the ChIP-seq 
for p27. In contrast, asynchronously growing HCT116 cells 
were used for the ChIP-seq studies using anti-PCAF. After 
DNA isolation, ChIP samples, together with the input, were 
sequenced. Libraries were prepared using the NEBNext </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>ChIP-Seq Library Prep Reagent Set for Illumina 
® kit (ref. 
E6200S) according to the manufacturer's protocol. Briefly, </p>



<p>10 ng of input and ChIP enriched DNA were subjected 
to end repair, addition of 'A' bases to 3 ends and ligation 
of PE adapters. All purification steps were performed us-
ing Qiagen PCR purification columns (refs. 50928106 and 
50928006). Library size selection was done with 2% low-
range agarose gels. Library amplification was performed by 
PCR on the size selected fragments. Final libraries were an-
alyzed using Agilent DNA 1000 chip to estimate the quan-
tity and check size distribution, and were then quantified 
by qPCR using the KAPA Library Quantification Kit (ref. 
KK4835, KapaBiosystems) prior to amplification with Illu-
mina's cBot. Sequencing was done on the HiSeq2000, Single 
Read, 50 nts. </p>

<p>ChIP-seq data analysis </p>

<p>Illumina pipeline analyzed short reads were uniquely 
aligned allowing at best two mismatches to the UCSC (The 
Genome Sequencing Consortium) human genome version 
hg18, using the program <rs type="software">BOWTIE</rs> (19). Peak caller algo-
rithm <rs id="software-14" type="software">MACS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-14" type="version-number">version 1.4</rs>) was used to determine enriched 
peak region with parameters: -nomodel, -tsize = 46, -bw = 
300. Shift size were determined using <rs type="software">Pyicos</rs> (20) strand cor-
relation method. Enriched peaks were annotated to near-
est <rs id="software-16" type="software">EnsEMBL</rs> (21) gene (EnsEMBL Biomart <rs corresp="#software-16" type="version-number">version 54</rs>) 
using Bioconductor package <rs type="software">ChIPpeakAnno</rs> (22). Distri-
bution of enriched reads along the genomes and transcrip-
tion start site (TSS) of RefSeq genes were determined using 
<rs type="software">CEAS</rs> (23). Data from ChIP-seq experiments have been de-
posited in GEO (accession number GSE93975). </p>

<p>De novo motif discovery </p>

<p>To determine the over-represented short sequence motifs in 
enriched peaks, we used total 100nt sequences (from peak 
summit, 50 bp down and 50 bp up). We used top 1000 
peaks (based on fold change) for finding motifs using both 
<rs type="software">WEEDER</rs> (24) and <rs type="software">MEME</rs> (25) programs. </p>

<p>Functional enrichment analysis </p>

<p>Functional annotation of target genes is based on Gene 
Ontology (GO) (26) Consortium, 2000; (http://www. 
geneontology.org) as extracted from <rs type="software">EnsEMBL</rs> (21) and 
KEGG pathway database (27). Accordingly, all genes are 
classified into the ontology categories biological process 
(GOBP) and pathways when possible. We have taken only 
the GO/pathway categories that have at least 10 genes an-
notated. We used <rs type="software">Gitools</rs> for enrichment analysis and heat 
map generation (28) (http://www.gitools.org). Resulting P-
values were adjusted for multiple testing using the Ben-
jamin and Hochberg's method of False Discovery Rate (29). 
Enrichment analysis was also performed using the public 
<rs type="software">DAVID</rs> tools (Database for Annotation, visualization and 
integrated discovery v 6.7) (http://david.abcc.ncifcrf.gov) 
(30). </p>

<p>Putative transcription factor binding </p>

<p>Possible occurrence of transcription factor (TF) motifs in 
peak regions (150 bp around peak summit), or in target gene </p>

<p>promoters were predicted with STORM algorithm (31) with 
a P-value cutoff determined based on the size of the input 
sequence as (1/100 × sequence-size), and using position fre-
quency matrices (PFM) from TRANSFAC database (pro-
fessional version release 2009.4). </p>

<p>Co-occurrence and enrichment of TFs around enriched peaks </p>

<p>Possible occurrence of TF motifs in peak regions (150 bp 
around peak summit) and overrepresentation of these TFs 
is based on the tool <rs type="software">Pscan</rs> (32) with parameter: mixed back-
ground hg18, TRANSFAC matrix. Pscan evaluates local 
enrichment, comparing with a t-test mean and standard de-
viation of the score of the best matching oligonucleotides in 
the input regions to mean and standard deviation of the best 
match in the genomic regions flanking the input ones. Local 
enrichment can be used to identify motifs with significant 
preference for binding within the regions, that is, the mo-
tif corresponding to the ChIP'ed TF, as well as other TFs 
likely to interact with it and binding in its neighborhood. 
Local enrichment P-value (L.PV): describing whether the 
motif is over-or underrepresented in the 150 bp input re-
gions with respect to the genomic regions flanking them, 
indicating whether the motif is overrepresented. </p>

<p>Overlap analysis </p>

<p>Overlap of genomic position range data was done using 
<rs type="software">BedTools</rs> (33) and significance of overlap was analyzed by 
Hypergeometric test. However, Venn-diagram generation 
and overlap of target genes analysis was performed using 
in-house R programming language script. Significance of 
overlap calculated based on Chi-square test. Unless stated, 
peak overlap is defined as overlap by at least 1 bp. </p>

<p>RNA extraction, reverse transcription-PCR and quantitative 
PCR (qPCR) for gene expression analysis </p>

<p>Total RNA from cells was extracted using High Pure RNA 
Isolation kit (Roche). cDNA was obtained from 1 g of 
RNA using SuperScript VILO cDNA synthesis (Invitro-
gen) according to manufacturer's instructions. Gene ex-
pression was analyzed by real-time PCR, using Express 
SYBR GreenER qPCR supermix (Invitrogen), corrected by 
GADPH expression and expressed as relative units. Primer 
sequences used for qPCR assessment of mRNA levels of 
target genes are listed in Supplementary Table S2. Primer 
sequences used for qPCR assessment of the primary non-
spliced transcripts of target genes are listed in Supplemen-
tary Table S3. </p>

<p>ShRNA lentiviral infection </p>

<p>HCT116 or MCF-7 cells were infected with MISSION 
shRNA control vector and specific p27 or PCAF shRNA 
(Sigma Aldrich) with the following sequences: 
p27: 5 -CCGGGTAGGATAAGTGAAATGGATAC 
TCGAGTATCCATTTCACTTATCCTACTTTTTG-3 
PCAF:5 -CCGGGCAGACTTACAGCGAGTCTTTC 
TCGAGAAAGACTCGCTGTAAGTCTGCTTTT-3 
The protocol for viral particles production and cell in-
fections has been described elsewhere (34). Twenty four </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 9 5089 </p>

<p>hours after infection, cells were selected with 2 mg/ml of 
Puromycin (Sigma Aldrich) for five days. shRNA-mediated 
down-regulation was tested by WB with specific antibodies. </p>

<p>CRISPR/Cas9 transfection </p>

<p>HCT116 cells were co-transfected with Control 
CRISPR/Cas9 (sc-418922), p27 CRISPR/Cas9 KO 
(sc-400074) or PCAF CRISPR/Cas9 KO (sc-400753) plas-
mids from Santa Cruz and with pLPCX plasmid (K1061-1, 
Clontech) using Lipofectamine 2000 transfection reagent 
(Invitrogen P/N 52887) according to manufacturer's 
protocol. Transfected cells were subsequently selected with 
media containing 2 mg/ml of Puromycin (Sigma Aldrich) 
for 3-5 days. Successful transfection was confirmed by 
WB with specific antibodies. For the stable generation 
of a p27KO cell line we used the CRISPR/Cas9 system 
transfecting HCT116 cells with p27 Double Nickase Plas-
mid (sc-400074-NIC) and with Control Double Nickase 
(sc-437281) for the control cell line. Individual GFP pos-
itive colonies were isolated by cell sorting (FACSAriaII) 
and seeded in 96-well plates and grown for 2-3 weeks 
until the positive colonies reached confluence when they 
were transferred to 24-well plates. When the latter reached 
confluence, cells were trypsinized and an aliquot was kept 
for protein screening by WB and mRNA levels validation. 
The remaining cells were frozen or expanded in 60 mm 
dishes for additional analyses. </p>

<p>Expression microarrays </p>

<p>Asynchronously growing HCT116 cells were washed with 
PBS and RNA was isolated from 3 different sets of cells 
transfected with shRNA control or shRNAPCAF. To-
tal RNA was extracted using the RNeasy Kit (Qiagen, 
Iberia, Madrid, Spain). RNA quality control was done with 
Agilent 2100 bioanalyzer. Samples were then hybridized 
with Affymetrix Human Gene 1.0 ST arrays. Dataset ob-
tained by Expression Console (Affymetrix) were analyzed 
by DNA-ChIP Analyzer (dChIP) software and tools. The 
normalization of the arrays was performed using the ro-
bust multi-array average (RMA) method as implemented in 
the Affymetrix package of R bioconductor. Quality control 
measurements were obtained with ArrayQualityMetrics, 
while the statistical analysis of significant hits with <rs type="software">Limma</rs> 
(35). Data from expression microarray experiments have 
been deposited in GEO (accession number GSE93694). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Differential distribution of PCAF and p27 chromatin binding 
sites in HCT116 cells </p>

<p>To analyze the transcriptional programs regulated by p27, 
ChIP-seq experiments were performed in HCT116 cells. Re-
sults showed that p27 significantly binds to the chromatin 
at 1981 sites that corresponded to 1012 genes. Analysis of 
p27-binding sites (p27-BSs) distribution overall genome in-
dicates that it mostly associates to distal intergenic regions 
(∼74%) and to intronic sequences (∼24%). In contrast, as-
sociation with proximal and exonic regions was minimal 
(Figure 1A). ChIP-seq analyses were also performed to </p>

<p>identify the putative PCAF-BSs. Results showed that PCAF 
associates to the chromatin at 10.878 specific sites that cor-
responded to 6.131 genes. PCAF mostly associates with dis-
tal intergenic (∼42%), intronic (∼42%) and exonic (∼8%) 
sequences. Interestingly, its association to proximal regions, 
although low (∼4%), was much higher than p27 (Figure 
1A). Because neither p27 nor PCAF interact directly with 
DNA, their association with chromatin has to be mediated 
by chromatin associated proteins. 
We also analyzed the distribution of p27-and PCAF-
BSs over chromosomes. As shown in Supplementary Figure 
S1, PCAF-BSs significantly accumulated in chromosomes 
8, 10, 16, 17, 19, 20, 21 and 22. Interestingly, the distribution 
of p27-BSs was quite similar. They accumulated in chromo-
somes 8, 10, 16, 17, 21 and Y. It worth's noting that the pres-
ence of both p27 and PCAF-BSs in chromosome X was ex-
tremely reduced. Finally, we also analyzed the biotype pro-
file of the genes potentially regulated by p27 or PCAF. In the 
case of PCAF the 76% of the genes were encoding for pro-
teins, the 13% for pseudogenes and the remaining 11% cor-
responded to non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs) (Figure 1B). In-
triguingly, the 41% of the genes putatively regulated by p27 
corresponded to nc-RNAs (23%) and to pseudogenes (18%) 
and only the 59% were genes encoding for proteins (Figure 
1B). These results indicate that both, p27 and PCAF, but 
p27 in a higher extension, can play a significant role in the 
expression of nc-RNAs and pseudogenes. </p>

<p>Gene ontology analysis of p27-BSs and PCAF-BSs </p>

<p>Gene ontology (GO) analysis of the protein encoding 
genes potentially regulated by p27 was performed using the 
DAVID program. Results revealed that the four more signif-
icant biological processes were: cell adhesion, neuron differ-
entiation, cell-cell signaling and ion transport (Figure 2A). 
In the case of PCAF, due the high number of peaks, the 
analyses had to be done in two separated groups. One group 
contained the genes with PCAF-BSs in intragenic regions 
and the other included genes with PCAF-BSs in intergenic 
regions. Interestingly, the four biological processes enriched 
in p27-target genes (p27-TGs) were also significantly en-
riched (Figure 2B and C). We observed that around 50% 
of p27-TGs in these four groups also contained PCAF-BSs 
(Supplementary Figure S2). These results suggest that p27 
and PCAF can collaborate in the transcriptional regulation 
of genes involved in these cellular functions. To further con-
firm this data, GO analysis using the Gitools program was 
additionally performed. Results showed that three of the 
biological processes (cell adhesion, neuron differentiation 
and ion transport) shared by p27 and PCAF-TGs were also 
found to be significantly enriched using this more restrictive 
program (Figure 2D). 
We next aimed to identify DNA consensus sequences that 
could interact with p27 or with PCAF using the MEME 
tool. These analyses allowed the identification of two con-
sensus sequences for p27 and three other sequences for 
PCAF (Figure 2E). </p>



<p>Genome HCT116 </p>

<p>ChIP p27 
ChIP PCAF </p>

<p>1.50 1.90 1.30 2.00 
0.70 </p>

<p>1.40 </p>

<p>7.60 </p>

<p>41.70 </p>

<p>41.60 </p>

<p>0.05 
0.25 
0.20 0.50 0.05 0.20 
1.00 </p>

<p>23.70 </p>

<p>73.90 </p>

<p>1.10 
1.30 
0.90 
1.30 0.40 
1.40 
1.90 </p>

<p>41.60 
50.00 </p>

<p>Promoter (&lt;= 1000bp) </p>

<p>Promoter (1000-3000bp) </p>

<p>Dowstream (&lt;=1000bp) </p>

<p>Dowstream (1000-3000bp) </p>

<p>5'UTR </p>

<p>3'UTR </p>

<p>Coding exon </p>

<p>Intron </p>

<p>Distal intergenic </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>59% 
18% </p>

<p>23% </p>

<p>ChIP p27 
ChIP PCAF </p>

<p>76% </p>

<p>13% </p>

<p>11% </p>

<p>Protein coding </p>

<p>Pseudogen </p>

<p>Noncoding 
RNAs </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Figure 1. Distribution of p27-and PCAF-BSs on the chromatin. (A) Distribution of different chromatin regions overall genome of HCT116 cells (upper 
panel), p27-BSs (Bottom panel, left) and PCAF-BSs (Bottom panel, right) obtained by ChIP-seq experiments. Results are represented as percentage. (B) 
The different biotypes of genes putatively regulated by p27 (left) or PCAF (right) are represented as percentage. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 9 5091 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>PCAF 
p27 </p>

<p>GO p27-BSs 
GO PCAF-BSs (intra) </p>

<p>GO PCAF-BSs (inter) </p>

<p>C 
E </p>

<p>GO p27/PCAF-BSs </p>

<p>cell adhesion 
regulation of nervous system development 
regulation of neurogenesis 
regulation of neuron differentiation 
synaptic transmission 
regulation of developmental process 
positive regulation of cell differentiation 
cation transport 
positive regulation of muscle cell differentiation 
metal ion transport 
muscle cell differentiation 
regulation of protein homodimerization activity 
regulation of cell communication 
regulation of signaling 
developmental process 
anatomical structure development 
regulation of signal transduction 
regulation of cellular process 
homeostatic process 
regulation of cell development </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
Enrichment score </p>

<p>Cell adhesion </p>

<p>Cell-cell signaling </p>

<p>Neuron differentiation </p>

<p>Regulation of transcription </p>

<p>Embryonic organ development </p>

<p>1 
3 </p>

<p>Cell adhesion </p>

<p>Neuron differentiation </p>

<p>Cell-cell signaling </p>

<p>Ion transport </p>

<p>Enrichment score </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>9.5e-4 </p>

<p>2.6e-4 </p>

<p>2.3e-4 </p>

<p>1.2e-4 </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>Ion transport </p>

<p>Cell adhesion </p>

<p>Cell-cell signaling </p>

<p>Neuron differentiation </p>

<p>0 
4 
8 
Enrichment score </p>

<p>2 
6 
10 </p>

<p>2.4e-14 </p>

<p>1.6e-10 </p>

<p>1.6e-5 </p>

<p>7.3e-4 </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>1.8e-7 </p>

<p>5.2e-5 </p>

<p>7.8e-5 </p>

<p>5.3e-7 </p>

<p>2.3e-6 </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>E-value </p>

<p>E-value </p>

<p>Figure 2. Gene ontology analysis of protein encoding genes with p27-or PCAF-BSs in their proximity. The Database for Annotation, Visualization and 
Integrated Discovery (<rs type="software">DAVID</rs>) program was used to define biological processes enriched in the protein encoding genes putatively regulated by p27 (A), 
PCAF (intragenic BSs) (B) and PCAF (intergenic BSs) (C). (D) The <rs type="software">Gitools</rs> program was used to define biological processes enriched in the protein 
encoding genes putatively regulated by p27 or PCAF. (E) <rs type="software">MEME</rs> programs were used to identify short sequence motifs enriched in the p27-BSs (upper 
panel) or PCAF-BSs (bottom panel). </p>



<p>Identification of protein encoding genes containing p27-and 
PCAF-binding sites </p>

<p>By comparing the p27 and PCAF ChIP-seq data we iden-
tified 269 protein encoding genes that contain BSs for both 
proteins (Figure 3A). These genes represent the 45% of all 
the protein encoding p27-TGs, a percentage similar to that 
observed in the four biological processes most significantly 
regulated by these two proteins according to the GO analy-
sis (Supplementary Figure S2). Interestingly, in most cases, 
the chromatin region able to associate with PCAF is differ-
ent to that interacting with p27. GO analysis of these 269 
genes revealed that the biological processes ionic transport, 
cell adhesion, and cell-cell signaling were significantly en-
riched (Figure 3B). </p>

<p>Expression microarrays in HCT116 cells knocked down for 
PCAF </p>

<p>HCT116 cells were knocked down (KD) for PCAF us-
ing a specific shRNA (Supplementary Figure S3A). Then, 
expression microarray analyses, in PCAF-KD cells versus 
control, were performed. Results showed that 852 genes 
were differentially expressed in these cells being 557 genes 
up-regulated and 295 down-regulated (Figure 3C). GO 
analysis revealed that the most significantly enriched group 
was cell cycle (Figure 3D). Interestingly, GO analysis of 
down-regulated genes revealed that most of these cell cycle 
regulatory genes were down-regulated in PCAF-KD cells 
(Supplementary Figure S3B). These results suggest that 
PCAF regulates cell cycle progression by controlling the ex-
pression of a number of relevant cell cycle regulatory genes. 
Genes up-regulated are mainly involved in translation and 
apoptosis (Supplementary Figure S3C). 
On comparing ChIP-seq and expression microarrays data 
we observed that 156 genes from those differentially ex-
pressed in the PCAF-KD cells also showed PCAF-BSs sug-
gesting that PCAF participates in the regulation of the ex-
pression of these genes by associating with regulatory pro-
tein complexes at these specific sites (Figure 3E). The rest of 
the genes could be genes indirectly regulated by PCAF. GO 
analysis of these 156 genes showed that a significant num-
ber of them are involved in cellular functions related to cell 
adhesion and neurogenesis (Supplementary Figure S3D). 
We also observed that 5 of these genes (IGF1R, GABRG2, 
CRBN, SPAG9 and ZWINT) also contain p27-BSs (Figure 
3E). </p>

<p>Role of p27 and PCAF in the regulation of transcription </p>

<p>To define the role of p27 and PCAF on the expression 
of TGs we analyzed the effect of knocking down p27 
or/and PCAF on transcription of a number of selected 
common targets (Table 1) using specific shRNAs (Supple-
mentary Figure S3A). Determinations were performed in 
asynchronously proliferating cells (mostly in G1) thus min-
imizing the cell cycle progression differences between p27-
KD cells and PCAF-KD cells (both proliferating slightly 
faster than controls) as observed by determining the gener-
ation time (Supplementary Figure S4A and B). We found 
that in p27-KD cells the mRNA levels of most TGs were 
increased (Figure 4A). To investigate whether these higher </p>

<p>levels of mRNA were due to increased rates of transcription 
we determined the amount of the primary non-spliced tran-
scripts (PNST) by qPCR. Results revealed that these tran-
scripts were elevated in p27-KD cells indicating that p27 re-
presses transcription of these genes (Figure 4B). 
We also found that the mRNA levels of common TGs 
were significantly lower in PCAF-KD cells than in control 
cells (Figure 4C) and that this reduction was due to a de-
creased rate of transcription (Figure 4D). This indicates 
that PCAF activates transcription of these TGs. To con-
firm the transcriptional regulatory role of p27 and PCAF 
we performed similar experiments using the CRISPR/Cas9 
methodology. Thus, after knocking out p27 (Supplemen-
tary Figure S4A) we observed that the levels of mRNA and 
primary non-spliced transcripts were increased (Figures 4E 
and 4F). In contrast in PCAF-KD cells the levels of mRNA 
and primary non-spliced transcript were found to be de-
creased (Figure 4G and H). We analyzed the expression of 
specific target genes for only p27 or PCAF as controls (Sup-
plementary Figure S5A). The protein levels in p27KO or 
PCAF-KD cells were also determined (Supplementary Fig-
ure S5B). 
We also investigated the effect of the double KD (2KD) 
of p27 and PCAF on transcription. In 2KD-cells obtained 
using shRNAs we observed that the amount of the primary 
non-spliced transcripts was reduced in all the cases indi-
cating that the co-activator effect of PCAF overrides the 
repressor role of p27 in all the cases (Figure 5A). These 
results were corroborated by generating 2KD cells using 
CRISP/Cas9 (Figure 5B). In these cells the levels of mRNA 
(Figure 5C) primary non-spliced transcripts (Figure 5D) 
and protein (Supplementary Figure S5C) were significantly 
reduced. Additionally, KD experiments using the MCF-7 
breast cancer cell line gave similar results: whereas the KD 
p27 increased transcription of TGs, the KD of PCAF re-
duced their expression (Supplementary Figure S6). </p>

<p>PAX5 collaborates with p27 and PCAF in the regulation of 
transcription </p>

<p>The identification of TFs that could bind to p27-and 
PCAF-BSs was performed by studying 150 bp regions of 
these peaks (75 bp up the maximum and 75 bp down) by 
using the STORM tool for the scanning of the peaks and 
the TF-BSs motif position weight matrix from TRANS-
FAC. The ten TFs more significantly identified have been 
represented in a heat map that compares results from p27 
and PCAF (Figure 6A). Interestingly, only PAX5 appears 
to be able to significantly associate to the p27-BSs. In con-
trast, a number of different TFs can putatively associate to 
the PCAF-BSs and among these different candidates PAX5 
was one of the most significant (Figure 6A). Interestingly, 
The consensus sequence for Pax5 (Supplementary Figure 
S7) is quite similar to the sequences found for p27 and 
PCAF (Figure 2E and Supplementary Figure S7). Interest-
ingly, the sequence analysis of the chromatin peaks for p27 
and PCAF of a number of genes (Table 1) also revealed that 
these sequences also include regions of high similarity with 
the PAX5 consensus sequence (data not shown). Hence, 
we aimed to analyze the putative interaction of PAX5 with 
both p27 and PCAF by IP. We observed that PAX5 levels </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 9 5093 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>GO p27-and PCAF-BSs 
p27-and PCAF-BSs </p>

<p>GO PCAF regulated genes </p>

<p>2.1e-3 </p>

<p>9.0e-4 </p>

<p>1.1e-2 </p>

<p>3.5e-2 </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>4.4e-12 </p>

<p>1.2e-5 </p>

<p>1.1e-4 </p>

<p>2.1e-3 </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>1.1e-2 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Identification of genes putatively regulated by p27 and PCAF. (A) Venn diagram representing the number of genes encoding for proteins identified 
by ChIP-seq with anti-PCAF antibodies (pink) or with anti-p27 (blue). (B) The biological processes enriched in the group of genes sharing p27 and PCAF-
BSs (269 genes) were identified by using the <rs type="software">DAVID</rs> program. (C) Number of genes differentially expressed in PCAF-KD versus control HCT116 cells 
identified by expression microarray analysis and main characteristics of the data. (D) The biological processes enriched in the group of genes differentially 
expressed in PCAF-KD cells versus control were identified using the DAVID program. (E) Venn diagram representing the number of genes encoding for 
proteins identified by ChIP-seq with anti-PCAF antibodies (pink), with anti-p27 (blue) or differentially expressed in PCAF-KD cells (green). </p>

<p>5094 Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 9 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Fold enrichment </p>

<p>CR Ctrl 
CR p27 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** 
*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Fold enrichment </p>

<p>CR Ctrl 
CR p27 </p>

<p>G 
H </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>Fold enrichment </p>

<p>CR Ctrl </p>

<p>CR PCAF </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>Fold enrichment </p>

<p>CR Ctrl </p>

<p>CR PCAF </p>

<p>**** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>mRNA </p>

<p>mRNA </p>

<p>mRNA </p>

<p>mRNA </p>

<p>PNST </p>

<p>PNST </p>

<p>PNST </p>

<p>PNST </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effect of knocking down p27 or PCAF on the expression of target genes. (A) HCT116 cells were infected with a specific shRNA for p27 (shp27) 
or with a control shRNA (sh(-)). Then, mRNA levels of different common target genes (see Table 1) were determined by qPCR. In these cells, the levels of 
primary non spliced transcripts (PNST) were also determined by qPCR (B). (C) HCT116 cells were infected with a specific shRNA for PCAF (shPCAF) 
or with a control shRNA (sh(-)) and the levels of mRNA of different common target genes were subsequently determined by qPCR. In these cells, the 
levels of primary non spliced transcripts (PNST) were also determined by qPCR (D). Levels of mRNA (E) or of primary non spliced transcripts (PNST) 
(F) from different common target genes were determined in p27 knocked down cells using the CRISPR/Cas9 (CR p27) methodology and in control cells 
(CR Ctrl). Levels of mRNA (G) or of primary non spliced transcripts (PNST) (H) from different common target genes were determined in PACF knocked 
down cells using the CRISPR/Cas9 (CR PCAF) methodology and in control cells (CR Ctrl). In all experiments results are the mean value ± SEM of four 
independent experiments and are represented as fold enrichment versus control. Statistical analyses were performed using the t-student's test. *P &lt; 0.05, 
**P &lt; 0.01 and ***P &lt; 0.001. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 9 5095 </p>

<p>Table 1. List of selected genes that have both p27 and PCAF-binding sites (BSs) in their vicinity. The table includes localization and extension of the p27-
and PCAF-BSs and the intensity of the binding (Fold-enrichment) </p>

<p>ChIP-seq 
Cromosome 
Start 
End </p>

<p>Fold-
enrichment 
Inside feature 
Distance to feature </p>

<p>GABRG2 
p27 
chr5 
161583970 
161584252 
9.91 
Downstream 
156675 
PCAF 
chr5 
161580341 
161580611 
11.44 
Downstream 
153046 
GHR 
p27 
chr5 
42434475 
42434749 
8.49 
Upstream 
-25308 
PCAF 
chr5 
42267322 
42267561 
10.01 
Upstream 
-192461 
GRIN3A 
p27 
chr9 
103520403 
103520670 
8.49 
Inside 
20280 
PCAF 
chr9 
103539425 
103539691 
8.58 
Inside 
1258 
IGF1R 
p27 
chr15 
97121406 
97121648 
9.91 
Inside 
111104 
PCAF 
chr15 
97135969 
97136244 
11.86 
Inside 
125667 
PCAF 
chr15 
96961148 
96961421 
8.46 
Upstream 
-49154 
ROBO1 
p27 
chr3 
79257543 
79257776 
9.83 
Upstream 
-163 
PCAF 
chr3 
80182644 
80183002 
11.44 
Upstream 
-460893 
PCAF 
chr3 
80060831 
80061238 
10.15 
Upstream 
-339080 
UNC5D 
p27 
chr8 
35345752 
35346062 
8.49 
Inside 
132907 
p27 
chr8 
35652578 
35652839 
8.49 
Inside 
131126 
PCAF 
chr8 
35828412 
35828659 
8.58 
Downstream 
306960 
IL7 
p27 
chr8 
80047436 
80047703 
11.32 
Upstream 
-167123 
p27 
chr8 
80007304 
80007574 
9.91 
Upstream 
-126991 
PCAF 
chr8 
79892345 
79892640 
7.98 
Upstream 
-12032 
ARHGEF7 
p27 
chr13 
110645835 
110646168 
6.97 
Upstream 
-9802 
PCAF 
chr13 
110492766 
110493092 
10.15 
Upstream 
-73017 
RERGL 
p27 
chr12 
18151836 
18152131 
11.32 
Upstream 
-17455 
PCAF 
chr12 
17993973 
17994265 
12.87 
Downstream 
140408 
SPAG9 
p27 
chr17 
46415723 
46416022 
8.9 
Inside 
63547 
PCAF 
chr17 
46406076 
46406443 
8.87 
Inside 
73194 
CRBN 
p27 
chr3 
3355488 
3355749 
9.64 
Upstream 
-159098 
p27 
chr3 
3328299 
3328565 
11.32 
Upstream 
-131909 
PCAF 
chr3 
3417081 
3417428 
11.44 
Upstream 
-220691 
GLI3 
p27 
chr7 
42180561 
42180853 
11.32 
Inside 
48859 
PCAF 
chr7 
42190975 
42191217 
8.12 
Inside 
38445 
ZNF716 
p27 
chr7 
57555151 
57555705 
7.79 
Downstream 
41320 
PCAF 
chr7 
57555035 
57555523 
7.7 
Downstream 
41204 
DGCR6 
p27 
chr22 
17263635 
17264251 
9.48 
Upstream 
-10144 
PCAF 
chr22 
17263972 
17264283 
8.79 
Upstream 
-9807 </p>

<p>are constant along cell cycle (Supplementary Figure S8A). 
IP experiments using anti-PAX5 were performed in asyn-
chronously growing HCT116 cells. Results revealed that this 
protein interacts with both p27 and PCAF (Figure 6B). 
Also reciprocal IPs using anti-p27 and anti-PCAF showed 
this interaction (Supplementary Figure S8B and C). Inter-
estingly, the absence of PCAF did not affect the interac-
tion between PAX5 and p27 (Supplementary Figure S8D). 
Similarly, the absence of p27 did not alter the association 
between PAX5 and PCAF (Supplementary Figure S8E). 
These results suggest that PAX5 is able to bind to both (p27 
and PCAF), most probably through different binding sites 
because in the absence of p27 the levels of PCAF associated 
to PAX5 are quite similar to those associated in its presence 
(Supplementary Figure S8E). The interaction of p27 with 
its specific binding site in the GRIN3A, SPAG9, ROBO1 
and UNC5D genes was validated by ChIP in HCT116 cells 
(Figure 6C, upper panel). Additionally, the specificity of the 
interaction was validated by ChIP in HCT116 p27KO cells 
(Supplementary Figure S9A). Moreover, the interaction of 
PCAF with its specific binding site in the same genes was 
also validated by ChIP (Figure 6C bottom panel). Next, 
ChIP analysis with anti-PAX5 showed the binding of PAX5 
to the p27-and PCAF-BSs of the same group of genes (Fig-
ure 6D) indicating that PAX5 is able to associate to both 
p27 and PCAF-BSs. Finally, ChIP experiments performed 
in HCT116 cells knocked down for PAX5 revealed a sig-</p>

<p>nificant decreased association of p27 and PCAF to their re-
spective binding sites, suggesting that PAX5 mediates the in-
teraction of both proteins with DNA (Supplementary Fig-
ure S9B). Interestingly, we observed that the mRNA and 
the protein levels of several target genes were increased in 
PAX5-KD cells (Figure 6E, F and G). All these data indi-
cate that PAX5 collaborates in the transcriptional regula-
tion of specific p27 and PCAF target genes playing a role as 
a repressor. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>PCAF is a member of the GNAT (GCN5-related N-
acetyltransferases) family of acetylases that participates in 
large multi-subunit complexes involved in transcriptional 
regulation (36). It also possesses an intrinsic ubiquitin E3 
ligase activity that allows specific ubiquitylation of tar-
get proteins (37). PCAF behaves as a transcriptional co-
activator by acetylating a number of different substrates, 
the most well-known being histones, although non-histones 
proteins are also substrates of PCAF (36). These include 
TFs as c-myc, E2F1, GATA-2 and Myo-D (38-41), other 
proteins involved in transcription as Cdk9 and some cell cy-
cle regulatory proteins as p27, cdk2 and cyclin A (6,42-44). 
The evidence showing that PCAF acetylates p27 inducing 
its degradation (6) and that p27 behaves as a transcriptional 
repressor (9,11) suggested the possibility of the cooperation 
between both proteins in the regulation of transcription. We </p>

<p>5096 Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 9 </p>

<p>2 KD CTR </p>

<p>CRISPR </p>

<p>p27 </p>

<p>PCAF </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>Fold enrichment </p>

<p>CR Ctrl </p>

<p>CR 2KD </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>D 
C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>Fold enrichment </p>

<p>CR Ctrl 
CR 2KD </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>PNST </p>

<p>PNST 
mRNA </p>

<p>Figure 5. Effect of knocking down both, p27 and PCAF on the expression of target genes. (A) HCT116 cells were infected with a specific shRNA for p27 
alone, or with shRNAs for p27 and PCAF or with a control shRNA (sh(-)). Then, the levels of primary non spliced transcripts (PNST) were determined by 
qPCR. (B). Cells were Knocked down for p27 and PCAF (double knockout) (2KD) using the CRISPR/Cas9 methodology. Then, the levels of PCAF and 
p27 were determined by WB. Levels of mRNA (C) or of primary non spliced transcripts (PNST) (D) from different common target genes were determined 
in double knock down cells (CR 2KD) and in control cells (CR Ctrl) by qPCR. In all experiments results are the mean value ± SEM of four independent 
experiments and are represented as fold enrichment versus control. Statistical analyses were performed using the t-student's test. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 
and ***P &lt; 0.001. </p>

<p>analyzed this possibility by performing ChIP-seq analysis 
in HCT116 cells using both anti-PCAF and anti-p27 anti-
bodies. The first interesting observation was that the distri-
bution of the binding sites of both proteins overall genome 
was very different. Intriguingly, only a small number of p27-
BSs were on gene promoters while most of them were in dis-
tal intergenic (74%) or in intronic regions (24%). These re-
sults expand the previous information of the identification 
of p27-BSs performed by ChIP on chip in NIH3T3 cells in 
which only the association of p27 with gene promoters was 
analyzed (9) and reveals for the first time that the role of p27 
in the regulation of transcription is mainly produced by as-
sociating to chromatin regions distal from the promoters. 
In contrast, around the 60% of the PCAF-BSs were on the 
gene body (intron and exon regions) or in proximal regions. 
Another attractive observation was that a significant 
number of the p27-BSs (40%) were close to pseudogenes 
or sequences of non-coding RNAs. Similar results were ob-
served for PCAF although the proportion was lower (25%). </p>

<p>This observation suggests a putative role of both proteins in 
the regulation of ncRNA and pseudogene expression. Due 
to the relevance of these types of RNAs in multiple cellular 
functions and their involvement in different pathologies, as 
for instance cancer, these data reveal a putative new role of 
p27 and PCAF as transcriptional regulators of these RNAs 
(45-48). 
Results reported here also yield up that both p27 and 
PCAF proteins regulate the expression of similar functional 
groups of genes as cell adhesion, neuronal differentiation, 
ion transport and cell signaling. It's worth noting that the 
45% of protein-encoding p27-TGs also contain PCAF bind-
ing sites indicating that this transcriptional co-activator 
could be a very important partner of p27 in the regulation of 
transcription. In fact, we demonstrate here the cooperation 
between these two proteins in the regulation of transcription 
of a number of common targets. Specifically, by knocking 
down p27, PCAF or both we have seen that PCAF operates 
as a co-activator and p27 as a repressor and that PCAF is </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 9 5097 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>p27 
PCAF </p>

<p>ARNT 02 
PAX4 01 
AHRARNT 01 
PAX5 01 
ARNT 01 </p>

<p>MYCMAXARNT 01 
AHRARNT 02 
PAX5 02 </p>

<p>NMYC 01 
STAF 01 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>PAX 5 </p>

<p>p27 </p>

<p>PCAF </p>

<p>IgG 
PAX5 
input </p>

<p>IP </p>

<p>Pax5/GAPDH </p>

<p>Sh Ctrl 
shPAX5 </p>

<p>0,0 </p>

<p>1,0 </p>

<p>2,0 </p>

<p>3,0 </p>

<p>4,0 </p>

<p>5,0 </p>

<p>6,0 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>ROBO1 </p>

<p>SPAG9 </p>

<p>GRIN3A </p>

<p>UNC5D </p>

<p>ShCtrl shPAX5 </p>

<p>Tubulin </p>

<p>Tubulin </p>

<p>Tubulin </p>

<p>Tubulin </p>

<p>ShCtrl shPAX5 </p>

<p>PAX 5 </p>

<p>Tubulin </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>GRIN3A ROBO1 UNC5D SPAG9 </p>

<p>Fold enrichment </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>GRIN3A SPAG9 ROBO1 UNC5D 
Fold enrichment </p>

<p>Ctrl 
p27 </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>GRIN3A SPAG9 ROBO1 UNC5D 
Fold enrichment </p>

<p>Ctrl 
PCAF </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>GRIN3A SPAG9 ROBO1 UNC5D 
Fold enrichment </p>

<p>p27-BS </p>

<p>Ctrl 
PAX5 </p>

<p>* 
*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>GRIN3A SPAG9 ROBO1 UNC5D 
Fold enrichment </p>

<p>PCAF-BS </p>

<p>Ctrl 
PAX5 </p>

<p>* 
* 
** 
** </p>

<p>p27-BS </p>

<p>PCAF-BS </p>

<p>mRNA 
mRNA </p>

<p>Figure 6. PAX5 collaborates in the regulation of p27-and PCAF-target genes. (A) Enrichment analysis of the putative transcription factors that could 
significantly associate to p27-or PCAF-BSs was performed using GiTools, the STORM tool for the scanning of the peaks and the TF-BSs motif position 
weight matrix from TRANSFAC. (B) IP experiments were performed using anti-PAX5 antibodies or IgG as a control. The presence of p27, PAX5 and 
PCAF in the inputs and in the immunoprecipitates was determined by WB. (C) The interactions of p27 (upper panel) or PCAF (bottom panel) with their 
specific chromatin binding sites in several target genes were performed by ChIP using anti-p27, anti-PCAF or no-antibodies as a control. Results are 
represented relative to the control. (D) The interaction of PAX5 with the p27-BSs (upper panel) and PCAF-BSs (bottom panel) of the target genes was 
analyzed by ChIP using anti-PAX5 antibodies or no-antibodies as a control. Results are represented relative to the control (E) Cells were infected with 
a specific shRNA for PAX5 or a control shRNA. Then, the levels of PAX5 mRNA (upper panel) and PAX5 protein (bottom panel) were determined by 
qPCR or WB, respectively. (F) The mRNA levels of different target genes were determined by qPCR in cells infected with a specific shRNA for PAX5 
(white bars) or a control shRNA (black bars). Results are represented as a fold change relative to the control. In all cases, results are the mean value ± 
SD of three independent experiments. Statistical analyses were performed using the t-student's test. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 and ***P &lt; 0.001. (G) Protein 
levels of the different TGs were determined by WB in PAX5-KD cells. Tubulin was used as a loading control. </p>



<p>needed for the expression of p27-TGs because in the double 
knock-down cells gene expression is blocked. Curiously, in 
this cooperative role each one of these proteins associates to 
different regulatory sites of the chromatin. 
The evidence that PCAF acetylates K100 sited in D2 sub-
domain of p27 and that this acetylation induces p27 ubiq-
uitylation and the subsequent degradation (6) together with 
results reported here allows us to postulate a model of how 
p27 and PCAF can cooperate in the regulation of tran-
scription. In this model, p27 associated to specific regula-
tory domains of the chromatin represses transcription of 
its target genes. To activate transcription PCAF (associated 
to a different regulatory domain) interacts with p27, possi-
ble by a change in chromatin conformation. Then, PCAF 
acetylates p27 inducing its degradation. Whether the p27-
ubiquitylating enzyme is the own PCAF still remains un-
known but this is an attractive possibility. Degradation of 
p27 would eliminate the repressor role of this protein and 
would allow PCAF to act as a transcriptional co-activator. 
That PCAF mediated acetylation occurs on p27 associated 
to the regulatory chromatin BSs still remains to be demon-
strated. However, a similar mechanism has been reported 
to operate during the activation of the Hedgehog pathway 
(49). Authors described that cells subjected to a genotoxic 
stress induce the p53-dependent transcriptional activation 
and accumulation of PCAF (50). Then, PCAF associates 
with and acetylates the TF GLI1 that is subsequently ubiq-
uitylated by the intrinsic ubiquitin E3 ligase of PCAF that 
induced its degradation. As a consequence, GLI1 targets 
cannot be transcribed. 
We also report here that PAX5 participates in the tran-
scriptional regulation mediated by p27 and PCAF. PAX5 
belongs to the PAX family of TFs that include 9 members 
that are involved in the control of development (51). Specif-
ically, PAX5 is essential for commitment of lymphoid pro-
genitors to the B lymphocyte lineage. It activates the ex-
pression of B-lineage specific genes but represses a subset 
of genes not needed for this process of differentiation (52). 
Interestingly, mice lacking PAX5 in mature B cells develop 
aggressive lymphomas (53). We report here that PAX5 in-
teracts with both p27 and PCAF, that it associates to p27-
and PCAF-BSs and that the knockdown of PAX5 increased 
transcription of p27/PCAF-TGs indicating that it behaves 
as a transcriptional repressor of these genes together with 
p27. An attractive speculation is that PAX5, similarly to 
p27, could be a PCAF substrate and that PAX5 acetyla-
tion could lead to its inactivation as a transcriptional re-
pressor. However, this possibility remains to be explored. 
In summary, we describe here a novel mechanism of tran-
scriptional regulation mediated by p27, PAX5 and PCAF 
that might be relevant for the control of several important 
biological processes and that can participate in the devel-
opment of different pathological situations as for instance 
tumorigenesis. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad (MINECO) 
[SAF2012-38078 to O.B. and BFU2015-65311-R to R.A.]; 
Instituto de Salud Carlos III [RD12/0036/0054 to O.B. and 
CB16/12/00244 (CIBERONC) to A.B.]; 'La Caixa' Foun-
dation 2016-052407 (to R.A.). Funding for open access 
charge: MInisterio the Economia y Competitividad, Spain 
La Caixa Foundation. Spain. 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



</text></tei>