<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5458338" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>CDKL5 disorder is a neurodevelopmental disorder still without a cure. Murine models of CDKL5 disorder have been recently 
generated raising the possibility of preclinical testing of treatments. However, unbiased, quantitative biomarkers of high 
translational value to monitor brain function are still missing. Moreover, the analysis of treatment is hindered by the 
challenge of repeatedly and non-invasively testing neuronal function. We analyzed the development of visual responses in a 
mouse model of CDKL5 disorder to introduce visually evoked responses as a quantitative method to assess cortical circuit 
function. Cortical visual responses were assessed in CDKL5 null male mice, heterozygous females, and their respective con-
trol wild-type littermates by repeated transcranial optical imaging from P27 until P32. No difference between wild-type and 
mutant mice was present at P25-P26 whereas defective responses appeared from P27-P28 both in heterozygous and homozy-
gous CDKL5 mutant mice. These results were confirmed by visually evoked potentials (VEPs) recorded from the visual cortex 
of a different cohort. The previously imaged mice were also analyzed at P60-80 using VEPs, revealing a persistent reduction of 
response amplitude, reduced visual acuity and defective contrast function. The level of adult impairment was significantly 
correlated with the reduction in visual responses observed during development. Support vector machine showed that multi-
dimensional visual assessment can be used to automatically classify mutant and wt mice with high reliability. Thus, moni-
toring visual responses represents a promising biomarker for preclinical and clinical studies on CDKL5 disorder. </p>

<p>Cyclin-dependent kinase-like 5 (CDKL5) disorder, also known as 
early infantile epileptic encephalopathy type 2 (EIEE2, OMIM 
number: #300672) is a severe neurological condition character-
ized by early-onset seizures in the first month of life, intellec-
tual disability, motor and social impairment. This disease has </p>

<p>recently been considered as an autonomous etiopathological 
entity (1), with a clearly distinct genetic and clinical phenotype 
respect to other similar infantile encephalopathies such as Rett 
syndrome (RTT) and X-linked infantile spasm syndrome 1 
(ISSX1). No effective treatment is currently available for this dis-
ease. At a molecular level, CDKL5 is a serine/threonine kinase </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. 
Received: January 22, 2017. Revised: March 23, 2017. Accepted: March 25, 2017 </p>

<p>V C The Author 2017. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. 
For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>



<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2017, Vol. 26, No. 12 
2290-2298 </p>

<p>doi: 10.1093/hmg/ddx119 
Advance Access Publication Date: 28 March 2017 
Original Article </p>

<p>that is highly expressed in the central nervous system. 
Intracellular localization of CDKL5 appears to vary in different 
brain areas and during development with expression present 
both in the cytosolic and nuclear fractions (2). CDKL5 was also 
found to be localized in postsynaptic structures, where it can 
regulate dendritic spine maturation and density, and modulate 
excitatory synaptic function (3,4). The synaptic localization of 
CDKL5 seems to be mediated by its interaction with the palmi-
toylated form of postsynaptic density protein 95 (PSD-95) (5,6) or 
by the formation of a complex involving PSD-95 and NGL-1 (3). 
In mice, CDKL5 is strongly upregulated postnatally with high 
levels of expression in the forebrain (2,7,8). 
Recently, CDKL5 loss-of-function murine models that reca-
pitulate some aspects of the human disease have become avail-
able (9,10), raising the possibility of preclinical testing of 
treatments. However, unbiased, quantitative biomarkers of 
high translational value to monitor brain function are still miss-
ing. Moreover, the analysis of treatment and washout effects 
are hindered by the challenge of repeatedly and non-invasively 
testing neuronal function over the course of the disorder. 
Recent work introduced the use of visually evoked responses as 
a quantitative method to assess cortical circuit function in RTT 
patients carrying MeCP2 mutations (11). The results obtained in 
humans revealed a good correlation with the results in the 
mouse model (11,12) suggesting that the analysis of visual phe-
notype could also be extended to other diseases, including the 
CDKL5 disorder, in which abnormal function of cortical circuits 
can be hypothesized and animal models are available. Indeed, 
clinical studies indicated that several CDKL5 patients show vi-
sual impairments (13-16) and abnormal electroencephalo-
graphic (17) waveforms deriving from impaired activity of the 
cerebral cortex, in keeping with findings of morphofunctional 
alterations in sensory cortical circuits of cdk o5 mutant mice 
(4,9,10). Thus, we investigated the developmental trajectory of 
cortical visual responses in male mice totally missing CDKL5, 
and in heterozygous cdkl5 females, better recapitulating the 
mosaic distribution of mutant cells present in the majority of 
CDKL5 patients. Two independent techniques were used: longi-
tudinal transcranial intrinsic optical signal (IOS) imaging and 
intracortical VEP recordings. The data showed the presence of 
an impairment of visual response both in male and in female 
mutants, first detectable at P27. This early alteration of visual 
responses was correlated with impairments of different param-
eters of cortical visual function in adulthood, and can be ex-
ploited as a classifying biomarker providing rational targets for 
treatment assessment. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Longitudinal IOS imaging reveals decreased amplitude 
of cortical visual responses in developing cdkl5 
mutants </p>

<p>To determine the impact of cdkl5 mutation on visual cortical 
development we examined cortical responses to visual stimula-
tion using intact skull repeated IOS imaging in juvenile animals, 
and tracking response maturation in binocular visual cortex 
during visual development (P25-32) (18). We examined IOS re-
sponses in the same subjects, both male cdkl5 null and female 
heterozygous mice compared with their age and sex matched 
wt littermates, at three different developmental stages (Fig. 1A). 
Figure 2A and E shows typical examples of responses from the 
different experimental groups consisting in a decrease in reflec-
tance (dark area) induced by visual stimulation in the visual </p>

<p>cortex. Data quantitation showed that at the first age tested 
(P25-26), the amplitude of the responses to contralateral eye 
stimulation was comparable between cdkl5 null and control 
mice, however, at later ages (P27-28 and P31-32) cdkl5 null mice 
showed a significantly reduced response with respect to wt (Fig. 
2B, wt N ¼ 9, cdkl5 null N ¼ 7; two-way ANOVA genotype 
P ¼ 0.035, post hoc Holm-Sidak wt versus mutants P25-26 
P ¼ 0.91, P27-28 P ¼ 0.0016, P31-32 P ¼ 0.0047). The responses to 
the ipsilateral eye showed a similar pattern: no difference be-
tween genotypes at P25-26 and significantly reduced amplitude 
in cdkl5 null mice at P27-28 and at P31-32 (Fig. 2C, wt N ¼ 9, 
cdkl5 null N ¼ 7; two-way ANOVA genotype P ¼ 0.0017, post hoc 
Holm-Sidak wt versus mutants P25-26 P ¼ 0.5, P27-28 P ¼ 0.024, 
P31-32 P ¼ 0.0028). Interestingly, female heterozygous cdkl5 
mice also showed a similar developmental impairment of con-
tralateral evoked responses, but preserved ipsilateral response 
amplitude (Fig. 2F and G, wt N ¼ 11, cdkl5 het N ¼ 7; 
Contralateral responses: two-way ANOVA time Âgenotype 
P ¼ 0.017, post hoc Holm-Sidak wt versus mutants P25-26 
P ¼ 0.53, P27-28 P ¼ 0.046, P31-32 P ¼ 0.049; Ipsilateral responses: 
two-way ANOVA time Âgenotype P ¼ 0.17, genotype P ¼ 0.87). 
This differential effect on ipsilateral and contralateral responses 
resulted in an abnormal ocular dominance index (ODI) biased 
toward ipsilateral eye in heterozygous mutants with respect to 
wt (Fig. 2H, wt N ¼ 11, cdkl5 het N ¼ 7; t-test P ¼ 0.003). No change 
in ODI was present in null mice with respect to controls (Fig. 2D, 
wt N ¼ 9, cdkl5 null N ¼ 7; t-test P ¼ 0.87). Thus, defective devel-
opment of visual responses is present after P27 both in null and 
heterozygous cdkl5 mutant mice. </p>

<p>Impaired VEP responses in juvenile and adult cdkl5 
mutants </p>

<p>To assess cortical visual responses in cdkl5 mutants using a dif-
ferent technique, we recorded intracortical VEP responses to 
pattern reversal by means of a multielectrode inserted into the 
binocular visual cortex of p27-32 mice, a time point represent-
ing the onset of the visual response deficit previously observed 
by IOS imaging in heterozygous and null mice. VEP results 
reproduced IOS data showing a reduced VEP amplitude in male 
cdkl5 null mice for both contralateral and ipsilateral stimulation 
(Supplementary Material, Fig. S1, wt N ¼ 5, cdkl5 null N ¼ 4; two-
way ANOVA genotype P &lt; 0.001, post hoc Holm-Sidak wt versus 
mutants Ipsilateral eye P ¼ 0.04, Contralateral eye P &lt; 0.001), and 
reduced VEP amplitude for contralateral eye stimulation in het-
erozygous cdkl5 mice (Supplementary Material, Fig. S1, wt N ¼ 4, 
cdkl5 het N ¼ 5; two way ANOVA interaction eye Âgenotype 
P ¼ 0.014, post hoc Holm-Sidak wt versus mutants Ipsilateral eye 
P ¼ 0.13, Contralateral eye P &lt; 0.001). 
To investigate whether the developmental visual impair-
ment persists into adulthood we recorded VEPs in P60-P80 
mice. To establish whether the defect observed in juvenile mice 
was correlated with adult visual cortical responses, we analyzed 
the same mice that were studied during development by means 
of IOS imaging, a non-terminal procedure that allows recovery 
of the animal at the end of the procedure. We found that VEP 
amplitude was reduced in adult cdkl5 null mice for both contra-
lateral and ipsilateral eye stimulation (Fig. 3A, wt N ¼ 6, cdkl5 
null N ¼ 6; two way ANOVA genotype P &lt; 0.0001, post hoc Holm-
Sidak wt versus mutants Ipsilateral eye P ¼ 0.028, Contralateral 
eye P ¼ 0.0001). Similarly, contralateral, but not ipsilateral, eye 
responses were significantly reduced in heterozygous cdkl5 fe-
males (Fig. 3C, wt N ¼ 8, cdkl5 het N ¼ 8; two way ANOVA </p>

<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2017, Vol. 26, No. 12 | </p>

<p>eye Âgenotype P ¼ 0.029, post hoc Holm-Sidak wt versus mutants 
Ipsilateral eye P ¼ 0.31, Contralateral eye P ¼ 0.0004) resulting in 
an abnormal ODI in cdkl5 heterozygous mice (Fig. 3D, wt N ¼ 8, 
cdkl5 het N ¼ 8; t-test P ¼ 0.03), but not in cdkl5 null males (Fig. 
3B, wt N ¼ 6, cdkl5 null N ¼ 6; t-test P ¼ 0.22). No difference was 
observed between VEP waveforms in any of the genotypes 
(Supplementary Material, Fig. S2). These data, obtained in adult 
mice, overlap with the results found during early development 
using IOS imaging. 
VEPs are usually employed to assess visual parameters such 
as contrast sensitivity and spatial visual acuity that well corre-
late with vision assessed behaviorally in both mice and humans 
(11,19-22). To investigate whether contrast responses are af-
fected by cdkl5 mutation, we recorded VEPs in response to grat-
ings of different contrast in cdkl5 null and heterozygous 
animals (Fig. 4A and B). Contrast response curves were fitted 
with a Naka-Rushton function (23,24) to derive two parameters: 
C 50 representing the contrast eliciting the half-maximal re-
sponse, and N representing the slope of the curve. We found 
that cdkl5 mutants reached half maximum responses at much 
higher contrast values than wt mice (Fig. 4C and D; wt N ¼ 5, 
cdkl5 null N ¼ 6; t-test P ¼ 0.035; wt N ¼ 7, cdkl5 het N ¼ 6; t-test </p>

<p>P ¼ 0.0096) while the N parameter was not significantly affected 
(Fig. 4E and F; males t-test P ¼ 0.49; females t-test P ¼ 0.50). 
Electrophysiological visual acuity was assessed by stimulating 
the animal with gratings of different spatial frequency (22). We 
found that both heterozygous and null animals had a signifi-
cantly lower spatial resolution (visual acuity) as compared to 
their sex-matched wt littermates (Fig. 5; wt N ¼ 5, cdkl5 null 
N ¼ 6; t-test P ¼ 0.011; wt N ¼ 7, cdkl5 het N ¼ 6; t-test P ¼ 0.0097). </p>

<p>Early IOS responses are correlated with adult VEP 
amplitude, visual acuity and contrast response curve </p>

<p>The altered VEP responses found in adult cdkl5 null and hetero-
zygous mice could result from an abnormal development of 
neural circuits. Since adult VEP recordings were performed in 
the same mice employed for IOS assessment, we investigated if 
there was a correlation between IOS responses during develop-
ment and adult electrophysiological measurements. For this 
reason, we computed the correlation matrix between z-scored 
amplitudes of the contralaterally evoked IOS and VEPs, VEP vi-
sual acuity and the C 50 parameter obtained from contrast curve 
fit (Fig. 6A). Intriguingly, all these variables were significantly 
correlated indicating that IOS measures are in agreement with 
VEPs, and that altered developmental trajectories could be at 
the basis of the visual impairment found in adult cdkl5 mu-
tants. These data also suggest that monitoring IOS responses 
during development could be a predictive tool of adult cortical 
visual processing. </p>

<p>Visual responses are a robust disease biomarker </p>

<p>To evaluate the reliability of the visual phenotype as a bio-
marker, we evaluated its accuracy, sensitivity, specificity and d </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(Table 1 and Fig 6C) using linear support vector machine (SVM), 
a supervised machine-learning algorithm for data classification. 
When trained with the entire dataset (All), the algorithm 
showed a remarkable discriminative capability (d 
0 ¼ 1.32) be-</p>

<p>tween mutated and wild-type mice. We then performed a prin-
cipal components analysis (PCA) and we selected the first two 
components accounting for 66.7% of the variance in the entire 
dataset. By using these variables, subjects were readily segre-
gated between wt and mutants (Fig. 6B) and the d 
0 was signifi-</p>

<p>cantly improved (d 
0 ¼ 1.52; one-way ANOVA P &lt; 0.0001, post hoc </p>

<p>Holm-Sidak All versus PCA P &lt; 0.0001). Since ease of testing is a 
key factor in the applicability of a disease biomarker, we also as-
sessed whether smaller subsets of variables could reach a simi-
lar discriminative performance. The tested data subsets were 
composed of: visual acuity and C 50 (Thresholds); contralateral 
and ipsilateral VEP amplitude (VEP); contralateral IOS amplitude 
at P27-28 and P31-32 (IOS-C); ipsilateral IOS amplitude at P27-28 
and P31-32 (IOS-I). As a control we also repeated the procedure 
after bootstrapping the dataset of principal components 
(Bootstrap). Thresholds, VEP and IOS-C models showed signifi-
cantly better performances than the bootstrap condition 
(Thresholds d 
0 : 1.21, VEP d 
0 : 0.97, IOSI-C d 
0 : 1.00; post hoc Holm-</p>

<p>Sidak P &lt; 0.0001 for all comparisons versus Bootstrap), indicat-
ing that even simple sets of physiological parameters could be 
used as a tool for monitoring both disease progression and the 
effect of potential treatments. Interestingly, IOS-I model had a 
remarkably lower efficiency not significantly different from the 
Bootstrap model (d 
0 : 0.16; post hoc Holm-Sidak P ¼ 0.20). </p>

<p>Figure 1. (A) Sketch of the experimental protocol. (B) Picture of the 3D printed 
imaging chamber. (C) Example of DR/R visual responses. Shaded area represents </p>

<p>duration of the visual stimulation. Horizontal scale bar¼1 s, vertical scale bar </p>

<p>(DR/R)¼2Â10 
À4 . (D) Flow chart of image processing for automated binocular </p>

<p>visual cortex ROI generation. Frame size: 2Â2 mm. </p>



<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The availability of animal models has greatly benefited the ef-
forts to individuate molecular and cellular underpinnings of 
cdkl5 syndrome (9,10). Moreover, behavioral assessment 
has outlined significant impairments in different domains 
(9,10,25,26). However, there remains a pressing need for bio-
markers of high translational value to non-invasively and quan-
titatively monitor brain function throughout progression of the 
disorder and during treatment. Here, we used transcranial IOS 
and intracortical VEPs to investigate visual cortical function in 
cdkl5 mutant mice. The results showed that cortical responses 
are dramatically reduced in amplitude already at P27-P28, as as-
sessed both with IOS and VEPs, and that this reduction is signifi-
cantly correlated with decreased response amplitude, abnormal 
contrast response function, and impaired visual acuity in adult 
mutants. Importantly, these alterations were detected both in 
male mice with no expression of cdkl5 and in heterozygous fe-
male mutants with mosaic expression of the remaining cdkl5 
allele. Sensitivity analysis revealed that visual responses were 
able to correctly classify mice in mutant or wild-type with more 
than 93% accuracy and 92% sensitivity proving the robustness 
of this technique in phenotype assessment. 
In recent years, the visual cortex has become an impor-
tant model to assess cortical processing in mouse model of 
neurodevelopmental disorders (12,27,28). For instance, the 
use of visually evoked responses has been suggested as a rel-
atively common quantitative method to directly compare 
cortical function in RTT patients and mouse models carrying 
mecp2 mutations (11,12). VEPs have also been used to reveal 
alterations in West Syndrome patients, EIEE1 (OMIM ref: 
#308350), and in EIEE3 (OMIM ref: #609304), supporting the 
translational and clinical applicability of this technique even 
in presence of seizures or hyperexcitability (29,30). Our re-
sults suggest that monitoring deficits in cortical visual 
function could also be applied to cdkl5 syndrome. This </p>

<p>possibility is in agreement with clinical studies indicating 
that cdkl5 patients show visual impairments (13,15,16). 
Moreover, previous studies showed that adult cdkl5 mutant 
mice have altered neural responses in sensory cortices (9,10) 
and impaired visual optokinetic reflex (9). A fundamental is-
sue in analyzing phenotypes in mouse models of neurodeve-
lopmental disorders is to understand whether the defective 
phenotype is a primary deficit occurring at the disease onset 
or a late secondary manifestation of the disease. Knowledge 
about the onset of the symptoms is useful to optimize treat-
ment schedule and to formulate hypotheses on the underly-
ing neurobiological defects generating the deficit. Our results 
indicate that, both in cdkl5 null males and in heterozygous 
females, an impairment in visual responses begins to be pre-
sent during development, in correlation with the increase of 
cdkl5 expression occurring during forebrain postnatal devel-
opment (2,7,8). Furthermore, the degree of impairment of 
cortical visual responses present in juvenile mutants was 
correlated with the deficits observed in the same animals 
when they became adult, suggesting that the alteration of 
developmental maturation mechanisms by cdkl5 mutation is 
responsible for the impaired visual cortical function during 
adulthood. 
Both the onset of visual response impairment in mice and 
the appearance of symptoms in humans take place during a pe-
riod of intense synaptogenesis and synaptic plasticity, in agree-
ment with the proposed role of cdkl5 in synaptic organization 
(3-6). Studies performed in cdkl5 mice reported abnormal turn-
over and density of dendritic spines, and reduced expression of 
proteins involved in excitatory synaptic structure in different 
brain areas, including sensory cortices (4,9,26). In particular, a 
recent morphological analysis focused on the developing visual 
cortex showed reduced staining for the activity-dependent pro-
tein c-fos and for key components of the excitatory postsynap-
tic protein assembly together with increased numbers and </p>

<p>Figure 2. (A) Images collected at different ages in one male wild-type (WTm) and one cdkl5 null (KO) mice. Responses to contralateral (Contra) and ipsilateral eye (Ipsi) </p>

<p>eye stimulation are reported. (B) IOS amplitude in response to contralateral eye stimulation at different ages in WTm and KO mice. (C) IOS amplitude in response to ip-</p>

<p>silateral eye stimulation at different ages in WTm and KO mice. (D) Ocular dominance index (ODI) in WTm and KO mice. (E) Images collected at different ages in one fe-
male wt (WTf) and one cdkl5 heterozygous (HET) mice. Responses to contralateral (Contra) and ipsilateral eye (Ipsi) eye stimulation are reported. (F) IOS amplitude in </p>

<p>response to contralateral eye stimulation at different ages in WTf and HET mice. (G) IOS amplitude in response to ipsilateral eye stimulation at different ages in WTf </p>

<p>and HET mice. (H) Ocular dominance index (ODI) in WTf and HET mice. In all panels, values are average6SEM. *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01. Frame size: 2Â2 mm. </p>

<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2017, Vol. 26, No. 12 | </p>

<p>connectivity of parvalbumin-positive inhibitory interneurons 
(31). The possibility that cdkl5 acts both on excitatory and inhib-
itory neurons is strengthened by previous work showing dis-
tinct but overlapping phenotypes in mice with cdkl5 deletion 
selectively from excitatory or inhibitory neurons (9). Therefore, 
a defective maturation of excitatory and inhibitory circuits 
could contribute to the impaired visual cortical responses ob-
served here. 
Intriguingly, our data suggest that the contralateral and the 
ipsilateral responses could be differentially sensitive to cdkl5 
mutation. Indeed, ipsilateral responses of mutant heterozygous 
females, albeit consistently reduced, were not statistically af-
fected. Whether this is due to differential effects of cdkl5 on the 
crossed and uncrossed pathways, or to the low statistical power 
due to the combination of low signal-to-noise ratio of mouse ip-
silateral responses and the variability intrinsic to cdkl5 mosai-
cism, is still to be clarified. 
In summary, we found that the developmental trajectory of 
visual cortical development is altered in cdkl5 mutants. Our 
data were obtained with two different techniques that provided 
highly correlated data increasing the robustness of the results. 
Moreover, we showed that visual assessment can be used to au-
tomatically classify subjects with high reliability. Importantly, </p>

<p>VEP and IOS reduction of contralateral responses in both null 
and het cdkl5 mice exhibited a large effect size (&gt;1.3) that was 
obtained with approximately the same number of animals for 
both sexes, suggesting that contralateral visual response deficit 
is not linearly dependent on the percentage of cells carrying the 
mutation. VEP recordings can be readily applied to humans and 
other species, increasing the translational value of the visual 
biomarker. Transcranial IOS imaging, a minimally invasive and 
longitudinal technique, is also comparable to techniques used 
in humans: indeed, it detects the same blood-oxygenation level 
dependent signal measured by other widely used methods to 
assess responsiveness in newborns and infants like functional 
magnetic resonance imaging or functional near infrared spec-
troscopy or tomography. We expect that these techniques will 
be extremely valuable to monitor longitudinally the effective-
ness of treatments and washout effects in preclinical, and pos-
sibly clinical, studies of novel treatments for cdkl5 disorder. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Animal handling </p>

<p>Animals were maintained in rooms at 22 
C with a standard </p>

<p>12-h light-dark cycle. During the light phase a constant illumi-
nation below 40 lux from fluorescent lamps was maintained. 
Food (standard diet, 4RF25 GLP Certificate, Mucedola) and water 
were available ad libitum and changed weekly. Open-top cages 
(36.5Â20.7Â14 cm; 26.7Â20.7Â14 cm for up to 5 adult mice or </p>

<p>Figure 3. (A) Average VEP amplitude to 0.03 cyc/deg gratings for contralateral 
and ipsilateral eye stimulation in male wt (WTm) and cdkl5 null (KO) mice. </p>

<p>Representative VEPs from single animals are reported above the corresponding </p>

<p>histogram bar. (B) Ratio between contralateral and ipsilateral eye responses (C/I </p>

<p>ratio) in WTm and KO mice. (C) Average VEP amplitude to 0.03 cyc/deg gratings 
for contralateral and ipsilateral eye stimulation in female wt (WTf) and cdkl5 </p>

<p>heterozygous (HET) mice. Representative VEPs from single animals are reported </p>

<p>above the corresponding histogram bar. (D) C/I ratio in WTf and HET mice. </p>

<p>Horizontal scale bar in (A and C)¼50 ms, vertical scale bar in (A and C)¼100 lV. 
In all panels, values are average6SEM. *P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Figure 4. (A) Contrast function for contralateral eye stimulation in male wt 
(WTm) and cdkl5 null (KO) mice. Representative examples from single animals </p>

<p>are reported. Data points are fitted with the Naka-Rushton function. (B) Contrast </p>

<p>function for contralateral eye stimulation in female wt (WTf) and cdkl5 hetero-</p>

<p>zygous (HET) mice. Representative examples from single animals are reported. 
Data points are fitted with the Naka-Rushton function. (C) C 50 parameter (con-</p>

<p>trast eliciting half-maximal response) of the Naka-Rushton fit in WTm and KO </p>

<p>mice. (D) C 50 parameter in WTf and HET mice. (E) N parameter (slope) of the </p>

<p>Naka-Rushton fit in WTm and KO mice. (F) N parameter in WTf and HET mice. 
In all panels, values are average6SEM. *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01. </p>



<p>42.5Â26.6Â15.5 cm for up to 8 adult mice) with wooden dust-
free bedding were used. All the experiments were carried out in 
accordance with the directives the European Community 
Council (2011/63/EU) and approved by the Italian Ministry of 
Health. All necessary efforts were made to minimize both stress 
and the number of animals used. The mice used in this work de-
rive from the cdkl5 null strain in C57BL/6N background devel-
oped in (9) and backcrossed in C57BL/6J for three generations. 
Male wt mice were bred with female hets to obtain mutant and 
wt littermates. Weaning was performed at P21-23. Genotyping 
(P10-12) was performed on tail tissue as described in (9). Colony 
founders were selected for the absence of the rd8 retinal degen-
eration allele spontaneously present in C57BL/6N mice (32). The 
experimental groups were divided by sex: male cdkl5 null and 
female heterozygous mice were compared with male wt and fe-
male wt littermates, respectively. Data analysis was performed 
by experimenters blind to the genotype. For chronic evaluation 
of IOS/VEP responses and for VEP recordings at p27-32, mutant 
and littermate control animals from 9 and 5 different litters 
were used, respectively. </p>

<p>Experimental protocol </p>

<p>Mice of the four experimental groups (female wt, female cdkl5 
heterozygous, male wt, male cdkl5 nulls) underwent three </p>

<p>sessions of IOS imaging during development and VEP recordings 
at P60-80 (protocol scheme depicted in Fig. 1A). Throughout im-
aging sessions weight gain was monitored in all animals as a 
measure of general health status. No differential effect was de-
tected between wild-type and mutant mice (Supplementary 
Material, Fig. S3). A separate cohort of mice was analyzed at 
P27-32 using VEPs. </p>

<p>Chronic IOS imaging </p>

<p>Surgery 
For chronic IOS preparations, mice (P23-24) were deeply box-
anesthetized and maintained with isoflurane (respectively, 3 
and 1%), placed on a stereotaxic frame and head fixed using ear 
bars. Body temperature was controlled using a heating pad and 
a rectal probe to maintain the animals' body at 37 
C. Local </p>

<p>anesthesia was provided using subcutaneous lidocaine (2%) </p>

<p>Figure 5. (A) Spatial frequency response curve for contralateral eye stimulation </p>

<p>in male wild-type (WTm) and cdkl5 null (KO) mice. Representative examples </p>

<p>from single animals are reported. Data points are linearly fitted. (B) VEP visual 
acuity in WTm and KO mice. (C) Spatial frequency response curve for contralat-</p>

<p>eral eye stimulation in female wt (WTf) and cdkl5 heterozygous (HET) mice. </p>

<p>Representative examples from single animals are reported. Data points are line-</p>

<p>arly fitted. (D) VEP visual acuity in WTf and HET mice. In all panels, values are 
average6SEM. *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01. </p>

<p>Figure 6. (A) Correlation matrix between average contralaterally evoked IOS am-</p>

<p>plitude during development (IOS-C), contralaterally evoked VEP amplitude at 
P60-80 (VEP-C), VEP acuity at P60-80 (ACUITY), and the C 50 parameter at P60-80 </p>

<p>derived from Naka-Rushton fit of the contrast response curve (C 50 ). Non-para-</p>

<p>metric Spearman correlation analysis revealed significant correlation (*P&lt;0.05, </p>

<p>**P&lt;0.01, P-values corrected for multiple comparisons using Benjamini-
Hochberg false discovery rate) between all the variables. The correlation coeffi-</p>

<p>cient R is reported for each correlation in the corresponding plot. (B) Scatter plot </p>

<p>of all the experimental subjects analyzed with VEP and IOS imaging plotted in </p>

<p>the space of the first two principal components of PCA. (C) Comparison of 
d-prime for different SVM classifiers trained and tested, respectively, with: the </p>

<p>entire dataset (All), the first two principal components (PCA), Visual acuity and </p>

<p>C 50 parameter from the contrast sensitivity curve (Thresholds), VEP amplitudes </p>

<p>(VEP); contralateral IOS amplitudes (IOS-C); ipsilateral IOS amplitudes (IOS-I) 
and randomly permuted dataset (Bootstrap). n.s., not significative; all other </p>

<p>comparisons have P&lt;0.05. Values in C are presented as mean695% CI. </p>

<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2017, Vol. 26, No. 12 | </p>

<p>injection and eyes were protected with dexamethasone-based 
ointment (Tobradex, Alcon Novartis). The scalp was removed 
and the skull carefully cleaned with saline. Skin was secured to 
the skull using cyanoacrylate. Then a thin layer of cyanoacry-
late is poured over the exposed skull to attach a custom made 
metal ring (9 mm internal diameter) centered over the binocular 
visual cortex. When the glue dried off, a drop of transparent nail 
polish was spread over the area to ameliorate optical access. 
After surgery the animals were placed in a heated box and mon-
itored to ensure the absence of any sign of discomfort. Before 
any other experimental procedure, mice were left to recover for 
24/48 h. During this period, paracetamol (5 mg/ml) was adminis-
tered in the water as antalgic therapy. </p>

<p>Visual stimulation, data acquisition and analysis 
IOS recordings were performed under avertin anesthesia (20 ll/ 
g, i.p.) at P25-26, P27-28 and P31-32. Images were visualized us-
ing an Olympus microscope (BX50WI). Red light illumination 
was provided by 8 red LEDs (625 nm, Knight Lites KSB1385-1P) 
attached to the objective (Zeiss Plan-NEOFLUAR 5x, NA: 0.16) us-
ing a custom made metal LED holder (33). The animal was se-
cured under the objective using a ring-shaped neodynium 
magnet (www.supermagnete.it; date last accessed April 1, 2017, 
R-12-09-1.5-N) mounted on an arduino-based 3D printed imag-
ing chamber that also controls eye shutters and a thermostated 
heating pad (Fig. 1B; http://labrigger.com/blog/2015/11/30/open-
source-intrinsic-imaging/; date last accessed April 1, 2017). 
Visual stimuli were generated using <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> Psychtoolbox and 
presented on a gamma corrected 9.7 in. monitor, placed 10 cm 
away from the eyes of the mouse. Square wave gratings were 
presented in the binocular portion of the visual field (À10 </p>



<p>to þ10 
relative to the horizontal midline and À5 
to þ50 
rela-</p>

<p>tive to the vertical midline) with a spatial frequency of 0.03 cyc/ 
deg, mean luminance 20 cd/m 
2 and a contrast of 90%. The stim-</p>

<p>ulus consisted in the abrupt contrast reversal of a grating with a 
temporal frequency of 4 Hz for 1 s, time locked with a 16-bit 
depth acquisition camera (Hamamatsu digital camera C11440) 
using a parallel port trigger. Interstimulus time was 14 s. Frames 
were acquired at 30 fps with a resolution of 512Â512 pixels. A 
total of 210 frames were captured for each trial: 30 before the 
stimulus as a baseline condition and 180 as post-stimulus. The 
signal was averaged for at least 30 trials and downsampled to 10 
fps. Fluctuations of reflectance (R) for each pixel were computed 
as the normalized difference from the average baseline (DR/R). 
For each recording, an image representing the mean evoked re-
sponse was computed by averaging frames between 0.5 and 
2.5 seconds after stimulation. The mean image was then low-
pass filtered with a 2D average spatial filter (30 pixels, 117 lm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>square kernel). To select the binocular portion of the primary vi-
sual cortex for further analysis, a region of interest (ROI) was </p>

<p>automatically calculated on the mean image of the response to 
ipsilateral stimulation by selecting the pixels in the lowest 30% 
DR/R of the range between the maximal and minimal intensity 
pixel (34). The same ROI was used for the analysis of contralat-
eral eye responses. A scheme of the data processing is shown in 
Figure 1D. Mean evoked responses were quantitatively esti-
mated as the average intensity inside the ROI. ODI was calcu-
lated as (C À I)/(C þ I) for each pixel, where C and I indicate the 
amplitude of contralateral and ipsilateral responses, respec-
tively (34). To weaken background fluctuations a manually se-
lected polygonal region of reference (ROR) was subtracted. The 
ROR was placed where no stimulus response, blood vessel arti-
fact or irregularities of the skull were observed (35). An example 
of the time course of the DR/R response to visual stimulation af-
ter processing is shown in Figure 1C. </p>

<p>Visually evoked potentials </p>

<p>Surgery 
General anesthesia was induced in mice with 3% isoflurane, 
subsequently deeply anesthetized with an intraperitoneal injec-
tion of urethane (0.7 ml/h g; 20% solution in lactated ringer solu-
tion) and head-fixed in a stereotaxic frame. After the removal of 
the ring implant, the skull was exposed and a small craniotomy 
(2Â 2 mm) overlying the visual cortex was performed, leaving 
the dura mater intact. Then, a multichannel neural probe (Q-
trode tetrode configuration, Neuronexus) was slowly inserted at 
a depth of 150À200 lm, in the binocular visual cortex (lamb-
da: þ3.2 mm lateral, þ0.2 mm rostral and following IOS derived 
coordinates), where a high amplitude positive VEP is detectable. 
Signal was acquired using Cheetah 32 (Neuralynx) recording 
system at 30.3 kHz of sampling rate with a band pass filter of 
0.1À250 Hz. Signal from each channel was averaged to obtain 
VEPs. </p>

<p>Visual stimulation and data acquisition 
Both stimuli and analysis for VEP recordings were performed 
using custom software written in Matlab Psychtoolbox and dis-
played onto a gamma corrected 21 inch CRT monitor placed 
20 cm in front of the animal. Stimuli consisted in contrast rever-
sal square wave gratings with a spatial frequency of 0.03 cyc/ 
deg, mean luminance of 25 cd/m 
2 and a contrast of 90%. </p>

<p>Monitor was centered on animal head and stimuli covered 655 </p>



<p>relative to vertical and À5 
þ30 
relative to vertical midline. </p>

<p>Stimulus temporal frequency was 2 Hz. VEP responses were av-
eraged for at least 100 trials per eye. Each condition was re-
peated for at least eight times. The amplitude quantification of 
the response was calculated as the peak to baseline difference 
of the first positive component (at $100 ms). Visual acuity is cal-
culated presenting contrast reversal sinewave gratings with </p>

<p>Table 1. Performance evaluation of SVM classifiers trained with different datasets </p>

<p>Training dataset 
Accuracy % (95% CI) 
Sensitivity % (95% CI) 
Specificity % (95% CI) 
d 
0 (95% CI) </p>

<p>All 
89.96 (89.34-90.58) 
89.50 (88.53-90.47) 
91.50 (90.14-92.86) 
1.32 (1.29 to 1.36) 
PCA 
93.10 (92.56-93.64) 
92.21 (91.11-93.32) 
97.08 (96.14-98.03) 
1.52 (1.49 to 1.55) 
Thresholds 
87.63 (86.72-88.55) 
83.79 (82.07-85.50) 
92.83 (91.24-94.42) 
1.21 (1.16 to 1.25) 
VEP 
82.58 (81.55-83.60) 
82.79 (80.78-84.80) 
82.50 (80.32-84.68) 
0.97 (0.92 to 1.02) 
IOS-C 
82.94 (81.80-84.08) 
85.14 (83.16-87.13) 
80.58 (78.65-82.52) 
1.00 (0.96 to 1.05) 
IOS-I 
64.88 (63.58-66.19) 
73.43 (71.25-75.61) 
53.17 (49.91-56.42) 
0.16 (0.06 to 0.25) 
Bootstrap 
55.94 (54.83-57.06) 
49.86 (46.32-53.40) 
50.83 (47.22-54.45) 
0.08 (À0.03 to 0.19) </p>

<p>IOS, intrinsic optical signal; VEP, visually evoked potentials; SVM, support vector machine; PCA, principal component analysis. </p>



<p>different spatial frequencies (0.03, 0.06, 0.012, 0.024, 0.048, 0.96 
and 0 cyc/deg) and calculating the maximal spatial frequency 
resolved by linear fit estimation of parameters and extrapola-
tion of amplitude at 0 lV in a semi-logarithmic space. Contrast 
sensitivity was calculated using 0.03 cyc/deg contrast reversal 
sine wave gratings with different contrasts (90, 50, 25, 12, 6, 3 
and 0%). Normalized amplitude data was fitted to a sigmoid 
curve using Naka-Rushton function, Resp(c) ¼ 1 C </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>/(C 50 
n þ C 
n ), to </p>

<p>extract contrast sensitivity parameters (23,24,36). C 50 is the con-
trast evoking half the maximum response and n describes the 
shape of the curve. </p>

<p>SVM classifier 
Z-scored values of each physiological parameter were used for 
linear SVM classification. SVM is a supervised machine learning 
method for data classification that can be trained to find the 
best hyperplane that separates all data points in two user-
defined classes and can subsequently be exploited to blind-
predict the class to which a new observation belongs (37-39). 
We defined two classes: mutated (heterozygous and null) and 
wild-type (males and females) mice. By using the <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> func-
tion svmtrain, we trained the SVM with a subset of data consist-
ing of 50% of the dataset and we than used the remaining 50% 
for testing, using the svmclassify function. Accuracy, sensitivity, 
specificity and D-prime (d 
0 ) were then computed for the categor-</p>

<p>ical classification in order to evaluate its performance. This pro-
cedure was repeated 200 times, each one with a randomly 
divided training and testing subsets. Values for accuracy, sensi-
tivity (or true positive rate), specificity (or true negative rate) 
and d 
0 were averaged across iterations. Accuracy, sensitivity </p>

<p>and specificity were defined as (TP þ TN)/total, TP/P and TN/N, 
respectively, where TP: True positive, TN: True Negative, P: total 
positives, N: total negatives. D-prime, which measures the dis-
tance between the signal and the noise means in standard 
deviation units (40), was calculated using <rs type="software">matlab</rs> function 
dprime_simple 
(https://it.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileex 
change/47711-dprime-simple-m; date last accessed April 1, 
2017). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-3" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">version 6</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, San Diego, CA, USA). All values 
were presented as mean 6 SEM unless otherwise stated. 
Differences between groups were tested for significance using 
two-way ANOVA, unless otherwise indicated. Holm-Sidak's 
multiple comparisons post hoc tests were performed, where ap-
propriate, to correct for multiple hypothesis testing. In the fig-
ures, n.s., not significative, *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 and ***P &lt; 0.001. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Supplementary Material is available at HMG online. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Areg Barsegyan for technical suggestions on imaging 
implants. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest statement. None declared. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>International Foundation for cdkl5 Research and the 
Fondazione Telethon (GGP15098). Funding to pay the Open 
Access publication charges for this article was provided by 
Fondazione Telethon. </p>



<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2017, Vol. 26, No. 12 | </p>





</text></tei>