<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5008171" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Although it has been generally recognized that there are 
inconsistencies among Regional Review Boards in the assignment of 
points for model for end-stage liver disease (MELD)/pediatric end-
stage liver disease (PELD) exception patients with resulting 
considerable variation in appeal denial rates, data to actually prove 
this have been limited. We reviewed 6533 MELD/PELD exception 
applications submitted between 2005 and 2008, calculated the 
variation in approval/denial rates, and followed these cases through 
mid-2013 to assess the effects on patient outcomes. We found highly 
significant regional variations in denial rates for appeals by exception 
patients and in transplantation rates. The odds of transplant for 
patients whose appeals are approved is 2.45 times that of patients 
not approved; that this effect does not vary by region suggests that 
the variation in transplant rates is driven, at least in part, by the 
variation in appeal denial rates. Health deterioration or death 
accounts for more than two-thirds of wait list removals among 
patients removed for reasons other than transplant. Our findings add 
to the weight of evidence that a national review board that uses 
current clinical expertise, peer review literature, and data to 
consistently assign priority could reduce regional inequities and 
move toward equitable allocation of organs and compliance with the 
United States Regional review boards (RRBs) were created to 
address the concern that "exception" patients-
those with a model for end-stage liver disease 
(MELD) or pediatric end-stage liver disease 
(PELD) score that does not accurately represent 
the severity of their medical illness -might have a 
progressive disease that ultimately prevents them 
from obtaining a transplant or results in their 
dying on the liver transplant waiting list. In such 
cases, although scores are not elevated by the 
standard three components of the MELD calcula-
tion (creatinine, International Normalized Ratio, 
and bilirubin), the patient's advocate interprets 
their current medical condition as life threatening 
or believes that there is a risk of wait list removal 
due to progression of underlying disease. Cur-
rently, each of the 11 geographic regions in the 
United States has a separate RRB that assesses 
such cases. For certain specific conditions termed 
recognized exceptional diagnoses (REDs; including 
metabolic diseases, hepatocellular carcinoma, he-
patoblastoma, hepatopulmonary syndrome, pri-
mary oxaluria, and familial amyloidosis), Organ 
Procurement and Transplantation Network 
(OPTN) policies allow exemptions from use of the 
true MELD/PELD scores to determine transplant 
priority, and provide guidelines for increases in 
the scores. With other conditions that are not spe-
cifically recognized by OPTN policies (non-REDs), 
it is possible for a physician to request an 
increased MELD score for any patient whose 
score is not thought to accurately reflect mortality 
risk. If the RRB approves, the patient may receive 
a higher MELD score and thus a higher wait list 
priority. However, there are no United Network 
for Organ Sharing (UNOS) guidelines for 
increases in the scores of patients with many of 
these non-RED conditions (including benign 
structural diseases such as cysts and adenomas, 
cholangitis in primary sclerosing cholangitis, and 
others). In the end, for all patients whose MELD/ 
PELD scores do not accurately reflect mortality 
risk, positions on the waiting list, wait list mortal-
ity, and wait list removals for medical illnesses 
that preclude liver transplant will depend on the 
judgment made by the RRB based on the expert 
opinions of RRB members. 
Unfortunately, because of the lack of well-
defined predictive models for estimating the risk 
of waiting list removal for non-RED conditions, 
RRBs across the United States have differed very 
considerably on which conditions should receive 
additional MELD points and on how exception 
case requests should be prioritized (1). Although 
it seems to be generally recognized in the trans-
plant community that this results in considerable </p>

<p>variation across UNOS regions in appeal denial 
rates for non-RED patients, data to actually 
prove this and determine the effects of denials on 
patient outcomes have been limited. A 2005 study 
found significant variation in the distribution of 
petitions for non-REDs per region (range 0.7-
8.3%), the percentage of petitions approved 
among regions (range 28-75%), and the scores 
granted after review (2). However, this study did 
not assess the effect of denials on patient out-
comes. A 2011 study that compared only symp-
tom-based exception likelihoods across regions 
also found significant variation, with the region-
specific percentage of the study population receiv-
ing exception awards ranging from 1.5% to 6.2% 
(3). Transplantation occurred in 69% of patients 
with granted exception requests compared to 31% 
of patients with denied requests; only 17% of 
patients with granted requests suffered waiting list 
death or removal due to illness compared to 30% 
of patients with denied requests. Another 2011 
study reported that the proportion of patients per 
region receiving non-HCC exceptions ranged from 
3.7% to 9.5% and that patients receiving a 
MELD exception were transplanted at higher 
rates and dropped out at lower rates (4). 
Although it did not assess variation across UNOS 
regions, a 2013 study found that within individual 
UNOS regions, there were substantial between-
center differences in the proportions of non-RED 
exception applications that were approved and 
that patients with approved non-RED exceptions 
were significantly more likely to undergo liver 
transplantation than patients with denied requests 
(68.3% vs. 53.4%) (5). To assess the specific out-
come of RRB decisions on non-RED patient 
appeals across UNOS regions, we reviewed 
requests for non-RED MELD/PELD exception 
applications over three yr' time, calculated the 
variation in approval/denial rates and transplan-
tation rates, and followed these cases through 
mid-2013 to assess the effects on patient out-
comes. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>We reviewed 6533 MELD/PELD exception appli-
cations derived and extracted from the UNOS 
database via a data request submission to the Sci-
entific Registry of Transplant Recipients. These 
MELD appeals for exception points were submit-
ted to RRBs through <rs type="software">UNet</rs> 
SM between 2005 and 
2008, representing 3337 patients. This analysis 
included all sequential initial applications as well </p>



<p>Gish et al. </p>

<p>as subsequent appeals of denied applications and 
three-month extensions for each patient included 
in the original RRB application. Any application 
that was in effect at UNOS during this time period 
but was submitted and approved prior to January 
1, 2005, was excluded from this data extraction 
and analysis. Other exclusions included applica-
tions for HCC that did not meet the criteria in Pol-
icy 3.6.4.4, including patients with tumors outside 
the T2 criteria and patients with "downstaged" 
tumors, because regional variances addressed 
many of these patients. This analysis also excluded 
patients automatically not approved due to some 
administrative reason (e.g., missed extension dead-
line). 
To establish the patients' clinical profiles for 
this data analysis, three reviews of the data set 
were carried out. To maintain consistency in the 
scoring system, one analyst completed the initial 
review process and scored each patient blindly, 
after which two additional analysts did separate 
reviews to confirm the scoring. The first review 
established a complete list of all diagnoses that 
were presented to the RRBs via electronic submis-
sion as the reason for the RRB appeal for MELD 
exception points. The second case review scored 
each case and each subsequent appeal, if applica-
ble, and identified up to 10 "exception" diagnoses 
which were placed as the "exception" code(s) for 
each patient. These codes were either a specific 
medical diagnosis or a quality of life diagnosis. 
The third and final review then took place to 
establish a "primary" exception code because 
many patients had multiple diagnoses that were 
included in the appeal for review points and 
which could be a specific life-threatening disease, 
such as GI bleeding or infection. These patients 
would be scored using a "composite" code of 
multiple diagnoses. An example of the latter 
would be diagnoses such as GI bleeding and 
sepsis that could result in being discussed and 
possibly listed for transplantation with a primary 
exception score or being listed for retransplan-
tation. These perceived life-threatening medical 
complications were presented to the RRBs when 
the patient's advocate determined that the singu-
lar or composite diagnosis could influence wait 
list mortality or wait list removal as too ill. 
After completion of this initial process, two 
additional analysts separately performed second-
ary validations of the scoring; one analyst 
reviewed the entire data set; the second analyst 
reviewed a randomly selected subset representing 
10% of the patient cohort; both reviews con-
firmed the accuracy and consistency of the 
exception coding. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Summary statistics were computed for patient age, 
sex, and race. The percentage of patients on the 
liver waiting list with exceptions was calculated 
using "snapshots" of the waiting list at a point in 
time. Specifically, 16 end-of-the-month snapshots 
from 2005 to 2008 were extracted from the OPTN 
database. The percentage of patients with an 
exception was calculated as an average across all 
16 time points. To include similar candidates in the 
numerator and denominator, candidates listed as 
Status 1A/1B or temporarily inactive were 
excluded. Exceptions for HCC were also excluded. 
These data were then analyzed for each of the 11 
UNOS regions. 
The percentage of exception applications that 
were denied by the RRB was computed for each of 
the 11 Regions. Differences in that percentage 
across all regions were tested using the chi-squared 
test. Region 6 had no denials and was excluded 
from this part of the analysis. Only initial applica-
tions were included in this analysis (appeals and 
extensions excluded). Due to limitation in the sam-
ple sizes when stratified by both region and diagno-
sis, the analysis was limited to the three most 
common diagnoses for exception (ascites/hepatic 
hydrothorax, cholangitis/bacteremia, and bleed-
ing). A generalized linear mixed-effects model with 
logit link function was fit for the outcome of RRB 
decision using region as a covariate; a second 
model was fit to adjust for the number of diagnoses 
designated as bases for exception as well as region. 
Both models include a random intercept grouped 
by patient ID to account for correlation between 
multiple applications from the same patient. All 
regions, including the region with no denials, were 
included in the mixed-effects modeling. Likelihood 
ratio tests were used to assess the overall signifi-
cance of the variable Region. 
Before further analyzing transplantation rates, 
the dataset was reduced to one record per unique 
patient ID by deleting duplicate applications and 
concatenating or removing multiple applications 
for the same patient. Patients were followed until 
July 5, 2013. The rates of removal due to trans-
plant were computed, and homogeneity across 
regions in the rates was tested using a Pearson's 
chi-squared test. The rates were also computed 
conditional on the exception application status. 
Independence between RRB decision and removal 
for transplantation was assessed using a chi-
squared test for both the overall sample and within 
each region, and odds ratios comparing approved 
and denied patients were computed. P-values for 
the within-region tests were corrected using the </p>



<p>Regional variation in appeal denials </p>

<p>Holm-Bonferroni method. A likelihood ratio test 
was used to assess the regional variation in the 
effect of application status on the odds of receiving 
transplantation. Mortality rates for exception 
approved and denied patients were calculated 
using the Kaplan-Meier estimate; the difference in 
survival between the groups was assessed using the 
log-rank test. The hazard ratio for denied vs. 
approved patients was estimated using the Cox 
proportional hazards model. Patients with 
Removal Code 8 in the OPTN database (indicating 
removal due to death) were recorded as having had 
the event; survival times for all other removal 
codes were treated as censored. The analyses were 
performed using the statistical software R: A Lan-
guage and Environment for Statistical Computing, 
version 3.1.1. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The final cohort included 3161 applications for 
3060 individual candidates. The median age of 
patients was 50; 60% were male; 73% were white; 
12% Hispanic; and 8.1% black. The top 10 diag-
noses and combined diagnoses which were the 
bases for exceptions for initial applications are 
shown in Tables 1-4. Diagnoses such as cholangi-
tis, infection, and bacteremia were grouped, as 
were diagnoses such as quality of life, pain, and 
pruritus. The number of patients who were 
appealed for each region ranged from 62 to 443. 
When adjusted by total number of active, non-Sta-
tus one patients, the range was 2.7-6.6%, including 
HCC cases, and 1.1-2.8%, excluding HCC cases. 
When patients with MELD scores &lt;15 were 
excluded, the range was 1-3.3%. 
The chance of approval by region ranged from 
54.7% to 100% (p &lt; 0.0001); inversely, denial 
rates ranged from 0% to 45.3% (Fig. 1). For 
refractory ascites/hepatic hydrothorax, the denial 
rate by region ranged from 24.1% to 80% (exclud-
ing one region with 0% denials), p &lt; 0.0001 
(Fig. 1). For cholangitis/bacteremia, the range was 
6.1% to 48.5% (p &lt; 0.0001) and for bleeding, 
8.3% to 75% (p = 0.0026; Fig. 1). 
Based on the likelihood ratio test, there was sig-
nificant variation by region in the odds of denial, 
even when controlling for Number of Diagnoses 
(p &lt; 0.0001). When adjusting for Region, Number 
of Diagnoses was not found to be significant 
(p = 0.074). Number of Diagnoses did not appear 
to have a large impact on the effect for Region, as 
suggested by the relatively small perturbation of 
estimated effects between the two models displayed 
in Table 5. Fig. 2 displays a heat map visualizing 
the proportion of applications denied, cross-tabu-</p>

<p>lated by Region and Number of Diagnoses. The 
data for these analyses include region 6, which had 
no denials. 
After reducing the dataset to one record per 
patient, 2178 subjects had their request for excep-
tion points approved and 882 had their request 
denied. Of these 3060 subjects, 2320 received a 
transplant, 666 were removed from the list for a 
reason other than transplant, and 74 had censored 
removal time. These censored patients were 
excluded from the following analyses. There was 
significant evidence that transplantation rate varies 
by region (p &lt; 0.001; Table 6). The chance of 
removal for transplant was found to be signifi-
cantly different (p &lt; 0.001) between patients 
approved for exception points (82.4%) and those </p>

<p>Table 1. Bases for exception for all applications combined 
a : top 10 </p>

<p>diagnoses </p>

<p>Diagnosis </p>

<p>Number of 
patients </p>

<p>Percentage of 
patients </p>

<p>Refractory ascites/ 
hepatic hydrothorax </p>

<p>1435 
28 </p>

<p>Cholangitis/bacteremia 
1070 
21 
Bleeding (gastrointestinal, 
variceal) </p>

<p>431 
8 </p>

<p>Quality of life issues 
(including pain and pruritus) </p>

<p>378 
7 </p>

<p>Cholangiocarcinoma 
283 
5 
"Pediatric candidate" 
212 
4 
Metabolic disorders 
194 
4 
Hepatic encephalopathy 
156 
3 
Hyponatremia 
153 
3 
Retransplantation candidate 
122 
2 </p>

<p>These top 10 diagnoses represent 85% of all patients. 
a Including initial applications, appeals, and extensions. </p>

<p>Table 2. Bases for exceptions for initial applications only: top 10 
diagnoses </p>

<p>Diagnosis </p>

<p>Number of 
patients </p>

<p>Percentage of 
patients </p>

<p>Refractory ascites/ 
hepatic hydrothorax </p>

<p>854 
31 </p>

<p>Cholangitis/bacteremia 
500 
18 
Bleeding (gastrointestinal, 
variceal) </p>

<p>232 
8 </p>

<p>Quality of life issues (including 
pain and pruritus) </p>

<p>134 
5 </p>

<p>Cholangiocarcinoma 
130 
5 
Hyponatremia 
124 
4 
"Pediatric candidate" 
109 
4 
Hepatic encephalopathy 
101 
4 
Retransplantation candidate 
70 
3 
Metabolic disorders 
68 
2 </p>

<p>These top 10 diagnoses represent 84% of all patients. </p>



<p>Gish et al. </p>

<p>who were not approved (65.7%; Table 7). The 
effect of exception application status on the odds 
of removal for transplant was not found to vary 
significantly across regions (p = 0.526). Corre-
sponding results for removal due to reasons other 
than transplant are given in Tables 6 and 7; the 
chance of removal for reasons other than trans-
plant was found to be significantly different 
(p &lt; 0.001) between patients approved for excep-
tion points (17.6%) and those who were not 
approved (34.3%), with the odds for approved 
patients in the overall sample estimated to be 0.41 
times that of patients not approved. Among 
patients removed from the list for reasons other 
than transplant, death (40.5%) and deteriorating 
health condition (26.7%) were the most frequent 
causes of removal, together accounting for just 
over two-thirds of all such removals. Improving 
health conditions were responsible for just 12.6% 
of all patients removed from the wait list without a 
transplant (Fig. 3). 
There was a significant difference in survival fol-
lowing RRB decision between approved and 
denied patients (p = 0.025), with denied patients 
having a higher risk of mortality while on the wait-
ing list than approved patients (hazard ratio 1.322, 
95% confidence interval, 1.036, 1.688). Estimated 
mortality rates for 90-day, 180-day, one-yr, 
three-yr, and five-yr survival are given in Table 8. 
Estimates of the survival curves are shown in 
Fig. 4. Curves for the five most frequent diagnoses 
specified as the main basis for exception among 
denied patients are plotted in Fig. 5. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>With the ultimate goal of achieving fair and equi-
table allocation of organs, a number of modifica-
tions of liver allocation policies have been 
described, including those related to socioeco-
nomic issues, transplant benefit, preventing dis-
crimination, feasibility, and geography. The latter 
was given particular prominence as an area of 
concern with the April 1998 publication by United 
States Department of Health &amp; Human Services 
(HHS) of the "Organ Procurement and Trans-
plantation Network; Final Rule" which specifi-
cally mandated that "Neither place of residence 
nor place of listing shall be a major determinant 
of access to a transplant" (6). At the time this rule 
was announced, HHS summarized its intent as 
being "to assure that allocation of scarce organs 
will be based on common medical criteria, not 
accidents of geography" (7). 
More than a decade and a half later, we 
have found a large and highly statistically sig-
nificant variation in denial rates in various 
UNOS regions for appeals by patients with 
medical illnesses that are not addressed by the 
MELD components. Although such discrepan-
cies are widely observed and recognized in the 
transplant community, our study is one of only 
a handful of studies to both determine the 
regional variation in RRB approval rates and </p>

<p>Table 3. Bases for exception for all applications combined </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: top 10 
pairs of diagnoses </p>

<p>Diagnosis </p>

<p>Number of 
patients </p>

<p>Percentage of 
patients </p>

<p>Refractory ascites + 
hepatic encephalopathy </p>

<p>679 
13.0 </p>

<p>Cholangitis + biliary 
stricture(s) </p>

<p>532 
10.2 </p>

<p>Refractory ascites + 
wasting </p>

<p>477 
9.1 </p>

<p>Bleeding + pediatric 
candidate </p>

<p>339 
6.5 </p>

<p>Quality of life + pain 
333 
6.4 
Refractory ascites + pediatric 
candidate </p>

<p>333 
6.4 </p>

<p>Pediatric candidate + wasting 
331 
6.3 
Hepatic encephalopathy + 
TIPSS contraindicated </p>

<p>322 
6.2 </p>

<p>Cholangitis + bacteremia 
321 
6.1 
Cholangitis + retransplant 
candidate </p>

<p>321 
6.1 </p>

<p>a Including initial applications, appeals, and extensions. </p>

<p>Table 4. Bases for exception for all applications combined </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: top 10 
triples of diagnoses </p>

<p>Diagnosis </p>

<p>Number of 
patients </p>

<p>Percentage of 
patients </p>

<p>Refractory ascites + 
hepatic encephalopathy + 
TIPSS contraindicated </p>

<p>244 
4.7 </p>

<p>Cholangitis + retransplant + 
strictures </p>

<p>221 
4.2 </p>

<p>Refractory ascites + pediatric 
candidate + wasting </p>

<p>177 
3.4 </p>

<p>Refractory ascites + hepatic 
encephalopathy + wasting </p>

<p>169 
3.2 </p>

<p>Cholangitis + bacteremia + 
biliary stricture(s) </p>

<p>168 
3.2 </p>

<p>Refractory ascites + quality of life + 
hepatic encephalopathy </p>

<p>152 
2.9 </p>

<p>Pediatric patient + wasting + 
development delay </p>

<p>150 
2.9 </p>

<p>Refractory ascites + bleeding + 
hepatic encephalopathy </p>

<p>147 
2.8 </p>

<p>Cholangitis + retransplant + 
bacteremia </p>

<p>136 
2.6 </p>

<p>Refractory ascites + hepatic 
encephalopathy + failed TIPPS </p>

<p>134 
2.6 </p>

<p>a Including initial applications, appeals, and extensions. </p>



<p>Regional variation in appeal denials </p>

<p>show the serious consequences of this variation 
for the transplantation rates themselves, for 
which we also found strong evidence of sub-
stantial variation by region. It comes as no sur-
prise that approved exception applicants were 
shown to have a statistically significant increase 
in the odds of transplantation, with their odds 
of receiving a transplant approximately two and 
one-half times that of patients not approved. 
We found that this effect does not appear to 
vary by region, suggesting that the variation in 
transplant rates is driven, at least in part, by 
the variation in appeal denial rates. We also 
clearly showed that among those patients who 
are eventually removed from the wait list for 
reasons other than transplant, a deterioration in 
health condition or death account for slightly 
more than two-thirds of removals. This high-
lights the accuracy of appeals to RRBs where 
the providers are predicting a high risk of death 
or medical deterioration where the patient may </p>

<p>not survive until the liver transplantation using 
standard MELD criteria for organ allocation. 
Contrary to the opinion that has sometimes 
been expressed, only a small percentage of rem-
ovals (12.6%) are the result of improving 
health. 
A potential limitation of this study is that it does 
not fully explore the role that may be played by 
diagnosis type and severity as explanatory factors 
of the regional variation in RRB decisions. When 
considering the list of top five diagnoses within 
each region, refractory ascites and cholangitis 
appear in the lists for all 11 regions, while hepato-
cellular carcinoma and bleeding occur in ten and 
nine of the lists, respectively. Thus, in terms of 
diagnoses, the regions are fairly similar but not 
uniform. Estimation of the specific effect of 
regional differences in diagnosis types is an area 
for further study. Regional differences in severity 
may also have some effect on the observed phe-
nomenon. While data on the severity for each case </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The percentage of initial exception applications that were denied by regional review boards in each of the 11 regions. The per-
centage of initial exception applications that were denied is shown on the vertical axis. The 11 regions are shown on the horizontal 
axis. Top left: all bases for exception; top right: ascites/hepatic hydrothorax only; bottom left: cholangitis/bacteremia only; bottom 
right: bleeding only. Note that there were no denials in region 6. </p>



<p>Gish et al. </p>

<p>were not available, we did attempt to adjust for 
some measure of patient status by including the 
number of diagnoses listed as a covariate in the 
GLM analysis. While not ideal, this measure may 
capture some of the information on severity and 
may be considered a partial proxy. Looking at the 
overall results of our analyses, it seems very clear 
that, for some patients, accidents of geography are 
still a factor in determining transplantation out-
come and, ultimately, survival. 
In June 2010, the OPTN/UNOS Board charged 
the Liver and Intestinal Organ Transplantation 
Committee with "making recommendations to 
reduce geographic disparities in waitlist mortality" 
(8). With consideration of public feedback, the 
Concept Document: Next Steps Toward Improving 
Liver Distribution was developed (8). The three key 
concepts proposed for further consideration were </p>

<p>Share 15 National, expedited graft placement, and 
tiered regional sharing and sharing threshold. 
Share 15 National and Share 35 Regional were 
implemented in June 2013. In Share 15 National, 
adult deceased donor livers are offered nationally 
to status 1 patients and patients with MELD 15 or 
higher before local/regional/national patients with 
MELD scores &lt;15. In Share 35 Regional, adult 
deceased donor livers are offered to regional 
patients with MELD scores above 35 before local 
patients below a MELD score of 35. All of these 
concepts assume that MELD scores are assigned in 
the same manner throughout the nation. 
Our data clearly demonstrate wide variations 
across regions for patients with non-standard 
MELD exception conditions. As Share 15 
National and Share 35 Regional have now been 
instituted, it will be important to re-assess data </p>

<p>Table 5. Generalized linear mixed-effects model fits for impact of region on the odds of denial </p>

<p>Covariates </p>

<p>Region 
Region + Number of diagnoses </p>

<p>Coefficient (SE) 
p-Value 
Coefficient (SE) 
p-Value </p>

<p>Intercept </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>À0.982 (0.147) 
&lt;0.001 
À0.850 (0.161) 
&lt;0.001 
Region 1 
0.987 (0.268) 
&lt;0.001 
0.999 (0.259) 
&lt;0.001 
Region 2 
À0.421 (0.170) 
0.014 
À0.429 (0.169) 
0.011 
Region 3 
0.148 (0.185) 
0.424 
0.138 (0.138) 
0.448 
Region 4 
0.092 (0.177) 
0.605 
0.074 (0.175) 
0.673 
Region 5 
0.750 (0.176) 
&lt;0.001 
0.783 (0.783) 
&lt;0.001 
Region 6 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>À16.661 (25.600) 
0.515 
À16.689 (558.346) 
0.976 
Region 7 
À0.287 (0.198) 
0.147 
À0.330 (0.198) 
0.096 
Region 9 
0.686 (0.187) 
&lt;0.001 
0.682 (0.183) 
&lt;0.001 
Region 10 
À0.207 (0.189) 
0.274 
À0.215 (0.187) 
0.249 
Region 11 
À0.096 (0.188) 
0.609 
À0.127 (0.187) 
0.496 
# Diagnoses 
-
-
À0.034 (0.018) 
0.066 </p>

<p>The estimated coefficients represent the effects of Region and Number of diagnoses on the log odds of denial; larger values correspond to greater odds 
that a patient is denied. 
a Region 8 is used as the reference level and its effect appears as the intercept term. 
b Region 6 has very large negative coefficients and standard errors because there were zero denials in this region. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Heat map displaying proportion of applications denied, cross-tabulated by region and number of diagnoses. Cells for which 
there were zero applications for a given region and number of diagnoses are colored gray. </p>



<p>Regional variation in appeal denials </p>

<p>on exceptions. However, there have been ongoing 
and evolving discussions by the Liver and Intesti-
nal Organ Transplantation Committee related to 
making recommendations to further reduce geo-
graphic disparities in wait list mortality by mov-
ing to expanded sharing policies. Having agreed 
in 2012 that the geographic disparities in organ 
allocation were unacceptably high, the OPTN/ 
UNOS Board of Directors charged the Liver and 
Intestinal Organ Transplantation Committee to 
investigate how the current geographic patterns 
of organ distribution may affect transplant candi-
dates' chances to receive organ offers. In the con-
cept paper presented by the Committee in June 
2014, it is clearly acknowledged that despite 
changes over the years, geographic variation in 
the level of medical urgency many candidates 
must reach to receive liver transplants has not 
been significantly reduced, with candidates in 
some parts of the country having to wait until 
they are much more severely ill compared to 
patients in other areas (9). One possibility sug-
gested to decrease overall variation in MELD/ 
PELD scores at which candidates receive a trans-
plant is organ distribution based on a limited 
number of allocation districts instead of the exist-</p>

<p>ing local and regional boundaries. Statistical 
modeling shows that these optimized maps might 
reduce variation in the MELD/PELD scores at 
transplant and reduce both waiting list and total 
deaths. The Committee also proposed consider-
ation of changing to a national review board, 
noting that, just as we have shown in our study, 
the current RRB system does not promote con-
sistent reviews of the MELD/PELD scores 
nationwide. 
In an ideal world, research identifying factors 
associated with wait list removals for patients 
with each of the non-RED conditions would have 
been carried out and used to construct a predic-
tive model that accurately estimates risk of wait-
ing list removals. That identified risk could then 
serve as the measure by which prioritization is 
determined. Unfortunately, little research has yet 
been performed and because many such condi-
tions occur infrequently, valid cohort studies that 
could result in reproducible, clinically relevant 
results may not be possible in the near term, if 
ever. Thus, for the foreseeable future, expert 
opinion will continue to play a key role in priori-
tization policy. 
The large variation across UNOS regions in 
denial rates for patient appeals which we report 
here gives strong support for the creation of an 
alternate system. We suggest simultaneously mov-
ing toward super regional/national sharing con-
cepts and, as has been proposed by the Liver and 
Intestinal Organ Transplantation Committee and 
other authors (2, 5), a national review board to 
replace the current RRB system for non-standard 
conditions which require MELD exceptions. 
Ideally, a national review board process that uses 
current clinical knowledge combined with stan-
dardized data collection methods and analysis pro-
tocols could assign priority on a consistent basis. A 
new program that includes a national policy with 
consistency in the medical criteria and scores </p>

<p>Table 6. Transplantation rates by region </p>

<p>Region 
Removed for transplant (%) 
Removed for other (%) </p>

<p>Overall 
2320 (77.7) 
666 (22.3) 
1 
60 (65.9) 
31 (34.1) 
2 
342 (75.0) 
114 (25.0) 
3 
211 (80.5) 
51 (19.5) 
4 
201 (77.0) 
60 (23.0) 
5 
336 (72.7) 
126 (27.3) 
6 
53 (76.8) 
16 (23.2) 
7 
160 (82.5) 
34 (17.5) 
8 
160 (84.2) 
30 (15.8) 
9 
263 (74.9) 
88 (25.1) 
10 
272 (82.4) 
58 (17.6) 
11 
262 (81.9) 
58 (18.1) </p>

<p>Table 7. Transplantation rates by region, according to regional review board decision </p>

<p>Region 
Approved (%) 
Not approved (%) 
p-Value 
Odds Ratio (confidence intervals) </p>

<p>Overall 
1764 (82.4) 
556 (65.7) 
&lt;0.001 
2.45 (2.04, 2.93) 
1 
35 (76.1) 
25 (55.6) 
0.195 
2.55 (1.04, 6.24) 
2 
278 (79) 
64 (61.5) 
0.004 
2.35 (1.47, 3.76) 
3 
165 (87.8) 
46 (62.2) 
0.001 
4.37 (2.30, 8.29) 
4 
153 (82.7) 
48 (63.2) 
0.008 
2.79 (1.53, 5.09) 
5 
219 (76.8) 
117 (66.1) 
0.063 
1.7 (1.12, 2.58) 
6 
53 (76.8) 
0 (0) 
7 
121 (85.8) 
39 (73.6) 
0.195 
2.17 (1, 4.7) 
8 
116 (85.9) 
44 (80) 
0.426 
1.53 (0.67, 3.46) 
9 
194 (81.5) 
69 (61.1) 
&lt;0.001 
2.81 (1.71, 4.64) 
10 
224 (85.8) 
48 (69.6) 
0.015 
2.65 (1.43, 4.92) 
11 
206 (85.8) 
56 (70) 
0.015 
2.6 (1.42, 4.73) </p>



<p>Gish et al. </p>

<p>assigned for non-RED conditions could help to 
prevent "MELD creep" or MELD inflation, 
greatly reduce regionally driven MELD inequities, 
and disincentivize today's situation in which some 
patients with resources (especially financial) pursue 
centers with high rates of approval for exceptions 
and shorter wait times. 
At the same time, data on transplant benefit and 
wait list removals for disease progression should 
be collected for each non-RED condition to 
improve the knowledge base with which guidelines 
can be developed. Ultimately, a rational approach 
to a national system created through changes in 
UNOS policy may be our best hope for equalizing 
the assignment of MELD exception points and 
providing equity for transplant candidates in all 
regions with the singular or composite medical </p>

<p>illnesses that currently fall in the category of 
non-RED conditions. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This manuscript was not funded or prepared in any part by 
a commercial organization. This project was partially 
supported by the National Institutes of Health, Grant 
UL1TR000100. The authors would like to express their 
gratitude to Dr. Lark Lands for her invaluable assistance in 
preparing the manuscript for publication. </p>

<p>Authors' contributions </p>

<p>Robert G. Gish: Concept/design, data collection, 
drafting article, critical revision of article, and 
approval of article; Robert J. Wong: Data analy-
sis/interpretation, critical revision of article, and 
approval of article; Gordon Honerkamp-Smith: </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>ie </p>

<p>d 
( 4 0 . 5 % </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>C 
a n d id </p>

<p>a t e 
c o n d it io </p>

<p>n 
d e t e r i o r a t e d </p>

<p>( 2 6 . 7 % </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>O 
t h e r ( 1 5 . 5 % </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>C 
a n d i d a t e </p>

<p>c o n d it io </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>im 
p r o v e d 
( 1 2 . 6 % </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>R 
e f u s e d 
t r a n s p la </p>

<p>n t ( 3 . 2 % </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>U 
n a b le </p>

<p>t o 
c o n t a c t c a n d id </p>

<p>a t e 
( 1 . 5 % </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Number of patients </p>

<p>Reasons for Removal Without Transplant </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Reasons for removal from the wait list other than 
receiving transplant. </p>

<p>Table 8. Kaplan-Meier estimates of mortality (95% confidence inter-
vals) </p>

<p>Approved 
Not approved </p>

<p>90 days 
0.04 (0.03, 0.05) 
0.07 (0.05, 0.09) 
180 days 
0.09 (0.07, 0.10) 
0.11 (0.08, 0.13) 
1 yr 
0.15 (0.12, 0.18) 
0.16 (0.12, 0.19) 
3 yr 
0.24 (0.19, 0.29) 
0.28 (0.22, 0.32) 
5 yr 
0.29 (0.20, 0.36) 
0.38 (0.30, 0.45) </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Kaplan-Meier curves for approved and denied 
patients. Times are measured from date of regional review 
board decision. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Kaplan-Meier curves within denied patients, stratified 
by top five most frequent diagnoses. Times are measured from 
date of regional review board decision. </p>



<p>Regional variation in appeal denials </p>

<p>Statistics, data analysis/interpretation, critical 
revision of article, and approval of article; Ron-
ghui Xu: Statistics, data analysis/interpretation, 
approval of article; Robert W. Osorio: Data 
analysis/interpretation, drafting article, critical 
revision of article, and approval of article. </p>





<p>Gish et al. </p>

</text></tei>