<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5413540" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>COPD is an increasing important cause of morbidity and mortality worldwide and leads 
to a significant economic and social burden. 1,2 Advanced-stage COPD is characterized 
by irreversible severe flow limitation and chronic hypercapnia. The mechanisms related </p>

<p>Correspondence: rongchang Chen 
state Key laboratory of respiratory 
Disease, guangzhou Institute of 
respiratory Disease, The First 
Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou 
Medical University, 151 Yanjiang 
road, guangzhou 510120, People's 
republic of China 
Tel/fax +86 20 8306 2882 
email chenrc@vip.163.com </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of COPD 
27 April 2017 </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1280 </p>

<p>Zhou et al </p>

<p>to chronic hypercapnia in COPD include the imbalance of 
respiratory impedance and reduced respiratory muscle func-
tion. Chronic hypercapnia could result in respiratory acidosis 
and desensitization of respiratory central drive in response 
to hypercapnia. Noninvasive ventilation (NIV) is possible 
to unload the respiratory muscles, reduce hypercapnia and 
restore the sensitivity of respiratory center. 3 
Physiological studies in literature had shown that NIV 
could improve ventilation as well as important physiologi-
cal variables such as lung hyperinflation and blood gases 4 
in COPD patients with hypercapnia. Results from several 
clinical studies showed improvements in survival, exercise 
capacity, health-related quality of life (HRQL) and sleep 
quality. 5-8 In addition, NIV use at home might be associ-
ated with lower overall treatment costs and fewer hospital 
admissions. 9 On the other hand, there were also reports 
showing that NIV provided no additional benefits than 
long-term oxygen therapy alone in patient's survival rate, 
hospital admission rate, arterial blood gases and quality of 
life. The reasons for these controversial results are unclear. 
Patient selection, methodology and quality control of NIV 
were supposed to be the main reasons for explanation of 
discrepancy of different studies results. Respiratory events 
occur during home NIV, such as asynchrony and leakage, 
are common and not readily detectable at home use setting. 
Compliance and ventilator parameters settings are another 
important factors attributable to the outcomes of NIV. NIV 
ventilator with built-in software for monitoring and record-
ing can provided the possibility to check the compliance of 
use and respiratory events during NIV treatment, 10,11 so that 
clinician can find out and fix the problem. 
This study thus aims to investigate the effects of home 
NIV on stable COPD patients with chronic hypercapnic 
respiratory failure by using NIV ventilator equipped with 
built-in software. </p>

<p>Methods 
ethics statement </p>

<p>The study was approved by The First Affiliated Hospital of 
Guangzhou Medical University Ethics Committee, China. 
Informed consent was obtained from COPD patients or 
surrogates (the next of kin who had the authority to sign on 
behalf of the inclusive patients in case patients were illiterate) 
before participating in this study. The trial was registered 
with ClinicalTrials.gov, number NCT02499718. </p>

<p>study design and patients </p>

<p>Our study was a multicenter prospective, randomized, 
controlled clinical trial using a prospective, randomized, </p>

<p>open, blinded endpoint (PROBE) design. 12 Patients were 
recruited from 20 respiratory units from October 1, 2015, 
and recruitment was terminated with a record of the vital 
statistics on May 31, 2016. Patients with clinically stable, 
GOLD stages III and IV flow limitation and chronic hyper-
capnic (prolonged hypercapnia during daytime at rest without 
oxygen or ventilatory support for at least 3 months), aged 
$40 years, were eligible for this study. Patients were judged 
as clinically stable if they had no acute exacerbation, which 
was defined as an increase in or new onset of more than one 
respiratory symptom (cough, sputum production, sputum 
purulence, dyspnea, and wheezing) lasting $2 days and 
requiring any change of pharmacological treatment during 
the 4-week run-in period before randomization. 
Patients were ineligible if they had abnormalities of 
the lung or thorax other than COPD. Additional exclusion 
criteria were previously initiated NPPV (NPPV was used 
as a routine therapy in home before inclusion), obstructive 
sleep apnea, COPD with obstructive sleep apnea overlap 
syndrome, severe heart failure (New York Heart Association 
stage IV), severe arrhythmias, unstable angina, and malignant 
comorbidities. We also did not include the COPD patients 
in impaired general condition that could preclude follow-up 
visit. We did not include highly selected patients to main-
tain the generalizability of the results. COPD patients were 
recorded the screening procedure (including eligible, not 
eligible, and randomized) in a screening log. </p>

<p>randomization and masking </p>

<p>After a 4-week run-in period, patients were admitted to 
hospital and randomly distributed to one of the following two 
groups: NPPV group and control group (LTOT). Randomiza-
tion was via a computer-generated block randomization lists 
with a block size of four patients. When a patient was included, 
the peripheral investigators contacted an independent study 
coordinator, who would register patient's baseline data and 
disclosed the group allocation for this patient. The interven-
tion was unblinded as an effective sham noninvasive ventila-
tor is not available; however, outcome assessors were blinded 
to treatment assignment throughout the trial. </p>

<p>study procedure and ventilator setting </p>

<p>All included patients received regular maintenance pharma-
cologic treatments as well as home long term oxygen therapy 
(LTOT) according to the recommendation of GOLD 2014 at 
least since the run-in period. All patients received LTOT via 
nasal cannula at a flow rate of 1-3 L/min to achieve oxygen 
saturation $90% and the cumulative time was at least 15 hrs 
daily. 13 In the NIV group, NIV was used at home setting, at least </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1281 </p>

<p>nPPV in stable hypercapnic COPD </p>

<p>5 hrs daily. The built-in software installed in the ventilator could 
record the parameters (including estimation of leaks, inspiratory 
positive airway pressure [IPAP], expiratory positive airway 
pressure [EPAP], tidal volume, minute ventilation, respiratory 
rate, back-up frequency, and percentage of inspirations trig-
gered by the patient) (Figures 1 and 2). The time of using NIV 
depended on patient's preference, although we recommend the 
patients to use NIV during sleep as the first choice. 
Flexo ST 30 NIV ventilator (Curative Co. SuZhou, 
People's Republic of China) was used for the study. The 
parameter settings were as following. S/T mode, EPAP set at 
4 cmH 2 O and backup frequency at 16 breaths/min. The IPAP 
was titrated by gradually increasing IPAP to the maximally 
tolerated level and IPAP-EPAP difference (pressure support 
level) more than 10 cmH 2 O 7 . The Face masks or nasal masks 
were used according to the patients' comfort and preference. 
After randomization, all patients in NIV group receive at least 
one hour NIV treatment in hospital setting in order to get used 
to NIV treatment under the observation of study staff who </p>

<p>were trained to provide NIV treatment. Furthermore, educa-
tion of patients and patient's family members was provided 
for ventilator use, mask fitting, etc. 
Our primary endpoint was PaCO 2 . We did all blood gas 
measurements from arterialized capillary blood during 
spontaneous breathing, at least 1 h after the patients in the 
intervention group had switched from NPPV to spontaneous 
breathing. We assessed HRQL using the Severe Respiratory 
Insufficiency (SRI) Questionnaire 14,15 and the COPD assess-
ment test (CAT) as tools. We estimated pulmonary function, 
6-min walk distance (6MWD), blood oxygen saturation, 
baseline dyspnea index (BDI), and transition dyspnea index 
(TDI) as previously specified. 16-18 The estimators who took 
these measurements were blinded to treatment assignment 
and not involved in the study. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-6" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">17.0</rs> for Win-
dows (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>, Chicago, IL, USA). All primary analyses, </p>

































































<p>Figure 1 scatter plot of leak recorded in built-in software. 
Abbreviations: MV, minute volume; Vt, tidal volume; BPM, breath per minuter; IT, inspiratory time. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1282 </p>

<p>Zhou et al </p>

<p>as well as the primary endpoint analysis, were conducted 
on an intention to treat analysis (ITT). One-way analysis of 
variance was used to analyze the effect of NPPV on changes 
from baseline to follow-up of endpoints (forced vital capac-
ity [FVC], forced expiratory volume in 1 s [FEV 1 ], arterial 
oxygen pressure [PaO 2 ], PaCO 2 , arterial oxygen saturation 
[SaO 2 ], pH, TDI, and HRQL summary measures [SRI and 
CAT]). Chi-square test was used for comparing the differ-
ences between the two groups. P,0.05 was considered as 
statistically significant. Bland-Altman plots were used to 
evaluate the differences of ventilator parameters between the 
data from the built-in software and the PowerLab system. 
The range of agreement was shown with 95% limits of agree-
ment (LoA) that stands for the mean difference ±1.96 SD. 
Narrower 95% LoA indicated better agreement. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Among the 174 patients, 115 patients met the criteria and 
were enrolled in this study (Figure 3). Among them, 57 and 
58 patients were in the intervention and control groups, </p>

<p>respectively. The baseline characteristics were similar in 
these two groups (Table 1). As expected, approximately 
two-thirds of the subjects were male, with a mean age in the 
late 65 years. Patients had severe airflow obstruction and 
very low carbon monoxide gas transfer consistent with sig-
nificant awake hypoxemia and hypercapnia while breathing 
room air. A total of 55 patients in the intervention group 
completed the study, and two patients (3.5%) discontinued 
NPPV treatment: the reasons were mask intolerance in one 
patient and patients' impression of uselessness of NPPV 
in one patient. A total of 55 patients in the control arm 
successfully completed the study. One patient's death and 
two patients' drop-off were recorded, whereas the rate of 
loss was 5.1%. 
The mean inspiratory pressure was 17.8±2.08 cmH 2 O, 
and the mean expiratory pressure was 4.2±0.1 cmH 2 O. 
Patients on NPPV adhered well to the therapy. The overall 
compliance to NIV treatment was well. Mean time of NIV 
usage was 5.6±1.4h per day. A total of 48 patients (84%) 
exceeded the prescribed usage time of .5 h/day. The usage </p>























































































































<p>Figure 2 Parameters recorded in built-in software. 
Abbreviations: MV, minute volume; Vt, tidal volume; BPM, breath per minuter; IT, inspiratory time. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1283 </p>

<p>nPPV in stable hypercapnic COPD </p>

<p>16.8 h/day and 52 patients (90%) exceeded the prescribed 
usage time of .15 h/day. 
Bland-Altman plots showed a low mean bias value 
between two measurements (PowerLab system and ventilator), 
as shown in Figure 4. In comparing the estimation of leak, we 
observed the lowest bias values (0.5 L/min) and the lowest 
LoA values (−2.5 to 3.5 L/min). In the estimation of pres-
sure, the lowest bias value was −0.21 cmH 2 O and the lowest 
LoA value was −0.52 to 0.1 cmH 2 O. All the above results 
supported that the built-in software could provide accurate 
monitoring of the performance of the ventilator. 
For the primary endpoint, 55 (96%) of the 57 patients 
in the intervention group and 55 (95%) of the 58 patients 
in the control group finished the follow-up visit. Comparing 
with the baseline, the decrease in PaCO 2 was evident in the 
intervention group than in the control group (−10.41±0.97 
vs −4.32±0.68 mmHg, P=0.03). Furthermore, the rate of 
subjects with more than the minimum clinical improvement 
of 6MWT was higher in NIV group than in the control group 
(21 [38.2%] vs 10 [18.2%], P=0.02) (Table 2). The change in 
CAT scores had a positive trend in the intervention arm than 
in the control arm (−4.98±6.25 vs −3.31±4.28, P=0.06). How-
ever, no significant between-group differences were noted 
for changes in SRI scores, SaO 2 , pH, PaO 2 , BE, FVC, FEV 1 , 
FEV 1 /FVC, and TDI (all P.0.05) (Table 3). Seven patients </p>







<p>@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ </p>



















<p>
Figure 3 CONSORT flow diagram. 
Abbreviations: COnsOrT, consolidated standards of reporting trials; lTOT, long-term oxygen therapy; nPPV, noninvasive positive pressure ventilation. </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline demographic and clinical characteristics of 
patients </p>

<p>NPPV + LTOT 
LTOT </p>

<p>Male, n (%) 
36 (80) 
35 (77.78) 
age, years 
66.91±7.10 
68.47±6.57 
BMI, kg/m 2 
19.43±3.10 
20.56±3.36 
saO 2 , % 
90.80±4.61 
92.44±3.11 
IPaP, mmh 2 O 
17.8±2.08 
-
ePaP, mmh 2 O 
4.2±0.1 
-
∆Ps, mmh 2 O 
12.29±2.08 
-
ph 
7.37±0.04 
7.36±0.05 
PaCO 2 , mmhg 
57.78±2.88 
58.07±3.50 
PaO 2 , mmhg 
69.76±15.83 
73.99±27.85 
FVC, l 
1.60±0.65 
1.48±0.53 
FVC, % predicted 
51.16±16.45 
50.26±17.28 
FeV 1 , l 
0.55±0.19 
0.62±0.22 
FeV 1 , % predicted 
23.34±7.48 
28.02±11.97 
FeV 1 /FVC, % 
37.56±9.66 
38.05±17.36 </p>

<p>Notes: Data are mean ± sD, unless otherwise stated. ∆Ps= IPaP-ePaP. 
Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; ePaP, expiratory positive airway pressure; 
FeV 1 , forced expiratory volume in 1 s; FVC, forced vital capacity; IPaP, inspiratory 
positive airway pressure; lTOT, long-term oxygen therapy; nPPV, noninvasive 
positive pressure ventilation; PaO 2 , arterial oxygen pressure; PaCO 2 , arterial carbon 
dioxide pressure; saO 2 , arterial oxygen saturation. </p>

<p>time was ,4 h in 8.7% of patients. The mean estimation 
of leak was 37.99±13.71 L/min, among whom 87% of the 
patients displayed with leak ,40 L/min. The mean estimation 
of leak recorded in the ventilator was 37.99±13.71 L/min. 
In the LTOT treatment arm, the mean LTOT usage was </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1284 </p>

<p>Zhou et al </p>

<p>(12%) reported skin rash at the facial skin, which could be 
managed by changing mask. We did not judge this as a rel-
evant adverse event as minor skin lesions can often happen 
during noninvasive ventilation. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This is the first randomized controlled trial report to date 
of using NIV ventilator equipped with built-in software to 
monitor the ventilator parameters in home setting in stable 
hypercapnic COPD patients. In order to estimate the accuracy 
of built-in software in ventilators, data downloaded from 
software were compared using the <rs type="software">PowerLab</rs> system. The 
finding showed that the estimation of leak and pressure was a 
low mean bias value between built-in software and <rs type="software">PowerLab</rs> 
system. Previous study showed that the rate of abnormali-
ties was 66% and leak was the most common abnormality 
(34.2%) followed by desaturation dips (23.8%) in home 
NPPV. 19 In addition, studies have further reported that leak 
increases ineffective trigger, patient-ventilator asynchrony, 
and hypoventilation in patients. 20-22 In our study, the mean 
estimation of leak was 37.99 L/min and 87% of the leaks </p>

<p>were ,40 L/min, which was greatly lower than the threshold 
leak influencing the effects of NPPV as reported by previous 
study, 23 which could ensure the appropriateness of NIV use 
and reliability of the results. 
By using built-in software, ventilators, respiratory events 
were occurring in 12 patients (21%) during NPPV, which 
were corrected by study staff to ensure the proper use of 
NPPV. Also, this trial provided evidence that three months 
use of NPPV at home could improve PaCO 2 and 6MWD in 
chronic stable COPD with hypercapnia as compared with 
LTOT alone. Quality of life (CAT scores) was shown to have 
tendency of improvement, but the improvement did not reach 
the level of statistical significance (P=0.06) probably due to 
the small sample size. Additionally, NPPV treatment was 
not associated with significant improvements in pulmonary 
function and dyspnea. 
Struik et al 24 found that the level of PaCO 2 in hypercapnic 
COPD patients, who received NPPV for .5 h, decreased 
remarkably after 3 months. The findings of our study simi-
larly confirmed that NPPV plus LTOT could significantly 
reduce PaCO 2 than LTOT alone, which may be associated 
with noninvasive ventilation that could unload respiratory 
muscles fatigue and reset central respiratory drive. Another 
important finding was that NPPV significantly improved the 
exercise endurance of the hypercapnic COPD patients (the 
mechanisms related to this improvement are not clear and 
were not studied in this trial). We hypothesized that NIV 
might be able to improve quality of life if NPPV were used 
for longer time in a larger population. The minimal clini-
cal improvement in the 6MWD of 54 min 25 was reached in 
21 (36.8%) patients in the NPPV group versus 10 (17.2%) </p>

<p>Figure 4 Bland-altman plots for absolute reliability of parameters estimation between the Flexo and labChart. 
Notes: (A) Bland-altman plots for absolute reliability (means vs differences) of leak estimation between the Flexo and labChart. (B) Bland-altman plots for absolute 
reliability (means vs differences) of pressure estimation between the Flexo and labChart. 
Abbreviation: sD, standard deviation. </p>















































































<p>
Table 2 6MWD </p>

<p>Group 
6MWD change, n 
Total </p>

<p>Improved 
(∆d $54 min) </p>

<p>Unimproved 
(∆d ,54 min) </p>

<p>lTOT 
10 
48 
58 
nPPV + lTOT* 
21 
36 
57 
Total 
31 
84 
115 </p>

<p>Note: *Chi-square test, P=0.02. 
Abbreviations: lTOT, long-term oxygen therapy; 6MWD, 6-min walk distance; 
nPPV, noninvasive positive pressure ventilation. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1285 </p>

<p>nPPV in stable hypercapnic COPD </p>

<p>patients in the control group (P=0.02). Although we did not 
observe statistical significance in the scores of SRI and CAT 
between the two groups, our findings suggested that NPPV 
tended to improve the quality of life of COPD patients and 
the negative outcomes could be associated with the short 
follow-up visit (3 months). Additionally, no significant 
improvements in pulmonary function were found in the 
present study at 3 months after intervention, which was in 
agreement with the results reported in previous studies. 6,24 
Nevertheless, the current study presents several limi-
tations. First, the average IPAP was only 17.8 cmH 2 O. 
In recent years, some researchers stressed the importance of 
high-intensity noninvasive ventilation. 26-28 However, patients 
included in those studies were European and American 
who were different from Asian patients. Although the mean 
pressure was low in the present study, we demonstrated that 
NPPV also decreased the PaCO 2 and improved the exercise 
endurance and had a positive trend in improving the quality 
of life. Second, the follow-up time was short (3 months) in 
this study. In our future studies, ventilators equipped with 
built-in software will be used for the evaluation of the long-
term effects of NPPV (including the survival, the frequency 
of acute exacerbation of COPD, and economic evaluation of 
the cost of COPD) in stable hypercapnic COPD patients. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Ventilators equipped with built-in software provided meth-
odology for monitoring NPPV use at home, which could 
facilitate the improvement of compliance and quality control 
of NPPV use. It was shown that three months use of NPPV at 
home could reduce the PaCO 2 and improve exercise tolerance 
(6MWD) in chronic hypercapnic COPD patients. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors wish to thank the Curative for providing 
the ventilators. The study was supported by the Natural 
Science Foundation of China (NSFC; 813111129) and the 
Science and Technology Project of Guangdong Province 
(2014A020215033). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>All authors contributed toward data analysis, drafting and 
critically revising the paper and agree to be accountable for 
all aspects of the work. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors received financial support from Curative Medical 
Co. China for the research. The authors report no other con-
flicts of interests in this work. </p>



<p>Table 3 Treatment period effect between two groups </p>

<p>90 days change from baseline (95% confidence interval) 
Difference 
P-value </p>

<p>NPPV + LTOT 
LTOT </p>

<p>saO 2 
1.2% (−0.8% to 3.2%) 
0.3% (−0.8% to 1.5%) 
0.9% (−0.6% to 2.4%) 
0.15 </p>

<p>FVC 
6.6% (−6.4% to 18.6%) 
6.7% (0.6% to 12.8%) 
−0.1% (−5.6% to 23.1%) 
0.20 
FeV 1 
17.3% (−8.5% to 43.2%) 
−1.4% (−7.7% to 5.0%) 
18.7% (−5.4% to 33.6%) 
0.10 
ph 
0.002 (0 to 0.003) 
0.002 (0 to 0.004) 
−0.001 (0.001 to 0.002) 
0.56 
PaCO 2 
−17.7% (−21.5% to −13.9%) 
−7.2% (−9.7% to −5.7%) 
−10.5% (−4.7% to −12.3%) 
0.03 
PaO 2 
4.3% (−4.6% to 13.2%) 
−3.1% (−9.6% to 3.5%) 
7.4% (−5.4% to 4.1%) 
0.58 
srI 
24.7% (15.3% to 34.1%) 
5.5% (−0.9% to 11.9%) 
19.2% (2.1% to 17.6%) 
0.21 
CaT 
−14.7% (−21.3% to −10.2%) 
−11.9% (−18.3% to −5.5%) 
6.8% (−20.3% to −4.2%) 
0.06 
TDI 
−6.9% (9.6% to −4.2%) 
−9.4% (−11.9% to −6.9%) 
2.5% (5.3% to −3.2%) 
0.79 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CaT, COPD assessment test; FeV 1 , forced expiratory volume in 1 s; FVC, forced vital capacity; lTOT, long-term oxygen therapy; nPPV, noninvasive 
positive pressure ventilation; PaO 2 , arterial oxygen pressure; PaCO 2 , arterial carbon dioxide pressure; saO 2 , arterial oxygen saturation; SRI, Severe Respiratory Insufficiency; 
TDI, Transitional Dyspnea Index. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-chronic-obstructive-pulmonary-disease-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of COPD is an international, peer-reviewed 
journal of therapeutics and pharmacology focusing on concise rapid 
reporting of clinical studies and reviews in COPD. Special focus is given 
to the pathophysiological processes underlying the disease, intervention 
programs, patient focused education, and self management protocols. </p>

<p>This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine and CAS. The 
manuscript management system is completely online and includes a 
very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1286 </p>

<p>Zhou et al </p>



</text></tei>