<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5111481" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Automated insulin management features of the MiniMed 
Ò 640G sensor-augmented pump system 
include suspension in response to predicted low sensor glucose (SG) values (''suspend before low''), suspension 
in response to existing low SG values (''suspend on low''), and automatic restarting of basal insulin delivery 
upon SG recovery. The effectiveness of these features was evaluated using <rs type="software">CareLink</rs> 
Ò software data. 
Methods: Anonymized data from MiniMed 640G system users (n = 4818), MiniMed 530G system users 
(n = 39,219), and MiniMed Paradigm 
Ò VeoÔ system users (n = 43,193) who voluntarily uploaded pump and 
sensor data were retrospectively analyzed. Comparisons were made between days in which system features 
were enabled at any time and those in which they were not. Comparisons were also made between pump 
suspension events for which insulin delivery was automatically or manually resumed and between glycemic 
parameters of users who switched from the MiniMed Paradigm Veo system to the MiniMed 640G system. 
Results: Days in which the MiniMed 640G ''suspend before low'' feature was enabled had lower percentages of 
SG readings £70 mg/dL (3.9 mmol/L) or  ‡240 mg/dL (13.3 mmol/L) than days when it was not enabled 
(P &lt; 0.001 for each). Users who switched from the MiniMed Paradigm Veo system to the MiniMed 640G 
system had fewer excursions below £70 mg/dL (P &lt; 0.001) and  ‡240 mg/dL (P &lt; 0.001). SG values following 
automatically resumed pump suspension events recovered more rapidly and had a more stabilized endpoint than 
following manually resumed events. 
Conclusions: Automated insulin management features of the MiniMed 640G system can reduce the frequency 
of both high and low SG values and help stabilize SG after resumption of insulin delivery. </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>ensor-augmented pump systems provide insulin de-
livery and continuous glucose monitoring therapies that 
can improve the management of diabetes. The MiniMed 
Paradigm Veo and MiniMed 530G systems (Medtronic, 
Northridge, CA) are capable of suspending insulin delivery in 
response to sensor glucose (SG) values at or below a pre-
specified threshold (Low Glucose Suspend [LGS] and 
Threshold Suspend [TS], respectively) (Table 1). The sus-
pension automatically resumes (''auto-resume'') in 2 hours 
unless basal insulin delivery is manually resumed. Four hours </p>

<p>after automatic insulin delivery resumption, the threshold 
suspend feature of both systems can allow resuspension of 
insulin delivery if the sensor glucose is still at or below pre-
specified threshold. This feature significantly reduces the se-
verity and duration of hypoglycemic events once they occur, 
and has a salutary effect on the frequency of such events. </p>

<p>1-7   In addition to a threshold suspend feature (''suspend on 
low''), the MiniMed 640G system (Medtronic) can suspend 
insulin delivery based on predicted hypoglycemia (''suspend 
before low'') (Table 1), which can reduce the frequency of 
hypoglycemic events to a greater extent. 
8,9 When ''suspend 
before low'' is enabled, basal insulin delivery is stopped if the </p>

<p>1 Medtronic, Northridge, California. 
2 Diabetes Research Group, King's College London, London, United Kingdom. </p>

<p>ª Alex Zhong et al., 2016; Published by Mary Ann Liebert, Inc. This Open Access article is distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Noncommercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits any noncommercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited. </p>

<p>DIABETES TECHNOLOGY &amp; THERAPEUTICS 
Volume 18, Number 10, 2016 
Mary Ann Liebert, Inc. 
DOI: 10.1089/dia.2016.0216 </p>



<p>SG value is predicted to reach or fall below a preset low limit 
within 30 min. Similar to the MiniMed Paradigm Veo and 
MiniMed 530G systems, basal insulin delivery can be man-
ually resumed at any time during a suspend event and auto-
matically resumes after 2 hours. In contrast, ''auto-resume'' 
can occur sooner if, at 30 min since the start of pump sus-
pension, the SG value is above the low limit and predicted to 
remain above the low limit within 30 min. 
<rs type="software">CareLink</rs> 
Ò Personal Therapy Management Software for 
diabetes provides remote storage and retrospective analysis 
capabilities of data from the pump, sensor, and blood glucose 
meter. 
10 <rs type="software">CareLink</rs> software data from individual users can be 
reviewed in collaboration with healthcare providers to guide 
therapy adjustments, or can be aggregated and analyzed to 
detect large-scale patterns and outcomes in an anonymized 
manner. The effectiveness and usage patterns of the automated 
insulin management features of the MiniMed 640G system, in 
addition to specific MiniMed Paradigm Veo and MiniMed 
530G comparator data, were evaluated. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Anonymized <rs type="software">CareLink</rs> data, voluntarily uploaded from 
4818 individuals using the MiniMed 640G system between 
January 13, 2015, and January 14, 2016 (286,149 user-days 
of data); 39,219 individuals using MiniMed 530G system 
between October 15, 2013, and June 25, 2015 (2,777,117 
user-days of data); and 43,193 individuals using the MiniMed 
Paradigm Veo system between October 1, 2011, and July 14, 
2015 (4,101,706 user-days of data); were analyzed. Users of 
each system uploaded, at least, 5 days of <rs type="software">CareLink</rs> data 
during the aforementioned time periods. The aforementioned 
data included information on insulin delivery from the pumps 
and information from CGM sensors (Enlite 
Ò sensor [Mini-
Med 530G system] and Enhanced Enlite 
Ò sensor [MiniMed 
Paradigm Veo and MiniMed 640G systems]; Medtronic). 
For this retrospective analysis, users were not provided 
specific instruction from healthcare professionals on when or 
how long to use system features or how often to calibrate 
systems with self-monitored blood glucose measurements. 
Voluntarily uploaded and anonymized data were captured 
from <rs type="software">CareLink</rs> software. To compare SG trajectories associ-
ated with different types of pump suspension, user-days were </p>

<p>assigned to the feature (i.e., predictive ''suspend before low'' 
or reactive ''suspend on low'') in use during that day. The 
threshold range for the MiniMed 640G ''suspend before low'' 
and ''suspend on low'' was 50-90 mg/dL (3.3-5.0 mmol/L). 
The threshold range for the MiniMed Paradigm Veo system 
was 40-110 mg/dL (2.2-6.1 mmol/L) and that for the Mini-
Med 530G was 60-90 mg/dL (2.8-5.0 mmol/L). While the 
MiniMed Paradigm Veo LGS and the MiniMed 530G TS 
features differ in suspend threshold range, they are considered 
functionally equivalent. 
2 For simplicity, the threshold suspend 
features in all three systems have been referred to as ''suspend 
on low''. Pump suspension events were characterized ac-
cording to whether insulin delivery was resumed automati-
cally or manually. Hypoglycemia and hyperglycemia were 
defined as SG values £70 mg/dL (£3.9 mmol/L) and 240-
300 mg/dL (13.3-16.7 mmol/L), respectively, and were com-
pared across systems using a Kruskal-Wallis analysis. Severe 
hyperglycemia was defined as  ‡300 mg/dL (16.7 mmol/L). 
Hypoglycemic and hyperglycemic excursions were defined as 
 ‡2 consecutive hypoglycemic or hyperglycemic SG values 
per day or night (8:00 PM-8:00 AM) and, in addition to area 
under the glucose concentration-time curve (AUC), were 
compared between the MiniMed Paradigm Veo and MiniMed 
640G systems using a Wilcoxon signed-rank analysis. 
Glycemic variability between manual and automatic re-
sumptions, as measured by a coefficient of variability (CV, 
standard deviation/mean), was calculated using the last SG 
value collected from each resumption and analyzed using a 
paired t-test. To characterize the postsuspend behavior of SG 
values, ''recovery time'' was defined as the interval from 
pump suspend to the start of the first 20-min interval with SG 
values 68-119 mg/dL (3.8-6.6 mmol/L). 
For additional glycemic comparisons between the ''suspend 
before low'' and the ''suspend on low'' features, we identified 
851 people who switched from the MiniMed Paradigm Veo 
system to the MiniMed 640G system and uploaded  ‡7 days of 
data from both systems between February 28, 2010, and 
September 29, 2015. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The MiniMed 640G ''suspend before low'' feature was 
used on 83% of the user-days, ''suspend on low'' on 11% of </p>

<p>Table 1. Sensor-Augmented Pump System Features </p>

<p>Sensor-augmented pump system </p>

<p>MiniMed Paradigm Veo 
MiniMed 530G 
MiniMed 640G </p>

<p>Suspend on low </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Yes (LGS) 
Yes (TS) 
Yes (LGS) 
Suspend before low 
No 
No 
Yes 
Suspend threshold range 
40-110 mg/dL 
(2.2-6.1 mmol/L) </p>

<p>60-90 mg/dL 
(3.3-5.0 mmol/L) </p>

<p>50-90 mg/dL 
(2.8-5.0 mmol/L) 
Auto-resume based on SG 
No 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Maximum suspension 
duration, hours </p>

<p>2 
2 
2 </p>

<p>Minimum interval between 
suspension, hours </p>

<p>4 
4 
4 </p>

<p>a The difference between LGS and TS is the suspend threshold range. 
b Automatic resumption can occur sooner if, at 30 min since the start of pump suspension, the SG value is above the low limit and 
predicted to remain above the low limit within 30 min. 
LGS, Low Glucose Suspend; SG, sensor glucose; TS, Threshold Suspend. </p>

<p> 
ZHONG ET AL. </p>

<p>FIG. 1. The distribution of manual and automatic pump resumption events across bins of suspend duration time (min) is 
shown for MiniMed 640G (A), MiniMed 530G (B), and MiniMed Paradigm Veo (C) systems. For all three, a majority of 
pump resumption events were triggered manually within the first 15 min of pump suspension. </p>



<p>the user-days, and neither suspend feature on 6% of the user-
days. More than 99% of all users used one or both suspend 
features at least once; most (59%) used ''suspend before 
low'' exclusively. Among all SG values from MiniMed 640G 
users when ''suspend before low'' was enabled, 0.39% were 
in the £50 mg/dL range, 2.11% were in the 50-70 mg/dL 
range, 63.53% were in the 70-180 mg/dL range, 30.42% 
were in the 180-300 mg/dL range, and 3.55% were in the 
&gt;300 mg/dL range. In comparison, the ''suspend on low'' 
feature was used on 72% of the MiniMed Paradigm Veo and 
82% of MiniMed 530G user-days. Among all SG values from 
MiniMed Paradigm Veo users, when ''suspend on low'' was 
enabled, 1.0% were in the £50 mg/dL range, 4.1% were in the 
50-70 mg/dL range, 61.2% were in the 70-180 mg/dL range, 
29.6% were in the 180-300 mg/dL range, and 4.1% were in the 
&gt;300 mg/dL range. Among all SG values from MiniMed 530G 
users, when ''suspend on low'' was enabled, 0.7% were in the 
£50 mg/dL range, 3.4% were in the 50-70 mg/dL range, 60.6% 
were in the 70-180 mg/dL range, 30.7% were in the 180-
300 mg/dL range, and 4.6% were in the &gt;300 mg/dL range. 
Basal insulin delivery was automatically suspended as a 
result of enabled MiniMed 640G ''suspend before low'' on 
693,626 occasions, at an average rate of 2.9 per user-day. 
Over half of the suspend events (55%, 381,803) ended due to 
''auto-resume'' based on SG, 11.5% (79,525) due to the 2-h 
''auto-resume,'' and the remainder due to manual resumption 
(33.5%, 232,298). The mean duration of MiniMed 640G 
''auto-resume'' based on SG events was 58 -25 min and that 
of the manually resumed events was 33 -23 min. SG values 
associated with automatically resumed events showed less </p>

<p>glycemic variability than those associated with manually 
resumed events, as measured by the coefficient of variation 
(CV) (P &lt; 0.001, 0.18 vs. 0.24, respectively), and faster re-
covery times (P &lt; 0.001, 29.4 vs. 35.1 min, respectively). 
The distribution of pump suspension events across duration 
for each system is shown in Figure 1. About one-third of 
manually resumed events for the MiniMed 640G system 
(Fig. 1A) and more than half for the MiniMed 530G (Fig. 1B) 
and MiniMed Paradigm Veo (Fig. 1C) systems occurred 
within the first 15 min of suspension. The distribution in au-
tomatically resumed events for the MiniMed 640G system was 
partly bimodal. Specifically, many ''auto resume'' events 
occurred soon after the minimum 30-min interval (inherent to 
MiniMed 640G technology) and continued, although at a de-
creased percent, until the maximum suspend duration of 
2 hours. 
Figure 2 shows the number and percent of ''suspend be-
fore low'' events during the day and night associated with 
the set low limit SG value (Mean -SD = 66.7 -9.9 mg/dL 
[3.7 -0.5 mmol/L]). Overall, 75% (353,748 [Day] + 166,470 
[Night] = 520,218) of the 693,626 predicted hypoglycemic 
events were not followed by an SG value at or below the 
low limit. Most suspend events occurred during the daytime 
hours, and the hypoglycemia prevention rate was slightly 
higher for suspend events occurring at night. 
The benefits of automated pump suspension with predictive 
versus reactive pump suspension features during nocturnal 
hypoglycemia are shown in Table 2. The duration of hypo-
glycemia between 8:00 PM and 8:00 AM was calculated for 
users of the MiniMed Paradigm Veo, MiniMed 530G, and </p>

<p>Table 2. Duration of Nighttime Hypoglycemia </p>

<p>MiniMed Paradigm Veo 
MiniMed 530G 
MiniMed 640G </p>

<p>Setting </p>

<p>Suspend on 
low OFF </p>

<p>Suspend on 
low ON </p>

<p>Suspend on 
low OFF </p>

<p>Suspend on 
low ON </p>

<p>Suspend before 
low OFF </p>

<p>Suspend before 
low ON </p>

<p>Hypoglycemia, 
hours/night, Mean -SD </p>

<p>0.4 -0.8 
0.2 -0.5 
0.4 -1.0 
0.2 -0.4 
0.4 -1.0 
0.1 -0.3 
P &lt; 0.001 
P &lt; 0.001 
P &lt; 0.001 
Users, N 
24,715 
30,785 
13,166 
34,402 
1230 
4480 </p>

<p>Night time = 8:00 PM-8:00 AM. Hypoglycemia was defined as £70 mg/dL (3.9 mmol/L). </p>

<p>FIG. 2. The MiniMed 640G-enabled ''suspend before low'' feature resulted in the avoidance of 73.9% of predicted 
hypoglycemic events during the day and 77.4% of predicted hypoglycemic events during the night (white bars). The 
proportion of events that reached or fell below the preset limit (black bars) was 26.1% and 22.6%, respectively. </p>

<p> 
ZHONG ET AL. </p>

<p>MiniMed 640G systems on nights when the pumps' suspend 
features were not in use and compared to nights when they 
were in use. Statistically significant reductions were seen when 
either pump suspension feature was used (P &lt; 0.001), but 
the reductions associated with the predictive feature of the 
MiniMed 640G system were greater. 
The ''suspend before low'' and ''suspend on low'' pump 
suspension features are compared in Figure 3, in which SG 
trajectories surrounding 59,823 ''suspend before low'' events 
of any duration were compared with trajectories surrounding 
603,592 ''suspend on low'' events of any duration. In all 
cases, the low limit was set to 60 mg/dL. At the outset, the 
median SG value for ''suspend on low'' events was 58 mg/ 
dL, whereas the median value at the time the ''suspend before 
low'' events began was 92 mg/dL. For both types of suspend 
events, the median SG value stabilized to around 144 mg/dL 
by 4 hours. SG values associated with ''suspend before </p>

<p>low'' events followed a more predictable trajectory during 
the recovery phase, as indicated by the narrower inter-
quartile range. 
A separate analysis of data from 851 users who switched 
from the MiniMed Paradigm Veo system to the MiniMed 
640G system is presented in Table 3. After switching, users 
experienced less time in hypoglycemia and their hypogly-
cemic exposure was significantly less in duration and se-
verity as measured by excursions and the AUC. There was 
also a significant improvement in severe hyperglycemic 
parameters after switching to the 640G system. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Hypoglycemia remains an important concern for people 
with diabetes. The rate of hypoglycemia, whether severe or 
nonsevere, during the day or at night, may be underestimated </p>

<p>FIG. 3. SG trajectories associated with enabled event start time (min) for ''suspend before low'' and ''suspend on low'' 
features. The thick solid line shows median SG values for 59,823 MiniMed 640G ''suspend before low'' events of any 
duration for which the low limit was set to 60 mg/dL. The thick dashed line shows median SG values for 603,592 MiniMed 
Paradigm Veo ''suspend on low'' events of any duration for which the low limit was set to 60 mg/dL. Thin solid and dashed 
lines show the 25th and 75th percentile values. SG, sensor glucose. </p>

<p>Table 3. Glycemic Parameters Associated with Suspend on Low and Suspend Before Low </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>Suspend on Low 
Suspend before Low </p>

<p>P 
Median 
25th 
75th 
Median 
25th 
75th </p>

<p>Hypoglycemia 
Excursions per day, n 
0.949 
0.606 
1.508 
0.738 
0.398 
1.214 
&lt;0.001 
Duration, min/day 
25.796 
14.731 
46.520 
15.721 
7.831 
28.889 
&lt;0.001 
AUC, mg/dL · day 
0.393 
0.271 
0.536 
0.280 
0.197 
0.396 
&lt;0.001 
Severe Hyperglycemia 
Excursions per day, n 
0.420 
0.185 
0.752 
0.333 
0.130 
0.723 
&lt;0.001 
Duration, min/day 
15.975 
6.410 
32.186 
12.778 
4.163 
31.820 
&lt;0.001 
AUC, mg/dL · day 
2.208 
1.547 
3.069 
1.737 
1.050 
2.589 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Hypoglycemia was defined as SG £70 mg/dL (3.9 mmol/L). Severe Hyperglycemia was defined as SG  ‡300 mg/dL (16.7 mmol/L). The 
''suspend on low'' comprised data from the 851 MiniMed Paradigm Veo users who transitioned to MiniMed 640G. 
AUC, area under the glucose concentration-time curve. </p>

<p>EFFECTIVENESS OF 640G SENSOR-AUGMENTED INSULIN PUMP </p>

<p>
in clinical trial settings, 
11 stressing the need for retrospective 
real-world analyses such as this one. In 2015, Dexcom re-
ported data from 300 users of their Platinum G4 
Ò CGM 
system, 
12 in which users experienced a mean of 1.2 -1.9 
(Mean -SD) hours per day with sensor readings £70 mg/dL, 
half of which were at night. This rate is in agreement with 
data from users of Medtronic CGM systems on nights when 
system suspend functions were not used. As shown in 
Table 2, the duration of nocturnal hypoglycemia was re-
duced by *50% with use of the MiniMed Paradigm Veo 
and MiniMed 530G ''suspend on low'' features, and was 
reduced by *75% with use of the MiniMed 640G ''sus-
pend before low'' feature. This reduction in hypogly-
cemia exposure (i.e., number of events) attributable to 
the predictive insulin pump suspension technology in the 
MiniMed 640G system agrees with that reported in a recent 
study of children and adolescents that found slight eleva-
tions in overnight mean glucose levels and no increase in 
morning blood ketosis on nights that pump suspensions 
occurred. </p>

<p>13   The hypoglycemia prevention attributable to the MiniMed 
640G system was also measured in a recent Predictive Low 
Glucose Management (PLGM) pivotal study, 
14 in which 
standardized increases in basal insulin delivery were used to 
trigger insulin pump suspension. A 60% reduction in hypo-
glycemia was reported based on 68 automatic pump-
suspension events, among which the hypoglycemic criterion 
(two or more reference plasma glucose levels of &lt;65 mg/dL) 
did not occur in 41 cases. This is less than the 75% prevention 
rate reported here and the 83% prevention rate reported in a 
PLGM user evaluation study. 
8 The smaller reduction ob-
served in the pivotal study was likely due to the basal insulin 
delivery escalation protocol known to result in hypoglycemia 
93% of the time, 
15 relative to the day-to-day environment 
settings of the later studies. 
In the present study data, the MiniMed 640G algorithm 
governing automatic resumption of insulin delivery based on 
SG appeared to work well and resumed insulin delivery 
primarily within 30-45 min after pump suspension. While 
more than half of manually resumed events occurred within 
the first 15 min after pump suspension for the MiniMed 
Paradigm Veo or MiniMed 530G systems, only one-third 
occurred within the same period for MiniMed 640G. It is not 
known what user characteristics or physiologic and metabolic 
factors may have influenced the different extent of manual 
resumption between the systems. The ''auto resume'' based 
on SG feature, not available in MiniMed Paradigm Veo or 
MiniMed 530G systems, appeared to allow a more immediate 
real-time solution for maintaining target glucose levels. 
Specifically, there was a faster hypoglycemia recovery and 
less glycemic variability (as measured by the CV of SG 
values), compared to users who restart the pump manually. 
This study benefits from the large number of users and 
user-days available for analyses, although data from system 
users who did not upload to <rs type="software">CareLink</rs> software were un-
available. A limitation of the study is that the MiniMed 
640G ''suspend on low'' versus MiniMed 640G ''suspend 
before low'' data could not be analyzed, due to an insuffi-
cient number of events during use of the former feature. The 
lack of detailed user demographic information is another 
limitation, as is a lack of detailed information regarding 
user-system interface (e.g., calibrations, sensor changes, </p>

<p>and CareLink software upload frequency), physician-to-
user instructions, and dietary and exercise behaviors. The 
false-positive rate of predictive pump suspensions, as well 
as sensor accuracy, could not be assessed because of the 
study's retrospective nature. The effect of sensor life on the 
rate of pump suspension events was also not possible to 
assess. Within-user comparisons of MiniMed Paradigm Veo 
and MiniMed 640G system use may have been influenced 
by the unidirectional nature of the MiniMed Paradigm Veo 
system use preceding MiniMed 640G system use, and by 
uncharacterized or unknown behaviors related to becoming 
familiar with a new pump system. 
Several challenges remain on the path to a fully closed-loop 
insulin delivery system. Although no such systems are com-
mercially available, a recent Hybrid-Closed Loop (HCL) piv-
otal trial, completed in April 2016 (NCT02463097), allowed 
subjects to wear investigational systems in an unsupervised 
outpatient setting for an extended period of time (i.e., 3 months). 
In other outpatient studies, HCL systems outperformed sensor-
augmented pumps in terms of glucose control, time in hypo-
glycemia, and glycated hemoglobin levels. </p>

<p>16,17   The MiniMed 640G system is the first commercially 
available system to offer predictive suspension and automatic 
resumption, based on SG, of basal insulin delivery. The 
benefits attributable to these features were previously re-
ported in the context of a user evaluation study. 
8 Analysis of 
real-world usage patterns of MiniMed 640G use and the 
predictive pump suspension feature reported here supports 
earlier results and establishes the validity of this integrative 
technology for routine use in insulin-requiring individuals 
with diabetes. </p>

<p>Author Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>A.Z., C.M., P.A., J.B.W., T.L.C., and F.R.K. are or 
were employees of Medtronic during development of 
this manuscript. P.C. has received research support from 
Medtronic. </p>

<p>Product Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>The MiniMed 530G system is available for use only in the 
U.S. The MiniMed Paradigm Veo and MiniMed 640G sys-
tems are not commercially available for use in the U.S. </p>



<p>Address correspondence to: 
Alex Zhong, MS 
Medtronic 
18000 Devonshire Street 
Northridge, CA 91325 </p>

<p>E-mail: alex.zhong@medtronic.com </p>

<p>EFFECTIVENESS OF 640G SENSOR-AUGMENTED INSULIN PUMP </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>