<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5435264" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background: The Union-Bloomberg Initiative tobacco </p>

<p>control projects were implemented in Himachal 
Pradesh (a hilly state in North India) from 2007 to 
2014. The project focused on the establishment of an 
administrative framework; increasing the capacity of 
stakeholders; enforcement of legislation; coalition and 
networking with multiple stakeholders; awareness 
generation with focus on earned media and monitoring 
and evaluation with policy-focussed research. This 
study aimed to systematically analyse all earned print 
news items related to the projects. </p>

<p>Methods: In this cross-sectional descriptive study, </p>

<p>quantitative content analysis of earned print news 
items was carried out using predetermined codes 
related to areas of tobacco control policies. We also 
carried out a cost description of the hypothetical value 
of this earned media. The area of the news item in cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>was multiplied by the average rate of space for the paid 
news item in that particular newspaper. </p>

<p>Results: There were 6348 news items: the numbers </p>

<p>steadily increased with time. Focus on Monitoring 
tobacco use, Protecting people from tobacco smoke, 
Offering help to quit, Warning about dangers of 
tobacco, Enforcing a ban on tobacco advertising and 
promotion, Raising tax on tobacco products was seen 
in 24, 17, 9, 23, 22 and 3% of news items, 
respectively. Press releases were highest at 44% and 
report by correspondents at 24%. Further, 55, 23 and 
21% news items focused on smoking, smokeless 
and both forms of tobacco use, respectively. Sixty-six 
per cent and 34% news items, respectively, were 
focused on youth and women. The news items had a 
hypothetical value of US$1503 628.3, which was three 
times more than the funds spent on all project 
activities. </p>

<p>communicable diseases. 
1 The WHO intro-
duced Monitoring tobacco use, Protecting 
people from tobacco smoke, Offering help 
to quit, Warning about dangers of tobacco, 
Enforcing a ban on tobacco advertising and 
promotion, Raising tax on tobacco products 
measures (MPOWER) to assist in country-
level implementation of effective interven-
tions to reduce the demand for tobacco, con-
tained in the WHO's Framework Convention 
on Tobacco Control (WHO FCTC). </p>

<p>2   India has an estimated 275 million tobacco 
users, which includes 111 million smokers. 
India was the seventh country in the world to 
ratify WHO FCTC in February 2004. To </p>

<p>Key questions </p>

<p>What is already known about this topic? </p>

<p>▸ Earned media is one of the strategies when there 
is limited funding available for effective imple-
mentation of Framework Convention on Tobacco 
Control/Monitoring Tobacco Use, Protecting 
People From Tobacco Smoke, Offering Help To 
Quit, Warning About Dangers Of Tobacco, 
Enforcing A Ban On Tobacco Advertising And 
Promotion, Raising Tax On Tobacco Products 
policies. 
▸ There is limited evidence of the role of earned 
media in tobacco control, mostly from the west. </p>

<p>What are the new findings? </p>

<p>▸ This is the first study to systematically analyse 
all earned print news items associated with a 
tobacco control project in a state in North India. 
▸ The project was able to strategically use earned 
media to promote tobacco control policies: 
hypothetical costs of earned media were more 
than the project itself. </p>

<p>Recommendations for policy </p>

<p>▸ Earned media should be used as a strategy for 
an aware generation in tobacco control interven-
tions/projects. 
▸ Earned media saves a significant amount of 
costs. </p>

<p>Sharma R, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2017;2:e000208. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000208 </p>



<p>Original research </p>

<p>effectively control tobacco use in the country, the 
Government of India enacted the comprehensive 
tobacco control legislation, namely 'The Cigarettes and 
Other Tobacco Products (Prohibition of Advertisement 
and Regulation of Trade and Commerce, Production, 
Supply and Distribution) Act, 2003'. 
3 4 India also 
launched the National Tobacco Control Programme in 
2007 with mass media as an important component. </p>

<p>5   The role of mass media has been critical to the evolu-
tion of effective tobacco control interventions in the 
21st century. 
6 While paid mass media campaigns can be 
expensive and unaffordable, they have been shown to 
be effective in a wide range of studies in tobacco 
control. </p>

<p>7-9   Earned media is one of the strategies under article 12 
of FCTC guidelines on education, communication, train-
ing and public awareness. 
10 Earned media is defined as 
any publicity which has not been paid and that is owned 
and created by a third party. 
11 Traditionally, the term 
'earned media' has been used when publicity is gener-
ated through public relations invested in targeting influ-
encers to increase awareness about a brand, online and/ 
or offline. 
11 Earned media has not been used much in 
tobacco control and most of the evidence is from the 
west, mostly dealing with increasing the demand for tele-
phone or web-based quit lines </p>

<p>7 12-14   The International Union Against Tuberculosis and 
Lung Disease (The Union) with support from the 
Bloomberg Initiative To Reduce Tobacco Use (BI) sup-
ported tobacco control initiatives in a state in North 
India through a civil society partner. In close collabor-
ation with the National Tobacco Control Programme at 
state and district levels, the project focussed on establish-
ment of a politico-administrative and institutional frame-
work; increasing capacity of stakeholders; enforcement 
of legislation; coalition and networking with multiple sta-
keholders; awareness generation and monitoring and 
evaluation with policy-focused research. Since there was 
no funding for public education and awareness gener-
ation including paid media, earned media in the form 
of print news items was used as a strategy for awareness 
generation on harms of tobacco, developing institutional 
framework, ensuring multistakeholder engagement, 
highlighting violations and strengthening enforcement 
of legislation. 
There was anecdotal evidence that earned print media 
was instrumental in generating an excellent support for 
project implementation and making inroads and pene-
tration into semiurban and rural areas of this difficult 
terrain state. Considering the extent of the project, a sys-
tematic analysis of earned media provides us an oppor-
tunity to understand how we used earned media and 
guide the use of the same in future tobacco control pro-
jects. Therefore, we aimed to systematically analyse the 
trend, types of news items and hypothetical costs saved 
through all earned print news items in the state during 
the project. Specific objectives were to describe the earned 
print news items based on (1) year-wise trend; (2) type </p>

<p>of news item: print release, report by correspondence, a 
feature article, a column or an editorial; (3) MPOWER 
focus area: Monitor, Protect, Offer, Warn, Enforce, Raise 
taxes; (4) focus area of tobacco control institutional 
infrastructure and framework as required under India's 
tobacco control programme; (5) intent of news item: 
whether antitobacco or protobacco and (6) hypothetical 
costs saved as a result of using earned media. </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METHODS 
Study design and study period 
This was a cross-sectional descriptive study of all earned 
print news items related to The Union-BI tobacco 
control project activities which appeared in newspapers 
across Himachal Pradesh (India) from Jul 2007 to Dec 
2014. </p>

<p>Setting 
General setting: Himachal Pradesh is a state in North 
India with a predominantly hilly terrain. It is flanked by 
Uttarakhand in the southeast, Haryana in the south, 
Punjab in the southwest and Jammu and Kashmir in the 
north. 
15 It is administratively divided into 12 districts. 
According to the Global Adult Tobacco Survey India 
(2009), the prevalence of current tobacco use (any 
form) among adults is 21.2%: 38.5% among men and 
3.7% among women. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Study setting: The Union-BI tobacco control project in 
Himachal Pradesh was implemented between 2011 and 
2014 through a civil society partner Himachal Pradesh 
Voluntary Health Association (HPVHA). Between July 
2007 and March 2011, there was only technical support 
and very limited funding support (about US$10 000 in 
2010). An excellent collaboration between HPVHA and 
the State Department of Health and Family Welfare, 
Government of Himachal Pradesh was instrumental in 
implementing the project work plan with regular onsite 
and offsite technical support from The Union. </p>

<p>Data collection 
The project staff of HPVHA, the civil society partner of 
the project, did the data collection. A list of publicly 
available print newspapers in the state (national, state 
and local newspapers), with no language barrier, was 
prepared. It was updated from time to time as the study 
period was over 8 years. As and when the print news 
items related to project activities appeared, they were cut 
and stored. This was done by staff at the district level 
and state headquarters. We did not include online news 
items. </p>

<p>Data analysis 
For objectives 1-5, quantitative descriptive content ana-
lysis of the print news items was done. 
6 16 Each print 
news item was given a unique serial number. The 
themes/codes were predetermined and the coders were 
asked to classify the print news item under the following </p>



<p>Sharma R, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2017;2:e000208. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000208 </p>

<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>themes/codes: MPOWER focus area (monitor, protect, 
offer, warn, enforce, raise taxes); type of news item 
( press release, correspondence, feature articles, column, 
editorial, others); institutional system of tobacco control 
under focus (sensitisation/advocacy, awareness gener-
ation/information education and communication, legis-
lation and enforcement, stakeholder engagement and 
capacity building of stakeholders); intent of news item 
(anti or protobacco); type of tobacco and age/gender 
focus. These predetermined codes were identified after 
brainstorming among the investigators. We also looked 
for tobacco industry (TI) interference (TII) and related 
issues like illicit trade and corporate social responsibil-
ities (CSR). We also collected information on year of 
publication; name and language of newspaper. Coding 
was done by the same staff that collected the print news 
item. They received training for coding from the union 
technical advisor (RJS). The coding process was ran-
domly supervised (10% of print news items) by the 
supervisors at the state headquarters. 
For objective 6, a cost description was undertaken to 
find out the hypothetical value of this earned print 
media. The area of the news item in cm 
2 was multi-
plied by the average rate of space per cm 
2 for a paid 
news item in that particular newspaper during the 
year 2007 to 2014 (obtained in Indian rupee (INR) 
from the offices of the newspapers). The hypothetical 
value of earned print media in INR was converted to 
US$ at the average monthly value of US$ between 
2008 and 2014 as the conversion factor. (US$1=INR 
51.84). 
Frequency and proportion was used to summarise the 
analytic outputs using <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">MS</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Excel</rs>. </p>

<p>Ethics 
The need for ethics review for this study was waived off 
by the Ethics Advisory Group of The Union. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
A total of 26 newspapers had news items related to the 
project: 17 were in Hindi and nine in English. A total 
of 6348 news items were published. Characteristics of 
these news items have been summarised in table 1. In 
2007-2008, there were only 51 items; it increased 
during 2010-2011 (1178 news items); and continuous 
improvement was seen until 2014 with 1687 news items 
(figure 1). 
Of the 6348 news items, 3816 (60%) were press 
releases and 1716 (27%) were correspondence. In terms 
of the MPOWER strategy, the media focused on all 
policy provisions: 64, 45, 22, 56, 50 and 6%, respectively 
(there was some overlap of focus areas). Around 25% 
and 34% of media focus, respectively, was on sensitisa-
tion and advocacy of politico-administrative leadership 
and awareness generation of general public about the 
tobacco epidemic and need for strengthening and 
scaling up for prioritisation of tobacco control in the </p>

<p>state. Further, 50, 40 and 39% news items focused on 
enforcement of tobacco control laws, multistakeholder 
engagement and capacity building, respectively (there 
was an overlap of categories). Further analysis revealed 
that 6232 (98%) had an antitobacco theme, 4063 (64%) 
dealt with smoking, 3529 (56%) news items focused on 
children/youth and 1642 (26%) focused on women. 
(Table 1) Around 1% of news items focused on TII, </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of earned media (print news items) 
related to The Union-Bloomberg Initiative tobacco control 
project activities which appeared in newspapers across 
Himachal Pradesh, India, from Jul 2007 to Dec 2014 </p>

<p>Variable 
Number Percentage 
Total 
6348 
100 </p>

<p>Type of news item </p>

<p>Press release 
3817 
60 </p>

<p>Correspondence 
1716 
27 </p>

<p>Feature article 
239 
4 </p>

<p>A column 
103 
2 </p>

<p>Editorial/op-ed* 
65 
1 </p>

<p>Others 
408 
6 </p>

<p>MPOWER focus area </p>

<p>Monitor 
4033 
64 </p>

<p>Protect 
2867 
45 </p>

<p>Offer 
1386 
22 </p>

<p>Warn 
3564 
56 </p>

<p>Enforce 
3426 
54 </p>

<p>Raise 
396 
6 </p>

<p>Focus on institutional system for tobacco control </p>

<p>Sensitisation/advocacy of 
politico-administrative leadership </p>

<p>1599 
25 </p>

<p>IEC/awareness generation 
2169 
34 </p>

<p>Legislation mechanism and 
enforcement </p>

<p>3144 
50 </p>

<p>Stakeholders' engagements 
2542 
40 </p>

<p>Capacity building of stakeholders 2475 
39 </p>

<p>Intent of the news item </p>

<p>Antitobacco 
6232 
98 </p>

<p>Protobacco 
130 
2 </p>

<p>Type of tobacco </p>

<p>Smoking 
4063 
64 </p>

<p>Smoke less 
479 
8 </p>

<p>Both 
1862 
28 </p>

<p>Age/gender focus </p>

<p>Children/youth 
3529 
56 </p>

<p>Women 
1642 
26 </p>

<p>*Opposite editorial. 
IEC, information education and communication; MPOWER, 
Monitoring Tobacco Use, Protecting People From Tobacco Smoke, 
Offering Help To Quit, Warning About Dangers Of Tobacco, 
Enforcing A Ban On Tobacco Advertising And Promotion, Raising 
Tax On Tobacco Products. </p>

<p>Sharma R, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2017;2:e000208. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000208 </p>



<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>13% focused on illicit trade of tobacco products and a 
few on CSR activities undertaken by TI (data not 
shown). Finally, 11% of the coverage also focused on the </p>

<p>fragile and suboptimal approach of the government for 
tobacco control in the state (data not shown). 
All the news items had a hypothetical cost of US 
$1503 628.3 (table 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
This is the first study worldwide to systematically analyse 
all earned print media associated with a tobacco control 
project, and the way in which the scale of this earned 
print media was described in the form of hypothetical 
costs saved is unique. Before this, a purposive sample of 
online earned media was studied, 
14 including the effect 
of earned media in relation to activities specific to 
tobacco cessation. 
7 12 13 We demonstrated how we used 
earned media strategically to further our cause of 
tobacco control in the state. The hypothetical value of 
earned print media (US$1503 628.3) was very significant 
(more than three times higher) when compared with 
the total expenditure of the project funded by The 
Union under the BI grants programme (≈US$470 000). </p>

<p>Figure 1 Earned media print news items related to The 
Union-Bloomberg Initiative tobacco control project activities 
which appeared in newspapers across Himachal Pradesh, 
India, year wise, from Jul 2007 to Dec 2014. </p>

<p>Table 2 Cost description of earned media (print news items) related to The Union-Bloomberg Initiative tobacco control project 
activities which appeared in newspapers across Himachal Pradesh, India, from Jul 2007 to Dec 2014 </p>

<p>Name of newspapers 
Language 
Total area in cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Rate @ INR/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Amount (INR) 
Amount (US$)* </p>

<p>Ajit Samachar 
Hindi 
4391.32 
35 
153696.2 
2964.8 </p>

<p>Amar Ujala 
Hindi 
49760.64 
333 
16570293.1 
319643.0 </p>

<p>Apka Faisla 
Hindi 
12732.78 
55 
700302.9 
13508.9 </p>

<p>Chamba Express 
Hindi 
576 
20 
11520.0 
222.2 </p>

<p>Business 
English 
356.17 
85 
30274.5 
584.0 </p>

<p>Daily Post 
English 
387.02 
75 
29026.5 
559.9 </p>

<p>Dainik Bhaskar 
Hindi 
18 259 
125 
2282375.0 
44027.3 </p>

<p>Dainik Jagaran 
Hindi 
50926.65 
504 
25667031.6 
495120.2 </p>

<p>Dainik Tribune 
Hindi 
566.55 
95 
53822.3 
1038.2 </p>

<p>Dainik Savera 
Hindi 
1110 
20 
22200.0 
428.2 </p>

<p>Divya Himachal 
Hindi 
47748.75 
90 
4297387.5 
82897.1 </p>

<p>Encounter News 
Hindi 
714 
23 
16422.0 
316.8 </p>

<p>Himachal Dastak 
Hindi 
22596.66 
45 
1016849.7 
19615.2 </p>

<p>Himachal Plus 
English 
1404.07 
225 
315915.8 
6094.1 </p>

<p>Hindustan Times 
English 
4349.17 
787.5 
3424971.4 
66068.1 </p>

<p>Indian Express 
English 
307.55 
500 
153775.0 
2966.3 </p>

<p>Jansatta 
Hindi 
96 
240 
23040.0 
444.4 </p>

<p>Pahli Khabar 
Hindi 
103.2 
55 
5676.0 
109.5 </p>

<p>Panjab Kesari 
Hindi 
85352.56 
250 
21338140.0 
411615.4 </p>

<p>Satya Swadesh 
Hindi 
756 
23 
17388.0 
335.4 </p>

<p>Readers Digest 
English 
195.5 
30 
5865.0 
113.1 </p>

<p>The Pioneer 
English 
336 
35 
11760.0 
226.9 </p>

<p>The Tribune 
English 
3528.09 
125 
441011.3 
8507.2 </p>

<p>Times of India 
English 
1865.3 
671 
1251616.3 
24143.8 </p>

<p>Himjan Awaz 
Hindi 
3402 
30 
102060.0 
1968.8 </p>

<p>Dainik Nayay Setu 
Hindi 
162 
35 
5670.0 
109.4 
Total 
311982.98 
77948089.9 
1503628.3 </p>

<p>*US$1=INR 51.84 (average monthly value of US$ between 2008 and 2014. 
INR, Indian rupee. </p>



<p>Sharma R, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2017;2:e000208. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000208 </p>

<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>The study results are representative as all the news 
items were studied with no purposive or random sam-
pling. We used STrengthening the Reporting of 
OBservational studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) 
guidelines for conduct and dissemination of study find-
ings. 
17 There were some limitations of this study. Each 
print news item was coded by one coder due to resource 
constraints. The role of subjectivity, despite 10% being 
rechecked, cannot be ruled out. It would be interesting 
to consider who was likely to be reading these print 
news items including the socio-demographic character-
istics of readership. However, this literature is not avail-
able and was also beyond the scope of this study. 
Evidence in tobacco control is limited regarding the 
impact of earned print media coverage on behaviour, 
and therefore we have to be careful in assuming that 
newspaper coverage will have an impact on behaviour. 
During 2007-08, there were no regular project activ-
ities. Limited print news items were due to occasional 
activities done by HPVHA (figure 1). After that, the 
increase in news items every year demonstrated the con-
tinued engagement with the print media, increase in 
activities under the project, increase in interest by news-
papers and increased multistakeholder engagement with 
time. Press release was the most common type of news 
item. This showed that the project was proactive in 
media involvement for greater visibility. This was done 
with support from the public relations officer of the gov-
ernment, wherever possible, which added credibility to 
the project activities. Around one-third of the items were 
correspondence; this meant that the newspaper corre-
spondents and reporters were interested to cover the 
news and the same interest was shown by the editorial 
board of the newspaper. The high proportion of news 
items dealing with the 'M' component of MPOWER 
could be explained by the fact that a series of compli-
ance assessment studies were conducted in the state and 
widely disseminated. 
18 19 The focus was minimum on 'R' 
(6%), perhaps because tobacco taxes were mainly the 
mandate of the central government with a small compo-
nent of value added tax which may be levied by the state 
government. A majority of news items were against 
tobacco; this indicated that proper briefing of the media 
with all scientific evidences, best practices and tobacco 
industry tactics was done to tilt media support in favour 
of tobacco control. As far as type of tobacco use was con-
cerned, around two-thirds of the news items highlighted 
smoking forms of tobacco use, which was also the most 
commonly used tobacco in the state as per the Global 
Adult Tobacco Survey 2009. </p>

<p>3   There was all-round coverage of issues related to institu-
tional systems for tobacco control. (Table 1) The focus 
on establishing an institutional system is very important 
to ensure that tobacco control is sustainable and inte-
grated with multistakeholder engagement. Further, even 
in the early phase of tobacco control in the state, TII, 
illicit trade of tobacco products and CSR activities by </p>

<p>tobacco industry picked up and were highlighted by the 
media. A good number of news items also highlighted a 
fragmented and suboptimal approach of the state govern-
ment which helped in initiating corrective actions by the 
government. The project was sensitive to the issue of 
tobacco use among youth and women as suggested by the 
sufficient focus on child/youth and women (Table 1). 
This earned print media revolution in the state 
reduced the financial burden in implementing various 
project objectives and activities including enforcement 
of the legislation from 2008 to 2014. On the other hand, 
there was a huge rupee (dollar) gain on the investments 
for which the authors made a marathon effort to get a 
rough hypothetical value. 
There is limited evidence of the role of earned media 
in tobacco control; 
7 12-14 however, earned media com-
mands an important place in marketing, business and 
other fields. 
20 21 It is often neglected because it is the 
one communication tool that requires working closely 
with the media and requires a good rapport, confidence 
building and tangible relationships with journalists, and 
raising legitimate concern with evidence-based and 
truthful information. 
22 The same principles were fol-
lowed by the project. Though paid media has been 
shown to be effective in tobacco control, the advantage 
of earned media lies in it being absolutely 'free' and 
getting something akin to a 'third party' testimonial. </p>

<p>11 17   There are some risks and challenges in the public 
health community using earned media. There is lack of 
control and difficulty in measuring effectiveness and it 
takes time, effort and requires investment in internal 
and external media content generation. There are also 
concerns about negative comments, misdirecting and 
reshaping of the message. Further, social media tools are 
already there and if earned media becomes more of a 
focus, in times to come there would be a need for con-
sensus among the public health community on collec-
tion and assessment of data through social media 
tools. </p>

<p>14   During the course of the project, the state-level moni-
toring committee and district-level monitoring commit-
tees were constituted in all 12 districts of the state, with 
appointment of nodal officers. Enforcement teams/task 
forces were established at the state, district and subdis-
trict levels. Compliance with smoke-free laws ranged 
from 20% to 30% at baseline, which increased to 
around 85%. Advertisement and promotion of tobacco 
products decreased in all the districts of the state and 
overall compliance rates increased from 24 to 82%. The 
state of Himachal Pradesh was declared smoke free in 
July 2013 and progressed to become fully compliant 
with the country's tobacco control legislation along with 
advancing other provisions of the MPOWER policy 
package. During this process, the project strategically 
used earned media. However, this being a descriptive 
study, the exact effect of earned print media on compli-
ance cannot be ascertained. </p>

<p>Sharma R, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2017;2:e000208. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000208 </p>



<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>Conclusion 
The Union-BI tobacco control project, implemented in 
collaboration with HPVHA and the state government, 
was able to strategically use earned print media on a 
large scale to promote tobacco control policies. </p>

<p>Handling editor Seye Abimbola. </p>

<p>Twitter Follow Hemant Shewade @HShewade </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors sincerely acknowledge the print media in 
Himachal Pradesh for their tremendous support provided for control of this 
public health challenge in the state. We also acknowledge the project team of 
Himachal Pradesh Voluntary Health Association (HPVHA) led by Dr Narinder 
Sharma, Mr Shriniwas Joshi (honorary consultant for the project) and Mr 
Sudhanshu S Dogra for collecting, collating and analysing the print media 
coverage and Dr Gopal Chauhan and Dr Ravinder Kumar of the Department of 
Health and Family Welfare, Government of Himachal Pradesh for providing 
support and leadership to implement various tobacco control initiatives in the 
state. We acknowledge the Bloomberg Initiative to Reduce Tobacco Use for 
financial support to HPVHA for establishing, strengthening and sustaining 
tobacco control in the state. Finally, we thank the Department for International 
Development, UK, for funding the Global Operational Research Fellowship 
Programme at the International Union Against Tuberculosis and Lung Disease 
(The Union), Paris, France in which Dr Hemant Deepak Shewade works as a 
senior operational research fellow. </p>

<p>Contributors RS was the principal investigator; RJS was the senior author; 
RKB was the site investigator who collected and collated print news items; RS 
and RJS conceived and designed the protocol; RS, HDS, BG and RKB 
developed the tools and plan of analysis; RS prepared the first draft of the 
manuscript; HDS provided expert support to write and refine the manuscript; 
all authors were involved in critically reviewing the paper and giving approval 
for the final version to be published. </p>

<p>Funding The study was conducted as an operational research under the 
project conditions using project staff. Therefore, no separate budget was 
required. The submission of the paper to an open access journal was 
supported by funds from The International Union Against Tuberculosis and 
Lung Disease (The Union), South-East Asia Office. </p>

<p>Disclaimer The contents of this paper do not necessarily reflect the views of 
the NGO or The Union. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Sharma R, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2017;2:e000208. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000208 </p>

<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

</text></tei>