<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5244966" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The present study aimed to investigate the effects 
of 17β-estradiol and tamoxifen, an agonist and inhibitor of 
the estrogen receptor (ER), respectively, on the proliferation 
and apoptosis of gastric cancer cells, as well as the messenger 
(m)RNA expression levels of ER-α36. Nested reverse tran-
scription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) confirmed that 
ER-α36 was expressed in the BGC823, MKN45 and SGC7901 
human gastric cancer cell lines. Subsequently, the BGC823 cell 
line was stimulated with various concentrations of 17β-estradiol 
or tamoxifen for 24 or 48 h, and the proliferation, apoptosis 
and mRNA expression levels of ER-α36 were determined by 
water-soluble tetrazolium (WST)-1 assay, flow cytometry and 
RT-quantitative PCR, respectively. Epidemiological studies have suggested that gastric cancer is 
predominant in males, and that the ratio of morbidity of gastric 
cancer between male and female patients is 2:1-3:1 (1-3). The 
differences between the genders become negligible when 
female patients reach the menopause, and the morbidity associ-
ated with gastric cancer was reported to decrease in men who 
had been treated with estrogen for prostate carcinoma (1-3). 
These findings suggested that estrogen has a positive associa-
tion with gastric cancer, although the underlying reasons are 
unclear. Estrogen acts by binding to its ligand (4,5). Previous 
studies reported that estrogen receptors (ERs) were expressed 
in the tumors of estrogen-independent organs, including the 
stomach, which indicates that, in these organs, the occurrence 
and development of a tumor is associated with estrogen (6-10). 
ER-α36 is a novel ER va r iant identified by 
Professor Zhaoyi Wang (4), and whose molecular weight is 
35.7 kDa. The difference between ER-α36 and the traditional 
ER is that ER-α36 lacks intrinsic transcriptional activity due to </p>

<p>Effects of 17β-estradiol and tamoxifen on gastric cancer 
cell proliferation and apoptosis and ER-α36 expression </p>

<p>XUMING WANG </p>

<p>1,2* </p>

<p>, QIUYUE CHEN 
3* , XUAN HUANG 
1,2 , FENG ZOU 
1,2 , </p>

<p>ZHENGQI FU 
1,2 , YING CHEN 
1 , YAN LI 
1,2 , ZHAOYI WANG 
4 and LIJIANG LIU </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology and Pathophysiology, School of Medicine, Jianghan University; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Jiangda Pathology Institute, Jianghan University, Wuhan, Hubei 430056; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Guilin Medical University, Guilin, Guangxi 541004, P.R. China; 
4 Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Creighton University Medical School, Omaha, NE 68178, USA </p>

<p>Received May 14, 2015; Accepted July 15, 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/ol.2016.5424 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Professor Lijiang Liu, Department of </p>

<p>Pathology and Pathophysiology, School of Medicine, Jianghan 
University, Building J12, Room C202, 8 Sanjiaohu Road, Wuhan, 
Hubei 430056, P.R. China 
E-mail: liulijiang@163.com </p>

<p>* Contributed equally </p>

<p>Key words: estrogen receptor-α36, 17β-estradiol, tamoxifen, gastric </p>

<p>cancer cell growth </p>

<p>WANG et al: ER-α36 AND GASTRIC CANCER </p>



<p>the loss of the activation function (AF) 1 and AF2 domains (4,5). 
Previous studies have demonstrated that ER-α36 is located 
at the cytomembrane, where is involved in various biological 
processes, including cell differentiation, proliferation and 
apoptosis, by mediating rapid signal transduction (5). There 
are few reports regarding the function, mechanism and clinical 
significance of ER-α36 in gastric cancer, although previous 
studies suggested that ER-α36 has a central role in balancing 
the proliferation and apoptosis of gastric cancer cells (11-14). 
17β-estradiol, which is a type of agonist of the ER, has a critical 
role in physiological processes by binding to its ligand to mediate 
the expression of various genes (15-17). Conversely, tamoxifen, 
which is a non-steroidal triphenylethylene, affects the prolifera-
tion and apoptosis of cells by selectively competing with estrogen 
for the ER binding site, thus altering the expression levels of 
various cytokines (18-20). The present study aimed to investigate 
the effects of 17β-estradiol and tamoxifen on the proliferation and 
apoptosis of gastric cancer cell lines cultured in vitro. In addition, 
the role of ER-α36 in the proliferation and apoptosis of gastric 
cancer cells was evaluated by reverse transcription-quantitative 
polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR). </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Reagents. The BGC823 human gastric cancer and MCF-7 
human breast adenocarcinoma cell lines were purchased 
from the Institute of Basic Medical Sciences at the Chinese 
Academy of Medical Sciences (Beijing, China). The MKN45 
and SGC7901 human gastric cancer cell lines were donated 
by the Department of Immunology at Huazhong University of 
Science and Technology (Wuhan, China). Gibco 
® RPMI-1640 
medium and fetal bovine serum (FBS) were purchased from 
Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc., (Waltham, MA, USA). Trypsin 
was purchased from Sangon Biotech, Co., Ltd., (Shanghai, 
China) and glutamine was obtained from Ameresco, LLC 
(Solon, OH, USA). 17β-estradiol and tamoxifen were purchased 
from Sigma-Aldrich (Merck Millipore, Darmstadt, Germany). 
The water-soluble tetrazolium (WST)-1 kit was purchased from 
Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology (Haimen, China). The 
RT-PCR kit and PCR primers were purchased from Sangon 
Biotech, Co., Ltd. The THUNDERBIRD 
® SYBR 
® qPCR 
Mix was purchased from Toyobo Co., Ltd. (Osaka, Japan). 
The Annexin V-fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)/propidium 
iodide (PI) Apoptosis Detection kit was purchased from 
Nanjing KeyGen Biotech Co., Ltd. (Nanjing, China). </p>

<p>Cell culture. BGC823, SGC7901, MKN45 and MCF-7 cells 
were cultured in RPMI-1640 medium supplemented with 10% 
FBS at 5% CO 2 and 37˚C. The cells were digested using trypsin 
and passaged upon reaching 70-80% confluence, followed by 
passaging every 2-3 days. BGC823 cells were digested and 
plated at a density of 1x10 
5 cells/well onto Costar 
® 6-well 
plates in RPMI-1640 medium containing 10% FBS at 37˚C. 
After 24 h, the culture medium was removed, and the cells 
were washed twice with phosphate-buffered saline, followed 
by culturing in phenol red-free RPMI-1640 medium containing 
1% charcoal-stripped FBS for 6 h at 37˚C. Subsequently, 
BGC823 cells were cultured in the same medium containing 
various concentrations of 17β-estradiol or tamoxifen for 24 or 
48 h at 37˚C. The MCF-7 control cells were cultured in medium </p>

<p>containing 1:1,000 absolute ethyl alcohol at 37˚C. 17β-estradiol 
and tamoxifen, which were dissolved in absolute ethyl alcohol 
and stored at a concentration of 10 
-5 and 10 
-2 mol/l, respectively, 
at -20˚C, were diluted prior to use. BGC823 cells were treated 
with 10 
-12 , 10 
-11 or 10 
-10 mol/l 17β-estradiol, or with 5x10 
-6 or 
1x10 
-5 mol/l tamoxifen, for 24 or 48 h. </p>

<p>Nested RT-PCR. Total RNA was extracted from BGC823 cells 
upon reaching 80% confluence, using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen; 
Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.) according to the manufacturer's 
protocol, and was reverse transcribed into complementary (c) 
DNA using an RT-PCR kit. The RT system (25 µl) consisted of the 
forward and reverse glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase 
(GAPDH) primers, and the forward and reverse ER-α36 first and 
second nested primers. The primer sequences were as follows: 
GAPDH (452 bp) forward, 5'-ACC ACA GTC CAT GCC ATC AC-3' 
and reverse, 5'-TCC ACC ACC CTG TTG CTGTA-3; ER-α36 first 
nested primer (290 bp) forward, 5'-CAA GTG GTT TCC TCG 
TGT CTA AAG-3' and reverse, 5'-TGT TGA GTG TTG GTT GCC 
AGG-3'; and ER-α36 second nested primer (219 bp) forward, 
5'-TGG TTT CCT CGT GTC TAA-3' and reverse, 5'-CAA AGT 
TTG TGG GTA GCT-3' . The first nested PCR system consisted of 
2 µl cDNA, 2 µl first nested primer, 1.0 µl MgCl 2 , 2 µl 10X PCR 
buffer, 0.2 µl Taq polymerase (5 U/µl) and 13.2 µl double distilled 
(dd)H 2 O in a total volume of 20 µl. The cycling conditions were 
an initial denaturation for 1 min at 94˚C, followed by 20 cycles 
consisting of denaturation at 94˚C for 45 sec, an annealing step at 
53˚C for 45 sec and an extension step at 72˚C for 60 sec. This was 
followed by a final extension at 72˚C for 10 min. The second nested 
PCR system consisted of 2 µl cDNA, 2 µl each of the forward 
and reverse GAPDH primers, 1.5 µl MgCl 2 , 2 µl 10X PCR buffer 
(15 mmol/l), 0.1 µl Taq polymerase (5 U/µl) and 12.4 µl sterile 
ddH 2 O. The cycling conditions for this reaction system were 
an initial denaturation for 1 min at 94˚C, followed by 15 cycles 
consisting of denaturation at 94˚C for 45 sec, an annealing step at 
55˚C for 45 sec and an extension step at 72˚C for 60 sec. This was 
followed by a final extension at 72˚C for 10 min. PCR products 
were separated by 1.5% agarose gel electrophoresis and visual-
ized by ethidium bromide staining under ultraviolet illumination. </p>

<p>WST-1 assay for assessment of cell proliferation. Exponential 
phase BGC823 cells were digested using trypsin and plated at 
a density of 3x10 
3 cells/well onto 96-well plates. Each group 
included five parallel wells. To each well, 20 µl WST-1 solution 
was added and, after 24 or 48 h, the absorbance at 450 nm 
was measured using a microplate reader after culturing for a 
further 2 h in an incubator at 5% CO 2 and 37˚C. </p>

<p>RNA extraction and quantitative (q)PCR. Total RNA was extracted 
from gastric cancer cells using TRIzol 
® reagent (Invitrogen; 
Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.), according to the manufacturer's 
protocol. Total RNA was reverse transcribed into cDNA using an 
RT-PCR kit. qPCR was performed on a StepOnePlus Real-Time 
PCR System (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.) using the THUN-
DERBIRD 
® SYBR 
® qPCR Mix. The qPCR consisted of 35 cycles 
of 94˚C for 30 sec, 56˚C for 30 sec and 72˚C for 30 sec. ER-α36 
and β-actin primers were designed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Primer Premier</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">5.0</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Premier Biosoft International</rs>, Palo Alto, CA, USA), 
and had the following sequences: ER-α36 forward, 5'-ACA AGT 
GGT TTC CTC GTG TCTAA-3' and reverse, 5'-GGG TGT TGA </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 13: 57-62, 2017 </p>



<p>GTG TTG GTTGC-3'; and β-actin forward, 5'-ATG ATG ATA 
TCG CCG CGCTC-3'; and reverse, 5'-GTA CAT GGC TGG GGT 
GTTGA-3' . β-actin was used as an internal invariant endogenous 
control for qPCR. Expression levels were determined using the 
relative 2(-∆∆C(T)) method. All experiments were performed at 
least three times to ensure the reproducibility of the results. </p>

<p>Apoptosis assay. The cells were stained using the 
Annexin V-FITC/PI Apoptosis Detection kit, according to the 
manufacturer's protocol, and apoptotic cells, including early 
apoptotic cells (Annexin V 
+ /PI </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>) and necrotic or late apoptotic 
cells (Annexin V 
+ /PI </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), were measured by flow cytometry. 
Briefly, BGC823 cells were treated with 17β-estradiol or tamox-
ifen for 24 or 48 h, and subsequently, the cells were collected 
and resuspended in phenol red-free RPMI-1640 medium with 
1% charcoal-stripped FBS at a density of 1x10 
6 cells/ml. Next, 
the cells were stained with 5 µl Annexin V-FITC and 5 µl PI in 
300 µl binding buffer (10 mmol/l 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-piper-
azineethanesulfonic acid, pH 7.4, 140 mmol/l NaOH and 
2.5 mmol/l CaCl 2 ) for 15 min at room temperature in the dark. 
Quantification of apoptotic cells was performed using a flow 
cytometer (FACScan; Beckman Coulter, Inc., Brea, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Statistical analyses were performed 
using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">12.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS, Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). 
Data are presented as the mean ± standard deviation of three 
replicate samples, and differences were compared using the 
Student's t-test or one-way analysis of variance. P&lt;0.05 was 
considered to indicate a statistically significant difference. All 
experiments were performed at least three times to ensure the 
reproducibility of the results. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Expression of ER-α36 in various human gastric cancer 
cell lines. The expression of ER-α36 messenger (m)RNA in 
BGC823, MKN45 and SGC7901 human gastric cancer cell lines 
was determined by semiquantitative nested RT-PCR, using the 
MCF-7 cell line as a positive control. Notably, ER-α36 mRNA 
expression was positive in the gastric cancer cell lines, and there 
was no detection of gene amplification (Fig. 1). These results 
suggest that ER-α36 is highly expressed in gastric cancer cells. </p>

<p>WST-1-based detection of cell proliferation in gastric cancer 
cells treated with an ER-α36 agonist or inhibitor. BGC823 cells 
were stimulated with various concentrations of 17β-estradiol 
or tamoxifen for 24 or 48 h, and WST-1 assays were then 
performed to assess cell proliferation. In the cells treated with 
10 
-12 mol/l 17β-estradiol for 24 h, proliferation was increased 
by 13.2% compared with the control group, and the difference 
was significant (P=0.013; Fig. 2A). Conversely, the proliferation 
rates of the cells treated with 10 
-11 mol/l (P=0.0841) or 10 
-10 mol/l 
(P=0.0735) 17β-estradiol for 24 h were not significantly different 
from those exhibited by the control (P&gt;0.05; Fig. 2A). After 
48 h, the cell growth activity was increased by 30.5, 23.9 and 
13.8% in the 10 
-12 mol/l (P=0.0015), 10 
-11 mol/l (P=0.0178) and 
10 
-10 mol/l (P=0.0245) 17β-estradiol-treated groups, respectively, 
as compared with the control group, and the difference was 
significant (Fig. 2A). These results suggest that 17β-estradiol 
promotes the proliferation of gastric cancer cells in vitro. </p>

<p>There was no significant difference in the cell proliferation 
rate between BGC823 cells treated with 5x10 
-6 mol/l tamox-
ifen and the control group after 24 h (P=0.0724; Fig. 2B). After 
24 h, the activity of the BGC823 cells treated with 1x10 
-5 mol/l 
tamoxifen was 56.4% of that displayed by the control group, </p>

<p>Figure 1. Messenger RNA expression of ER-α36 was detected in three 
different human gastric cancer cell lines using nested reverse transcrip-
tion-polymerase chain reaction. MCF-7 cells were used as a positive control 
and double distilled H 2 O as a negative control. ER, estrogen receptor. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Effect of various concentrations of (A) 17β-estradiol and (B) tamox-
ifen on the proliferation of BGC823 human gastric carcinoma cells after 
24 and 48 h of treatment. Data are presented as the mean ± standard devia-
tion. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. the 24 h control group; 
# P&lt;0.05 vs. the 48 h control group. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>WANG et al: ER-α36 AND GASTRIC CANCER </p>



<p>which was significantly different (P=0.0233; Fig. 2B). The 
activity of the BGC823 cells treated with 5x10 
-6 mol/l was 
61.5% of that of the control group after 48 h (P=0.0021), and 
the cell activity of the 1x10 
-5 mol/l group was 29.9% of that of 
the control group after 48 h (P= 0.0059), which were signifi-
cantly different (Fig. 2B). These results suggest that tamoxifen 
inhibits the growth of gastric cancer cells in vitro. </p>

<p>Gastric cancer cell apoptosis following treatment with 
an ER-α36 agonist or inhibitor. The apoptosis rate was 
significantly reduced in the BGC823 cells treated with 
17β-estradiol for 24 h (10 
-12 mol/l, P=0.013; 10 
-11 mol/l, 
P=0.023; and 10 
-10 mol/l, P=0.017) and for 48 h (10 
-12 mol/l, 
P=0.002; 10 
-11 mol/l, P=0.011 and 10 
-10 mol/l, P=0.033) (Fig.3). 
Conversely, the rates of the apoptosis were significantly 
increased in the BGC823 cells as the tamoxifen concentration 
increased after 24 h (5x10 
-6 mol/l, P=0.002; and 5x10 
-5 mol/l, </p>

<p>P=0.001) and after 48 h (5x10 
-6 mol/l, P=0.014; and 10 
-5 mol/l, 
P=0.0021), as compared with the control group. These results 
indicate that tamoxifen inhibits the growth of BGC823 cells, 
potentially by promoting gastric cancer cell apoptosis. </p>

<p>Alterations in the expression levels of ER-α36 following treat-
ment of gastric cancer cells with 17β-estradiol or tamoxifen. 
BGC823 cells were treated with various concentrations of 
17β-estradiol or tamoxifen for 24 or 48 h, and subsequently, 
the mRNA expression levels of ER-α36 were determined by 
RT-qPCR. After 24 h, the mRNA expression levels of ER-α36 in 
the 10 
-12 mol/l (P=0.024), 10 
-11 mol/l (P=0.0113) and 10 
-10 mol/l 
(P=0.0037) 17β-estradiol-treated groups exhibited a fold-change 
of 1.78, 1.44 and 1.15, respectively, as compared with those in 
the control (Fig. 4). After 48 h, the mRNA expression levels of 
ER-α36 in the 10 
-12 mol/l (P=0.0164), 10 
-11 mol/l (P=0.0342) and 
10 
-10 mol/l (P=0.0198) 17β-estradiol-treated groups displayed </p>

<p>Figure 3. Effect of various concentrations of 17β-estradiol and tamoxifen on the apoptosis of BGC823 human gastric carcinoma cells after 24 and 48 h of 
treatment. Data are presented as the mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. the 24 h control group. 
# P&lt;0.05 vs. the 48 h control group. PI, propidium iodide; 
FITC, fluorescein isothiocyanate. </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 13: 57-62, 2017 </p>



<p>a fold-change of 2.15, 1.56 and 1.26, respectively, as compared 
with those in the control (Fig. 4). Conversely, the mRNA expres-
sion levels of ER-α36 were decreased by 29.6% after 24 h in the 
5x10 
-6 mol/l tamoxifen-treated group (P=0.0233), as compared 
with the mRNA levels observed in the control group, while 
those in the 1x10 
-5 mol/l tamoxifen-treated group (P=0.007) 
were decreased by 53.7%, as compared with the mRNA levels 
detected in the control group (Fig. 4). In the 5x10 
-6 mol/l 
tamoxifen-treated group (P=0.001), the mRNA expression levels 
of ER-α36 were decreased by 40.7% after 48 h, as compared 
with the levels measured in the control group, and those in the 
1x10 
-5 mol/l tamoxifen-treated group (P=0.0153) were decreased 
by 64.8%, as compared with the levels displayed by the control 
group (Fig. 4). These results suggest that tamoxifen downregu-
lates the expression of ER-α36 in gastric cancer cells. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Gastric cancer is a type of gastrointestinal cancer and, as 
compared to other gastrointestinal cancers, there is no funda-
mental difference in its diagnosis and treatment (21). Recurrence 
is commonly observed in patients with advanced gastric cancer 
who have missed the opportunity for surgical resection and 
have instead undergone non-radical surgery. Although novel 
methods for the targeted treatment of gastric cancer are 
abundant, reports regarding the effects of these treatments 
have been less than satisfactory (21). It is not a coincidence 
that the incidence of gastric cancer is higher in males than in 
females (1-3). The present study aimed to investigate the role of 
estrogen in gastric cancer, in order to aid the development of 
better prophylactic and therapeutic strategies for gastric cancer 
and to improve the understanding of its ontogenesis. 
Estrogen performs its biological functions by binding to the 
ER, which belongs to a family of receptors consisting of α and β 
subtypes. The ER exerts its function via the estrogen response 
element (ERE) and activating protein-1 in its target genes. It 
is considered that the ER is a ligand-dependent transcriptional 
activator (4,5). It has been demonstrated that membrane-bound </p>

<p>ER quickly activates an intracellular second messenger to exert 
its biological functions in numerous cell types (5,22-24). 
ER-α36 is a novel subtype of ER that was discovered and 
cloned by Professor Zhaoyi Wang, and whose molecular weight 
is 35.7 kDa. As compared with the traditional ER, ER-α36 
does not participate in the activation of the ERE due to loss of 
the AF1 and AF2 domains (4,5). However, ER-α36 possesses 
three myristoylation sites, including amino acids 25-30 [glycine 
(Gly)-valine-tryptophan-serine-cysteine-glutamate (Glu)], 
76-81 [Gly-methionine (Met)-Met-lysine-Gly-Gly] and 171-176 
[Glu-leucine (Leu)-Leu-threonine-asparagine-Leu], which are 
associated with the receptor's location at the membrane (5). 
Wang et al (4) reported that the phosphorylation of extracellular 
signal-regulated kinase (ERK) 1/2 was increased following 
stimulation of HEK-293 cells overexpressing ER-α36 with 
17β-estradiol for 5 min. The level of ERK1/2 phosphorylation 
peaked at 30 min, and then commenced to decline, which may 
suggest that ER-α36 promotes the proliferation of cells by 
activating the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK)/ERK 
signaling pathway (15). 
The present study demonstrated that a low concentra-
tion of 17β-estradiol was able to promote the proliferation 
of gastric cancer cells in vitro, and that the proliferation of 
these cells was negatively correlated with the concentration of 
17β-estradiol. Low-dose 17β-estradiol displayed an enhanced 
ability to promote the proliferation of gastric cancer cells, as 
compared with high concentrations of 17β-estradiol. These 
results were consistent with the findings of previous epide-
miological studies, in which lower levels of estrogen in males 
were associated with higher morbidity of gastric cancer in 
males compared with females (1). In addition, in the present 
study, the proliferation of gastric cancer cells was inhib-
ited by tamoxifen in a concentration-and time-dependent 
manner. These results suggested that gastric cancer cells 
were sensitive to estrogen, and that gastric cancer tumors are 
estrogen-responsive. Furthermore, the rate of apoptosis was 
increased in gastric cancer cells treated with tamoxifen, thus 
indicating that tamoxifen induces gastric cancer cell apop-
tosis in vitro. 
The present study demonstrated that the proliferation of 
gastric cancer cells was increased to a greater extent following 
stimulation with lower concentrations of 17β-estradiol than 
using higher concentrations of this molecules. In addition, the 
current study demonstrated that the mRNA expression levels 
of ER-α36 were increased in the 17β-estradiol-treated group 
compared with the control group at all times, particularly 
when 17β-estradiol was obviously promoting cell proliferation. 
Tamoxifen was observed to induce gastric cancer cell apop-
tosis in vitro, and its concentration was negatively correlated 
with the expression of ER-α36. The apoptosis of gastric cancer 
cells was more obvious, and their mRNA expression levels of 
ER-α36 were decreased to a greater extent, which indicated 
that ER-α36 is important in the balance between proliferation 
and apoptosis of gastric cancer cells. 
Since the ER is located at the cell membrane, ER-α36 
may activate members of the MAPK family. MAPK is the 
main transducer of information from the cell surface to the 
nucleus (4). In eukaryotic cells, at least four types of MAPK 
signal transducers have been reported, including ERK, c-Jun 
N-terminal kinase (JNK), P38 and ERK5 (24). It has been </p>

<p>Figure 4. Messenger RNA expression levels of ER-α36 in BGC823 human 
gastric carcinoma cells stimulated with 17β-estradiol or tamoxifen for 24 or 
48 h. Data are presented as the mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. the 
24 h control group. 
# P&lt;0.05 vs. the 48 h control group. ER, estrogen receptor. </p>

<p>WANG et al: ER-α36 AND GASTRIC CANCER </p>



<p>hypothesized that JNK mediates the apoptosis of cells in the 
emergency response, thus inhibiting apoptosis and promoting 
proliferation when the ERK cascade is dominant, while initi-
ating apoptosis when the JNK cascade is dominant (25-33). 
In conclusion, the present study demonstrated that low 
concentrations of 17β-estradiol were able to promote ER-α36 
expression in gastric cancer cells, which in turn led to their 
increased proliferation, potentially via activation of the 
MAPK signaling pathway. Conversely, high concentrations of 
tamoxifen downregulated ER-α36 expression, which led to the 
apoptosis of gastric cancer cells. The aforementioned results 
indicated that a high concentration of tamoxifen could be 
important in the curative treatment of stomach cancer. Further 
studies are required to validate the results of the present study. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The present study was supported by the National Natural 
Science Foundation of China (Beijing, China; grant 
nos. 81470110, 81272754 and 30870981), the National Natural 
Science foundation of Guangxi (grant no. 0848014) and the 
Science Foundation of the Health Office of Hubei Province 
(Wuhan, China; grant no. WJ2015Z059). </p>



</text></tei>