<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5122609" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background Older people are more sensitive to drugs and 
adverse drug reactions than younger people because of age-
related physiological changes such as impaired renal 
function. As people with dementia are particularly vul-
nerable to the effects of drugs, it is especially important to 
evaluate the dosages of renally cleared medications in this 
group. 
Objective The aim of this study was to estimate the 
prevalence of impaired renal function and inappropriate 
prescriptions on the basis of renal function among older 
patients with dementia or cognitive impairment. 
Methods The medical records of 428 patients aged 
C65 years who were admitted to two hospitals in northern 
Sweden were reviewed and renally cleared medications 
were identified. The Cockcroft-Gault equation was used to 
evaluate renal function. Doses were evaluated according to 
the Geriatric Dosage Handbook. 
Results Renal function was impaired (estimated glomeru-
lar filtration rate \60 ml/min) in 65.4 % of the study 
population. Impaired renal function was associated with 
increasing age. Among 547 prescriptions identified as 
renally cleared medications, 9.1 % were inappropriate 
based on the patient's renal function; 13.5 % of the 326 
patients prescribed renally cleared medications had </p>

<p>inappropriate prescriptions. Inappropriate prescriptions 
were more common among patients living in nursing 
homes. 
Conclusions Impaired renal function is common and 
inappropriate prescription is prevalent among old people 
with cognitive impairment in northern Sweden. Continuous 
consideration of renal function is important when pre-
scribing medications to this group. </p>

<p>Key Points </p>

<p>Prescriptions classed as inappropriate on the basis of 
impaired renal function is prevalent among older 
people with cognitive impairment and dementia. </p>

<p>Impaired renal function is common among older 
people with cognitive impairment and dementia. </p>

<p>Ageing populations are characterised by an increased 
proportion of older people [1, 2]. In older populations, 
chronic diseases, including dementia and mild cognitive 
impairment, and comorbidity are common [2, 3]. 
Polypharmacy is common among older people with mul-
tiple chronic conditions. This situation is of particular 
concern as older people are more sensitive to drugs and 
adverse drug reactions (ADRs) than younger individuals 
[2, 4]. The changes in neurotransmitter substances that </p>

<p>Electronic supplementary material The online version of this 
article (doi:10.1007/s40266-016-0408-8) contains supplementary 
material, which is available to authorized users. </p>

<p>&amp; Maria Gustafsson 
maria.gustafsson@umu.se </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Pharmacology and Clinical Neuroscience, 
 University, 901 87 , Sweden </p>

<p>Drugs Aging (2016) 33:889-899 
DOI 10.1007/s40266-016-0408-8 </p>

<p>occur in people with dementia make this patient group 
especially vulnerable to the effects of drugs, including 
ADRs [1, 2, 5]. 
Age-related physiological changes affect the pharma-
cokinetic parameters of a drug, and the elimination of 
drugs is particularly affected by impairment of renal 
function [1, 2]. Renal mass declines with age as do the 
number and size of nephrons [6], and this process results in 
reduced glomerular and tubular filtration [2]. Chronic 
kidney disease (CKD), defined as estimated glomerular 
filtration rate (eGFR) \60 ml/min, is a common and 
growing problem in older populations [6-8]. Renally 
excreted drugs with narrow therapeutic indices, such as 
digoxin and lithium, can accumulate and concentrations 
can become toxic [9]. Drugs such as morphine and 
glibenclamide that have active metabolites may cause 
ADRs [10, 11]. Estimation of renal function is thus 
important when prescribing renally excreted drugs to older 
people to avoid inappropriate prescribing, which is defined 
as ''a situation where risk from the adverse effects of a 
prescribed medication outweighs the desired clinical ben-
efits of treating a particular condition'' [4]. 
eGFR is increasingly used in healthcare to estimate 
patients' renal function. The use of serum creatinine level 
alone as a measure of renal function is not reliable [12] 
because creatinine production, which is dependent on 
muscle mass, decreases with age; thus, the use of serum 
creatinine level alone leads to overestimation of renal 
function [1, 6]. Two commonly used methods for calcu-
lating eGFR on the basis of serum creatinine level are the 
Cockcroft-Gault (CG) equation and the Chronic Kidney 
Disease Epidemiology Collaboration (CKD-EPI) equation 
[2, 13]. The CG equation calculates the absolute eGFR (ml/ 
min) [14]. Most recommendations published in dosage 
handbooks are based on renal function estimated by the CG 
equation [2, 6]. The CKD-EPI equation calculates the rel-
ative eGFR (ml/min/1.73 m 2 ) and is used to detect and 
characterise CKD [13-15]. Estimates of renal function 
obtained via creatinine-based equations are less accurate in 
certain patients such as those who are malnourished, 
amputees and the morbidly obese [2, 12]. Debate con-
cerning the most suitable equation for calculating eGFR is 
ongoing [6, 13, 16, 17]. 
As people with dementia are particularly vulnerable to 
drugs, evaluation of whether medications need to be 
adjusted according to renal function is especially important 
in this group [5]. Several studies have evaluated older 
people's prescriptions in relation to their renal function 
[4, 6, 8, 16, 18-22]. To our knowledge, no similar study 
has been conducted among people with dementia or cog-
nitive impairment. 
The purpose of this study was to estimate the prevalence 
of impaired renal function and inappropriate prescription of </p>

<p>renally cleared medications among older people, aged 
C65 years, with dementia or cognitive impairment. Factors 
associated with impaired renal function and inappropriate 
prescription were also investigated. </p>

<p>2 Methods </p>

<p>2.1 Setting and Study Design </p>

<p>This cross-sectional study used data collected in a ran-
domised controlled intervention study conducted in two 
hospitals in northern Sweden. The purpose of the inter-
vention was to investigate whether drug-related readmis-
sions were reduced when clinical pharmacists conducted 
medication reviews as part of ward teams. Patients 
admitted to the acute internal medicine or orthopaedic ward 
at Norrland University Hospital and to a medical ward at 
the county hospital in  were recruited between 9 
January 2012 and 2 December 2014. All admissions were 
emergencies, except for one that was elective. The most 
common reasons for admission were fractures/falls, heart 
failure or pneumonia. A total of 460 people were ran-
domised to the intervention and control groups. Eligible 
patients were those aged C65 years who had dementia or 
cognitive impairment. Dementia diagnoses were collected 
from medical records. Patients were considered to have 
cognitive impairment if sufficient information related to 
memory, orientation or executive function was noted in 
their medical records prior to the index hospitalization. In 
addition, patients in whom dementia was suspected and 
medical investigation had been or would be commenced 
were included. Ambiguous or uncertain cases were exclu-
ded. The procedure described was chosen to avoid the risk 
of including people without dementia who had developed a 
delirious or confused state during the hospital stay 
(Gustafsson M et al., 2016, unpublished observations). 
Each patient in the intervention group received an addi-
tional medication review by a clinical pharmacist, while 
the control group received standard care. 
Data for the present study were gathered from the 
intervention study, with the patients assigned to the inter-
vention and control groups treated as a single study sample. 
The study population comprised 460 people with dementia 
or cognitive impairment. People who died (n = 31) or 
withdrew from the intervention study (n = 1) before dis-
charge from the index hospitalization were excluded, 
resulting in a final sample of 428 people. </p>

<p>2.2 Data Extraction </p>

<p>Data about the patients' medications were extracted from 
the medical records at the time of the patients' index </p>

<p> 
E.  et al. </p>

<p>hospitalization, before any medication review was per-
formed. The Geriatric Dosage Handbook (GDH) was used 
to identify renally cleared medications from among all 
prescribed drugs to obtain internationally applicable results 
[23]. Doses, strengths and drug formulations were noted for 
every drug at the individual patient level. Pro re nata 
medications, over-the-counter medications and formula-
tions designed for local administration were not included in 
the analysis. 
The GDH guidelines were used to evaluate whether 
prescriptions were inappropriate relative to patients' renal 
function [23]. Another guideline was used for morphine 
prescriptions as the GDH guideline was considered unclear 
for this specific drug [10]. Moreover, mirabegron pre-
scriptions were evaluated according to another guideline 
because the GDH did not include guidelines regarding this 
drug [24]. Angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors were 
excluded because of the large pharmacodynamic variations 
and because these drugs are monitored after clinical 
response [25]. Digoxin and dalteparin were excluded, as 
consideration of serum concentrations and therapeutic 
responses to these drugs is important [23, 26]. Inappro-
priate prescriptions were classified as representing exces-
sive doses (more than the maximum daily dosage) or 
contraindications for patients with renal impairment 
according to previous research [4, 6, 19]. Prescriptions not 
requiring dosage adjustment were classified as having 
appropriate doses relative to renal function. 
The classification system shown in Table 1 was used to 
define CKD stages. Renal function was considered to be 
impaired in stages 3-5 (i.e. eGFR \ 60 ml/min[/1.73 m 2 ]). 
The CG equation, shown in Table S1 of the Electronic 
Supplementary Material (ESM), was used to calculate the 
eGFR (eGFR CG ) to estimate the prevalence of impaired 
renal function and inappropriate prescription. To compare 
the frequencies of patients at different CKD stages using 
different estimation methods, the relative eGFR was </p>

<p>calculated using the CKD-EPI equation, and the absolute 
eGFR was calculated from the relative eGFR values 
(equations shown in ESM Table S1). 
The values required to calculate eGFR were extracted 
from patients' medical records. Data were collected on the 
date of randomisation, which was usually within 2 days 
(maximum 22 days) of admission date. We recorded 
patients' age, sex, serum creatinine level, weight (actual) 
and height as well as the type of dementia, classified as 
Alzheimer's disease, vascular dementia or other or 
unspecified (UNS) dementia. When available, Mini-Mental 
State Examination (MMSE) scores were recorded. 
Patients' living situations were classified as living at home 
or in a nursing home. </p>

<p>2.3 Data Analysis </p>

<p>Descriptive statistics were used to summarise the data. 
Frequencies and proportions were calculated for dichoto-
mous variables, and continuous variables are presented as 
mean values with standard deviations. 
Simple logistic regression analyses were conducted to 
investigate the association between impaired renal function 
and factors extracted from the medical record: age, sex, 
living situation and MMSE score. A multiple logistic 
regression analysis was conducted including all variables 
from the simple models except MMSE score because of the 
large proportion of missing values and the absence of any 
differences found on univariate analysis. 
Further, simple logistic regression analyses were con-
ducted to investigate the association between inappropriate 
prescription and factors extracted from the medical record 
(age, sex, living situation and MMSE score). A multiple 
logistic regression analysis was conducted including all 
variables from the simple models except MMSE score 
because of a large proportion of missing values and the 
absence of any differences found on univariate analysis. 
Results are presented as odds ratios (ORs) with 95 % 
confidence intervals (CIs). All analyses were conducted 
using <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> Statistics <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">22</rs> (Somers, NY, USA). </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>Of the 428 people included in the study, 270 (63.1 %) were 
women; the mean age was 83.2 ± 6.6 years. The 
mean ± standard deviation (SD) serum creatinine level 
was 89.0 ± 39.7 lmol/l. The mean eGFR, calculated using 
the CG equation, was 55.3 ± 22.6 ml/min. The absolute 
and relative eGFRs using the CKD-EPI equation were 
64.8 ± 22.0 ml/min and 64.6 ± 21.1 ml/min/1.73 m 2 , 
respectively. The most common type of cognitive impair-
ment was other or UNS dementia (n = 225 [52.6 %]), and </p>

<p>Table 1 Classification of the different stages of chronic kidney dis-
ease based on glomerular filtration rate [1] </p>

<p>Stage Physiologic change 
GFR 
(ml/min/1.73 m 2 ) </p>

<p>-
At increased risk for CKD 
C90 with risk 
factors </p>

<p>1 
CKD with normal or increased kidney 
function </p>

<p>C90 </p>

<p>2 
CKD with mild impairment of kidney 
function </p>

<p>60-89 </p>

<p>3 
Moderate impairment of kidney function 30-59 </p>

<p>4 
Severe impairment of kidney function 
15-29 </p>

<p>5 
Terminal renal failure 
\15 </p>

<p>CKD chronic kidney disease, GFR glomerular filtration rate </p>

<p>Inappropriate Prescription and Renal Function Among Older Patients with Cognitive Impairment </p>

<p>
the majority of patients (n = 304 [71.0 %]) lived at home 
(Table 2). 
The distribution of the five CKD stages in the study 
sample is presented in Table 3. According to the absolute 
eGFR calculated using the CKD-EPI equation, 173 
(41.0 %) patients were estimated to have CKD stages 3-5 
(i.e. eGFR \ 60 ml/min). Calculation of the relative eGFR 
indicated that 173 (40.4 %) patients had eGFRs \ 60 ml/ 
min/1.73 m 2 . According to the CG equation, 280 (65.4 %) 
patients were estimated to have impaired renal function 
(i.e. eGFR \ 60 ml/min). Impaired renal function was 
more common among women (OR 2.046 [95 % CI 
1.358-3.082]) and in older patients (OR 1.204 [95 % CI 
1.154-1.256]). There were no significant differences 
between people with and without impaired renal function 
in relation to living situation or MMSE score. In a multi-
variable model in which impaired renal function was the 
dependent variable and sex, age and living situation were 
independent variables, age remained significant (OR 1.203 
[95 % CI 1.152-1.257]) (Table 4). </p>

<p>Of the drugs prescribed to the 428 patients, 58 were 
classified as renally cleared medications; 547 prescriptions 
of these 58 drugs were recorded (Table 5). Of these 547 
prescriptions, 50 (9.1 %) were classified as inappropriate 
and 497 prescriptions (90.9 %) were considered appropri-
ate on the basis of the patient's renal function. When 
absolute and relative eGFR were calculated according to 
the CKD-EPI equation, the corresponding prevalences of 
inappropriate prescriptions were 28 (5.1 %) and 32 
(5.9 %), respectively. Inappropriate prescriptions were 
found for 20 (34.5 %) of the 58 identified drugs. Of the 50 
inappropriate prescriptions, 17 were for doses that were too 
high and 33 were for contraindicated drugs; these consti-
tuted 3.1 % (17/547) and 6.0 % (33/547), respectively, of 
all identified prescriptions. Eight (47.1 %) prescriptions 
with excessive doses were for allopurinol and 12 (36.4 %) 
contraindicated prescriptions were for metformin 
(Table 5). 
The majority (326/428 [76.2 %]) of patients in the study 
sample were prescribed one or more renally cleared med-
ications. Of these 326 patients, 44 (13.5 %) had inappro-
priate prescriptions on the basis of their renal function; 
these patients constituted 10.3 % of the total study sample. 
Among the 326 patients prescribed one or more of the 
identified medications, 15 (4.6 %) had one or more pre-
scriptions with excessive doses and 31 (9.5 %) had one or 
more contraindicated prescription. 
Inappropriate prescriptions were more common among 
people living in nursing homes (OR 2.060 [95 % CI 
1.073-3.954]). No significant difference was seen between 
people with and without inappropriate prescriptions in 
terms of sex, age or MMSE score. Nor were any significant 
associations seen in a multivariable model in which inap-
propriate prescriptions was the dependent variable and sex, 
age and living situation were independent variables 
(Table 6). </p>

<p>Table 2 Descriptive statistics of the study sample </p>

<p>Characteristics of study sample </p>

<p>Cases (n) 
428 </p>

<p>Women 
270 (63.1) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
83.2 ± 6.6 (65-99) </p>

<p>Weight (kg) 
68.2 ± 15.4 (32.8-130.0) </p>

<p>BMI a (kg/m 2 ) 
25.1 ± 4.9 (13.3-46.6) </p>

<p>Number of medications at admission 
7.8 ± 3.5 (0-20) </p>

<p>Renal function </p>

<p>C s,cr (lmol/L) 
89.0 ± 39.7 (28.0-311.0) </p>

<p>eGFR CG (ml/min) 
55.3 ± 22.6 (12.8-144.3) </p>

<p>eGFR CKD-EPI 
a (ml/min) 
64.8 ± 22.0 (11.3-126.2) </p>

<p>eGFR CKD-EPI (ml/min/1.73 m 2 ) 
64.6 ± 21.1 (11.8-115.2) 
MMSE b (0-30) 
19.8 ± 4.6 (7-29) </p>

<p>Type of dementia </p>

<p>Alzheimer's disease 
131 (30.6) </p>

<p>Vascular dementia 
72 (16.8) </p>

<p>Other or UNS dementia 
225 (52.6) </p>

<p>Living situation </p>

<p>Living at home 
304 (71.0) </p>

<p>Nursing home 
124 (29.0) </p>

<p>Data are presented as frequencies, n (%) or mean ± standard devia-
tion (range) unless otherwise indicated </p>

<p>BMI body mass index, C s,cr serum creatinine concentration, eGFR CG 
estimated glomerular filtration rate using the Cockcroft-Gault equa-
tion, eGFR CKD-EPI estimated GFR using Chronic Kidney Disease 
Epidemiology Collaboration equation, MMSE Mini-Mental State 
Examination, UNS unspecified 
a n = 422 due to lack of height data when calculating the BMI and 
absolute eGFR 
b n = 155 because the test was not performed in every patient </p>

<p>Table 3 Frequency of patients at different chronic kidney disease 
stages using the CKD-EPI equation as the renal function estimation 
method </p>

<p>CKD stage 
CKD-EPI a 
CKD-EPI b </p>

<p>1 
56 (13.3) 
42 (9.8) </p>

<p>2 
193 (45.7) 
213 (49.8) </p>

<p>3 
148 (35.1) 
149 (34.8) 
4 
23 (5.5) 
23 (5.4) </p>

<p>5 
2 (0.5) 
1 (0.2) </p>

<p>Total 
422 (98.6) 
428 (100) </p>

<p>Data are presented as n (%) </p>

<p>CKD Chronic Kidney Disease, CKD-EPI Chronic Kidney Disease 
Epidemiology Collaboration equation 
a Absolute value (ml/min) </p>

<p>b Relative value (ml/min/1.73 m 2 ) </p>

<p> 
E.  et al. </p>

<p>4 Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, nearly two-thirds of patients had 
impaired renal function, which was associated with 
advancing age. Close to 10 % of the identified prescrip-
tions were inappropriate, affecting more than 10 % of 
patients. The drugs most commonly involved were met-
formin, representing the majority of the contraindicated 
prescriptions, and allopurinol, representing the majority of 
the prescriptions with excessive doses. 
According to values calculated using the CG equation, 
the prevalence of impaired renal function was high in the 
present study. The reported prevalence of impaired renal 
function among older people ranges from 12 to 66 % 
[15, 17, 27]. The wide variation in this parameter may be 
due to differences in study setting, individual parameters 
and the estimation equations used. The association between 
impaired renal function and advancing age found in the 
present study was expected and has been reported in sev-
eral other studies [8, 19, 28, 29]. The rate of decline in 
renal function has been found to be greater in people with 
concomitant diseases; diabetes, for example, is one of the 
most common diseases associated with impaired renal 
function [30, 31]. In this study, no significant difference 
was seen between people with and without impaired renal 
function regarding degree of cognitive impairment. A 
similar result was seen in another study [27], which found 
no association between CKD and cognitive decline or the 
incidence of all-cause dementia. As the prevalence of 
impaired renal function in this group was high, and as 
impairment is often under-recognised among older people, 
routine monitoring to detect deteriorating renal function is </p>

<p>important to avoid the consequences of inappropriate pre-
scriptions [8]. 
In the present study, close to 10 % of the identified 
prescriptions were inappropriate when the CG equation 
was used to estimate renal function; one-third of these 
prescriptions had excessive doses given the patient's renal 
function and two-thirds were contraindicated. When the 
CKD-EPI equation was used, the prevalence of inappro-
priate prescriptions was between 5 and 6 %. These preva-
lence figures differ from those reported in previous studies 
of drug prescriptions that were inappropriate given 
impaired renal function. In one study of patients aged 
C70 years, 42.2 % of identified prescriptions had doses 
exceeding current guidelines [21]. Another study found 
13 % of prescriptions to be potentially inappropriate [18], 
similar to our results. While the chosen renal function 
estimation method might have affected the end result, we 
also found that the CKD-EPI equation overestimates and 
the CG equation underestimates renal function, which may 
explain the differences in prevalence seen in the present 
study [13, 15, 16]. Differences in the reported prevalence 
of inappropriate prescriptions may also be because pre-
scribers and researchers use different prescribing or dosage 
guidelines [4, 6, 8, 18-21]. For example, recommendations 
on dosage limits for metformin differ between guidelines 
[23, 26, 32]. In the present study, the majority of con-
traindicated prescriptions were for metformin, probably 
because it is commonly prescribed and considered con-
traindicated for patients with an eGFR \ 60 ml/min, 
according to the GDH [23]. Other guidelines continue to 
recommend low-dose metformin in patients with 
eGFRs [ 30 ml/min, which would alter the prevalence of </p>

<p>Table 4 Comparison between 
patients with an eGFR CG [60 
and \60 ml/min in the total 
sample </p>

<p>Patient 
characteristics </p>

<p>eGFR CG [ 60 ml/min 
(n = 148) </p>

<p>eGFR CG \ 60 ml/min 
(n = 280) </p>

<p>Simple OR 
Multiple OR </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Men 
71 (48.0) 
87 (31.1) 
Reference </p>

<p>Women 
77 (52.0) 
193 (68.9) 
2.046 
(1.358-3.082) </p>

<p>1.502 
(0.941-2.398) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
78.9 ± 6.4 
85.4 ± 5.5 
1.204 
(1.154-1.256) </p>

<p>1.203 
(1.152-1.257) </p>

<p>Living situation </p>

<p>Living at home 105 (70.9) 
199 (71.1) 
Reference </p>

<p>Nursing home 43 (29.1) 
81 (28.9) 
0.994 
(0.641-1.542) </p>

<p>0.687 
(0.410-1.151) </p>

<p>MMSE (0-30) 
20.2 ± 5.1 
19.6 ± 4.3 
0.970 
(0.900-1.046) </p>

<p>Data are presented as n (%) or mean ± standard deviation or odds ratio (95 % confidence interval). The 
multiple analysis includes sex, age and living situation. MMSE is not included in the model because of the 
small number of values obtained (n = 155), and the lack of a significant difference between the groups </p>

<p>eGFR CG estimated glomerular filtration rate using Cockcroft-Gault equation, MMSE Mini-Mental State 
Examination, OR odds ratio </p>

<p>Inappropriate Prescription and Renal Function Among Older Patients with Cognitive Impairment </p>

<p>
Table 5 Renally cleared medications, together with dose recommendations, and frequency, n (%), of total and inappropriate prescriptions for 
each identified drug [23] </p>

<p>Drug/GDH dosage recommendation 
Total 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Too high 
dose </p>

<p>Contraindicated 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Total inappropriate 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Acamprosate 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Acetylsalicylic acid 
152 (27.8) 
-
-
-
CL cr \ 10 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Alendronate 
15 (2.7) 
-
2 (6.1) 
2 (4.0) </p>

<p>CL cr \ 35 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Alfuzosin 
20 (3.7) 
-
1 (3.0) 
1 (2.0) </p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Allopurinol 
21 (3.8) 
8 (47.1) 
-
8 (16.0) </p>

<p>CL cr [ 140 ml/min: 400 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 121-140 ml/min: 350 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 101-120 ml/min: 300 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 81-100 ml/min: 250 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 61-80 ml/min: 200 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 41-60 ml/min: 150 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 21-40 ml/min: 100 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 11-20 ml/min: 100 mg every 2nd day </p>

<p>CL cr B 10 ml/min: 100 mg every 3rd day 
Amiloride 
5 (0.9) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 10-50 ml/min: 20 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 10 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Amoxicillin 
7 (1.3) 
1 (5.9) 
-
1 (2.0) </p>

<p>CL cr 10-30 ml/min: 1000 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 10 ml/min: 500 mg/day </p>

<p>Ampicillin 
1 (0.2) 
1 (5.9) 
-
1 (2.0) </p>

<p>CL cr C 10 ml/min: 2000 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 10 ml/min: 1000 mg/day </p>

<p>Atenolol 
10 (1.8) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 15-35 ml/min: 50 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 15 ml/min: 50 mg every 2nd day </p>

<p>Azathioprine 
2 (0.4) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 10-50 ml/min: 75 % of 3 mg/kg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 10 ml/min: 50 % of 3 mg/kg/day </p>

<p>Bendroflumethiazide 
19 (3.5) 
-
1 (3.0) 
1 (2.0) 
CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Cefadroxil 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 10-25 ml/min: 1000 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 10 ml/min: 1000 mg every 36th h </p>

<p>Cefotaxime 
9 (1.6) 
1 (5.9) 
-
1 (2.0) </p>

<p>CL cr 10-30 ml/min: 2000 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 10 ml/min: 2000 mg every 2nd day </p>

<p>Cetirizine 
2 (0.4) 
1 (5.9) 
-
1 (2.0) </p>

<p>CL cr 11-31 ml/min: 5 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 11 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Ciprofloxacin 
4 (0.7) 
1 (5.9) 
-
1 (2.0) </p>

<p>CL cr 30-50 ml/min: 1000 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 5-29 ml/min: 500 mg every 18th h </p>

<p> 
E.  et al. </p>

<p>Table 5 continued </p>

<p>Drug/GDH dosage recommendation 
Total 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Too high 
dose </p>

<p>Contraindicated 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Total inappropriate 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Codeine 
5 (0.9) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 10-50 ml/min: ER 450 mg/day, IR 360 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 10 ml/min: ER 300 mg/day, IR 240 mg/day </p>

<p>Dabigatran 
2 (0.4) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Diclofenac 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Dihydroergotamine 
2 (0.4) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr B 29 ml/min: contraindicated 
Fesoterodine 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: 4 mg/day </p>

<p>Fluconazole 
2 (0.4) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 50 ml/min: 400 mg/day </p>

<p>Fondaparinux 
2 (0.4) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Gabapentin 
12 (2.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr C 60 ml/min: 3600 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 30-59 ml/min: 1400 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 16-29 ml/min: 700 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 15 ml/min: 300 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 15 ml/min: reduce daily dose (from 300 mg) in 
proportion to CL cr </p>

<p>Galantamine 
28 (5.1) 
1 (5.9) 
-
1 (2.0) </p>

<p>CL cr 10-59 ml/min: 16 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 9 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Glibenclamide 
8 (1.5) 
-
2 (6.0) 
2 (4.0) </p>

<p>CL cr \ 50 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Glipizide 
7 (1.3) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 10 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Hydralazine 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 10-50 ml/min: 225 mg/day </p>

<p>Hydrochlorothiazide 
17 (3.1) 
-
2 (6.1) 
2 (4.0) </p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Ibuprofen 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Ketoprofen 
2 (0.4) 
1 (5.9) 
-
1 (2.0) 
CL cr 25-89 ml/min: 150 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 25 ml/min: 100 mg/day </p>

<p>Levetiracetam 
2 (0.4) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr [ 80 ml/min: 3000 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 50-80 ml/min: 2000 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 30-49 ml/min: 1500 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: 1000 mg/day </p>

<p>Lithium 
2 (0.4) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 10-50 ml/min: 1800 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 10 ml/min: 1200 mg/day </p>

<p>Memantine 
25 (4.6) 
2 (11.8) 
-
2 (4.0) </p>

<p>CL cr 5-29 ml/min: 10 mg/day </p>

<p>Inappropriate Prescription and Renal Function Among Older Patients with Cognitive Impairment </p>

<p>
Table 5 continued </p>

<p>Drug/GDH dosage recommendation 
Total 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Too high 
dose </p>

<p>Contraindicated 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Total inappropriate 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Methenamine 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 50 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Metformin 
34 (6.2) 
-
12 (36.4) 
12 (24.0) </p>

<p>CL cr \ 60 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Methotrexate 
4 (0.7) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 10 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Metoclopramide 
3 (0.5) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 40 ml/min: 30 mg/day </p>

<p>Mirabegron 
3 (0.5) 
-
-
-
CL cr \ 15 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Morphine 
40 (7.3) 
-
5 (15.2) 
5 (10.0) </p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Naproxen 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Nitrofurantoin 
5 (0.9) 
-
3 (9.1) 
3 (6.0) </p>

<p>CL cr \ 60 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Norfloxacin 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr B 30 ml/min: 400 mg/day </p>

<p>Piperacillin/tazobactam 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 20-40 ml/min: 8000/1000 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 20 ml/min: 6000/750 mg/day </p>

<p>Pramipexole 
3 (0.5) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>ER formulations: </p>

<p>CL cr 30-50 ml/min: 2.25 mg/day 
CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>IR formulations: </p>

<p>CL cr 30-50 ml/min: 2.25 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 15-29 ml/min: 1.5 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 15 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Pregabalin 
5 (0.9) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr C 60 ml/min: 600 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 30-59 ml/min: 300 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr 15-29 ml/min: 150 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 15 ml/min: 75 mg/day </p>

<p>Raloxifene 
1 (0.2) 
-
1 (3.0) 
1 (2.0) </p>

<p>CL cr \ 59 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Ranitidine 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 50 ml/min: 150 mg/day </p>

<p>Risedronate 
2 (0.4) 
-
-
-
CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Rosuvastatin 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: 10 mg/day </p>

<p>Saxagliptin 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr B 50 ml/min: 2.5 mg/day </p>

<p>Solifenacin 
6 (1.1) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: 5 mg/day </p>

<p>Spironolactone 
27 (4.9) 
-
3 (9.1) 
3 (6.0) </p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p> 
E.  et al. </p>

<p>inappropriate prescription of this drug [26]. When met-
formin was excluded from the analysis, the prevalence of 
inappropriate prescription was 7.4 %. Metformin is con-
sidered the first-line treatment for type 2 diabetes mellitus, 
and monitoring of renal function is essential to avoid lactic 
acidosis in patients receiving this drug [26, 32]. In addition 
to metformin and allopurinol, we also documented more 
than one inappropriate prescription each for alendronate, 
glibenclamide, hydrochlorothiazide, memantine, morphine, 
nitrofurantoin and spironolactone. In other studies, the </p>

<p>most frequently inappropriately prescribed drugs were non-
steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, atenolol, gabapentin, 
glyburide, ranitidine and nitrofurantoin [6, 8]. Gliben-
clamide has been associated with an increased risk of 
hypoglycaemia compared with other sulfonylureas, and 
other drugs in this class should be used for patients with 
impaired renal function [23, 32]. Nitrofurantoin is con-
traindicated because impaired renal function decreases its 
efficacy [23]. In general, patients with dementia or cogni-
tive impairment are especially vulnerable to ADRs, and it </p>

<p>Table 5 continued </p>

<p>Drug/GDH dosage recommendation 
Total 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Too high 
dose </p>

<p>Contraindicated 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Total inappropriate 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 15-30 ml/min: 1600/320 mg/day </p>

<p>CL cr \ 15 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Tolterodine 
4 (0.7) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 10-30 ml/min: 2 mg/day </p>

<p>Tramadol 
4 (0.7) 
-
1 (3.0) 
1 (2.0) </p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: ER contraindicated, IR 200 mg/day </p>

<p>Trimethoprim 
1 (0.2) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 15-30 ml/min: 100 mg every 18th h 
CL cr \ 15 ml/min: 100 mg/day </p>

<p>Venlafaxine 
5 (0.9) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr 10-70 ml/min: 168.75 mg </p>

<p>Zoledronic acid 
3 (0.5) 
-
-
-</p>

<p>CL cr \ 30 ml/min: contraindicated </p>

<p>Total, n (row %) 
547 (100) 
17 (3.1) 
33 (6.0) 
50 a (9.1) </p>

<p>Data are presented as n (%) </p>

<p>CL cr creatinine clearance, ER extended release, GDH Geriatric Dosage Handbook, IR immediate release 
a The number of inappropriate prescriptions shown in this table is not equal to the number of patients having identified inappropriate 
prescriptions </p>

<p>Table 6 Comparison between those with correct versus inappropriate prescriptions among patients being prescribed a renally cleared 
medication </p>

<p>Patient characteristics Correct prescriptions (n = 282) Inappropriate prescriptions (n = 44) Simple OR 
Multiple OR </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Men 
113 (40.1) 
17 (38.6) 
Reference </p>

<p>Women 
169 (59.9) 
27 (61.4) 
1.062 (0.553-2.038) 0.933 (0.477-1.826) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
82.7 ± 6.5 
84.8 ± 6.6 
1.051 (0.999-1.105) 1.044 (0.991-1.100) </p>

<p>Living situation </p>

<p>Living at home 
206 (73.0) 
25 (56.8) 
Reference </p>

<p>Nursing home 
76 (27.0) 
19 (43.2) 
2.060 (1.073-3.954) 1.889 (0.974-3.663) 
MMSE (0-30) 
19.5 ± 4.4 
20.8 ± 4.0 
1.074 (0.955-1.206) </p>

<p>Data are presented as n (%), mean ± standard deviation or OR (95 % confidence interval). The multiple analysis includes sex, age and living 
situation. MMSE is not included in the model because of the small number of values obtained (n = 122), and the lack of a significant difference 
between the groups </p>

<p>MMSE Mini-Mental State Examination, OR odds ratio </p>

<p>Inappropriate Prescription and Renal Function Among Older Patients with Cognitive Impairment </p>

<p>
is essential to avoid adverse reactions [33]. Hypoglycaemia 
as an adverse reaction to glibenclamide or worsening 
symptoms of urinary infection due to decreased nitrofu-
rantoin efficacy may have particularly harmful conse-
quences in this group. Older people with dementia are, on 
average, prescribed more medicines than older people 
without dementia [34]. This means it is even more 
important and urgent to evaluate prescriptions of renally 
excreted drugs to ensure that the correct doses are used and 
further ADRs are avoided. 
In this study, multiple logistic regression analysis 
showed that age, sex and living in a nursing home were not 
significantly associated with the record of one or more 
potentially inappropriate prescription. In contrast, other 
studies have found that inappropriate prescription in rela-
tion to renal function is more common in older people and 
among those living in nursing homes [6, 22]. Our uni-
variate model showed that living situation was associated 
with inappropriate prescription, but this association was not 
significant in the multivariable model. People who live in 
nursing homes may be older and have more concomitant 
diseases that affect renal function than older people living 
at home. 
Some limitations of the present study should be 
recognised. No baseline data about serum creatinine 
were collected, nor were changes in values followed-up 
during hospitalization. Therefore, we could not deter-
mine whether patients' GFRs were stable because we 
analysed only one serum creatinine level measurement 
per patient [12]. Also, no other markers of kidney 
damage were collected. Only one patient was admitted to 
the acute internal medicine ward because of acute kidney 
injury (AKI), but more people could possibly have suf-
fered from AKI even if the admission was classified 
otherwise. Serum creatinine level was recorded on the 
date of randomisation, which may have differed slightly 
from the date of hospital admission-from which the 
medication prescription data were taken. Actual body 
weight was also used for all patients, regardless of body 
composition, which may have affected eGFR values for 
patients with unusual muscle mass. Pro re nata drugs 
were not included in the analysis, which may have led to 
underestimation of the prevalence of inappropriate pre-
scription; for example, pro re nata doses of morphine are 
often prescribed. Dosage guidelines may differ between 
different dosage references. The GDH was chosen 
because of its international application and because it 
specifically addresses recommended doses for older 
people. However, the ranges for renal function were 
quite narrow for some of the drug dosage guidelines, 
which may have led to significant confounding in the 
present study. The cross-sectional design of the study, 
which involved assessment of patients' prescriptions at </p>

<p>the time of the medication record review, means we 
cannot comment on the appropriateness of medications 
when they were initially prescribed. Height data were 
lacking for six patients, which affected the absolute 
eGFR values calculated from the relative GFRs esti-
mated using the CKD-EPI equation. MMSE test results 
were available for only 155 patients in the sample. 
The study's strengths include the examination of a well-
defined group of patients and the collection of data from 
hospital settings and medical records, which are reliable 
sources of information for cross-sectional studies [35]. Data 
such as serum creatinine level, weight and prescribed 
medications were current. The CG equation was used to 
estimate renal function for the purpose of estimating dosa-
ges in a medical care setting at the time the study was 
conducted [2]. However, only serum creatinine was reported 
in the medical records and prescribers then had to calculate 
the eGFR themselves. Subsequent to completion of the 
study, the CKD-EPI equation has become the current stan-
dard method used to calculate the eGFR in medical records. 
The results thus provide a representative picture of clinical 
reality at the time of the study [6, 17, 23, 25]. </p>

<p>5 Conclusion </p>

<p>Impaired renal function is common and inappropriate 
prescription is prevalent among old people with cognitive 
impairment in northern Sweden. When prescribing medi-
cations, continuous consideration of renal function is 
important to avoid ADRs among older people with 
dementia or cognitive impairment. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments E. , M. Gustafsson and M.  
analysed and interpreted the data and prepared the manuscript. 
E.  and M. Gustafsson were responsible for the study 
concept and design and for acquisition of subjects. All authors par-
ticipated in critical revision of the manuscript, contributed comments 
and approved the final version. </p>

<p>Compliance with Ethical Standards </p>

<p>Funding This study was supported financially by grants from the 
Swedish Dementia Association and the County Council of 
. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest Eva , Maria  and Maria 
Gustafsson have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>Ethical approval The Regional Ethical Review Board of  
approved this study (Registration No. 2011-148-31M). </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which per-
mits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original </p>

<p> 
E.  et al. </p>

<p>author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons 
license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p>Inappropriate Prescription and Renal Function Among Older Patients with Cognitive Impairment </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>