<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5113931" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Prostate artery embolization (PAE) is emerging and is a promising minimally 
invasive therapy that improves lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) related to benign prostatic 
hyperplasia (BPH). The purpose of this article was to evaluate the efficacy and safety of PAE 
on LUTS related to BPH. 
Materials and methods: A literature review was performed to identify all published articles 
of PAE for BPH. The sources included MEDLINE, EMBASE and Cochrane Library from 1980 
to 2016. A systematic review and meta-analysis was conducted. The outcome measurements 
were combined by calculating the mean difference with 95% confidence interval. Statistical 
analysis was carried out using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Review Manager</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.3.0</rs>. 
Results: Twelve studies involving 840 participants were included. Compared with baseline, 
the International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF-5; International Prostate Symptom Score) 
scores, the quality of life scores, peak urinary flow rate (Q max ) and postvoid residual volume all 
had significant improvements during the 24-month follow-up (all P,0.00001). Both prostate 
volume (PV) and prostate-specific antigen had significant decrease during the 12-month 
follow-up (P,0.00001 and P=0.005, respectively), except postoperative 24 months (P=0.47 
and P=0.32, respectively). The IIEF-5 short form scores had significant increase at postopera-
tive 6 months (P=0.002) and 12 months (P,0.0001), except postoperative 1 month (P=0.23) 
and 24 months (P=0.21). For large volume (PV $80 mL) BPH, the results were similar. There 
were no life-threatening complications. 
Conclusion: PAE is an effective, safe and well-tolerable treatment for LUTS related to BPH, 
including large volume (PV $80 mL) BPH, with a good short-term follow-up. Studies with 
large number of cases and longer follow-up time are needed to validate our results. 
Lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) are main complaints resulting from benign 
prostatic hyperplasia (BPH), which is one of the most common diseases of aging men. </p>

<p>1   LUTS can range in severity and have a significant impact on the quality of life (QoL). 
The current treatment options include watchful waiting, medical therapy and surgical 
intervention. The patients refractory to preliminary treatments can be treated with 
surgical intervention. Transurethral resection of the prostate (TURP) is the gold standard 
therapy for LUTS/BPH and, for many years, has been considered the surgical treatment </p>

<p>Correspondence: Yong Zhang 
Department of Urology, Beijing Tian 
Tan Hospital, Capital Medical University, 
No 6 Tiantan Xi Li, Dong Cheng District, 
Beijing 100050, People's Republic of 
China 
Tel +86 10 6709 8393 
Fax +86 10 6709 6611 
email 18610711834@163.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Interventions in Aging 
11 November 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>of choice and the standard of care when other treatment 
methods fail. 
2 However, TURP has significant complica-
tions, including short-term bleeding, dilutional hyponatremia, 
sexual dysfunction and incontinence. The complication rate 
is higher for patients with large volume BPH. </p>

<p>3   Recently, prostate artery embolization (PAE) has started 
emerging and is a promising minimally invasive therapy 
that improves LUTS related to BPH and is associated with 
a decrease in prostate volume (PV). 
4 However, it is reported 
that as many as 25% of patients show no significant improve-
ment in symptoms and peak flow rate. In addition, the average 
reduction rate in the PV after PAE was only 20%. </p>

<p>5   The aim of this meta-analysis was to evaluate the efficacy 
and safety of PAE on LUTS related to BPH, which may help 
urologists make better choices in the case of elderly patients 
with large volume BPH. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Search strategy </p>

<p>A comprehensive literature search was carried out by two 
independent reviewers using MEDLINE (from 1980 to 
2016), EMBASE (from 1980 to 2016) and the Cochrane 
Central Register of Controlled Trials. The reference lists of 
the retrieved studies were also checked. The following search 
terms were used: "prostate artery embolization", "lower 
urinary tract symptoms" and "benign prostatic hyperplasia". </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria </p>

<p>Studies that met the following criteria were included: 1) a 
study design that included PAE for BPH; 2) a study that 
provided data on International Prostate Symptom Score 
(IPSS), QoL, PV, prostate-specific antigen (PSA), peak 
urine flow rate (Q max ), postvoid residual (PVR) volume and 
International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF-5) short form 
at different follow-up times, and 3) a study where its full text 
could be accessed. If these inclusion criteria were not met, 
then the study was excluded. </p>

<p>Trial selection </p>

<p>When the same study was published in various journals or 
in different years, the most frequently cited one was used. 
If the same group of researchers studied a group of subjects 
with multiple experiments, then each study was included. 
Together, we discussed each of the studies that were included 
and excluded. </p>

<p>Quality assessment </p>

<p>The quality of included studies was assessed using the 
Newcastle-Ottawa scale generating a maximum of nine </p>

<p>stars to each study, including four stars for the selection of 
participants, two stars for the comparability of participants 
and three stars for the assessment of outcomes. Quality 
was assigned according to the scores so that seven to nine 
stars indicated high quality, four to six stars indicated middle 
quality and zero to three stars indicated low quality. </p>

<p>Data extraction </p>

<p>Two independent reviewers extracted the data using a 
predesigned form. The following information was collected 
from each study: 1) the name of the first author and the 
publication year; 2) the sample size; 3) the country in which 
the study was conducted; 4) data on IPSS, QoL, PV, PSA, 
Q max , PVR volume and IIEF-5 at different follow-up times 
and 5) the number of participants with complications. Any 
disputes were resolved by group consensus. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was carried out using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Review Manager</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5.3.0</rs>. The changes in seven functional indexes were deter-
mined as differences between baseline and study completion. 
Outcome measurements were combined by calculating the 
mean difference with 95% confidence interval (CI). To 
quantify the effect of heterogeneity test result, I 
2 heteroge-
neity test was used. A random-effects model was used if 
I 
2 value was .50%; if not, a fixed-effects model was used. 
Publication bias was evaluated using the funnel plot. </p>

<p>Results 
Characteristic and quality assessment 
of eligible studies </p>

<p>Figure 1 shows the flow diagram of the study selection 
process. Finally, there were nine articles involving 12 studies 
eligible for this meta-analysis. 
6-14 All of the 12 studies 
reported the baseline IPSSs, QoL scores, PV, PSA levels, 
Q max , PVR volume and IIEF-5 scores. All 12 studies excluded 
patients with malignancy, advanced atherosclerosis and tor-
tuosity of the iliac arteries and/or prostate arteries, secondary 
renal insufficiency, large bladder diverticula or stones, neu-
rogenic bladder, detrusor muscle failure, active urinary tract 
infection and unregulated coagulation parameters. The main 
characteristic and quality assessment of eligible studies are 
presented in Table 1. </p>

<p>Changes after PAE </p>

<p>IPSSs </p>

<p>Six studies involving 582 participants, five studies involving 
451 participants, six studies involving 479 participants 
and three studies involving 117 participants included </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1611 </p>

<p>Prostate artery embolization for benign prostatic hyperplasia </p>

<p>data representing IPSS changes at postoperative 1 month 
(Figure 2A), 6 months (Figure 2B), 12 months (Figure 2C) 
and 24 months (Figure 2D), respectively. 
Compared with baseline, the IPSSs had significant 
decreases at postoperative 1 month (weighted mean differ-
ence (WMD) −12.74, 95% CI −15.10 to −10.39, P,0.00001), 
6 months (WMD −14.13, 95% CI −17.73 to −10.54, 
P,0.00001), 12 months (WMD −16.07, 95% CI −18.16 
to −13.98, P,0.00001) and 24 months (WMD −15.62, 95% 
CI −17.41 to −13.82, P,0.00001). </p>

<p>Qol scores </p>

<p>Nine studies involving 660 participants, eight studies 
involving 528 participants, six studies involving 414 
participants and three studies involving 117 participants 
included data representing QoL score changes at postopera-
tive 1 month (Figure 3A), 6 months (Figure 3B), 12 months 
(Figure 3C) and 24 months (Figure 3D), respectively. 
Compared with baseline, the QoL scores had significant 
decreases at postoperative 1 month (WMD −2.07, 95% 
CI −2.37 to −1.76, P,0.00001), 6 months (WMD −2.15, 95% 
CI −2.44 to −1.86, P,0.00001), 12 months (WMD −2.81, 
95% CI −3.45 to −2.17, P,0.00001) and 24 months 
(WMD −2.15, 95% CI −2.60 to −1.69, P,0.00001). </p>

<p>Prostate volume </p>

<p>Five studies involving 507 participants, five studies involv-
ing 386 participants, six studies involving 366 participants 
and three studies involving 106 participants included </p>

<p>data representing PV changes at postoperative 1 month 
(Figure 4A), 6 months (Figure 4B), 12 months (Figure 4C) 
and 24 months (Figure 4D), respectively. 
Compared with baseline, PV had significant decreases 
at postoperative 1 month (WMD −17.33, 95% CI −21.19 
to −13.47, P,0.00001), 6 months (WMD −31.62, 95% 
CI −46.75 to −16.48, P,0.0001) and 12 months (WMD −30.72, 
95% CI −42.91 to −18.53, P,0.00001). Although PV was 
also less at postoperative 24 months (WMD −16.89, 95% 
CI −62.61 to −28.83), the difference was not statistically 
significant (P=0.47). </p>

<p>Prostate-specific antigen </p>

<p>Five studies involving 520 participants, five studies involving 
383 participants, six studies involving 379 participants and 
three studies involving 104 participants included data repre-
senting PSA changes at postoperative 1 month (Figure 5A), 
6 months (Figure 5B), 12 months (Figure 5C) and 24 months 
(Figure 5D), respectively. 
Compared with baseline, PSA had significant decreases 
at postoperative 1 month (WMD −0.80, 95% CI −1.44 
to −0.16, P=0.01), 6 months (WMD −1.15, 95% CI −1.69 
to −0.60, P,0.0001) and 12 months (WMD −0.97, 95% 
CI −1.65 to −0.29, P=0.005). Although PSA was also less 
at postoperative 24 months (WMD −0.80, 95% CI −2.37 
to −0.77), the difference was not statistically signifi-
cant (P=0.32). </p>

<p>Q max </p>

<p>Six studies involving 502 participants, five studies involving 
368 participants, six studies involving 368 participants and 
three studies involving 104 participants included data repre-
senting Q max changes at postoperative 1 month (Figure 6A), 
6 months (Figure 6B), 12 months (Figure 6C) and 24 months 
(Figure 6D), respectively. 
Compared with baseline, Q max had significant 
increases at postoperative 1 month (WMD 4.40, 95% 
CI 3.00-5.80, P,0.00001), 6 months (WMD 4.71, 95% 
CI 2.62-6.81, P,0.0001), 12 months (WMD 5.60, 95% CI 
4.19-7.02, P,0.00001) and 24 months (WMD 5.89, 95% 
CI 5.08-6.7, P,0.00001). </p>

<p>PVR volume </p>

<p>Six studies involving 476 participants, five studies involv-
ing 348 participants, six studies involving 369 participants 
and three studies involving 104 participants included data 
representing PVR volume changes at postoperative 1 month 
(Figure 7A), 6 months (Figure 7B), 12 months (Figure 7C) 
and 24 months (Figure 7D), respectively. </p>

<p>Figure 1 The flow diagram of the study selection process. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1612 </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>Table 1 The main characteristic and quality assessment of eligible studies </p>

<p>Studies </p>

<p>Sample </p>

<p>size </p>

<p>Study design </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>Age 
(years) 
PV (mL) 
Other inclusion criteria </p>

<p>Outcome measures </p>

<p>Follow-up 
(month) </p>

<p>Quality 
assessment </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Gabr et al </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Retrospective study </p>

<p>Saudi Arabia </p>

<p>.50 </p>

<p>n 
BPH patients with LUTS refractory to BPH-
related medical therapy or those who had an 
indwelling urethral catheter due to refractory </p>

<p>urine retention </p>

<p>IPSS, QoL, PV, PSA, 
Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, PVR volume, IIEF-5 </p>

<p>1, 3, 9 </p>

<p>Four stars </p>

<p>Bilhim et al </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>186 </p>

<p>Retrospective study </p>

<p>Portugal </p>

<p>.55 </p>

<p>.30 
BPH patients, IPSS .18 </p>

<p>and Qol scores $3, </p>

<p>refractory to medical treatment for at least </p>

<p>6 months; Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>#12 
mL/s or those with acute </p>

<p>urinary retention </p>

<p>IPSS, QoL, PV, PSA, 
Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, PVR volume, IIEF-5 </p>

<p>1, 6, 12, 18, 
24 </p>

<p>seven stars </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>Prospective study </p>

<p>China </p>

<p>$75 </p>

<p>.40 
BPH patients, IPSS .18 </p>

<p>and Qol scores $3, </p>

<p>refractory to medical treatment for at least </p>

<p>6 months; Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>#12 
mL/s or those with acute </p>

<p>urinary retention </p>

<p>IPSS, QoL, PV, PSA, 
Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, PVR volume, IIEF-5 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Five stars </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>,75 </p>

<p>seven stars </p>

<p>Isaacson et al </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Prospective study </p>

<p>UsA </p>

<p>.40 </p>

<p>80-150 
Previous trial of BPH medication, IPSS $18, </p>

<p>life expectancy .1 </p>

<p>year </p>

<p>IPSS, QoL, PV, PSA, 
Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, PVR volume, IIEF-5 </p>

<p>1, 3 </p>

<p>Three stars </p>

<p>Bagla et al </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Prospective study </p>

<p>UsA </p>

<p>.45 </p>

<p>,50 
BPH patients with moderate-or severe-grade 
symptoms </p>

<p>QoL, IIEF-5 </p>

<p>1, 3, 6 </p>

<p>Four stars </p>

<p>Bagla et al </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>50-80 </p>

<p>Four stars </p>

<p>Bagla et al </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>.80 </p>

<p>Four stars </p>

<p>li et al </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Prospective study </p>

<p>China </p>

<p>.65 </p>

<p>.80 
BPH patients, IPSS .12, </p>

<p>Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>,15 </p>

<p>mL/s, </p>

<p>PSA ,4 
ng/mL or PSA level between 4 and </p>

<p>10 ng/mL but negative prostate biopsy </p>

<p>IPSS, QoL, PV, PSA, 
Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, PVR volume, IIEF-5 </p>

<p>1, 3, 6, 12 </p>

<p>Four stars </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>109 </p>

<p>Prospective study </p>

<p>China </p>

<p>.50 </p>

<p>.80 
BPH patients, IPSS .18 </p>

<p>and Qol scores .3, </p>

<p>refractory to medical treatment for at least </p>

<p>6 months, Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>,12 </p>

<p>ml/s </p>

<p>IPSS, QoL, PV, PSA, 
Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, PVR volume, IIEF-5 </p>

<p>1, 3, 6, 12, 24 </p>

<p>six stars </p>

<p>Pisco et al </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Prospective study </p>

<p>Portugal </p>

<p>.45 </p>

<p>.40 
BPH patients, IPSS .18, </p>

<p>and QoL score $3, </p>

<p>refractory to medical treatment for at least </p>

<p>6 months; Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>,12 
mL/s, sexual dysfunction </p>

<p>or accepting the risk of developing sexual 
dysfunction after treatment </p>

<p>IPSS, QoL, PV, PSA, 
Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, PVR volume, IIEF-5 </p>

<p>1, 3, 6, 12, 
18, 24 </p>

<p>Eight stars </p>

<p>Pisco et al </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Prospective study </p>

<p>Portugal </p>

<p>.60 </p>

<p>n 
BPH patients, IPSS .18 </p>

<p>and Qol score $3, </p>

<p>refractory to medical treatment for at least </p>

<p>6 months; Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>,12 
mL/s or those with acute </p>

<p>urinary retention </p>

<p>IPSS, QoL, PV, PSA, 
Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, PVR volume, IIEF-5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Three stars </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Seven to nine stars indicated high quality, four to six stars middle quality and zero to three stars low quality. "N" indicates not applicable. 
Abbreviations: AUA, American Urological Association Symptom Index; BPH, benign prostatic hyperplasia; IIEF-5, International Index of Erectile Function; IPSS, International Prostate Symptom Score; LUTS, lower urinary tract </p>

<p>symptoms; PSA, prostate-specific antigen; PV, prostate volume; PVR, postvoid residual; Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, peak urinary flow rate; QoL, quality of life. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1613 </p>

<p>Prostate artery embolization for benign prostatic hyperplasia </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>Figure 2 A forest plot about IPSS changes after PAE at postoperative 1 month (A), 6 months (B), 12 months (C), and 24 months (D). 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; IPSS, International Prostate Symptom Score; IV, intravenous; PAE, prostate artery embolization; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1614 </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>Figure 3 A forest plot about QoL score changes after PAE at postoperative 1 month (A), 6 months (B), 12 months (C), and 24 months (D). 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; IV, intravenous; PAE, prostate artery embolization; SD, standard deviation; QoL, quality of life. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1615 </p>

<p>Prostate artery embolization for benign prostatic hyperplasia </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>Figure 4 A forest plot about PV changes after PAE at postoperative 1 month (A), 6 months (B), 12 months (C), and 24 months (D). 
Note: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Using the fixed-effects model. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; IV, intravenous; PAE, prostate artery embolization; PV, prostate volume; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1616 </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>Figure 5 A forest plot about PSA changes after PAE at postoperative 1 month (A), 6 months (B), 12 months (C), and 24 months (D). 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; IV, intravenous; PAE, prostate artery embolization; PSA, prostate-specific antigen; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1617 </p>

<p>Prostate artery embolization for benign prostatic hyperplasia </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>Figure 6 A forest plot about Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>changes after PAE at postoperative 1 month (A), 6 months (B), 12 months (C), and 24 months (D). </p>

<p>Note: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Using the fixed-effects model. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; IV, intravenous; PAE, prostate artery embolization; SD, standard deviation; Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, peak urinary flow rate. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1618 </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>Figure 7 A forest plot about PVR volume changes after PAE at postoperative 1 month (A), 6 months (B), 12 months (C), and 24 months (D). 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; IV, intravenous; PAE, prostate artery embolization; PVR, postvoid residual; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1619 </p>

<p>Prostate artery embolization for benign prostatic hyperplasia </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>Figure 8 A forest plot about IIEF-5 score changes after PAE at postoperative 1 month (A), 6 months (B), 12 months (C), and 24 months (D). 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; IIEF-5, International Index of Erectile Function; IV, intravenous; PAE, prostate artery embolization; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Compared with baseline, PVR volume had significant 
decreases at postoperative 1 month (WMD −56.23, 95% 
CI −76.02 to −36.34, P,0.00001), 6 months (WMD −66.82, 
95% CI −89.34 to −44.29, P,0.00001), 12 months 
(WMD −82.69, 95% CI −113.64 to −51.74, P,0.00001) and 
24 months (WMD −49.07, 95% CI −97.67 to −0.47, P=0.05). </p>

<p>IIEF-5 scores </p>

<p>Nine studies involving 609 participants, eight studies involv-
ing 463 participants, six studies involving 372 participants 
and three studies involving 102 participants included data 
representing IIEF-5 score changes at postoperative 1 month 
(Figure 8A), 6 months (Figure 8B), 12 months (Figure 8C) 
and 24 months (Figure 8D), respectively. 
Compared with baseline, the IIEF-5 scores were slightly 
increased at postoperative 1 month (WMD 0.49, 95% </p>

<p>CI −0.30-1.28), but the difference was not statistically 
significant (P=0.23). There were significant increases at 
postoperative 6 months (WMD 1.29, 95% CI 0.48-2.10, 
P=0.002) and 12 months (WMD 1.36, 95% CI 0.69-2.02, 
P,0.0001). However, a slight decrease turned up at postop-
erative 24 months (WMD −0.81, 95% CI −2.08-0.46), which 
was not statistically significant (P=0.21). </p>

<p>Changes after PAE on large volume 
(PV $80 mL) BPH </p>

<p>Four studies, involving 179 participants, included data rep-
resenting changes in the large volume BPH (PV.80 mL). </p>

<p>9-12   All the results matched the earlier findings, except that PSA 
had no obvious decrease during the 3-month follow-up and 
that the IIEF-5 scores had no significant changes during 
the 12-month follow-up. The comparison of changes after </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>Table 2 Comparison of changes after PAE on large volume (PV $80 </p>

<p>mL) BPH with baseline </p>

<p>9-12 </p>

<p>Variables 
1 month </p>

<p>3 months </p>

<p>6 months </p>

<p>12 months </p>

<p>MD (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value 
MD (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value 
MD (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value 
MD (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>IPSSs </p>

<p>−15.97 (−17.25 to </p>

<p>−14.68) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−17.97 (−19.00 to </p>

<p>−16.94) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−18.61 (−19.74 to </p>

<p>−17.48) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−18.32 (−19.54 to </p>

<p>−17.09) </p>

<p>,0.00001 </p>

<p>Qol scores </p>

<p>−2.51 (−2.74 to </p>

<p>−2.29) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−2.64 (−3.30 to </p>

<p>−1.98) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−2.45 (−3.10 to </p>

<p>−1.80) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−2.50 (−2.83 to </p>

<p>−2.17) </p>

<p>,0.00001 </p>

<p>PV </p>

<p>−13.11 (−20.63 to </p>

<p>−5.60) </p>

<p>0.0006 
−43.39 (−49.92 to </p>

<p>−36.85) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−47.05 (−53.50 to </p>

<p>−40.60) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−47.58 (−53.94 to </p>

<p>−41.21) </p>

<p>,0.00001 </p>

<p>PSA 
−0.23 (−1.21 to 0.74) </p>

<p>0.64 </p>

<p>−0.45 (−1.41 to </p>

<p>−0.52) </p>

<p>0.36 </p>

<p>−0.74 (−1.15 to </p>

<p>−0.33) </p>

<p>0.0004 
−0.42 (−0.82 to </p>

<p>−0.03) </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>5.42 (4.73 to 6.12) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
6.66 (5.9 to 7.43) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
7.00 (5.95 to 8.05) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
6.00 (5.14 to 6.86) </p>

<p>,0.00001 </p>

<p>PVR volume </p>

<p>−76.64 (−84.98 to </p>

<p>−68.29) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−82.73 (−91.10 to </p>

<p>−74.36) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−88.35 (−96.39 to </p>

<p>−80.31) </p>

<p>,0.00001 
−76.80 (−121.87 to </p>

<p>−31.72) </p>

<p>0.0008 </p>

<p>IIEF-5 scores 
−0.04 (−1.31 to 1.22) </p>

<p>0.95 
−0.65 (−1.93 to 3.23) </p>

<p>0.62 
0.85 (−1.70 to 3.41) </p>

<p>0.51 
−0.24 (−5.12 to 4.63) </p>

<p>0.92 </p>

<p>Note: Data from Isaacson et al, </p>

<p>9   Bagla et al, </p>

<p>10   Li et al, </p>

<p>11   and Wang et al. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BPH, benign prostatic hyperplasia; CI, confidence interval; IIEF-5, International Index of Erectile Function; IPSS, International Prostate Symptom Score; MD, mean difference; PAE, prostate artery embolization; PSA, 
prostate-specific antigen; PV, prostate volume; PVR, postvoid residual; Q </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>, peak urinary flow rate; QoL, quality of life. </p>

<p>PAE on large volume (PV $80 mL) BPH with baseline is 
presented in Table 2. </p>

<p>Complications </p>

<p>There were no life-threatening complications. Only one 
serious adverse event was seen in the study by Pisco et 
al: 
14 a case of a small area (1.5 cm 
2 ) of bladder wall isch-
emia in the right side of the base without involvement of 
the urethra or urethral orifices. The area of ischemia at 
the bladder base was removed by surgery without further 
complications. 
Burning sensation in urethra (87/840, 10.4%) dur-
ing the procedure seemed to be the main complication. 
Hematuria occurred in 57/840 (6.8%) participants, hema-
tospermia in 49/840 (5.8%), a small rectal bleeding in 
38/840 (4.5%) and inguinal hematoma in 16/840 (1.9%). 
All these complications disappeared spontaneously 
without any treatment. In all, 21/840 (2.9%) participants 
developed urinary tract infection and all responded to 
suitable antibiotics. A total of 80/840 (9.5%) participants 
had acute urinary retention (AUR) at 1-3 days after PAE. 
For relief, a temporary bladder catheter was placed, and 
they were able to void spontaneously before discharge. 
There were no cases of sexual impotence or retrograde 
ejaculation. Complications reported in the eligible studies 
are presented in Table 3. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>PAE was first utilized in the 1970s to treat refractory bleeding 
following prostatic interventions as well as for intractable 
hematuria. 
15 It demonstrated a successful reduction in PV 
without serious complications in human beings in 2010. </p>

<p>2   The rationale for PAE is that prostate ischemia leads to PV 
reduction and hence clinical improvement. </p>

<p>16   In this meta-analysis, compared with baseline, there were 
significant improvements in the IPSSs (−12.74 points), QoL 
scores (−2.07 points), PV (−17.33 mL), PSA (−0.80 ng/mL), 
Q max (+4.4 mL/s) and PVR volume (−56.23 mL) after PAE 
at postoperative 1 month. It implied that PAE could take 
effect quickly. Furthermore, the IPSSs (−15.62 points), QoL 
scores (−2.15 points), Q max (+5.89 mL/s) and PVR volume 
(−49.07 mL) still had significant improvements during the 
24-month follow-up, suggesting that PAE had good control 
of symptoms within 2 years. 
For PV and PSA, significant decreases were found during 
the 12-month follow-up, but not at postoperative 24 months. 
We thought that the effect of PAE cannot be maintained in 
the long-term period. Besides prostate size increasing with </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1621 </p>

<p>Prostate artery embolization for benign prostatic hyperplasia </p>

<p>Table 3 Complications reported in the eligible studies </p>

<p>Studies 
Sample 
size </p>

<p>Complications </p>

<p>Urethral 
burning </p>

<p>Urinary tract 
infection </p>

<p>Hematuria 
Hematospermia 
Rectal 
bleeding </p>

<p>AUR 
Inguinal 
hematoma </p>

<p>Gabr et al </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>22 
15 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
Bilhim et al </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>186 
0 
1 
14 
15 
10 
9 
6 
Wang et al </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>47 
10 
0 
6 
4 
4 
16 
3 
Wang et al </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>100 
12 
0 
8 
8 
7 
9 
3 
Isaacson et al </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>12 
0 
1 
1 
1 
0 
1 
0 
Bagla et al </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>78 
0 
1 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 
li et al </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>22 
8 
0 
3 
2 
3 
7 
0 
Wang et al </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>109 
19 
0 
11 
9 
8 
31 
3 
Pisco et al </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>250 
23 
19 
14 
10 
6 
6 
0 
Pisco et al </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>14 
0 
2 
0 
0 
0 
1 
0 
Total 
840 
87 
24 
57 
49 
38 
80 
16 </p>

<p>Abbreviation: AUR, acute urinary retention. </p>

<p>age, revascularization of the prostatic arteries after PAE 
may play a role in prostate regrowth. Pisco et al 
13 observed 
this kind of revascularization in their patients with second 
PAE. Interestingly, the IPSSs still had a significant decrease 
despite prostatic enlargement at postoperative 24 months. 
This may suggest that physical reduction of the obstructing 
tissue was not the only reason for the improvement in LUTS 
after PAE. 
In terms of the IIEF-5 scores, there was no significant 
increase until 6 months after PAE. The epidemiological 
evidence had suggested a clear and clinically meaningful 
association between LUTS and sexual dysfunction that 
was independent of age and comorbidity. 
17 Along with the 
continuous improvement in LUTS, the IIEF-5 scores started 
to increase. 
In addition, patients with large volume (PV $80 mL) 
BPH are often elderly and may have severe comorbidi-
ties. They have increased operative risk of undergoing 
TURP/open surgery or refuse any surgical treatment. 
18 In 
this meta-analysis, for large volume (PV $80 mL) BPH, 
there were significant improvements in the IPSSs (−18.32 
points), QoL scores (−2.50 points), PV (−47.58 mL), 
Q max (+6.00 mL/s) and PVR volume (−76.80 mL) after PAE 
during the 12-month follow-up, and there were no life-
threatening complications. PAE does offer the ability to treat 
BPH in these patients, due to its minimally invasive nature 
with low morbidity and the possibility to use local anesthetic 
without sedation. </p>

<p>8   Subsequent studies have further compared the clinical 
outcome of PAE versus TURP. Carnevale et al 
19 reported 
that both groups experienced significant improvement in 
IPSS, QoL, PV, and Q max during the 12-month follow-up. 
TURP resulted in significantly higher Q max and smaller PV </p>

<p>than PAE but required spinal anesthesia and hospitalization, 
while IIEF scores were significantly higher in the PAE group. 
Gao et al 
20 reported a similar result during the 24-month 
follow-up, except that the PAE group showed more compli-
cations, mostly related to AUR (25.9%), postembolization 
syndrome (11.1%) and treatment failures (5.3% technical; 
9.4% clinical). 
Nevertheless, there are some limitations to our 
analysis. The major limitations include heterogeneity in 
the participants chosen, different materials and sizes of 
embolic agents and bilateral or unilateral embolization. 
The subgroup and sensitivity analysis or a random-effects 
model might reduce these limitations, but cannot eliminate. 
Additionally, the sample sizes of some included studies 
were small, and there was no long-term follow-up study. 
Data in the studies covered by this meta-analysis are 
insufficient to determine whether or not PAE is as good 
as TURP. Stratified trials with high volume and long 
follow-up time are awaited to strengthen the evidence and 
to update our findings. 
PAE is an effective, safe and well-tolerable treatment for 
LUTS related to BPH, including large volume (PV $80 mL) 
BPH, with good short-term follow-up. Studies with large 
number of cases and longer follow-up time are needed to 
validate our results. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/clinical-interventions-in-aging-journal </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging is an international, peer-reviewed journal 
focusing on evidence-based reports on the value or lack thereof of treatments 
intended to prevent or delay the onset of maladaptive correlates of aging 
in human beings. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine, </p>

<p>CAS, Scopus and the Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript 
management system is completely online and includes a very quick and fair 
peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress. 
com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1622 </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>



</text></tei>