<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5131455" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>As a result of rapid economic growth over the previous three decades, China has become the second largest 
economy worldwide since 2010. However, as a developing country with the largest population, this rapid 
economic growth primarily based on excessive consumption and waste of resources. Thus, China has been 
facing particularly severe ecological and environmental problems in speeding up industrialization and 
urbanization. The impact of the health risk factors is complex and difficult to accurately predict. Therefore, it 
is critical to investigate potential threats in the context of the human-animal-environment interface to protect 
human and animal health. The ''One Health'' concept recognizes that human health is connected to animal 
and environmental health. This review primarily discusses specific health problems in China, particularly 
zoonoses, and explains the origin and development of the One Health approach, as well as the importance of 
a holistic approach in China. </p>

<p>with the rapid growth of both the population and the 
national economy. </p>

<p>Impact on environmental health 
Worse situation of forest and wetland 
Anthropogenic activities and their impacts, including 
agricultural encroachment, deforestation, road construction, 
dam building, irrigation, wetland modification, mining, the 
concentration or expansion of urban environments, and 
coastal zone degradation (5), have necessitated more 
contact and interactions among humans, domestic ani-
mals, wildlife, and undeveloped environments. These 
activities cause changes that threaten the capacity and 
resilience of ecosystems. 
Currently, forest coverage is only 21.6% in China, 
whereas the global average is 31.0%, which indicates that 
the per capita forest area in China is only approximately 
one-quarter of the world average. The forest volume in 
China is 89 m 3 per hectare, whereas it is 300 m 3 per hectare 
in the developed countries in Europe. The forest area in 
China is only one-seventh of the world's average level (6). 
With accelerated urbanization and industrialization, the 
ecological restoration space has further been reduced. 
Additionally, in the past 5 years, illegal construction has 
consumed more than 2 million acres of woodland every 
year, and half of this woodland area had forest coverage. 
Serious land reclamation issues in the local areas create 
pressure and challenges in reforestation and ecological 
restoration overload. According to the Ministry of Land 
and Resources of the People's Republic of China, the 
number of lakes has been reduced to 34% since the 1950s, 
whereas the number of rivers has been reduced by appro-
ximately 30,000, and the wetland loss rate has increased 
up to 21.6% in the previous 50 years (7). Many main 
wetlands have suffered from severe eutrophication, which 
leads to loss of wildlife habitat. Thus, wildlife or other 
domestic animals were compelled to migrate, which may 
increase human exposure to new pathogens that threaten 
public health. </p>

<p>Environmental pollution 
With the fast-paced urbanization and increased energy 
consumption in modern China, the level of water, soil, and 
air pollution resulting from industry, heavy traffic, power 
generation, and coal smoke has been increasing at an 
alarming rate (8). According to the statistics of the En-
vironmental Protection Department in 2013, the national 
wastewater emission was 69.54 billion tons, sulfur dioxide 
emission was 20.44 million tons, nitrogen oxide emission 
was 22.27 million tons, and the national industrial solid 
waste was 3.28 billion tons. (9). The Ministry of Land and 
Resources reported that the country has 3.33 million 
hectares of contaminated farmland that cannot be used 
for any constructive purpose (10). The report from The 
Situation of Urban Living Garbage Management Survey 
indicated that urban garbage has increased from 25.08 </p>

<p>million tons in 1979 to 170.81 million tons in 2012. 
According to The National Soil Pollution Condition Survey, 
reported by the Environmental Protection Depart-
ment and the Ministry of Land and Resources, the first 
investigation to assess the extent of soil pollution was 
conducted between April 2005 and December 2013, and 
suggested that the national soil condition was bleak. 
Nationally, soil in 16.2% of the whole landed area was 
polluted, with inorganic pollutants (e.g. cadmium, mercury, 
arsenic, copper, lead, chromium, zinc, and nickel) and 
organic pollutants (e.g. DDT and polycyclic aromatic 
hydrocarbons) contributing to 82.8 and 3.8%, respectively. 
These health risks have a serious influence on the quality 
of life of individuals with chronic exposure. 
Climate change is no longer a distant threat (11). 
Global warming has been the most obvious phenomenon 
in countries all around the world. Warmer temperatures 
and extreme weather events reduce agricultural produc-
tion and also directly affect human health through various 
diseases, such as heat-related disorders, mental health 
problems, vector-borne diseases, food-borne and water-
borne diseases, and respiratory and allergic disorders (12). 
Relevant environmental regulations and laws have not yet 
solved air pollution in China, and the long-term effects of 
these measures remain obscure (13). 
Furthermore, China has been labeled 'the largest green-
house gases emitter and serious polluter in the world' (14). 
In 2012, according to the World Resources Institute (15), 
globally the total carbon dioxide emission was 33.84 
billion tons, with carbon dioxide emission in China being 
9.31 billion tons compared with 5.12 billion tons in 
America. Coal is the main source of energy in China. It 
has been reported that coal constitutes 67% of the total 
energy consumption in China, which accounted for half of 
the world's total coal consumption in 2012 (16). Addition-
ally, the number of private vehicles has increased rapidly 
from 1.36 million in 1978 to 109.33 million in 2012 (17), 
and the greenhouse gases emission in China accounted 
for 57.7% of the total greenhouse gases emission globally 
(18). In recent years, the grave air pollution in China has 
attracted worldwide attention. According to the WHO, 
16 of the 20 worst polluted cities worldwide are located 
in China. The negative impact of this serious pollution 
situation in China is the same or still worse than that of the 
SARS epidemic in 2003 (13), which in turn may increase 
the risk of health problems in the populace, including 
cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases (19, 20). </p>

<p>Impact on animal health 
Wildlife 
Human activities and their impacts, such as hunting and 
wildlife trade, the introduction of foreign species, urba-
nization, ecological tourism, construction of transporta-
tion infrastructure, climate change, pollution, and habitat 
destruction (5, 21Á23), have direct or indirect impacts on </p>

<p>Jianyong Wu et al. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Infection Ecology and Epidemiology 2016, 6: 33843 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/iee.v6.33843 </p>

<p>wildlife. These impacts include changes in behavior, 
population, distribution, community structure, reproduc-
tive capacity, biodiversity, and so on. 
Private possession drives illegal wildlife trade in China. 
Wildlife resource demands have rapidly increased because 
of the high profits in wildlife businesses, especially with 
regard to conservation and endangered species. Under the 
lure of high profits, some individuals illegally hunt and sell 
wildlife. For example, the number of Tibetan antelopes 
decreased from 200,000 to 20,000 in the 1980s because 
Tibetan antelope fur was much sought after in markets; 
thus, the species has become an internationally endan-
gered species. In addition, ecotourism endeavors, such as 
the highway in Changbai Mountain Nature Reserve's 
dense forest and the Qinghai-Tibet railway, has caused 
shrinkage and fragmentation of wildlife habitat, wildlife 
death, and changes in their migratory route, which has 
brought humans, domestic animals, and wild animals into 
close contact with each other and subsequently altered 
disease transmission. The role of wildlife in the transmis-
sion pathway of diseases has been described. 
Climate change and/or habitat loss is a primary mecha-
nism of biodiversity loss (24). Other factors have direct or 
indirect impact on biodiversity as well. According to the 
China Species Red List, which has recorded 10,211 species 
of animals (5,803) and plants (4,408), threatened inver-
tebrates, including critically endangered, endangered, 
and dangerous, accounts for 34.74%, compared with 
12.44% for threatened (nearly unstoppable). Threatened 
vertebrates account for 35.92%, whereas nearly unstop-
pable is 7.22%. Biodiversity loss plays a crucial role in the 
emergence and transmission of infectious diseases (22, 25, 
26). The 'dilution effect' holds that biological diversity 
inhibits infectious diseases (27), which means that biodi-
versity loss may increase disease risks to humans. </p>

<p>Poultry, domestic animals, and pets 
The demand for meat, eggs, and milk has rapidly in-
creased because of the improved living conditions in 
China. According to 'Meat Consumption in China Now 
Double That in the United States', which was reported by 
the Earth Policy Institute, China's meat consumption was 
one-third of the US consumption in 1978. However, by 
1992, China had exceeded the United States as the 
world's leading meat consumer. China's current annual 
meat consumption is more than double the consumption 
of United States. China's meat consumption continues 
to increase, whereas the corresponding data for the 
United States is showing a decline. Currently, China's 
per capita meat consumption is half of the United States; 
if it reaches the same level as that of the United States, 
China will end up consuming three-quarters of the beef 
and 80% of the chicken produced globally (28). 
To meet the demand for meat, the animal husbandry 
industry has been unprecedentedly developed in China. </p>

<p>Livestock production currently accounts for 40% of the 
gross value of agricultural production in China (29). 
However, livestock and poultry rearing have become the 
second largest sources of pollution, immediately behind 
industries. One example is that of the substantial blue-
green algae bloom in Tai Lake, which contaminated the 
drinking water of millions of people; ultimately, animal 
husbandry is also considered a main source of pollution. 
It was reported that domestic wastewater was the main 
source of pollution in the Yangtze Delta, followed by 
pollution from raising livestock and poultry, and indus-
trial wastewater. Pigs and poultry produced approxi-
mately 90% of the total pollutants related to animal 
husbandry. It has been reported that the daily discharge of 
sewage from one pig is equivalent to wastewater from 
seven humans, and 100 pigs produce 10,000 to approxi-
mately 30,000 tons of sewage each year, including 107 tons 
of nitrogen and 31 tons of phosphorus, which drain off 
into soil and are subsequently converted to nitrate and 
phosphate, which in turn pollute both soil and water (30). 
A substantial number of odorous gases produced by poul-
try rearing, which contain many poisonous and harmful 
ingredients, such as ammonia, sulfur, and methane, nega-
tively impact the air quality. In addition, the feces of 
livestock and poultry contain a substantial number of 
pathogenic microorganisms, including parasites that may 
spread zoonotic infectious diseases. 
Pathogens carried by pets have gradually aroused public 
concern (31). Presently, the number of pets is substantial, 
and the species are also diverse. In addition to traditional 
pets, such as dogs and cats, there are also other rare species, 
such as guinea pigs, lizards, and other wildlife, which 
become members of the family. It was reported that the 
total number of pets had reached 150 million in a span 
of 10 years (2003Á2013), an increase of 900% during the 
said period, and the pet economy has reached a staggering 
¥90 billion (32). Direct contact with pets may lead to 
transmission of infectious diseases. Furthermore, the num-
ber of stray pets has further increased, and its carrying 
rate of viruses, bacteria, and parasites is higher than 
domestic pets. Humans may be infected with rabies, 
toxoplasmosis, leptospirosis, or salmonella disease via 
contact or by being bitten (33). </p>

<p>Impact on human health 
Zoonosis 
Zoonosis has comprised an increasing share of global 
public health events since the 21st century. Economic 
globalization, the development of the tourism industry, 
population growth, and environmental changes (including 
agricultural intensification, climate change, and biodi-
versity) objectively intensify the spread of diseases (34Á36). 
It not only causes a serious threat to human health but also 
harms the development of animal husbandry, affects the </p>

<p>Challenges and research priority on one health in China </p>

<p>Citation: Infection Ecology and Epidemiology 2016, 6: 33843 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/iee.v6.33843 </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>quality and safety of animal production, and leads to 
economic losses. </p>

<p>Epidemiological situation of zoonosis 
It has been reported that 1,415 species of infectious 
organisms have been identified to be pathogenic to 
humans. Among these organisms, 868 are zoonotic, which 
may be transmitted between humans and animals (37). 
Of the emerging pathogens, 132 pathogens (75%) are 
zoonotic, and zoonotic pathogens are twice as likely to be 
associated with emerging diseases compared with non-
zoonotic pathogens (38). There are 43 infectious diseases, 
such as SARS, MERS, H5N1, H7N9, Ebola, and Mar-
burg that have newly emerged worldwide since the 1970s 
(39, 40). Twenty of these diseases were found in China. 
In addition, reemerging diseases, such as rabies, pulmon-
ary tuberculosis, and brucellosis, cause additional threats 
to humans. 
Wild animals are substantial natural reservoirs of patho-
gens (23, 37, 41, 42). Approximately 71.8% of zoonotic 
events occurring in humans can be traced to wildlife (43), 
including AIDS, avian flu, plague, foot and mouth dis-
ease, rabies, and dengue fever. Wildlife resources are very 
abundant in China where more than 5,300 types of 
vertebrates live (44). These wildlife species differ in their 
habits and also exist in diverse living environments, and 
the pathogens they carry are complex, which in turn forms 
a substantial natural pathogen reservoir. Generally, in-
fected wild animals may not exhibit symptoms; however, 
they can transmit the pathogens to humans via specific 
mechanisms. Living environments, such as high-density 
breeding, make contact between captive wild animals 
and humans easier, which in turn increases the chance 
of cross-infection. For example, the avian influenza virus 
H7N9 has emerged with the capacity of cross-species 
infection; humans would get infected via exposure to the 
asymptomatic avian influenza virus and then exhibit a 
high fatality rate (45). Thus, the frequent trade of wildlife 
and its products has also increased the risk of infection, 
which clearly threatens public health. </p>

<p>Hazard of zoonosis 
The features of emerging infectious diseases are as 
follows: a wider range of hosts, enhanced virulence during 
human infections, smaller regional differences, concealing 
of infected animals, rapid transmission rate, and higher 
morbidity and mortality. H5N1 has posed significant 
threats to both humans and animals since it re-emerged in 
South China in 1996, which caused an outbreak in goose 
in Guangdong Province. In 1997, 18 H5N1 patients were 
reported in Hong Kong, and six of them died (46Á49). By 
the end of 2014, there were 42 human infections, with 
27 fatalities, which indicated the mortality rate had 
increased to 64% (50). It has been reported that 5,327 
cases with 349 deaths occurred in mainland China during 
the 2003 worldwide SARS epidemic (51). In 2009, the </p>

<p>outbreak of H1N1 caused 164,902 cases and 878 deaths in 
China (50, 52, 53). Since the first human H7N9 cases were 
reported in Guangdong Province in February 2013, up to 
April 2016, 750 confirmed human cases and 314 deaths 
have been reported. This could possibly be an even worse 
threat than H1N1because H7N9 is a low pathogenic avian 
influenza virus. All pandemics so far have been caused by 
low pathogenic viruses, and not by high pathogenic viruses 
(54). In 2014, severe dengue fever outbreaks occurred, 
which posed a substantial socioeconomic burden, with 
46,864 cases being reported nationwide (50). 
Furthermore, resurging infectious diseases also threa-
ten humans and animals. There were only 159 rabies cases 
in 1996 in China. The reappearance of the rabies epide-
mic has been continuous and became a rapid growth trend 
in the early 21st century. There were 2,000 rabies cases 
in 2003, whereas there were 3,300 deaths in 2007; the 
fatality rate is nearly 100%, and the rabies situation in 
China remains severe. Additionally, there are 4.99 million 
tuberculosis cases nationwide, and this incidence rate is 
the second highest worldwide (55). There are also appro-
ximately 1 million new cases of tuberculosis in China, 
which is in the forefront of infectious diseases in China. 
Emerging and resurging infectious diseases appear to 
be a major public health problem, which calls for an in-
terdisciplinary and holistic approach to respond to, 
identify, and manage the disease outbreaks rapidly. </p>

<p>Food safety and security 
Globalization has triggered an increasing consumer 
demand for a wide variety of foods, which has resulted 
in an increasingly complex and longer global food chain, 
especially regarding animal products. Although corre-
sponding laws and regulations have been implemented to 
control food safety issues, massive food safety events have 
been frequently exposed. Examples include the contam-
ination of infant formula by melamine in 2008, which 
affected 300,000 infants and young children in China, 
including six children who died (www.who.int/media 
centre/factsheets/fs399/en/). 
The factors that cause food safety events include 
zoonoses (e.g. viruses, bacteria, and parasites), chemical 
pollutants (persistent organic pollutants), heavy metals, 
food additives, pesticide residues, and drug residues. 
Chemical fertilizers, pesticides, drugs, and growth-regulating 
agents originally had a substantial potential for food security 
problems. Around 0.5Á0.6 million tons of pesticides are 
used in farm crops every year, and 80% of these pesticides 
directly enter the environment. Organophosphorus and 
organochlorine are left in animal meat because it is dif-
ficult to be decomposed and are thus eventually trans-
mitted to humans (56). Zeng's study in 2012 demonstrated 
that fish in the South China Sea contained DDT, which 
was banned in 1985 (57). To prevent disease and promote 
growth, farmers use many antibiotics and hormone drugs, </p>

<p>Jianyong Wu et al. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Infection Ecology and Epidemiology 2016, 6: 33843 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/iee.v6.33843 </p>

<p>which cause resistance in animal food. In addition, the 
abusive use of food additives in food processing remains 
common. Currently, 22 types of 1,812 class food additives 
in China are used illegally and cause potential threats to 
human health. 
According to China's food safety public opinion report 
blue book, there were 1,942 food safety events in 2012, 
and 20,000 to 40,000 food poisoning cases occurred 
every year. Food poisoning caused by microorganisms 
accounted for 37.7% of total number of cases (www. 
nhfpc.gov.cn/zwgkzt/tjnj/list.shtml). </p>

<p>Antibiotic resistance 
Antimicrobials are essential to treat bacterial infection 
(58Á61). However, antibiotics abuse in both veterinary 
and human medicine has led to the emergence and spread 
of resistant bacteria, which bring about challenges to 
prevent and control diseases. According to the statistics 
of the China Pharmaceutical Industry Association, there 
are 210,000 tons of drug raw materials produced each 
year, including 97,000 tons used in the livestock industry. 
Overall, China has become one of the countries world-
wide with a major issue of bacterial resistance. The 
most serious consequence of drug abuse is the emergence 
of superbugs. Resistant bacteria enter the food chain 
through animals (e.g. Salmonella through chickens) and 
are subsequently transmitted to humans. In addition, 
antimicrobial resistance is one of the main threats to 
modern medicine. 
Bacterial resistance in animals may spread to humans, 
and the consequences are unimaginable. It is predicted 
that China will have 1 million human fatalities annually 
because of antibiotic resistance, and the economic losses 
would be as much as $20 trillion by 2050 (62), whereas in 
the United States, an excess of $20 billion would be spent 
on direct healthcare annually (63). </p>

<p>Chronic non-communicable diseases 
The chronic, non-communicable diseases caused by en-
vironmental changes are clear. Accumulating evidence 
suggests that air pollution is linked with an increased risk 
of cancers, including lung cancer, breast cancer, and 
bladder cancer (64). Data from the Global Burden of 
Disease Study showed that, in 2010, air pollution led to 
more than 1.3 million premature deaths in China (64), the 
highest among 15 countries (65). Also, cities, such as 
Beijing, have been described as 'uninhabitable for human 
beings' (13). </p>

<p>Impact on social economy 
Zoonoses have negative impacts on China's economy. 
The outbreak of SARS led to a total loss of $25.3 billion 
to China's economy, and a 1Á2% decrease in the growth 
rate of China's gross domestic product in 2003 (66). The 
emergence of the highly pathogenic avian influenza 
H5N1 virus in late 2003 has resulted in 140 million </p>

<p>poultry deaths and at least 92 human fatalities; it is 
reported to have cost the poultry industry US$10 billion 
in Asia (67). The outbreak of H5N1 in Hong Kong 
resulted in 1.5 million poultry being slaughtered in 1997. 
Since the first H7N9 human cases appeared in China 
in 2003, the economic loss of the poultry industry was 
more than ¥40 billion by the end of June 2013. The global 
outbreak of H1N1 has added to the problem of an 
oversupply of pork in China, and the price of pork had 
fallen sharply because of the H1N1 outbreak, resulting in 
huge economic losses of intensive industry. To treat the 
MERS patients who came from Korea, it has cost more 
than ¥8 million within 15 days in the Guangdong Province. </p>

<p>One Health practice in China </p>

<p>Development of One Health in China 
and initial success 
Faculties from the School of Public Health at Sun Yat-sen 
University and other research institutes are devoted to 
promoting the One Health approach in China. In 2014, an 
International Symposium on One Health Research was 
held in Guangzhou city (68); it was jointly hosted by Sun 
Yat-sen University, South China Agricultural University, 
the Academy of Military Medical Sciences, and Duke 
University. The conference topic was 'zoonosis, food 
safety and security, environment science, wildlife ecology, 
and antibiotics resistance'. Four Chinese academicians 
were invited to speak at the meeting. In addition, experts 
from America, Australia, Singapore, and other countries 
also attended. Two hundred international delegates in-
volved in the disciplines of public health, clinical medicine, 
veterinary medicine, and environmental and agricultural 
science, from more than seven countries, discussed the 
complex interactions between human health; livestock, 
pet, and wildlife health; and environmental health during 
the 2-day conference. 
The meeting provided a platform for international 
cooperation and established the first One Health web-
site, 'One Earth, One World, One Health' (www. 
healthonly.cn/sunshine.asp?a_id0253), which promotes 
the development of One Health in China. The initial 
success of One Health in China is as follows: 
First, with the help of the Zhongshan CDC, Guangzhou 
CDC, and animal husbandry and veterinary departments, 
Sun Yat-sen University and Duke University conducted 
a study of 'the relationship between occupational popula-
tion and influenza virus infection'. The findings indicated 
that in terms of H3N2 infection, the risk for occupational 
individuals is 3.4 times higher than community residents, 
which suggested that occupational exposure may be a risk 
factor for H3N2 (69). Second, professor LU chose rural 
areas in Henan Province as the research field and con-
ducted a baseline rabies investigation. Based on the base-
line, a specific community intervention model of One </p>

<p>Challenges and research priority on one health in China </p>

<p>Citation: Infection Ecology and Epidemiology 2016, 6: 33843 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/iee.v6.33843 </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Health was formulated to analyze the residents exposed to 
rabies. The findings indicated that with the implementa-
tion of the One Health community intervention model, 
the rabies incidence in the residents decreased by 7.59% 
compared with the previous incidence, and community dog 
vaccination increased from 13.9 to 82.5%. Third, a study of 
dengue fever conducted by the Zhongshan CDC and 
veterinary departments together with the team of profes-
sor LU determined that a negative dengue infection is a 
potential factor in dengue fever outbreak. These findings 
indicated that One Health plays a vital role in disease 
prevention and control. This collaboration was beneficial, 
as it resulted in reduced risks, financial savings, reduced 
time to detect disease outbreaks, as well as improved plant 
health services. </p>

<p>Application of the One Health approach 
to address practical problems in China 
Although the first One Health forum was held in China 
in 2014, the following approach has been applied to 
address the practical problems in China for many years: a 
schistosomiasis control program, based on the integra-
tion of case detection, health education, and morbidity 
control in humans; environmental management, such as 
molluscicide treatment; and livestock and farm manage-
ment. Subsequently, costÁbenefit analysis showed that 
the schistosomiasis control program generated a societal 
benefit of $6.20 per $1 invested. Additionally, the current 
mechanism to counter emerging diseases has been a 
substantial improvement in China concerning collabora-
tion and cooperation, monitoring and decision-making, 
early warning system and organization since the SARS 
epidemic in 2003. This responding mechanism for emer-
ging diseases has enabled China to successfully counter 
H5N1, H1N1, and H7N9 (70). 
These examples suggest that interdisciplinary, cross-
sectional, and cross-department cooperation can not only 
protect human health but also prevent unnecessary eco-
nomic loss, and the loss reduction can be substantial. 
Additional benefits are likely to be generated through 
building new social contact networks and collaborative 
projects among multiple disciplines; however, it seems 
impossible to monetize these benefits. </p>

<p>Future research priorities </p>

<p>Food safety and security through the food production 
chain has been referred to as a 'farm-to-fork' issue, which 
is related to the different stages of food production (71), 
but often originates at the farm (72). Both wild and 
domestic animals are often regarded as sources of food 
contamination (73). For example, the general under-
standing is that the SARS epidemic in 2003 originated 
directly from human contact with and/or consumption of 
wildlife or indirectly through contact between wildlife 
and domestic animals (74, 75). </p>

<p>Each sector has its own responsibilities and priorities; 
thus, it is difficult to work together if there is no common 
understanding or mutual interest. However, food safety 
and security is a good example of the intricate link 
between humans, animals, and the surrounding environ-
ment. The question arises as to why we should first apply 
One Health in food safety. First, it is the central issue that 
many sectors pay more attention to, and One Health 
clearly formulates the benefits of cross-sectoral collabora-
tions and sharing of data. Second, the experience of 
cross-sectoral collaboration already exists in this field. 
Finally, it involves food-borne diseases, zoonosis, and 
antimicrobial resistance, controlling of which may ensure 
food security and food safety. 
It is necessary to establish collaborations between 
human and veterinary medicine, food authorities, and 
environmental sectors, and these different sectors should 
collect data from both humans and animals. These data 
include the emerging and reemerging zoonotic pathogens 
(viruses, bacteria, and parasites) and the prevalence, 
variation, genomic data, and the life cycle of the natural 
reservoir, as well as antibiotic use and antibiotic sensi-
tivity. Moreover, a database is needed and should be 
available to scientists from different fields. One successful 
example in Denmark is an automated program referred 
to as <rs type="software">Vetstat</rs>, which has been introduced to collect quan-
titative data regarding all prescribed animal medicines 
from veterinarians, pharmacies, and feed mills to control 
microbial resistance (76). 
One Health mostly emphasized zoonosis in its early 
stage; however, in today's globalized world, it has shifted 
to a broad paradigm, including ecology, sustainable de-
velopment, economics, social justice, equity, and so on 
(77). For public health actors, a broader acceptance and 
understanding of One Health principles could influence 
their thought and values in practice. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Problems at the humanÁanimalÁenvironment interface 
have become acute and have involved resource waste, 
environmental disruption and pollution, biodiversity loss, 
food safety, antibiotic resistance, and emerging and re-
surging infectious diseases. These issues remind us that 
the health of humans, animals, and the ecosystem is 
closely interconnected. Addressing these problems at the 
interface requires collaborative, interdisciplinary, and 
cross-sectoral approaches. Using the One Health ap-
proach, the barriers between disciplines and sectors may 
be broken down and efforts to anticipate and combat 
serious challenges for the health of humans, animals, and 
the environment may be combined. </p>

<p>Authors' contributions </p>

<p>JYW and LLL contributed to the literature review and 
manuscript writing. JHL guided writing of the manuscript </p>

<p>Jianyong Wu et al. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Infection Ecology and Epidemiology 2016, 6: 33843 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/iee.v6.33843 </p>

<p>and provided the final approval of this version for 
publication. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We are indebted to Edward F. Fitzgerald for revising the language in 
this manuscript. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest and funding </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of 
interests. </p>





<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Infection Ecology and Epidemiology 2016, 6: 33843 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/iee.v6.33843 </p>

</text></tei>