<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5370249" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Linear measurements are mainly used to assess the 
thickness and height of the alveolar crest as part of the 
preoperative evaluation for implant treatment, to measure 
the distance between anatomical landmarks in orthodon-
tics and orthognathic surgery, and to estimate the size of 
pathological jaw lesions. The accuracy and reliability of 
linear measurements in cone-beam computed tomography 
(CBCT) images has been established in several published 
scientific studies, 
1,2-11 including studies where they have </p>

<p>been obtained from CBCT-derived models. </p>

<p>2,12 </p>

<p>Ostensibly, in imaging of the oral and maxillofacial </p>

<p>complex, spatial resolution is an important parameter of 
image quality that appears to be of special interest for 
dental applications. As available spatial resolution also 
determines the accuracy with which anatomic detail can 
be measured, it also affects important procedures, such as 
the planning of dental implants or cephalometric analysis. 
The spatial resolution of an image is directly influenced 
by the voxel size, which is the smallest unit in CBCT ima-
ges. 
13-16 To improve spatial resolution, the voxel size must </p>

<p>be reduced, 
17 and the CBCT images must be measured </p>

<p>accurately. However, spatial resolution is affected by mul-
tiple technical factors that make it difficult to predict from 
simple clues or to estimate from technical parameters. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>The presence of an increasing number of CBCT units on 
the market presents a need to understand and select from 
the various technical parameters. 
The impact of variation in voxel size on CBCT-based </p>

<p>Intraobserver and interobserver reproducibility in linear measurements on axial images 
obtained by cone-beam computed tomography </p>

<p>Nathália Cristine da Silva 
1 , Maurício Barriviera </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, José Luiz Cintra Junqueira 
1 , Francine Kühl Panzarella 
1 , </p>

<p>Ricardo Raitz 
1, * </p>

<p>1 São Leopoldo Mandic Research Center, Department of Oral Radiology, College of Dentistry, São Paulo, SP, Brazil 
2 Department of Oral Radiology, College of Dentistry, Catholic University of Brasilia, São Paulo, SP, Brazil </p>

<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Purpose: This study was performed to investigate the intra-and inter-observer variability in linear measurements 
with axial images obtained by PreXion (PreXion Inc., San Mateo, USA) and i-CAT (Imaging Sciences International, 
Xoran Technologies Inc., Hatfield, USA) CBCT scanners, with different voxel sizes. 
Materials and Methods: A cylindrical object made from nylon with radiopaque markers (phantom) was scanned 
by i-CAT and PreXion 3D devices. For each axial image, measurements were taken twice in the horizontal (distance 
A-B) and vertical (distance C-D) directions, randomly, with a one-week interval between measurements, by four 
oral radiologists with five years or more experience in the use of these measuring tools. 
Results: All of the obtained linear measurements had lower values than those of the phantom. The statistical analysis 
showed high intra-and inter-observer reliability (p = 0.297). Compared to the real measurements, the measurements 
obtained using the i-CAT device and PreXion tomography, on average, revealed absolute errors ranging from 0.22 
to 0.59 mm and from 0.23 to 0.63 mm, respectively. 
Conclusion: It can be concluded that both scanners are accurate, although the linear measurements are underesti-
mations, with no significant differences between the evaluators. (Imaging Sci Dent 2017; 47: 11-5) </p>

<p>KEY WORDS: Cone-Beam Computed Tomography; Dimensional Measurement Accuracy; Reproducibility of Results </p>

<p>Copyright ⓒ 2017 by Korean Academy of Oral and Maxillofacial Radiology </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Imaging Science in Dentistry·pISSN 2233-7822 eISSN 2233-7830 </p>

<p>Received May 23, 2016; Revised October 2, 2016; Accepted October 31, 2016 
*Correspondence to : Prof. Ricardo Raitz 
Rua Heitor Penteado, 1832, 101A, São Paulo, SP, Brazil, CEP 05438-300 
Tel) 55-11-35675208, Fax) 55-11-35675208, E-mail) ricardoraitz@ig.com.br </p>

<p>Intraobserver and interobserver reproducibility in linear measurements on axial images obtained by cone-beam computed tomography </p>



<p>diagnostics has been discussed. 
17 As the PreXion CBCT </p>

<p>device has a small voxel size and few studies 
18,19 have </p>

<p>evaluated it, this study investigated the intraobserver and 
interobserver variability in linear measurements with axi-
al images obtained by PreXion (PreXion Inc., San Mateo, 
CA, USA) and i-CAT (Imaging Sciences International, 
Xoran Technologies Inc., Hatfield, PA, USA), with differ-
ent voxel sizes. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>The phantom used for this study was based on that of a 
previous study. 
6 It was made from nylon, a slightly radi-</p>

<p>opaque material with a low thermal expansion coefficient, 
in a cylindrical shape (5 cm in diameter and 10 cm in 
length). It had 4 channels, each 1 mm in depth, arranged 
90° apart on the longitudinal axis of the cylinder, and 10 
channels, each with a depth of 1 mm, arranged transversely 
10 mm apart. 
The dimensional calibration of the phantom was per-
formed using the PML-0024 measuring procedure with 
a universal measuring machine (Mitutoyo Sul Americana 
Ltda, Suzano, São Paulo, Brazil) (Fig. 1), at room tem-
perature (20.0±0.5°C). The diameter of the phantom (the 
cylinder) was verified 4 times in 10 sections, as identified 
in the standard, in 2 coordinates, A/B and C/D, generating 
a report containing the resulting averages. The measure-
ment uncertainty was U = 0.01, based on a combined 
standard uncertainty, multiplied by a coverage factor of 
k = 2.3 for a confidence level of approximately 95%. The 
average values obtained by dimensional calibration of the 
phantom were considered the real measurements (the gold 
standard). 
To identify the "sections" of the phantom selected for </p>

<p>the experiment, zinc oxide and eugenol dotted portions 
were added at each channel intersection (Fig. 2), and the 
letters A, B, C, and D and the numbers 1 through 10 were 
applied for identification (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>After obtaining the real measurements, the phantom 
was scanned in the i-CAT device, following an image ac-
quisition protocol of a 6-cm × 16-cm field of view (FOV), 
20 seconds, and a 0.2-mm voxel size. In the PreXion de-
vice, the phantom was scanned following an image ac-
quisition protocol of 5-cm × 5-cm FOV, 19 seconds, and 
a 0.1-mm voxel size. Thereafter, multiplanar reformatting 
was performed, thereby obtaining axial sections with a 
thickness of 1.0 mm. The data were saved in the Digital 
Imaging and Communications in Medicine format using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Prexion3DViewer</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 2.4.1.20</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">PreXion Inc.</rs>., San Mateo, CA, USA) to measure the diameter of 
each axial image. 
The diameter of the phantom was measured in sections, 
using 2 coordinates (An/Bn and Cn/Dn) with numbers 
from 2 to 7, in the depth of the channel, that is, between </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The universal measuring machine. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Phantom image with the coordinates A1, B1, C1, and D1. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Identifying coordinates of the phantom. </p>



<p>Nathália Cristine da Silva et al </p>

<p>the "points" marked with zinc oxide and eugenol. This 
measurement was performed using a software tool. For 
each axial image, measurements were made in either hori-
zontal direction (the A-B distance) and in either vertical 
direction (the C-D distance), twice, with a 1-week interval, 
by 4 examiners (4 oral radiologists) with 5 years or more 
experience in the use of these measuring tools. All post-
processing procedures were carried out using the same 
software, <rs id="software-2" type="software">Prexion3DViewer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 2.4.1.20</rs>, and the im-
ages were visualized on a 24-inch LG E 2241 LCD moni-
tor with a matrix resolution of 1920 × 1080. The values of 
the 2 repetitions for each coordinate were entered into an 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">Excel</rs> spreadsheet (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Microsoft</rs>, Seattle, WA, USA), sepa-
rated by examiner, by scanner, by section, and by distance 
(A-B and C-D). 
Statistical analysis was applied to the collected data 
using <rs id="software-4" type="software">SPSS</rs> Statistics for Windows, (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">version 20.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA). Intraclass correlation coeffi-
cient (ICC) calculations were used to verify intraobserver 
and interobserver agreement and to compare the accuracy 
(reproducibility) of the i-CAT and PreXion CBCT with 
the real measurements (the gold standard). The linear mea-
surements (mm) were subjected to descriptive analysis 
to present the absolute and relative errors (in %) of the 
measurements performed on the acquisitions made with 
both CBCT machines in relation to the gold standard. The 
Student t-test was used to compare the scans to each other 
regarding the linear measurements. The significance level 
used for all tests was 5% (α = .05). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The ICC calculations revealed that the intra-observer 
agreement was excellent (ICC = 1.000) when comparing 
the linear measurements performed at the 2 image evalu-
ation stages, for both those obtained with the i-CAT scan-
ner and for those with the PreXion scanner, for the 4 ex-
aminers. </p>

<p>The inter-observer agreement when using the i-CAT or 
PreXion scanner was excellent (ICC = 1.000) in all com-
parisons between the 4 examiners. 
Table 1 presents the descriptive analysis, in terms of the 
mean, standard deviation, and absolute and relative errors 
(%) of the linear measurements (mm) of the cylindrical 
object (the phantom) obtained with the use of the i-CAT 
and PreXion computed tomography scanners. 
The measurements obtained in tomographic acquisition 
using the i-CAT device, on average, showed absolute er-
rors ranging from 0.22 mm to 0.59 mm when compared 
with the real measurements, which were underestimated. 
The linear measurements taken from acquisitions made 
with the PreXion scanner also underestimated the linear 
dimensions, with absolute errors ranging from 0.23 mm to 
0.63 mm. 
For the ICCs, it was found that with both scanners 
(i-CAT and PreXion), the accuracy of the linear measure-
ments compared to the real measurements (the gold 
standard) was excellent (Table 2). When comparing the 
CBCTs to each other, no significant difference was found 
(p = .297). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The use of CBCT technology to evaluate structures of 
the oral and maxillofacial complex increases the accuracy </p>

<p>Table 1. The means standard deviations and absolute and relative errors (%) of the linear measurements (mm) of the cylindrical object, ac-
cording to each examiner </p>

<p>Examiner 
i-CAT 
PreXion </p>

<p>Mean 
Absolute error* 
Relative error** 
Mean 
Absolute error* 
Relative error** </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>48.23 (0.11) 
48.59 (0.19) 
48.22 (0.10) 
48.25 (0.12) </p>

<p>-0.58 (0.20) 
-0.22 (0.26) 
-0.59 (0.20) 
-0.56 (0.23) </p>

<p>-1.19 (0.40) 
-0.45 (0.53) 
-1.21 (0.40) 
-1.15 (0.47) </p>

<p>48.23 (0.13) 
48.58 (0.14) 
48.18 (0.09) 
48.41 (0.12) </p>

<p>-0.53 (0.17) 
-0.23 (0.21) 
-0.63 (0.20) 
-0.40 (0.23) </p>

<p>-1.08 (0.34) 
-0.47 (0.42) 
-1.29 (0.41) 
-0.82 (0.46) </p>

<p>*: Obtained by subtracting the measurements derived from the use of each scanner from those designated as the gold standard, **: Obtained by the ratio of 
the absolute errors and the gold standard measures </p>

<p>Table 2. Agreement between the linear measurements obtained 
with the use of i-CAT and PreXion CBCT scanners and the real 
measurements (gold standard), according to each examiner </p>

<p>Examiner 
PreXion 
i-CAT </p>

<p>ICC 
Agreement 
ICC 
Agreement </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>1.000 
1.000 
1.000 
1.000 </p>

<p>Excellent 
Excellent 
Excellent 
Excellent </p>

<p>1.000 
1.000 
1.000 
1.000 </p>

<p>Excellent 
Excellent 
Excellent 
Excellent </p>

<p>ICC: intra-class correlation coefficient. </p>

<p>Intraobserver and interobserver reproducibility in linear measurements on axial images obtained by cone-beam computed tomography </p>



<p>and reliability of the measurements, because of its ability 
to manipulate the resulting digital data volumes across 
3 different views (sagittal, coronal, and axial) and to sel-
ectively contrast, emphasize, and reduce the images to 
view certain anatomical structures. 
20 This study evaluated </p>

<p>whether voxel size affected the intra-observer and inter-
observer variability of the linear measurements obtained 
from the axial images of 2 CBCT devices. 
In our study, the intra-observer and inter-observer agree-
ment values, when using the i-CAT or PreXion scanner, 
were excellent in all comparisons of the 4 examiners 
(ICC = 1.000), as shown in Tables 1 and 2. High interob-
server and intraobserver CBCT reliability was reported 
by Moshfeghi et al. 
11 and Kamburoğlu et al. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>, while in the 
study by Nikneshan et al. 
1 , reproducibility for all orienta-</p>

<p>tions was greater than 0.9. 
In a comparison of the different devices, it was found 
that there was no significant difference (p = .297) despite 
the difference between the voxel sizes (0.1 mm for the 
PreXion and 0.2 mm for the i-CAT). Lukat et al. 
21 have </p>

<p>already reported this result and emphasized that high spa-
tial resolution allows for the thorough detection of subtle 
structures, such as small changes in the cortical or the 
buccal bone of the temporomandibular joint. </p>

<p>3,5,22 </p>

<p>Measurements for preoperative implant site assessment 
taken from CBCT images should be considered accurate 
when the error was less than 1 mm. 
4,15 Owing to the me-</p>

<p>chanical construction of CBCT machines, which require 
a relatively slow trajectory of the source image detector 
unit around the patient's head, even slight patient move-
ment seems almost inevitable. Given the small voxel sizes 
applied in the machines, a slight movement of more than 
1 voxel will lead to errors in reconstruction. 
13 Therefore, </p>

<p>during clinical application, one should not expect greater 
accuracy than half a millimeter at best. If in doubt, users 
should avoid sub-millimeter accuracy and preferably add 
some margin of error to their planning. 
Table 1 shows the values of the measurements obtained 
using the i-CAT apparatus, on average, which produced 
absolute errors ranging from 0.22 mm to 0.59 mm com-
pared with the actual measurements, which were under-
estimated. As for the PreXion device, the measurements 
were lower than the actual linear dimensions, with ab-
solute error varying between 0.23 mm and 0.63 mm, in 
accordance with the results of the study from Waltrick et 
al. 
14 that reported mean absolute errors of 0.23±0.2 mm </p>

<p>using voxel sizes of 0.2 mm, 0.3 mm, and 0.4 mm. 
Using ICCs, it was found that the accuracy of the linear 
measurements versus the gold standard was excellent for </p>

<p>both devices (Table 2), although all linear measurements 
were underestimated by the examiners, corroborating the 
results of several studies described in the literature. </p>

<p>4,6,7,9-11,23 </p>

<p>In addition, thin bony structures of less than 0.5 mm in 
size are not relevant in actual clinical practice, which 
compromises the reliability of the CBCT images 
3,10 once </p>

<p>areas without bone are considered. This lack of precision 
leading to values that underestimate the real measurements 
may be explained by the partial volume effect. 
24-27 This </p>

<p>artifact results when the voxel reproduces an average val-
ue between the true values for 2 objects (e.g. tooth and 
surrounding air) with distinctive density. Therefore, the 
interpretation becomes questionable. 
One of the most common voxel sizes used in orthodon-
tics is 0.3 mm, although it should be used with caution if 
the goal is to assess small variations in bone thickness. A 
smaller voxel size would be more appropriate for these 
studies when it is possible to minimize the influence of 
partial volume averaging. 
27,28 Reducing the voxel size </p>

<p>results in an increased dose of radiation, which has an ef-
fect on the biological risk of X-ray exposure, especially in 
children. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>In the present study, known and calibrated measure-
ments from a geometric phantom from a previous study 
were used as the gold standard. 
6 This provides the advan-</p>

<p>tage of high reproducibility without exposure of living 
tissue. However, it was not possible to reproduce some 
physical phenomena that occur in anthropometric and 
clinical trials, such as attenuation of the radiation beam, 
dispersed radiation, and noise. 
High-resolution protocols provide images rich in detail 
and are associated with high levels of X-radiation; thus, 
further clinical studies are necessary. In conclusion, the 
intraobserver and interobserver variability and the accu-
racy of linear measurements in axial CBCT images were 
excellent. There were no differences in terms of the per-
formance of the CBCT scanners. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors wish to thank Mr. Carlos Kazuo Suetake for 
providing technical information and Mr. Abmael Henrique 
dos Santos and Mr. Bruno S. J da Silva for assistance with 
the phantom calibration at Mitutoyo Sul American Ltda. </p>





<p>Nathália Cristine da Silva et al </p>



</text></tei>