<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5478307" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) is a highly heterogeneous disease displaying considerable interfamilial and intrafamilial 
phenotypic variation, including disease severity, age of onset, and disease progression. This poorly understood variance raises the 
possibility of genetic modifier effects, particularly in MYBPC3-associated HCM. 
In a large consanguineous Chinese HCM family, we identified 8 members harboring the MYBPC3 c.3624delC (p.Lys1209Serfs) 
disease-causing mutation, but with very disparate phenotypes. Genotyping ruled out the modifying effect of previously described 
variants in renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system. Afterwards, we screened for modifying variants in all known causing genes and 
closely related genes for cardiomyopathy and channelopathy by performing targeted next-generation sequencing. For first time, we 
showed that a c.1598C&gt;T (p.Ser533Leu) mutation in voltage-dependent l-type calcium channel subunit beta-2 (CACNB2) was 
present in all severely affected HCM patients, but not in those moderately affected or genotype-positive phenotype-negative patients. 
This CACNB2 p.Ser533Leu mutation is extremely conserved in evolution, and was not found in 550 healthy controls. 
Our results suggest that CACNB2 is a possible candidate genetic modifier of MYBPC3-associated familial HCM, but more genetic 
evidence and functional experiments are needed to confirm. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: HCM = hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, LVH = left ventricular hypertrophy, MYBPC3 = myosin-binding protein C, 
MYH7 = b-myosin heavy chain, NGS = next-generation sequencing, RAAS = renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system. </p>

<p>Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) is the most common 
inherited cardiac disease, present in 1 in 500 of the general 
population. More than 1500 mutations in ≥11 causative genes 
have been identified in HCM, most of which are unique to 
individual families. 
[1] It is estimated that about 70% of patients 
who are positive for genetic tests carry mutations in b-myosin 
heavy chain (MYH7) and myosin-binding protein C (MYBPC3) 
genes; these 2 genes account for up to 50% of all clinically </p>

<p>diagnosed cases of HCM, whereas other genes account for &lt;10% 
of cases. 
[2] Clinically, HCM is a highly heterogeneous disease 
with not only considerable interfamilial, but also intrafamilial 
variability in disease phenotypes, which include disease severity, 
age of onset, and disease progression. 
[1,3] The extensive 
phenotypic variability cannot be fully explained by the causal 
mutations because even siblings sharing the same pathological 
mutation still show huge discordant phenotypes. This unex-
plained variance raises the possibility of contribution from other 
genetic factors, the so-called modifier genes. 
It is of great importance to identify these genetic modifiers in 
light of genetic-based diagnosis, risk stratification, and disease 
treatment. Pharmacologic interventions of the modifier genes 
involved in HCM-specific pathways might provide new thera-
peutic opportunities. However, identification of such modifier 
genes remains challenging and systemic exploration is absent in 
HCM. Among these few modifiers investigated in HCM, the most 
studied was genetic variations in the renin-angiotensin-aldoste-
rone system (RAAS) genes. It was first proposed in a HCM family 
with a causal MYBPC3 mutation that patients with the pro-left 
ventricular hypertrophy (LVH) genotypes in RAAS genes 
manifested cardiac hypertrophy, whereas those without pro-
LVH genotypes did not. 
[4] However, this observation was not 
confirmed in a recent study involving a large population of 368 
sporadic HCM patients who carried founder mutations in 
MYBPC3 gene, 
[5] indicating that there are other currently 
unknown modifiers to be discovered. 
Family study is important in modifier gene investigation 
because the population is homogeneous and more readily 
available than a large sample of unrelated patients, which is 
always a genetically heterogeneous population. In a Chinese 
HCM family, we recently identified 8 members harboring a </p>

<p>Editor: Weimin Guo. </p>

<p>X.Z. and J.X. contributed equally to this study. </p>

<p>The study was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (NO. 
81600312). </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Supplemental Digital Content is available for this article. </p>

<p>Department of Cardiology, Affiliated Drum Tower Hospital, Nanjing University 
School of Medicine, Nanjing, China. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Correspondence: Lian Wang, Biao Xu, Department of Cardiology, Affiliated 
Drum Tower Hospital, Nanjing University School of Medicine, 321 Zhongshan 
Road, 210008 Nanjing, China (e-mail: xubiao@medmail.com.cn); 
(e-mail: wanglian@medmail.com.cn). </p>

<p>Copyright © 2017 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-
ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is 
properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially 
without permission from the journal. </p>

<p>Medicine (2017) 96:24(e7010) </p>

<p>Received: 16 November 2016 / Received in final form: 3 May 2017 / Accepted: 
3 May 2017 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000007010 </p>

<p>Observational Study </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>OPEN </p>



<p>MYBPC3 disease-causing mutation but with very disparate 
phenotypes. It is most likely that other functional mutations in 
relevant genes provide synergistic effects with MYBPC3 mutation 
and lead to an early-onset and severe phenotype. We aimed to 
identify these possible genetic variants using the next-generation 
sequencing (NGS) technology to analyze all known causing genes 
and closely related genes for cardiomyopathy and channelop-
athy, given ion cycling deficiency and sarcomeric structure 
impairment were the major pathological mechanisms of HCM. </p>

<p>[6]   2. METHODS </p>

<p>2.1. Subjects </p>

<p>This study was conducted in accordance with the ethical 
guidelines of the Declaration of Helsinki, and approved by the 
local ethics committee at the Affiliated Drum Tower Hospital, 
Nanjing University School of Medicine. Written informed 
consent was obtained from all subjects. 
A large consanguineous Chinese HCM family with consider-
able phenotype heterogeneity was clinically examined (Fig. 1). An 
ethnically matched group of 550 control subjects with normal 
echocardiograms was also included. Venous blood samples were 
collected for DNA analysis. </p>

<p>2.2. Diagnosis </p>

<p>Clinical diagnosis of HCM in adult patients is based on the 
presence of left ventricular end-diastolic wall thickness ≥15 mm 
in ≥1 left ventricular myocardial segments by 2-dimensional 
echocardiography after excluding other cardiac or systemic 
diseases capable of producing a similar degree of 
hypertrophy. 
[7-9] For the diagnosis of HCM in first-degree 
relatives of patients with unequivocal HCM, the cut-off of left 
ventricular wall thickness was 13 mm. 
[8] Genetic testing is also 
used in the identification of affected relatives in families known to </p>

<p>have HCM; those relatives who carry HCM-definitive mutation 
but without cardiac hypertrophy are called genotype-positive 
phenotype-negative HCM patients. </p>

<p>[7,9]   2.3. Echocardiography </p>

<p>Echocardiography was performed by an experienced operator 
blinded of both genotype and control or study subject status. M-
mode, 2-dimensional images, and Doppler recordings were 
obtained using a Philips Sonos 5500 ultrasound system. Left 
ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) was assessed by using Simpson 
biplane method. Left ventricular end-diastolic diameter (LVDD) 
and left ventricular septal and posterior wall thickness were 
assessed from 2-dimensional images. Peak early (E) and late (A) 
transmitral velocities, E/A ratio, and E-wave deceleration time 
were measured from spectral Doppler images. Tissue Doppler e' 
velocity was measured at the septal and lateral corners of the mitral 
annulus. Subjects with normal echocardiograms were classified as 
unaffected members or members with unknown status. </p>

<p>2.4. Sanger sequencing for mutations in MYBPC3 and 
MYH7 </p>

<p>Genomic DNA was extracted from human peripheral blood 
samples using the DNeasy kit (Qiagen). DNA concentration and 
purity were measured with a Nanodrop 2000 spectrophotometer 
(Thermo scientific), and calibrated to 50 ng/mL for further use. 
The polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was performed using 
primers that cover all exons and exon-intron boundaries of 
MYBPC3 and MYH7. 
[10-11] PCR products were purified with the 
Gel Extraction kit (Omega) and sequenced on both strands using 
the BigDye Terminator v3.1 kit (Applied Biosystems). Sequence 
alignments were carried out with the ABI 3100 Genetic Analyzer 
(Applied Biosystems). </p>

<p>2.5. Genotyping the 5 polymorphisms in RAAS </p>

<p>Five polymorphisms previously investigated in RAAS were selected 
for genotyping. That includes rs4646994 in the angiotensin 
converting enzyme gene (ACE), rs5186 in the angiotensin II 
receptor type 1 gene (AGTR1), rs1800875 in the cardiac chymase 
A gene (CMA1), rs699 in the gene encoding angiotensinogen 
(AGT), and rs1799998 in the aldolase synthase gene (CYP11B2). 
The deletion/insertion (D/I) polymorphism (rs4646994) in ACE 
was genotyped as previously described 
[5] and genotyping of other 
polymorphisms was determined by Sanger sequencing. </p>

<p>2.6. Targeted ngs </p>

<p>Targeted NGS (including library construction, capture, and 
sequencing) was carried out at MyGenostics Gene Technologies 
(Beijing, China). The Cardiomyopathy panel (MyGenostics) was 
designed to cover 104 genes, which were known causes or related 
genes for cardiomyopathy and channelopathy (Table S1, http:// 
links.lww.com/MD/B745). Targeted gene enrichment was per-
formed with the GenCap Custom Enrichment Kit (MyGenostics) 
according to the GenCap protocol, as described previously. </p>

<p>[12-13]   Captured DNA libraries were sequenced with the Illumina HiSeq 
2000 instrument (Illumina, San Diego, CA) for 100-bp paired reads. </p>

<p>2.7. Data analysis </p>

<p>Mapping of the sequencing reads to the human genome reference 
sequence (hg19) was performed with the burrows-wheeler </p>

<p>Figure 1. Pedigree of a consanguineous Chinese family with hereditary 
hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. Squares denote male family members, circles 
female family members, black solid squares and circles severely affected HCM 
members, gray solid cycle moderately affected HCM member, blue solid cycles 
genotype-positive phenotype-negative, open squares and cycles healthy 
members with wild-type MYBPC3. A slash across the symbols denotes 
deceased individual, and asterisks denotes family members whose samples 
were sequenced. Genotypes for MYBPC3 and CACNB2 were shown below 
the symbol for each individual with a plus (+) indicating mutant and a minus (-) 
indicating wild type for that genotype. </p>

<p>Zhang et al. Medicine (2017) 96:24 
Medicine </p>



<p>alignment tool. 
[14] The Short Oligonucleotide Analysis Package 
(<rs type="software">SOAPsnp</rs>) and <rs type="software">the Genome Analysis Toolkit</rs> were used to 
discover single-nucleotide polymorphism and insertion-deletion, 
respectively. 
[15-16] Gene related annotation was mainly done 
with <rs type="software">ANNOVAR</rs>. 
[17] The pathogenicity of a variant was 
determined based on frequency in the population and in silico 
prediction. We excluded common variants (frequency &gt; 1%) 
present in the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute ESP 
(Exome Sequencing Project), the 1000 Genomes database, and 
exomes generated in house from 550 unaffected Chinese control 
samples. Variants annotated in the Human Gene Mutation 
Database (HGMD) were regarded as disease-causing. All 
nonsynonymous variants were subjected to in silico analysis, 
which included functional annotation algorithms such as SIFT, 
PolyPhen2, GERP++, and MutationTaster. All variants identified 
by NGS and deemed as pathogenic were verified by Sanger 
sequencing, using primers designed from Primer 3 online 
software (http://bioinfo.ut.ee/primer3-0.4.0/primer3/input.htm). </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Description of the pedigree </p>

<p>The index patient (V-1) was presented to our institution at age 
28 with exertional dyspnea and chest discomfort for 1 month. 
His electrocardiogram showed prominent LVH. Transthoracic 
echocardiography confirmed a severe form of HCM with a 
marked hypertrophic septum (27 mm) and a left-ventricular 
outflow obstruction (LVOTO) of 32 mmHg. Exercise echocar-
diography revealed that LVOTO increased to 60 mmHg. He 
received metoprolol treatment (190 mg/day), but refused to 
receive an implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD), percu-
taneous transluminal septal myocardial ablation (PTSMA), or 
septal myectomy because he remained fully active after drug 
therapy with only mild functional limitation (functional class 
New York Heart Association class II). He unfortunately 
suffered sudden death 1 year later when he was 29 years' 
old. His mother (IV-2) suffered from exertional angina for 
10 years and was diagnosed with HCM showing atypical 
hypertrophy (23 mm). Her symptoms improved on treatment 
with metoprolol, and her cardiac function remained stable from 
her recent echocardiography. </p>

<p>Two uncles of the index patient (IV-4 and IV-5) showed very 
similar clinical pictures: they both suffered from exertional 
dyspnea, had permanent atrial fibrillation, and hypertrophic 
interventricular septum (19 mm). Rest echocardiogram did not 
show evidence of LVOTO. IV-4 received pharmacological therapy 
of beta-blockers and low-dose loop diuretics, but unfortunately 
encountered sudden death at age 52. IV-5 did not receive any 
treatment and his NYHA functional class remained II to III. IV-6 
was diagnosed with HCM at the age 64 as part of clinical screening 
of the family. Her echocardiogram showed moderate asymmetrical 
hypertrophy with a maximum wall thickness (MWT) of 15 mm 
and normal LV dimensions and systolic function. IV-8 was 
diagnosed with hypertension (grade 2) at age 38 and did not receive 
any antihypertensive agents for 7 years. Ambulatory blood 
pressure monitoring at this screening confirmed uncontrolled 
hypertension with an average blood pressure of 155/99 mmHg. 
Auxiliary examinations ruled out secondary hypertension. He is 
asymptomatic and his echocardiogram showed a symmetric LV 
hypertrophy and a mildly increased LV chamber dilation and 
reduced systolic function. It was unlikely the burned-out 
phenotype of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. 
The clinical characteristics of the family were shown in Table 1. 
All family members were examined, and no member in the family 
showed phenotypes of Brugada syndrome. </p>

<p>3.2. Identification of the mutation in MYBPC3 by Sanger 
sequencing </p>

<p>It is well accepted that variants in MYBPC3 and MYH7 account 
for &gt;70% of HCM cases in which a mutation has been defined. 
We sequenced MYBPC3 and MYH7 genes in the 4 affected HCM 
patients and revealed no disease-causing mutation in MYH7, but 
the presence in all affected individuals of a heterozygous 
c.3624delC mutation within MYBPC3 (11p11.2), leading to a 
frameshift and a premature termination codon (p.Lys1209Serfs) 
and thus causing the loss of 49 amino acids in the protein (Fig. 2). 
This mutation has been reported previously in several HCM 
patients 
[18-19] , but was not found in the 1000 Genomes Project 
or the Exome Sequencing Project, nor in the 550 ethnically 
matched healthy control individuals in our study. In this family, 
we identified 8 members harboring this disease-causing mutation. 
All these 8 members were regarded as HCM patients, either as </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Clinical characteristics of family members. </p>

<p>Patient No. Sex Age, y ASO, y LVDD, cm IVSTD, cm LVPWTD, cm AoD, cm LAD, cm EF (%) E, m/s A, m/s E/A e 
0 , cm/s HR, bpm Cardiac rhythm </p>

<p>IV-2 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>F 
51 
40 
5.3 
1 (2.3 
 *  ) 
1 
3.1 
3.4 
63 
0.4 
0.6 
0.67 
8.5 
66 
Sinus 
IV-4 
M 
52 
47 
5.5 
1.9 
1.18 
3.4 
6.8 
47 
0.5 
0.6 
0.83 
9.4 
123 
AF 
IV-5 
M 
66 
45 
5.7 
1.9 
1.2 
2.9 
6.5 
44 
0.4 
0.6 
0.67 10.0 
90 
AF 
IV-6 
F 
64 
NA 
4.7 
1.5 
0.9 
3.1 
3.6 
61 
0.4 
0.9 
0.44 10.5 
75 
Sinus 
IV-8 
M 
45 
NA 
5.7 
1.1 
1.1 
3.3 
4.3 
51 
0.8 
0.6 
1.33 12.7 
86 
Sinus 
IV-10 
F 
43 
NA 
5.1 
0.9 
0.9 
3 
3.75 
61 
0.5 
0.7 
0.71 12.0 
75 
Sinus 
V-1 
M 
29 
27 
4.3 
2.7 
1.0 
2.6 
3.9 
55 
0.5 
0.65 0.77 
8.9 
76 
Sinus 
V-3 
M 
17 
NA 
5.4 
0.8 
0.8 
2.5 
3.6 
60 
1.0 
0.6 
1.67 13.1 
66 
Sinus 
V-5 
F 
22 
NA 
5.1 
0.75 
0.75 
2.6 
3.6 
67 
0.8 
0.6 
1.33 14.5 
75 
Sinus 
V-6 
M 
45 
NA 
4.9 
0.8 
0.8 
2.9 
3.5 
65 
0.8 
0.7 
1.14 12.0 
78 
Sinus 
V-7 
M 
41 
NA 
5.15 
0.8 
0.8 
3 
3.45 
60 
0.7 
0.65 1.08 13.1 
93 
Sinus 
V-8 
M 
18 
NA 
4.3 
0.9 
0.9 
2.3 
2.8 
61 
0.6 
0.5 
1.2 
14.3 
88 
Sinus 
V-9 
F 
12 
NA 
4 
0.5 
0.5 
2.1 
2.35 
61 
0.95 
0.65 1.46 15.2 
76 
Sinus 
V-10 
M 
11 
NA 
3.9 
0.55 
0.55 
2.1 
2.3 
62 
0.95 
0.8 
1.19 14.8 
88 
Sinus </p>

<p>AF = atrial fibrillation, ASO = age of symptom onset, EF = ejection fraction; F = female, HR = heart rate, IVSTD = interventricular septal end-diastolic thickness, LAD = left atrial diameter, LVDD = left ventricular 
diastolic diameter; LVPWTD = left ventricular posterior wall thickness at end-diastole, M = male; NA = not applicable. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>A moderate asymmetrical hypertrophy of 2.3 cm localized to apex of the left ventricle. </p>

<p>Zhang et al. Medicine (2017) 96:24 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>genotype-positive phenotype-positive or genotype-positive phe-
notype-negative patients. </p>

<p>3.3. Targeted NGS for modifying variants </p>

<p>Marked clinical heterogeneity was noted among these patients 
who shared the same disease-causing MYBPC3mutation: 4 (IV-2, 
IV-4, IV-5, and V-1) were considered severely affected because 
they had a greater maximal wall thickness (MWT), an earlier 
onset of HCM phenotype associated with marked symptoms and 
cardiac events (cardiac death or admission for heart failure or 
stroke); 1 (IV-6) was considered as moderately affected because 
she had documented LVH, but less MWT and no evidence of 
cardiac symptoms or event; the other 3 (IV-8, IV-10, and V-8) 
were genotype-positive phenotype-negative patients with no 
evidence of LVH or relevant clinical symptoms. However, V-8 
needs follow-up reevaluation because he was only 18 at his last 
clinical evaluation. This remarkable phenotypic variation 
indicates that disease modifiers exist. 
We first genotyped the five variations in RAAS genes and 
revealed no correlation between HCM phenotypes and these 
genotypes, which ruled out the modifying effect of these RAAS 
variants. We then performed targeted NGS for the index HCM 
patient using a panel covering all known causing genes and 
closely related genes of cardiomyopathy and channelopathy, and 
the RAAS genes. The NGS captured 99.5% of the target region. A 
mean coverage of 307Â was reached and 92.7% of target regions 
were covered to a depth of at least 20 Â. In total, we identified 301 
genetic variants in the index patient across the target region. After 
excluding synonymous genetic variants, 135 exonic or splice-site 
variants remained. Further excluding common variants (≥1.0%) 
reported in Exome Sequencing Project, 1000 Genomes, and 
exomes generated in house left us with 5 candidate variants 
(Table 2). Two of these, c.3624delC (p.Lys1209Serfs) within </p>

<p>MYBPC3 and c.1598C&gt;T (p.Ser533Leu) within voltage-depen-
dent l-type calcium channel subunit beta-2 (CACNB2; 
10p12.31), were predicted to be "damaging" by all algorithms, 
whereas the other 3 mutations, c.1058C&gt;T (p.Ala353Val) within 
transforming growth factor beta 1 (TGFB1; 19q13.2), 
c.8134G&gt;T (p.Ala2712Ser) within A-kinase anchoring protein 
9 (AKAP9, 7q21.2), and c.3923G&gt;A (p.Arg1308Gln) within 
desmoplakin (DSP; 6p24.3), were predicted "benign" according 
to at least 2 functional annotation algorithms. </p>

<p>3.4. Sanger sequencing confirmation in family members </p>

<p>Next we determined these 5 genotypes in all family members 
through Sanger sequencing. We found that among the 8 HCM 
patients carrying the MYBPC3 mutation, those severely affected 
(IV-2, IV-4, IV-5, and V-1) also carried the CACNB2 c.1598C&gt;T 
(p.Ser533Leu) mutation (Fig. 3), whereas the patient moderately 
affected (IV-6) and those 3 genotype-positive phenotype-negative 
patients (IV-8, IV-10, and V-8) did not carry this mutation in 
CACNB2. However, segregation analysis of the other 3 mutations 
in the family confirmed no association between these mutations 
and the phenotypes (Table 3). The good segregation of HCM 
phenotype with CACNB2 genotype suggests that CACNB2 might 
serve as a functional modifier in MYBPC3-related HCM. To 
support this, the affected amino acid of this mutation in CACNB2 
is extremely conserved in the evolution (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>4.1. MYBPC3-Lys1209Serfs causes HCM in humans </p>

<p>The MYBPC3-Lys1209Serfs mutation has been previously 
reported in several patients with HCM in 2 studies (including 
1 familial HCM), both of which were conducted in Chinese 
population. 
[19] This variant was not reported in public databases, </p>

<p>Figure 2. Electropherograms showing the MYBPC3 c.3624delC (p.Lys1209Serfs) heterozygous mutation and a wild type, control sequence. </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Genetic variants identified after targeted next-generation sequencing followed by adequate filtering. </p>

<p>Chr 
Position 
Gene 
Transcript 
Exon 
Nucleotide change 
Amino acid change 
Pathogenicity </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Control 
Associated diseases </p>

<p>11 
47354120 
MYBPC3 
NM_000256 
32 
c.3624delC 
p.P1208fs 
NA 
0/550 
HCM, DCM, LVNC 
10 
47367774 
CACNB2 
NM_201597 
14 
c.1598C&gt;T 
p.S533L 
Probably damaging 
0/550 
Brugada syndrome 
19 
41837072 
TGFB1 
NM_000660 
7 
c.1058C&gt;T 
p.A353V 
Benign 
0/550 
7 
91711950 
AKAP9 
NM_005751 
32 
c.8134G&gt;T 
p.A2712S 
Benign 
0/550 
Long QT Syndrome 
6 
7580346 
DSP 
NM_004415 
23 
c.3923G&gt;A 
p.R1308Q 
Possibly damaging 
2/550 
ARVC </p>

<p>ARVC = arrhythmogenic right ventricular cardiomyopathy, DCM = dilated cardiomyopathy, HCM = hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, LVNC = left ventricular non compaction, NA = not applicable. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Predictions are based on PolyPhen_2 program. </p>

<p>Zhang et al. Medicine (2017) 96:24 
Medicine </p>



<p>and was predicted to cause loss of 49 amino acids. The MYBPC3 
truncation mutation might result in haploinsufficiency because 
truncated proteins were prone to be degraded through nonsense-
mediated decay. </p>

<p>[20] </p>

<p>4.2. MYBPC3-Lys1209Serfs and other MYBPC3 mutations 
are associated with incomplete penetrance and mild 
prognosis </p>

<p>The MYBPC3-Lys1209Serfs mutation was first reported in a 3-
generation family with HCM. 
[19] Onset of cardiac symptoms did 
not occur until the sixth decade of life in this family, and all HCM 
patients lived to their 90s without the protection of ICDs. 
Consistently, other MYBPC3 mutations were also reported 
relatively mild in prognosis and were even considered as founder 
mutations in several general populations. 
[21] Our study con-
firmed that remarkable incomplete penetrance exists in 
MYBPC3-mutation-carrying HCM patients: 3 family members 
did not have echocardiographic manifestations of HCM at ages 
18, 43, and 45 years. However, 4 other HCM patients carrying 
the identical mutation showed earlier disease onset (3 at their 40s 
and 1 at 20s), severe echocardiographic manifestations (greater 
MWT), and much worse prognosis (1 suffered sudden cardiac 
death at 20s and 1 at 40 s) than the 3 genotype-positive 
phenotype-negative patients and most HCM patients reported in 
previously published literatures. These discrepancies indicate that 
a modifier gene may contribute to deteriorate disease phenotype 
in addition to the MYBPC3 mutation. </p>

<p>4.3. Evidences support channelopathy gene mutations 
could modify HCM phenotype </p>

<p>It is generally accepted that other disease modifiers exist beyond 
the specific disease-causing genetic mutations. HCM is a disease 
with complex pathogenesis, among which the most well-known 
were cycling deficiency and sarcomeric structure impairment. </p>

<p>[6]   Adrenergic system are also involved in the process of LVH or 
heart failure, 
[22-23] and reports showed possible modifying effect 
of variations in their related genes. 
[4-5] In our study, however, we 
did not found associations between these variations in adrenergic 
system and HCM phenotypes. 
Accumulating evidences support that HCM patients carrying 
&gt;1 sarcomere gene mutation were associated with more 
remarkable phenotypes and more adverse outcomes than those 
with a single mutation. 
[19,24] However, this is not the case in our 
study because we did not find patients carrying multiple 
sarcomere mutations. Instead, for the first time, we showed that 
CACNB2 is a possible genetic modifier of MYBPC3-associated 
familial HCM. Our findings were supported by a recently 
published study, in which Lopes et al 
[25] used targeted high-
throughput sequencing to investigate the genotype-phenotype 
associations in HCM, and demonstrated that in patients 
harboring sarcomere protein gene mutations, those who also 
carried Ankyrin-B gene (ANK2) variants had greater maximum 
wall thickness. It is notable that mutations in both ANK2 and 
CACNB2 could lead to channelopathies. 
[26] In this regard, it is 
reasonable to postulate that variants in non-sarcomere genes, 
particularly in candidate genes for channelopathies, are potential 
genetic modifiers of MYBPC3-related HCM. </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Detailed information of the 5 identified genetic variants in 8 HCM 
patients. </p>

<p>MYBPC3 
CACNB2 
TGFB1 
AKAP9 
DSP </p>

<p>IV-2 
+ 
+ 
À 
À 
+ 
IV-4 
+ 
+ 
À 
À 
+ 
IV-5 
+ 
+ 
À 
À 
À 
IV-6 
+ 
À 
À 
À 
À 
IV-8 
+ 
À 
À 
À 
+ 
IV-10 
+ 
À 
À 
À 
À 
V-1 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
V-8 
+ 
À 
À 
À 
+ </p>

<p>Genotypes were shown for each individual with a plus (+) indicating mutant and a minus (À) indicating 
wild type for that genotype. AKAP = A-kinase anchoring protein 9, CACNB2 = calcium channel subunit 
beta-2, DSP = desmoplakin, HCM = hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, MYBPC = myosin-binding protein 
C, TGFB1 = transforming growth factor beta 1. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Electropherograms showing the CACNB2 c.1598C&gt;T (p.Ser533Leu) heterozygous mutation and a wild type, control sequence. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Alignment of homologous CACNB2 protein sequences that flank the 
amino acid substitutions. </p>

<p>Zhang et al. Medicine (2017) 96:24 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>The proposed concept that channelopathy gene mutations 
may contribute to HCM phenotype was further advanced by a 
study screening for mutations in 7 Ca 
2+ regulatory genes (i.e., 
SRI, FKBP1B, CASQ2, PLN, SLN, CALR3, and CALM) in a 
cohort of 252 unrelated familial HCM patients. 
[27] Four 
variants with pathogenic significance were detected in these 
Ca 
2+ regulatory genes, among which 2 patients also carried 
the MYBPC3 sarcomere mutations. 
[27] The modifying effect 
of these variants was not fully illustrated because the family 
pedigrees were small and screening for other relatives was 
unavailable. In light of our observations and the data 
reviewed above, it is likely that most of the evidences 
concerning modifier genes in HCM are obtained on the basis 
of MYBPC3 mutations. This may be because of the "benign" 
nature of most MYBPC3 mutations, 
[3] as MYBPC3 mutations 
are usually associated with a mild hypertrophy, late-onset, 
incomplete penetrance, and a better prognosis. Besides, 
MYBPC3 gene is the only gene reported in HCM with 
founder mutations, for example, 2% to 8% of all major 
Indian populations carry a MYBPC3 deletion, and 0.4% of 
Iceland population carries a MYPPC3 missense mutation. </p>

<p>[21]   It would be of great interest to investigate genetic modifiers in 
these populations with founder mutations. </p>

<p>[21]   4.4. Possible mechanisms of the CACNB2 mutation 
modifying disease phenotype </p>

<p>CACNB2 encodes for an auxiliary voltage-dependent L-type 
calcium-channel (LTCC) Ca v b2 subunit and is predominantly 
expressed in the heart. The Ca v b2 subunit improves the calcium 
current by promoting the voltage-dependent opening of Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>channel and enhancing channel surface expression, probably 
through direct interaction with actin. Mice lacking Ca v b2 have 
functionally compromised heart and die at embryonic day 
10.5. 
[28] Diminished L-type Ca 
2+ currents were observed in these 
Ca v b2 
À/À mice, as well as in patients with Brugada syndrome 
harboring loss-of-function mutations in CACNB2. 
[28] Based on 
algorithmic prediction, it is likely that the CACNB2 mutation 
identified in our study could attenuate L-type calcium current 
in cardiomyocytes, and then inhibits the activation of calcium/ 
calmodulin (Ca 
2+ /CaM)-dependent protein kinase II (CaMKII), a 
key regulator of cardiac physiology and pathology. 
[29] Subse-
quently, on the one hand, CaMKII-mediated phosphorylation of 
cMyBP-C, which is critical in maintaining sarcomeric structure 
and function, is markedly decreased. Dephosphorylated cMyBP-
C is prone to degradation, 
[30] and thus leads to dramatic 
insufficiency of cMyBP-C. This situation is worsened given that 
the MYBPC3 truncation mutation itself causes haploinsuffi-
ciency. It is very likely that the serious cMyBP-C deficiency 
significantly exacerbates the development of HCM in those 
severely affected patients because a lack of functional full-length 
cMyBP-C has been demonstrated to cause HCM phenotypes. </p>

<p>[31]   On the other hand, CaMKII directly binds to the C terminus of 
Ca v b2 subunit and facilitates LTCC calcium currents through 
phosphorylation of Ca v b2. In CACNB2 mutation carriers, this 
process is inhibited and Ca 
2+ currents are further reduced. 
Considerable Ca 
2+ is stored in the sarcomere, but mutant 
sarcomeres may trap more Ca 
2+ than normal sarcomeres, causing 
a reduction in cytoplasmic Ca 
2+ . 
[32] Therefore, Ca 
2+ current 
dysfunction is extremely evident in those severely affected HCM 
patients who carry both the MYBPC3 and CACNB2 mutations, 
which could explain the high rate of sudden cardiac death of these 
patients. </p>

<p>4.5. Study limitations </p>

<p>Several limitations should be acknowledged in our study. First, 
we used targeted NGS technology instead of a hypothesis-free 
approach such as exome or genome sequencing. However, our 
sequencing panel included all known causing genes and closely 
related genes of cardiomyopathy and channelopathy, which very 
likely cover the modifier gene if it exists. Second, the mechanism 
of how MYBPC3 interacts with CACNB2 remains undetermined 
in our study; we were unable to obtain the left ventricular tissue of 
HCM patients for functional analyses because consent of 
myocardial biopsy was not provided and none of these patients 
received heart transplantation or postmortem examination. 
More genetic evidence and functional experiments are needed 
to confirm our observations. 
In this study, for the first time we showed that CACNB2 is a 
possible candidate hypertrophy-modifying gene contributing to 
disease variability of MYBPC3-associated familial HCM. We 
provided a new possible mechanism of HCM pathogenesis, that 
is, a combination effect of sarcomere gene and channelopathy 
gene mutations, which however needs confirmation with more 
genetic evidence and functional experiments. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank the patients and their families for their 
participation in the study. </p>









</text></tei>