<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5406524" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The coagulase-negative bacterium Staphylococcus condimenti and closely related species are commonly isolated from or found in starter </p>

<p>cultures of fermented sausage as well as fish and soy sauces, and have traditionally been considered nonpathogenic. Recently, however, </p>

<p>a case of catheter-related bacteraemia caused by S. condimenti was reported. In the present study we identified and characterized a </p>

<p>strain of S. condimenti isolated from a patient with a severe soft tissue infection, comparing it to S. condimenti and S. carnosus type </p>

<p>strains in order to elucidate the virulence potential of the clinical strain. Genome comparison showed high degree of conservation </p>

<p>between the clinical strain and the type strain used in food industry, as well as with S. carnosus. The genome of the clinical </p>

<p>S. condimenti strain contains few horizontally transferred regions and 37 putative virulence genes, including genes with similarity to </p>

<p>leucocidin and genes involved in immune evasion, proinflammatory and cytolytic activity. However, it remains to be tested </p>

<p>whether these putative virulence genes are expressed and functional. Although uncommon, S. condimenti may cause severe </p>

<p>infection in previously healthy persons. </p>

<p>The genus Staphylococcus consists of more than 50 species, 
which have traditionally been grouped in coagulase-positive 
and coagulase-negative staphylococci (CoNS). The majority 
of CoNS are commonly found on human and animal skin 
and mucous membranes, and these have been regarded as 
nonpathogenic or less virulent compared to the coagulase-
positive staphylococci, most notably S. aureus. However, 
some CoNS, especially S. epidermidis and S. haemolyticus, are </p>

<p>major nosocomial pathogens frequently causing biofilm-
associated infections related to prosthetic and other 
indwelling devices [1]. S. carnosus, S. piscifermentans and 
S. condimenti make up a phylogenetic subgroup of CoNS 
that are commonly isolated from or are used in starter 
cultures of fermented sausage as well as fish and soy sauces 
[2,3]. These species have until recently not been associated 
with human disease. The first reported case of a human 
infection caused by S. condimenti was catheter-related bac-
teraemia in a 17-year old female patient with severe dilated 
cardiomyopathy [4]. Given their role in food production, 
investigating the potential pathogenicity of these species is 
of importance. 
In this study, we identified and characterized a strain of 
S. condimenti isolated from a patient with a severe soft tissue 
infection, comparing it to the S. condimenti type strain DSM 
11674 and the related S. carnosus TM300 in order to elucidate 
the virulence potential of the clinical strain. </p>

<p>New Microbe and New Infect 2017; 18: 8-14 
© 2017 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/) 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nmni.2017.03.006 </p>

<p>Case Presentation </p>

<p>While on holiday, a 7-year-old girl from a Central European 
country with no history of disease was admitted to St Olavs 
University Hospital in August 2014. The patient had a lacer-
ation after cutting her left knee on a fragment of glass in a 
plastic swimming pool the previous evening. Debridement of 
the wound and irrigation of the knee were performed, and 
the patient was discharged the following day without 
antibiotics. 
At follow-up 4 days later, the patient presented with a 
temperature of 39°C, a painful knee and foul-smelling discharge 
from the wound. Blood samples showed C-reactive protein of 
199 mg/L, erythrocyte sedimentation rate of 108 mm/h, and 
normal leukocyte count. The patient was readmitted, and 
revision surgery was performed promptly. A synovial fluid 
aspirate and deep biopsy samples from infected tissues were 
collected and submitted for microscopy and culture. After 
surgery, intravenous antibiotic treatment was initiated with 
dicloxacillin and gentamicin. 
Synovial fluid and deep tissue samples from the left knee 
were cultured on aerobic and anaerobic media as well as media 
for the cultivation of mycobacteria. Microscopy of the samples 
showed presence of Gram-positive cocci. White catalase-
positive and coagulase-negative morphologically similar col-
onies grew abundantly from synovial fluid and all tissue samples 
on 5% bovine blood agar and chocolate agar after an incubation 
period of 2 days. A representative isolate was identified by 
matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass 
spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS) to the genus level, with the 
best hit being S. condimenti (log scores ranging from 1.27 to 
1.99), while biotyping gave an unacceptable profile identification 
(API ID 32 Staph profile 375152000), the nearest significant 
taxa being S. chromogenes, S. caprae, S. carnosus and S. simulans. 
16S rRNA gene sequencing analysis did not provide sufficient 
discrimination towards related species (99.8% sequence simi-
larity with S. carnosus and S. piscifermentans). PCR analyses for 
mecA, nuc, TSST-1, ETA and ETB genes were negative. The isolate 
was found to be susceptible to all antibiotics tested (Table 1). 
After an incubation period of 10 weeks, growth of acid-fast 
bacteria was not detected. S. condimenti was not recovered in 
samples from repeat revision surgeries. Histologic analysis of 
tissue samples showed inflammatory changes and necrosis of 
the superficial layer of the muscle tissue. 
Throughout the hospital stay, a total of 12 revision surgeries 
were performed due to severe infectious myositis with 
extensive involvement of the soft tissues of the right thigh up to 
the ischial tuberosity, and also involvement of the contralateral 
hip and thigh. Between revisions, the surgical wounds were left </p>

<p>open. On the basis of results of antimicrobial susceptibility 
testing, antibiotic treatment was adjusted to intravenous clin-
damycin and dicloxacillin from day 7. 
Two weeks after the first revision surgery, the surgical 
wounds were closed. The patient was discharged after 4 weeks' 
hospitalization with dicloxacillin tablets for 20 days' treatment. 
Clinical follow-up was to be scheduled in her home country. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Bacterial strains and typing 
The bacterial strains used in this study were the clinical isolate 
of Staphylococcus condimenti from the described case, hereafter 
referred to as S. condimenti StO 2014-01, and the S. condimenti 
DSM 11674 type strain (CCUG 39902T) [3] isolated from soy 
sauce mash. Bacterial cultures were identified by MALDI-TOF 
MS (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Bruker Daltonics</rs>) with <rs id="software-0" type="software">MALDI Biotyper</rs> software. Identi-
fication to the species level was defined as log scores 2.0, and </p>

<p>identification to the genus level on log scores between 1.7 and 
1.9, based on the manufacturer's guidelines. Antibacterial sus-
ceptibility testing was performed with agar disc diffusion and 
minimum inhibitory concentration testing by agar gradient 
diffusion. Interpretation of results was based on EUCAST/ 
NordicAST breakpoints for staphylococci. 16S rDNA was 
sequenced with PCR primers covering V1-V9 and Sanger 
sequencing using BigDye Terminator v 3.1 and ABI Hitachi 3130 
XL Genetic Analyser (Applied Biosystems). </p>

<p>Whole genome sequencing and assembly 
Bacterial cells were treated with proteinase K (2 mg/mL) and 
lysostaphin (0.1 mg/mL) for 15 minutes with shaking at 37°C, 
before heating for 15 minutes at 65°C. Genomic DNA was 
isolated using the Qiagen MagAttract DNA Mini M48 kit on </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Antibacterial susceptibility of Staphylococcus </p>

<p>condimenti StO 2014-01 and DSM 11674 strains </p>

<p>Antibiotic </p>

<p>S. condimenti 
StO 2014-01 </p>

<p>S. condimenti 
DSM 11674 </p>

<p>S-I-R MIC (mg/L) S-I-R MIC (mg/L) </p>

<p>Ciprofloxacin 
0.125 
0.125 
Clindamycin 
S 
0.125 
S 
0.125 
Cloxacillin/dicloxacillin 
S 
S 
Daptomycin 
0.125 
0.016 
Doxycycline 
S 
S 
Erythromycin 
S 
S 
Fusidic Acid 
S 
S 
Gentamicin 
S 
0.5 
S 
0.064 
Linezolid 
S 
1.0 
S 
1.0 
Penicillin G 
0.064 
Rifampicin 
0.016 
0.008 
Trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole S 
S 
Vancomycin 
1.0 
0.5 </p>

<p>I, intermediate; MIC, minimum inhibitory concentration; R, resistant; S, susceptible. </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>Gabrielsen et al. Virulence potential of S. condimenti </p>



<p>© 2017 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 18, 8-14 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Qiagen BioRobot M48. Illumina sequencing libraries were 
prepared using the Nextera XT sample prep kit, and were 
sequenced on the MiSeq platform with 300 bp paired-end reads 
(MiSeq Reagent Kit v3). MinION libraries were prepared from 
genomic DNA sheared by G-tube (Covaris) using the SQMAP-
004 kit (Oxford Nanopore Technologies). The MinION library 
was sequenced on a R7.3 flow cell using the MinION sequencer 
(Oxford Nanopore Technologies). Raw data were basecalled 
using <rs type="software">Metrichor</rs> software (r7.X 2D Basecalling rev 1.12), and 
extracted using <rs type="software">Poretools</rs> [5]. Data from two Nextera XT li-
braries and one MinION library (2D filtered reads) were hybrid 
assembled using the SPAdes Genome Assembler (v3.5.0) [6]. 
Contigs were assembled and circularized using the Geneious 
Assembler (Biomatters). The complete genome was annotated 
using the Rapid Annotation using Subsystem Technology 
(RAST) [7]. The S. condimenti StO 2014-01 chromosome and 
plasmid sequences were deposited in DDBJ/ENA/GenBank 
with accession numbers NZ_CP018776 and NZ_CP018777 
respectively. </p>

<p>Comparative genomics and identification of virulence 
factors 
Accessions of the reference genome sequences used in this 
study are provided in Table 2. BRIG [8] was used for whole 
genome comparison. Proteins were considered to be homologs 
having at least 90% sequence identity over at least 60% align-
ment length. <rs type="software">ClustalX2</rs> [9] and <rs id="software-4" type="software">FigTree</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">v1.4.2</rs> were used for 
sequence alignments and phylogeny. Putative virulence factors 
were identified by protein sequence blast against the Virulence 
Factors Database using BLAST+ and PfamScan against the Pfam-
A database. Putative horizontally transferred pathogenicity 
islands were identified using Alien Hunter [10]. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The genome of S. condimenti StO 2014-01 was sequenced and 
assembled into a complete 2 665 650 bp chromosome and a </p>

<p>35 235 bp plasmid. The genome encodes a total of 2535 
protein-encoding genes, of which 1866 (73.6%) were assigned 
to a function and 669 (26.4%) were defined as hypothetical, 
based on RAST. The plasmid (named pStO 2014-01) identified 
in S. condimenti StO 2014-01 displays very little sequence sim-
ilarity (maximum 25% alignment length) to known sequences in 
National Center for Biotechnology Information's nucleotide 
collection, and thus appears to be a new plasmid. </p>

<p>Comparative genomics of S. condimenti and closely 
related species 
We selected genomes of the most closely related species to 
S. condimenti for comparisons. These are strains originally iso-
lated from food sources and are thus not known to be path-
ogenic. Furthermore, we selected genomes of more distantly 
related species such as S. simulans, S. massiliensis, S. epidermidis 
and S. aureus to include in whole genome comparisons 
(Table 2). 
Whereas ribosomal gene (16S and 23S rDNA) alignments 
could not discriminate sufficiently between these staphylo-
coccal species (results not shown), an alignment of the sodA 
gene encoding superoxide dismutase, which is commonly used 
for species-level identification of coagulase-negative staphylo-
cocci [11], provided discrimination between the closely related 
S. condimenti and S. carnosus strains (Fig. 1). 
Alignments of the chromosomes of S. condimenti StO 2014-
01 and S. carnosus TM300 (Fig. 2) indicate a high degree of 
synteny and sequence identity between these two species. 
Between the two S. condimenti strains StO 2014-01 and DSM 
11674, there is an even higher degree of synteny and sequence 
identity, indicating that apart from a few horizontally trans-
ferred regions, the genomes are highly conserved in both 
structure and function. </p>

<p>Horizontally transferred genomic regions in 
S. condimenti StO 2014-01 
Identification of putative horizontal gene transfer (HGT) re-
gions in S. condimenti StO 2014-01 (Table 3, Fig. 2) revealed that </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Characteristics of staphylococcal strains and genomes used in this study. </p>

<p>Strain 
Source 
Type 
RefSeq accession no. 
Size (Mb) 
GC% 
Protein 
rRNA 
tRNA </p>

<p>S. condimenti StO 2014-01 
Human soft tissue infection 
Complete 
NZ_CP018776-7 
2.70 
34.6 
2535 
15 
58 
S. condimenti DSM 11674 
Soy sauce mash 
Complete 
NZ_CP015114 
2.66 
34.7 
2427 
18 
58 
S. carnosus subsp. carnosus TM300 
Meat starter culture 
Complete 
NC_012121 
2.57 
34.6 
2357 
15 
58 
S. carnosus subsp. utilis LTH7013 
South Tyrolean Ham 
Contigs 
NZ_LAIU00000000 
2.63 
34.4 
2399 
12 
57 
S. carnosus 336 
Beef trim 
Contigs 
NZ_LISV00000000 
2.67 
34.4 
2467 
12 
57 
S. simulans ACS-120-V-Sch1 
Human reproductive tract 
Scaffolds 
NZ_AGZX00000000 
2.67 
36.0 
2399 
14 
55 
S. simulans FDAARGOS_124 
Human blood 
Complete 
NZ_CP014016 
2.65 
36.0 
2390 
18 
59 
S. massiliensis CCUG 55927 
Human brain abscess 
Scaffolds 
NZ_AKGE00000000 
2.37 
36.5 
2106 
3 
55 
S. massiliensis S46 
Human healthy skin 
Contigs 
NZ_AMSQ00000000 
2.45 
36.3 
2251 
7 
53 
S. epidermidis ATCC 12228 
Reference strain 
Complete 
GCF_000007645 
2.56 
32.1 
2482 
16 
60 
S. aureus NCTC 8325 
Conjunctiva, corneal ulcer 
Complete 
GCF_000013425 
2.82 
32.9 
2767 
16 
61 </p>



<p>New Microbes and New Infections, Volume 18 Number C, July 2017 </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>© 2017 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 18, 8-14 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Midpoint rooted neighbour-</p>

<p>joining phylogenetic tree based on </p>

<p>sodA alignment (606 bp). Boot-</p>

<p>strapping values (1000 resamplings) </p>

<p>are displayed for each node. The </p>

<p>sodA gene of Staphylococcus con-</p>

<p>dimenti StO 2014-01 displays 100% </p>

<p>pairwise sequence identity to sodA of </p>

<p>S. condimenti DSM 11674, 96.54% </p>

<p>identity to S. carnosus LTH7013 and </p>

<p>S. carnosus 336, and 96.38% identity </p>

<p>to sodA of S. carnosus TM300. Identity </p>

<p>to S. simulans strains is 90.05%, to </p>

<p>S. massiliensis strains 81.05% and to </p>

<p>more distantly related S. aureus and </p>

<p>S. epidermidis strains from 78 to 83%. </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Whole genome comparison of the chromosome of Staphylococcus condimenti StO 2014-01 to the chromosomes of S. carnosus TM300 and </p>

<p>S. condimenti DSM 11674 created using BRIG [8]. Sequence identity is indicated by coloured key as specified. Putative horizontally transferred genomic </p>

<p>regions identified in S. condimenti StO 2014-01 are marked on the outer circle in black. </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>Gabrielsen et al. Virulence potential of S. condimenti </p>



<p>© 2017 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 18, 8-14 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>this strain contains a GroEL-integrated genomic island (SeR-
IFusB-like) that appears to be related to several phage-related 
resistance islands previously described in S. epidermidis [12]. 
The genomic island however lacks the region encoding the FusB 
gene providing resistance to fusidic acid. The clinical strain also 
contains a staphylococcal chromosomal cassette (SCC) that is 
99% identical to SCC M1 of S. aureus M1 [13]. The strain 
furthermore contains a 41.7 kb prophage similar to S. aureus 
phage 37 [14] as well as the well-characterized intercellular 
adhesion (ica) operon which is involved in biofilm formation 
[15]. Two other genomic regions (HGT 2 and HGT 3) identi-
fied as potentially horizontally transferred appear to be </p>

<p>involved in adherence. </p>

<p>Putative virulence factors identified in S. condimenti 
StO 2014-01 
We identified 37 putative virulence factors in S. condimenti StO 
2014-01, most of which were also found in either S. condimenti 
DSM 11674 and to a lesser extent in S. carnosus TM300 
(Table 4). Notably, S. condimenti StO 2014-01 encodes two 
proteins containing leukocidin domains that may form a puta-
tive bicomponent β-barrel toxin and have close homologs in 
S. condimenti DSM 11674. The S. condimenti clinical strain 
furthermore contains a number of genes which appear to 
encode functions related to immune evasion and suppression 
(Table 3). These include proteins encoding domains conserved 
in staphylococcal superantigens and toxins involved in modu-
lation of T-cell responses [16], immunoglobulin-binding domain 
B of staphylococcal protein A (SpA), as well as a putative sta-
phopain, extracellular fibrinogen-binding protein (Efb), staphy-
lococcal complement inhibitor (SCIN) and secreted von 
Willebrand factor-binding protein (VWbp). As is common in 
staphylococci, S. condimenti StO 2014-01 encodes a number of 
cell wall-anchored proteins, including microbial surface com-
ponents recognizing adhesive matrix molecules (MSCRAMMs) 
[17]. The strain furthermore encodes two putative phenol-</p>

<p>soluble modulins (PSMs), which have been implicated in 
proinflammatory and cytolytic activity, as well as in biofilm-
associated infections [18]. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study we have identified, sequenced the genome of and 
identified putative virulence traits of a strain of S. condimenti 
which caused severe soft tissue infection with extensive and 
prolonged inflammation of the leg and thighs in a patient with 
no known immune defects or underlying disease. This is the 
first reported genome of a S. condimenti strain involved in hu-</p>

<p>man disease. We compared the genome of the clinical strain 
with those of closely related staphylococci, i.e. the S. condimenti 
type strain DSM 11674 and three strains of S. carnosus, all of 
which have been isolated from food sources and have been 
considered to be nonpathogenic, in an attempt to elucidate 
which virulence traits contributed to the severity of disease 
observed in this case. 
S. condimenti was isolated in pure culture from both synovial 
fluid and several soft tissue samples collected via biopsy during </p>

<p>the first revision surgery 4 days after the first treatment for knee 
injury. S. condimenti must therefore be considered as the definite 
cause of infection in this case. The infection must also be classified 
as a severe, life-threatening condition because it progressed, 
necessitating multiple surgical revisions despite adequate intra-
venous antibiotic treatment. The 7-year-old patient did not have 
any known underlying disease or history of infections indicating 
primary immunodeficiency which could explain her susceptibility 
to a low-virulent bacterium, in contrast to the recently reported 
case of catheter-related bacteraemia in a patient with severe 
dilated cardiomyopathy [4]. 
Except the single case of infection mentioned earlier, 
S. condimenti has not previously been reported as a cause of 
infection in humans. This could reflect the low virulence of the </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Horizontally transferred regions identified in Staphylococcus condimenti StO 2014-01 </p>

<p>Name 
Type 
Locus 
Putative virulence genes </p>

<p>BLAST (nt/nr) best hit (% identity 
and % alignment length) </p>

<p>pStO 2014-01 
Plasmid 
1-35 235 (plasmid) 
Cadmium resistance 
operon, MSCRAMM </p>

<p>S. saphrophyticus strain FDAARGOS 168 
plasmid unnamed 1 (94%, 25%) 
SeRIFusB 
Genomic island 
1 087 133-1 102 997 
-
S. epidermidis NTUH-5907 antibiotic resistance 
island SeRIFusB-9507 (91%, 56%) 
SCCM1 
Staphylococcal 
chromosomal cassette </p>

<p>30 654-44 604 
-
S. aureus M1 composite island SCCM1 (99%, 100%) </p>

<p>Ica locus 
Genomic island 
78 554-97 039 
IcaADBC 
-
Leukocidin locus 
-
2 588 090-2 602 243 
Leukocidin genes 
-
Prophage 
Prophage 
1 972 956-12 014 682 
-
S. aureus phage 37 (95%, 29%) 
HGT region 2 
Genomic island/ 
prophage remnant </p>

<p>372 500-400 000 
MSCRAMMs 
-</p>

<p>HGT region 3 
Genomic island 
610 000-625 000 
Adhesins 
-</p>

<p>HGT, horizontal gene transfer; MSCRAMM, microbial surface component recognizing adhesive matrix molecules. </p>



<p>New Microbes and New Infections, Volume 18 Number C, July 2017 </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>© 2017 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 18, 8-14 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>species, but it may also be a consequence of the difficulty in 
identifying the species by phenotypic methods available in 
routine laboratories before matrix-assisted laser desorption/ 
ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS) 
was recently introduced [19]. Regardless, S. condimenti seems 
to be a rare cause of infections in humans. In a study including 
8388 CoNS identified by MALDI-TOF MS from clinical sam-
ples in a hospital in France, only three isolates were identified 
as S. condimenti [19]. Similarly, this bacterial species was 
identified in only one other clinical sample (one of four blood 
cultures) in addition to this case in the period since MALDI-
TOF MS was introduced in our university hospital labora-
tory in 2011. 
Both the clinical isolate and the S. condimenti type strain were 
susceptible to all antibiotics tested, which is in accordance with 
previous findings reporting low prevalence of antibiotic resis-
tance in this phylogenetic lineage of Staphylococcus [20]. The 
protracted course of infection in this patient was therefore not 
due to lack of susceptibility to the antibiotics used but rather to 
the aggressive nature of the infection. </p>

<p>Comparative genomic analysis of strain StO 2014-01 with 
genomes of related species shows high degree of conservation 
between the two S. condimenti genomes with few horizontally 
transferred genomic regions, although the low number of 
available genomes for comparison makes interpretation of re-
sults uncertain. Two of the pathogenicity islands, SCC M1 and 
seRiFusB-like, had a high degree of similarity to pathogenicity 
islands in S. aureus and S. epidermidis respectively. 
In this study we have identified a number of putative viru-
lence factors in S. condimenti StO 2014-01 which may have 
contributed to the observed severity of disease. Among these 
were proteins with similarity to leukocidin, involved in immune 
evasion, and with proinflammatory and cytolytic activity. 
However, to what extent these putative virulence factors are 
expressed and functional was not tested. In a previous study of 
CoNS isolated from food and starter cultures, no toxin pro-
duction was found in the two S. condimenti strains tested; 
however, one strain displayed moderate haemolytic activity on 
human blood agar [2]. Since most of the putative virulence 
genes identified in the strain StO 2014-01 were also present in </p>

<p>TABLE 4. Putative virulence factors and associated protein domains identified in Staphylococcus condimenti StO 2014-01 and their </p>

<p>presence or absence in S. condimenti DSM 11674, S. carnosus TM300, S. carnosus subsp. utilis LTH7013 and S. carnosus 336 </p>

<p>Protein 
Function and location 
Presence in strain </p>

<p>Locus 
Domains 
Putative function 
Location Group 
StO 2014-01 DSM 11674 TM300 LTH 7013 336 </p>

<p>87310-86081 
Glyco_tranf_2_3(D) 
Biofilm 
Ica region PIA 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
93502-90869 
SdrG_C_C(D), Fn_bind(R), 
Gram_pos_anchor(F) </p>

<p>Adhesion (Fn binding) 
MSCRAMMs + 
+ 
− 
− 
− </p>

<p>124775-125395 
Gram_pos_anchor(F) 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
128041-129885 
YSIRK_signal(M) 
+ 
+ 
+ 
− 
+ 
236818-240156 
Gram_pos_anchor(F), SdrG_C_C(D) 
Adhesion (Fn binding) 
MSCRAMMs + 
− 
+ 
+ 
+ 
356867-363328 
Gram_pos_anchor(F) 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
− 
381063-374938 
Gram_pos_anchor(F) 
HGT 2 
MSCRAMMs + 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
386132-381174 
Gram_pos_anchor(F) 
HGT 2 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
387035-386607 
YSIRK_signal(M) 
HGT 2 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
387441-396902 
YSIRK_signal(M), Collagen(R) 
Adhesion (Collagen binding) HGT2 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
401777-397014 
YSIRK_signal(M), Gram_pos_anchor(F) Adhesion 
HGT 2 
MSCRAMMs + 
− 
− 
− 
− 
440878-445341 
Cna_B(F), Gram_pos_anchor(F) 
Adhesion (Collagen binding) 
MSCRAMMs + 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
533545-532070 
Gram_pos_anchor(F) 
Adhesion 
MSCRAMMs + 
+ 
+ 
+ 
− 
581719-582465 
Wzz(F) 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
607537-608196 
Wzz(F) 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
610182-615884 
Gram_pos_anchor(F) 
Adhesion 
HGT 3 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
− 
616174-616500 
YSIRK_signal(M) 
HGT 3 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
1108237-1106822 B(D) 
Immune evasion 
Spa 
+ 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
1164228-1163152 Virul_fac_BrkB(F) 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
1558049-1559167 Virulence_fact(F) 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
1730473-1729709 SSL_OB(D), Stap_Strp_tox_C(F) 
Exotoxin/superantigen-like 
Toxins 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
1732147-1730576 Coagulase(D) 
Coagulase 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
1774244-1769928 Gram_pos_anchor(F) 
Adhesion 
MSCRAMMs + 
+ 
− 
− 
+ 
1859898-1859704 Staph_haemo(F) 
Haemolysis 
PSMs 
+ 
+ 
− 
+ 
− 
1860088-1859954 Staph_haemo(F) 
Haemolysis 
PSMs 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
1864696-1864199 efb-c(D) 
Adhesion/immune evasion 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
2081226-2082389 Staphopain_pro(D), Peptidase_C47(F) Immune evasion 
Staphopains + 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
2082420-2082749 Staphostatin_B(D) 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
2195344-2196078 Stap_Strp_tox_C(F) 
Exotoxin/superantigen-like 
Toxins 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
2513714-2511339 YSIRK_signal(M) 
+ 
+ 
− 
+ 
+ 
2589085-2588090 Leukocidin(D) 
Leukocidin 
Toxins 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
2590079-2589087 Leukocidin(D) 
Leukocidin 
Toxins 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
2597244-2596648 CompInhib_SCIN(F) 
Immune evasion 
SCIN 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
− 
2631010-2628557 YSIRK_signal(M) 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
2644454-2640147 YSIRK_signal(M) 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
− 
8288-6513 
Strep_67kDa_ant(F) 
Plasmid 
+ 
− 
− 
+ 
− 
31798-25526 
Gram_pos_anchor(F) 
Plasmid 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
− </p>

<p>HGT, horizontal gene transfer; MSCRAMM, microbial surface component recognizing adhesive matrix molecules; PSM, phenol-soluble modulin; SCIN, staphylococcal complement 
inhibitor; PIA, polysaccharide intercellular adhesin; D, domain; R, repeat; F, family; M, motif. </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>Gabrielsen et al. Virulence potential of S. condimenti </p>



<p>© 2017 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 18, 8-14 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>the type strain S. condimenti DSM 11674, it seems likely that the 
virulence potential of our clinical strain may also apply to strains 
associated with food and food production. 
In conclusion, we present a case of severe soft tissue infection 
caused by the CoNS S. condimenti, which has usually been 
considered nonpathogenic. Whole genome sequencing showed 
that the genome is highly conserved between the clinical strain 
and the type strain isolated from food. The genome contains 
several putative virulence factors, including leucocidin toxin-like 
proteins. Although uncommon, S. condimenti may cause severe 
infections in previously healthy persons. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>None declared. </p>





<p>New Microbes and New Infections, Volume 18 Number C, July 2017 </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>© 2017 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 18, 8-14 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

</text></tei>