<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5293859" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives Rates of chlamydia and gonorrhoea have 
been rising in urban centres in Canada, particularly 
among HIV-positive men who have sex with men 
(MSM). Our objective was to identify behavioural risk 
factors for diagnosis with chlamydia and gonorrhoea in 
this population, with a focus on the HIV status of sexual 
partners. 
Methods The OHTN Cohort Study follows people in 
HIV care across Ontario. We restricted the analysis to 
1997 MSM who completed questionnaires in 2010-
2013 at one of seven clinics that submit all chlamydia 
and gonorrhoea tests to the provincial public health 
laboratory; we obtained test results via record linkage. 
We estimated cumulative incidences using Kaplan-Meier 
methods and identified risk factors for diagnosis of a 
composite outcome (chlamydia or gonorrhoea infection) 
using Cox regression. 
Results At follow-up, there were 74 new chlamydia/ 
gonorrhoea diagnoses with a 12-month cumulative 
incidence of 1.7% (95% CI 1.1% to 2.2%). Risk factors 
for chlamydia/gonorrhoea diagnosis were: 5+ 
HIV-positive partners (HR=3.3, 95% CI 1.4 to 7.8; 
reference=none) and recreational drug use (HR=2.2, 
95% CI 1.2 to 3.9). 
Conclusions Heightened risks with recreational drug 
use and multiple HIV-positive partners suggest that 
chlamydia/gonorrhoea may have achieved high 
prevalence in certain sexual networks among HIV-
positive MSM. Interventions to promote safer sex and 
timely testing among MSM are needed. </p>

<p>Rates of chlamydia and gonorrhoea have risen in 
urban centres in Canada including an increase in 
case reports among men who have sex with men 
(MSM). 
1 Coinfection with HIV is particularly con-
cerning because sexually transmitted infections 
(STIs) can increase likelihood of HIV transmis-
sion. 
1 In Ontario, Canada, we previously reported 
demographic and clinical risk factors for new chla-
mydia and gonorrhoea diagnoses among an HIV 
clinical cohort followed from 2008 to 2011. 
2 Risk </p>

<p>was highest among MSM, particularly among 
younger MSM and (for gonorrhoea) among MSM 
with unsuppressed viral load, with little variation 
between ethnic groups. 
2 However, full characterisa-
tion of risk requires examination of behavioural 
risk factors since sexual behaviour and prevalence 
in sexual networks drive STI risk. 'Serosorting', 
selecting sexual partners of the same HIV serosta-
tus, could raise STI risk since condoms may be 
used less frequently, which could concentrate infec-
tion in sexual networks of HIV-positive persons. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Recreational drug use has also been linked to 
sexual risk taking. 
1 4 5 Our objective was to extend 
our previous analysis by longitudinally exploring 
behavioural risk factors for diagnoses of genital 
chlamydia and gonorrhoea infection among 
HIV-positive MSM attending HIV care in Ontario, 
specifically focusing on the risks associated with 
serosorting and recreational drug use. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>We analysed data from the Ontario HIV Treatment 
Network Cohort Study (OCS) which follows 
persons attending 10 HIV clinics across Ontario. 
The province has publicly funded, universal access 
to medically necessary healthcare. The OCS has 
been described in detail elsewhere 
6 and received 
ethical approval from the University of Toronto 
HIV Research Ethics Board ( protocol reference 
23954) and participating sites. Participation is vol-
untary. Data were collected through chart review, 
annual interviews and record linkage with the 
Public Health Ontario Laboratories (PHOL). At 
PHOL, simultaneous cotesting of chlamydia and 
gonorrhoea urine specimens was done by nucleic 
acid amplification testing using the Gen-Probe 
Aptima assay (Gen-Prose, San Diego, California, 
USA). Canadian guidelines recommend chlamydia 
and gonorrhoea testing annually for MSM at 
ongoing risk, regardless of HIV status. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Our focus was on sexual behaviour and recre-
ational drug use risk factors, adjusting for age, 
region and time-updated viral load as potential 
confounders. Men reported recreational drug use </p>

<p>Grewal R, et al. Sex Transm Infect 2017;93:71-75. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2015-052500 </p>

<p>
Epidemiology </p>

<p>in face-to-face interviews. Next, they self-completed a compu-
terised sexual behaviour questionnaire without interviewers 
present. 
As of 12/2013, there were 6408 enrolees. Our analysis 
included 1997 male participants reporting non-heterosexual 
orientation or sex with men as an HIV risk factor; self-
completed at least one sexual behaviour questionnaire between 
2010 and 2013 and attended one of seven clinics that submitted 
all chlamydia and gonorrhoea tests to PHOL, the primary pro-
vider for chlamydia and gonorrhoea tests for sexual health 
clinics (HIV specialty and primary care clinics may also send 
specimens to private laboratories). 
We conducted all statistical analyses using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, North Carolina, USA). p Values were two-sided 
and statistical significance was determined using the p value of 
&lt;0.05. We used Kaplan-Meier methods to estimate the cumula-
tive incidence proportions tested for or diagnosed with chla-
mydia or gonorrhoea following completion of the first sexual 
behaviour questionnaire. As previously done, diagnosis rates 
were calculated among tested and untested participants 
2 thus 
underestimating true incidence since asymptomatic infections 
among those untested are excluded from the numerator. 
For risk factor analysis, we grouped chlamydia and gonor-
rhoea into a composite outcome to improve statistical power 
and because their modes of transmission and clinical/public 
health implications are similar; HR estimates for separate chla-
mydia and gonorrhoea outcomes were not meaningfully differ-
ent. For men diagnosed more than once, we selected the earliest 
event, which occurred rarely. We excluded participants with 
missing data (1.3% of observations) and two cases with zero 
event times. Men with no events were censored using the earli-
est of the dates of loss to follow-up, death or 31 December 
2013. </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of HIV-positive men who have sex with 
men (MSM) at completion of their first sexual behaviour 
questionnaire, OHTN Cohort Study, 2010-2013 </p>

<p>Total N 
1997 (100%) 
Mean age at baseline (SD) 
47.7 (10.2) 
Self-reported sexual orientation 
Gay 
1767 (88.5%) 
Bisexual 
151 (7.6%) 
Heterosexual 
58 (2.9%) 
Unknown* 
21 (1.1%) 
Race/ethnicity 
White 
1492 (74.7%) 
Black/African 
80 (4.0%) 
Mixed race/ethnicity 
168 (8.4%) 
Indigenous 
85 (4.3%) 
Other 
170 (8.5%) 
Education 
High school or less 
448 (22.4%) 
Some postsecondary 
435 (21.8%) 
Completed postsecondary 
1111 (55.6%) 
Annual personal income 
&lt;$C20 000 
702 (35.2%) 
$C20 000-$C59 999 
794 (39.8%) 
≥$C60 000 
470 (23.5%) 
Unknown 
31 (1.6%) 
Region where receiving HIV care 
Toronto 
1703 (85.3%) 
Other 
294 (14.7%) 
Year of HIV diagnosis 
Prior to 2000 
1129 (56.5%) 
2000-2009 
737 (36.9%) 
2010 or later 
131 (6.6%) 
Median (IQR) 
1997 (1991-2005) 
HIV clinical status 
Initiated antiretroviral treatment 
1647 (82.5%) 
Mean CD4 cell count/mm 
3 (SD) 
537 (253) 
Undetectable viral load (&lt;40 copies/mL) 
1568 (78.5%) 
Recreational drug use in the preceding 6 months 
Any † 
418 (20.9%) 
Methamphetamines 
188 (9.4%) 
Cocaine 
205 (10.3%) 
Club drugs ‡ 
217 (10.9%) 
Other § 
187 (9.4%) 
Multiple (two or more) 
232 (11.6%) 
Sexual behaviours in the preceding 3 months </p>

<p>Number of sexual partners 
None 
710 (35.6%) 
One 
535 (26.8%) 
Two to four 
452 (22.6%) 
Five or more 
274 (13.7%) 
Number of HIV-positive partners 
None 
1210 (60.6%) 
One 
330 (16.5%) 
Two to four 
255 (12.8%) 
Five or more 
100 (5.0%) 
Number of HIV-negative/status unknown partners 
None 
1101 (55.1%) 
One 
364 (18.2%) 
Two to four 
229 (11.5%) 
Five or more 
214 (10.7%) </p>

<p>Continued </p>

<p>Table 1 Continued </p>

<p>Anal sex 
No partner 
710 (35.6%) 
Sexually active but no anal sex 
319 (16.0%) 
Anal sex always with a condom 
349 (17.5%) 
Any condomless anal sex 
551 (27.6%) 
Anal sex with HIV-positive partners ¶ 
No HIV-positive partners 
1210 (60.6%) 
Sexually active but no anal sex 
124 (6.2%) 
Anal sex always with a condom 
147 (7.4%) 
Any condomless anal sex 
416 (20.8%) 
Anal sex with HIV-negative/status unknown partners ¶ 
No HIV-negative/status unknown partners 
1101 (55.1%) 
Sexually active but no anal sex 
214 (10.7%) 
Anal sex always with a condom 
347 (17.4%) 
Any condomless anal sex 
257 (12.9%) </p>

<p>*Only 0.1% of the sample had missing data for race/ethnicity and 0.2% for education. 
 †Any recreational drug use includes anabolic steroids, amphetamines, 
methamphetamines, cocaine, crack/freebase, club drugs, heroin, other opiates, 
tranquilisers and other drugs, except cannabis as it was unmeasured for 4/7 
participating clinic sites. 
 ‡Club drugs include Ecstasy/MDMA (3,4-methylenedioxy-methamphetamine), Special 
K (ketamine), GHB (γ hydroxybutyrate), PCP (phencyclidine) and poppers (amyl 
nitrite). 
 §Other includes anabolic steroids, amphetamines, crack/freebase, heroin, other 
opiates, tranquilisers and 'other' option in drug use section of questionnaire. 
 ¶Serostatus-specific variables were not mutually exclusive. The sexual behaviour 
questionnaire had a series of questions for HIV-positive partners followed by 
questions specific to HIV-negative/status unknown partners allowing for the capture 
and coding of different sexual practices by HIV status of partners. </p>

<p> 
Grewal R, et al. Sex Transm Infect 2017;93:71-75. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2015-052500 </p>

<p>Epidemiology </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>At completion of their first sexual behaviour questionnaire, men 
were aged 48 years, on average (table 1). The median number of 
years since HIV diagnosis was 18 (IQR 10-24). The majority 
(64.4%) were sexually active in the preceding 3 months, 
whereas a minority (20.9%) reported recreational drug use 
(table 1). 
Men were followed a median of 2.9 years (IQR 1.8-3.3) for a 
sum of 5833 person-years. The Kaplan-Meier cumulative prob-
abilities of testing for chlamydia/gonorrhoea were 24.6% at 
12 months and 33.1% at 24 months. In all, 35.1% (700/1997) 
were tested over the entire course of follow-up. The majority of 
tests were ordered by participating HIV clinics (87.6%) with 
only 3.0% ordered by sexual health/STI/community health </p>

<p>clinics and 9.3% by other health providers. Stratum-specific 
12-month testing probabilities ranged from 15.8% among sexu-
ally inactive men to 42.5% among men reporting 5+ partners 
(table 2). 
At follow-up, 41, 46 and 74 men were diagnosed with chla-
mydia, gonorrhoea and either pathogen, respectively. The 
Kaplan-Meier 12-month cumulative incidence proportions were 
1.0% (95% CI 0.6% to 1.4%) for chlamydia, 1.2% (95% CI 
0.7% to 1.7%) for gonorrhoea and 1.7% (95% CI 1.1% to 
2.2%) for the composite outcome. Among cases, 53% (39 of 
74) had a history of syphilis compared with 9.5% among 
non-cases. 
Multiple sex partners and recreational drug use were signifi-
cant risk factors for diagnosis (table 2). Risk was elevated </p>

<p>Table 2 Behavioural risk factors for a diagnosis of genital chlamydia/gonorrhoea infection at follow-up among HIV-positive MSM, OHTN 
Cohort Study, 2010-2013 </p>

<p>Sexual behaviours in preceding 3 months* </p>

<p>Cumulative 
probability 
of testing 
at 12 months 
(95% CI) † </p>

<p>Cumulative 
incidence of 
diagnosis 
at 12 months 
(95% CI) † </p>

<p>Unadjusted HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Multivariable 
model A ‡: 
adjusted HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Multivariable 
model B ‡: 
adjusted HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Number of sexual partners 
None 
15.8 (13.3 to 18.4) 
0.4 (0.0 to 0.8) 
Reference 
Reference 
One 
20.0 (16.7 to 23.3) 
0.7 (0.0 to 1.4) 
2.7 (0.9 to 7.9) 
Two to four 
33.9 (29.7 to 38.1) 
3.0 (1.5 to 4.6) 
10.3 (4.0 to 26.6) 
3.1 (1.4 to 6.6) 
Five or more 
42.5 (36.7 to 48.3) 
4.8 (2.4 to 7.3) 
16.0 (6.1 to 41.7) 
3.7 (1.7 to 8.3) 
Number of HIV-positive partners 
None 
19.0 (16.9 to 21.2) 
0.8 (0.3 to 1.2) 
Reference 
Reference 
One 
26.8 (22.2 to 31.4) 
2.2 (0.7 to 3.8) 
2.3 (1.1 to 4.7) 
Two to four 
40.1 (34.2 to 45.9) 
2.9 (0.9 to 5.0) 
5.0 (2.7 to 9.4) 
1.6 (0.7 to 3.6) 
Five or more 
42.3 (32.8 to 51.7) 
8.3 (3.1 to 13.5) 
13.5 (7.1 to 25.5) 
3.3 (1.4 to 7.8) 
Number of HIV-negative/status UK partners 
None 
20.9 (18.6 to 23.2) 
1.1 (0.5 to 1.7) 
Reference 
Reference 
One 
22.3 (18.2 to 26.4) 
1.0 (0.0 to 2.0) 
1.0 (0.5 to 2.0) 
Two to four 
34.6 (28.6 to 40.5) 
2.5 (0.5 to 4.4) 
2.2 (1.2 to 4.3) 
1.2 (0.5 to 2.9) 
Five or more 
33.7 (27.6 to 39.9) 
4.8 (2.0 to 7.5) 
3.5 (1.9 to 6.2) 
1.2 (0.5 to 3.0) 
Anal sex 
No partner 
15.8 (13.3 to 18.4) 
1.0 (0.3 to 1.7) 
Reference 
Reference 
Sexually active but no anal sex § 
20.8 (16.5 to 25.1) 
1.3 (0.0 to 2.5) 
1.9 (1.1 to 3.3) 
0.5 (0.1 to 3.0) 
Anal sex always with a condom 
25.6 (21.2 to 30.0) 
3.4 (1.5 to 5.3) 
1.9 (0.5 to 6.9) 
3.3 (1.0 to 11.4) 
Any condomless anal sex 
36.8 (32.9, 40.7) 
6.0 (4.1 to 8.0) 
7.0 (2.5 to 19.0) 
3.6 (1.0 to 12.3) 
Anal sex with HIV+ partner 
No HIV+ partner 
19.0 (16.9 to 21.2) 
0.8 (0.3 to 1.2) 
Reference 
Reference 
Sexually active with HIV+ partner but no anal sex § 
17.1 (10.7 to 23.5) 
0.0 (0.0 to 0.0) 
1.0 (0.2 to 4.4) 
1.2 (0.3 to 5.2) 
Anal sex with HIV+ partner always with a condom 
28.5 (21.5 to 35.4) 
1.2 (0.0 to 2.8) 
4.0 (1.8 to 8.8) 
2.8 (0.6 to 13.4) 
Any condomless anal sex with HIV+ partner 
40.6 (35.9 to 45.2) 
5.4 (3.3 to 7.5) 
6.3 (3.7 to 10.8) 
2.2 (0.5 to 9.8) 
Anal sex with HIV−/UK partner 
No HIV−/UK partner 
20.9 (18.6 to 23.2) 
1.1 (0.5 to 1.7) 
Reference 
Reference 
Sexually active with HIV−/UK partner but no anal sex § 
22.3 (16.9 to 27.7) 
0.4 (0.0 to 1.3) 
0.7 (0.2 to 2.0) 
1.6 (1.5 to 5.1) 
Anal sex with HIV−/UK partner always with a condom 
29.6 (25.0 to 34.2) 
2.8 (1.2 to 4.5) 
2.0 (1.1 to 3.7) 
2.2 (0.7 to 6.9) 
Any condomless anal sex with HIV−/UK partner 
35.0 (29.3 to 40.7) 
3.3 (1.2 to 5.5) 
3.0 (1.6 to 5.3) 
1.7 (0.6 to 5.3) 
Any recreational drug use in preceding 6 months ¶ 
No 
21.1 (19.2 to 23.0) 
0.9 (0.4 to 1.3) 
Reference 
Reference 
Reference 
Yes 
38.2 (33.7 to 42.8) 
4.7 (2.8 to 6.7) 
5.0 (3.1 to 5.9) 
1.8 (1.1 to 3.2) 
2.2 (1.2 to 3.9) </p>

<p>UK=status unknown. 
*Behaviours were time-updated at each completion of a sexual behaviour questionnaire. 
 †Cumulative incidence proportions for testing and diagnosis were calculated using Kaplan-Meier methods. 
 ‡Multivariable models adjusted for variables shown plus baseline age, region and time-updated viral load. Model A includes measures of sexual behaviours with HIV-negative, 
HIV-positive and HIV status unknown partners grouped together. Model B distinguishes sexual behaviour according to partners' HIV status. 
 §The category 'sexually active, but no anal sex' was assigned to men who reported one or more partners to the question 'In the last 3 months how many male partners have you had 
sex with?' but responded 'Never' to the statements 'I had anal sex with him' for any reported HIV-positive or HIV-negative/status unknown partner. 
 ¶Drug use was time -updated at each completion of a face-to-face interview. All drugs were combined to avoid multicollinearity. 
MSM, men who have sex with men. </p>

<p>Grewal R, et al. Sex Transm Infect 2017;93:71-75. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2015-052500 </p>

<p>
Epidemiology </p>

<p>among men who reported 5+ HIV-positive partners but not for 
multiple HIV-negative/unknown partners in the adjusted model. 
Recreational drug use doubled risk. Point estimates indicated 
elevated risk with anal sex (regardless of condom use); however, 
there was inadequate precision to indicate statistical significance. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Among gay and other MSM in an Ontario HIV-positive clinical 
cohort from 2010 to 2013, the 12-month cumulative incidence 
of a genital chlamydia/gonorrhoea diagnosis was substantial at 
1.7% (95% CI 1.1% to 2.2%). Risk factors were having mul-
tiple HIV-positive partners and recreational drug use. Strengths 
of our analysis include a large sample, tests from a single labora-
tory and 98% completion rate of the sexual behaviour question-
naire. To our knowledge, our study is the first to compare 
longitudinal chlamydia/gonorrhoea diagnosis rates from mul-
tiple clinics among HIV-positive MSM by partners' HIV status. 
There are limitations. Canadian and US guidelines recom-
mend extragenital testing if engaging in oral or rectal inter-
course 
2 yet such tests were rarely done in our setting, meaning 
we could not identify rectal or pharyngeal infection risk factors. 
A 3-month time frame for sexual behaviours mitigated recall 
error but resulted in unmeasured behaviour between annual 
questionnaires, potentially explaining the non-zero diagnosis 
rate among men reporting no partners. Measurement of recre-
ational drug use via face-to-face interviews may have introduced 
social desirability bias. Voluntary participation may have intro-
duced selection bias. The OCS under-represents recent diagno-
ses; however, participants are generalisable to HIV-positive 
persons in Ontario according to sex, region, age at diagnosis 
and HIV exposure category. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Recreational drug use was also a risk factor for chlamydia/ 
gonorrhoea diagnosis in cross-sectional prevalence studies exe-
cuted in clinics in Madrid and the Netherlands, 
4 5 which was 
demonstrated for genital, rectal and pharyngeal infections. The 
Netherlands study reported multiple partners as a risk factor for 
chlamydia, gonorrhoea and syphilis combined; however, the 
association became null when syphilis and chlamydia/gonor-
rhoea were analysed separately. The Madrid study reported risk 
associated with serosorting, defined as having a stable 
HIV-positive partner, whereas in our setting having multiple 
HIV-positive partners was most important. 
Only 5% of men reported 5+ HIV-positive partners, but risk 
was highest in this group, with 12-month diagnosis rates of 
8.3% (95% CI 3.1% to 13.5%). After adjustment for 
HIV-positive partners, no additional risk was associated with 
having multiple HIV-negative/unknown partners. We propose 
three hypotheses. First, men may use condoms less frequently 
for 'poz' sex; however, we observed similar risks between 
condom users and non-users. Second, HIV-positive men may 
choose receptive anal sex with HIV-negative partners reducing 
their risk of genital infection; 
3 however, information on seropo-
sitioning was unavailable. Third, chlamydia/gonorrhoea may 
have achieved high prevalence in sexual networks among 
HIV-positive MSM seeking other positive men, and these net-
works may have low connectedness with HIV-negative MSM. 
That half of cases had a history of syphilis suggests presence of 
a core group where bacterial STIs are concentrated. In a study 
of German MSM, HIV-positive serosorters had threefold higher 
odds of bacterial STIs versus those with serodiscordant part-
ners. 
8 Together with our finding of heightened risk for recre-
ational drug use, we recommend further investigation of how 
'scene' participation (eg, poz parties, bathhouses) influences STI 
risk. 
1 Further, as more HIV-negative men use pre-exposure </p>

<p>prophylaxis for HIV prevention, sexual networks between 
HIV-negative and HIV-positive men may become more con-
nected if serosorting becomes less common, 
9 resulting in more 
population-level transmission of bacterial STI. 
Our findings have implications for chlamydia/gonorrhoea pre-
vention, testing and treatment among HIV-positive MSM. 
Non-zero diagnosis rates among men reporting condom-
protected anal sex suggests some acquisition through unmeas-
ured risk practices such as oral sex; 
1 sexual education messages 
should emphasise the differences in bacterial STI transmission 
routes compared with HIV. Testing was below recommended 
guidelines; the proportion of untested men reporting high-risk 
behaviours was substantial. We strongly encourage rectal testing 
which could detect up to 80% more asymptomatic infections. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>There is a need to design and deliver interventions to promote 
safer sex and testing in ways that are engaging, non-stigmatising 
and acceptable for men at risk. Potential clinic-based interven-
tions to optimise testing include algorithms targeting high-risk 
patients, clinical decision support systems, automated patient/ 
provider alerts and laboratory technologies to improve case 
detection. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Centre for Research on Inner City Health, Li Ka Shing Knowledge Institute, 
St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Public Health Laboratories, Public Health Ontario, Toronto, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Dalla Lana School of Public Health, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Baycrest Health Science, Toronto, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Ontario HIV Treatment Network, Toronto, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Department of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Toronto General Research Institute, University Health Network, Toronto, Ontario, 
Canada </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Division of Infectious Diseases, St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Institute of Health Policy, Management and Evaluation, University of Toronto, 
Toronto, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Division of General Internal Medicine, St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto, Ontario, 
Canada </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Department of Microbiology, Mount Sinai Hospital/University Health Network, 
Toronto, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>AIDS Bureau, Ontario Ministry of Health and Long-Term Care, Toronto, Ontario, 
Canada </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Department of Psychiatry, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Department of Family and Community Medicine, St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto, 
Ontario, Canada </p>

<p>Handling editor Jackie A Cassell </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors acknowledge the contribution of the late 
Dr Robert S Remis for guidance on earlier versions of this work. Further, we 
gratefully acknowledge all of the people living with HIV who volunteered to 
participate in the OHTN Cohort Study and the work and support of past and 
present members of the Governance Committee: Adrian Betts, Anita C. Benoit, 
Breklyn Bertozzi, Les Bowman, Lisungu Chieza, Tracey Conway, Patrick Cupido 
(Chair), Tony Di Pede, Brian Finch, Michael J. Hamilton, Brian Huskins, Rick 
Kennedy, Ken King, Nathan Lachowsky, Joanne Lindsay, Shari Margolese, Mark 
McCallum, John McTavish, Colleen Price, Lori Stoltz, Darien Taylor, Rosie Thein, 
and Drs AMB, Evan Collins, Curtis Cooper, Clemon George, Troy Grennan, Claire 
Kendall, and Greg Robinson. We thank all the interviewers, data collectors, 
research associates and coordinators, nurses and physicians who provide support 
for data collection and extraction. The authors wish to thank the OCS staff for 
data management, IT support, and study coordination (Madison Kopansky-Giles, 
Jason Globerman, Beth Rachlis, Robert Hudder, Gokul Kalaimani, Lucia Light, 
Veronika Moravan, Nahid Qureshi) and Public Health Ontario Laboratories for 
supporting record linkage with the HIV viral load, chlamydia and gonorrhoea test 
databases. </p>

<p>Collaborators The OHTN Cohort Study Team consists of Dr SBR (Principal 
Investigator), University of Toronto and OHTN; Dr Sergio Rueda, CAMH; Dr ANB, 
Dr AMB, Dr Kevin Gough and Dr DHST, St Michael's Hospital; Dr Jeffrey Cohen, 
Windsor Regional Hospital; Dr Curtis Cooper, Ottawa General Hospital; Dr Don 
Kilby, University of Ottawa Health Services; Dr Mona Loutfy and Dr Fred Crouzat, 
Maple Leaf Medical Clinic; Dr Anita Rachlis and Dr Nicole Mittmann, Sunnybrook 
Health Sciences Centre; Dr JR and Dr Irving Salit, Toronto General Hospital; Dr 
Edward Ralph, Dr Michael Silverman, St Joseph's Health Care; Dr Roger Sandre, </p>

<p> 
Grewal R, et al. Sex Transm Infect 2017;93:71-75. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2015-052500 </p>

<p>Epidemiology </p>



<p>Contributors RG conducted the analysis and wrote the manuscript. ANB was the 
principal investigator who conceived the project, obtained funding and contributed to 
the direction of the analysis and manuscript writing; she is the guarantor. ANB and 
SBR directed data collection at clinic sites. VGA and TM directed laboratory analysis at 
the PHOL and its interpretation. SG, VM and JR provided statistical expertise. AMB, 
RK, DHST and FM, contributed to the study protocol and guided interpretation. All 
authors provided critical input into the analysis, read an earlier version of the paper, 
provided substantive feedback and approved the final paper. </p>

<p>Funding This work was supported by Canadian Institutes of Health Research 
(CIHR) operating grant 111146, CIHR New Investigator awards to ANB and to DHST, 
an OHTN Chair and support from the Toronto and Western Hospital Foundation 
Skate the Dream Fund for JR and a Fondation Baxter and Alma Ricard Chair in Inner 
City Health at St Michael's Hospital for AMB. The OHTN Cohort Study is funded by 
the AIDS Bureau, Ontario Ministry of Health and Long-Term Care. </p>

<p>Disclaimer The opinions, results and conclusions are those of the authors and no 
endorsement by the Ontario HIV Treatment Network or Public Health Ontario is 
intended or should be inferred. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Ethics approval University of Toronto HIV Research Ethics Board ( protocol 
reference 23954). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement The OHTN may authorise the collection, use and 
disclosure of OCS data for the purpose of scholarly research if the proposal for the 
research project has been reviewed and approved and the research project principal 
investigator and all other members of the research project team have signed a 
researcher's agreement with the OHTN and adhere to all relevant OCS data and 
research policies. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which 
permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, </p>

<p>and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is 
properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Grewal R, et al. Sex Transm Infect 2017;93:71-75. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2015-052500 </p>

<p>
Epidemiology </p>

</text></tei>