<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5063056" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>PURPOSE. To determine whether levels of endogenous tear protein, lacritin, are linked to 
altered corneal innervation and dry eye severity in patients with 's syndrome (SS). </p>

<p>METHODS. Clinical data were obtained from 10 SS and 10 age-matched controls. Enzyme-linked 
immunosorbent assay was used to assess total tear lacritin extracted from Schirmer strips. Western 
blot was used to detect active lacritin monomer (~25 kDa), active lacritin fragment (~12-15 
kDa), and inactive tissue transglutaminase-generated lacritin ( ‡40 kDa). In vivo confocal 
microscopy was used to assess nerve fiber density (NFD) and length (NFL). Relationships between 
nerve morphology and tear lacritin were examined by Spearman correlation. Diagnostic 
performance of tear lacritin was analyzed using receiver operating characteristic. </p>

<p>RESULTS. Active tear lacritin was significantly reduced in SS patients (3.72 6 5.62 [SS] versus 18.17 
6 4.57 ng/100 ng total tear protein [controls]; P &lt; 0.001), while inactive lacritin was increased 
(84.99% 6 11.15% [SS] versus 51.04% 6 12.03% [controls]; P &lt; 0.001). Nerve fiber density 
(21.70 6 18.93 vs. 31.80 6 9.35; P ¼ 0.03) and NFL (4.18 6 3.44 vs. 6.54 6 2.47; P &lt; 0.05) were 
significantly decreased in SS patients compared to controls. Reduced NFL (r ¼ 0.74, P &lt; 0.01) 
and NFD (r ¼ 0.70, P &lt; 0.01) were highly correlated with reduced tear lacritin. Similarly, total 
tear lacritin was highly correlated with Schirmers (r ¼ 0.77, P &lt; 0.01), ocular staining (r ¼ 
À0.80, P &lt; 0.01), and corneal sensitivity (r ¼ 0.81, P &lt; 0.01). Tear lacritin showed equivalent or 
better diagnostic performance compared to traditional clinical measures for SS (100.00% 
sensitivity, 85.71% specificity, cutoff ¼ 14.50 ng/100 ng tear protein). </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS. Reduced tear lacritin levels in SS patients are highly correlated with clinical signs 
of dry eye, as well as decreased NFD and NFL. Lacritin and its components provide excellent 
diagnostic sensitivity and specificity in SS. </p>

<p>monomer and the 12-to 15-kDa fragment in tears of SS patients; 
however, the total amount of lacritin in tears was not explored, 
nor was the relative expression of active (&lt;40 kDa) versus inactive 
(&gt;40 kDa) species. 15 
Based on these data, we hypothesized that reduced levels of 
tear lacritin are functionally linked to altered integrity and 
innervation of the ocular surface in SS patients. Using tear 
proteins eluted from Schirmer strips, we are the first to quantify 
the amount of total lacritin and its three major isoforms in tears 
of SS patients and age-matched controls. In the same cohort, we 
used in vivo confocal microscopy (IVCM) to assess changes in 
corneal innervation and examine the relationships between 
corneal nerve morphology and tear lacritin levels. Our studies 
revealed profound reductions in corneal nerve fiber density and 
length that were highly correlated with reduced levels of active 
lacritin and increased levels of inactive lacritin in SS tears. These 
results provide the first evidence of an association between tear 
lacritin and altered corneal innervation, supporting the potential 
for a functional link that will be further explored in preclinical 
and clinical studies of lacritin as a treatment for aqueous-
deficient dry eye. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Human Subject Recruitment and Sample Collection </p>

<p>All aspects of the human subject studies presented in this 
manuscript followed the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki 
and were approved by the University of California-San Francisco 
(UCSF) Committee for Human Research prior to subject 
recruitment. Informed consent was obtained from all subjects 
and all study activities were Health Insurance Portability and 
Accountability Act compliant. Clinical data were obtained from 
SS patients (n ¼ 10) and age-matched controls (n ¼ 10). All SS 
patients met diagnostic criteria established by the 's 
International Collaborative Clinical Alliance (SICCA). 16 Briefly, 
each participant with SS tested positive for at least two of the 
three primary outcome variables: an ocular surface staining 
score (OSS) greater than or equal to 3; a labial salivary gland 
focus score greater than or equal to 1 focus/4 mm 2 ; and 
presence of autoantibody anti-SSB/La and/or -SSA/Ro or both 
antinuclear antibody (ANA) titer ( ‡1:320) and rheumatoid factor 
(RF). These SICCA classified cases and controls were used as 
''gold standards'' for diagnostic performance assessment. 
Outcome variables included unanesthetized Schirmer test (a 
measure of tear secretion), the OSS (a measure of ocular surface 
integrity), 17 tear breakup time (TBUT, a measure of tear 
stability), Cochet Bonet aesthesiometry (a method of corneal 
sensitivity testing [CST]), and the Ocular Surface Disease Index 
(OSDI, an established questionnaire used to assess severity of 
dry eye-associated symptoms). Exam procedures adhered to the 
protocol established by SICCA 17 with the addition of asking each 
patient to complete the OSDI questionnaire prior to examina-
tion and performing CST using Cochet Bonet at the beginning of 
each exam. Schirmer strips collected from SS (n ¼ 9) and control 
(n ¼ 7) patients were stored in a À808C freezer until analysis. At 
the time of analysis, strips were immersed in 30 lL PBS for 20 
minutes at room temperature and eluted by centrifugation, and 
the tear proteins were assessed by ELISA and Western blot. Tear 
protein concentration was assessed by the BCA assay (Thermo 
Scientific BCA Protein Assay Kit; Pierce Biotechnology, Rock-
ford, IL, USA) using bovine serum albumin as a protein standard. </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>Lissamine Green and fluorescein sodium were obtained from 
Leiter's Pharmacy and Compounding Center (San Jose, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Ocular surface integrity was assessed using the OSS developed by 
SICCA. Alcon Schirmer Standard Tear Test Strips (Fort Worth, TX, 
USA) were used to assess unanesthetized tear secretion. Enzyme-
linked immunosorbent assay and Western blots for lacritin were 
carried out using antibodies produced from the peptide 
EDASSDSTGADPAQEAGTS (Pep Lac N-Term), corresponding to 
the N-terminus of mature human lacritin (amino acids 1-19 
without signal peptide) synthesized &gt;85% purity and conjugated 
to keyhole limpet hemocyanin (KLH) by Bio-Synthesis, Inc. 
(Lewisville, TX, USA). New Zealand white rabbits were 
immunized in three boosts with Pep Lac N-Term-KLH. Final 
antiserum (anti-Pep Lac N-Term) was collected on day 70. </p>

<p>ELISA Methods </p>

<p>For assay of tear samples, 100 ng total tear protein was coated 
in each well. To generate a standard curve of recombinant 
lacritin, each plate contained triplicate wells to which 2, 4, 6, 
8, 10, 12, 14, or 16 ng protein was added. Wells were washed, 
blocked with PBS-Tween (PBS with 0.3% Tween-20 [PBS-T]), 
and then incubated for 1 hour at 378C with 100 lL anti-Pep Lac 
N-Term antiserum diluted 1:3000 in PBS-T. After washing three 
times with PBS-T, horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated 
goat anti-rabbit IgG (MP Biomedicals, Solon, OH, USA) diluted 
1:1000 in PBS-T was added for 1 hour (378C). Plates were 
washed three times with PBS-T, and then bound antibody was 
measured after incubation for 10 minutes with 100 lL OPD (o-
phenylenediamine dihydrochloride) substrate (Acros Organics, 
Geel, Belgium) by absorbance at 415 nm (model 680; Bio-Rad, 
Hercules, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Western Blotting </p>

<p>Tear samples were loaded on Any kD Mini-PROTEAN TGX 
Precast Protein Gels (Bio-Rad), electrophoresed at 200 V, and 
transferred to nitrocellulose (Protran BA 83; Whatman, Dassel, 
Germany). Blots were blocked with PBS-T, incubated with anti-
Lac Pep N-Term (1:1000 dilution in PBS-T) for 1 hour at room 
temperature, rinsed with PBS-T, and incubated for 1 hour at 
room temperature with HRP-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG 
(MP Biomedicals) diluted 1:5000 in PBS-T. Blots were rinsed 
with PBS-T and developed via chemiluminescence with Pierce 
ECL Western Blotting Substrate (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc., 
Rockford, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Quantification of Active and Inactive Lacritin 
Species Using Densitometry </p>

<p>The signal intensity of lacritin bands was determined by 
multiplying the area of the band with the average pixel 
intensity to provide volume-sum intensity for each band. The 
signal intensity of the 12-to 15-kDa, 25-kDa, and 40-kDa bands 
from each individual's tear sample was quantified using <rs id="software-2" type="software">ImageJ</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">(http://imagej.nih.gov/ij</rs>: provided in the public domain by the 
National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA). The signal 
intensity value of each band was expressed as area pixel 
density. Data were expressed as the relative percentage of 
lacritin species by dividing the signal intensity of each lacritin 
species (i.e., lacritin cleaved fragment [15 kDa], lacritin 
monomer [26 kDa], or inactive lacritin polymers &gt;40 kDa) 
by the total signal intensity of all lacritin species. </p>

<p>In Vivo Confocal Microscopy </p>

<p>Images of corneal nerves were collected using the Nidek 
Confoscan 4 (Nidek Technologies, Fremont, CA, USA) in vivo 
scanning confocal microscope equipped with a 340 lens. 
Images were obtained from the epithelial to endothelial surface 
of the central cornea (460 3 345 lm). To maintain masking, 
each set of images was renamed before selecting the series of </p>

<p>Dry Eye Alters Tear Lacritin and Corneal Nerves 
IOVS j October 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 13 j 5238 </p>

<p>frames that corresponded to the subepithelial compartment 
and contained images of the subbasal nerve plexus. Three 
trained observers assessed four parameters of nerve morphol-
ogy: nerve fiber density (NFD), nerve fiber length (NFL), nerve 
branch density (NBD), and tortuosity using <rs type="software">CC Metrics</rs>, a 
semiautomated nerve analysis program developed by Rayaz 
Malik, University of Manchester, Manchester, United Kingdom. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>All analyses are based on readouts obtained from single eyes 
randomly chosen from each patient. Demographic variables, 
tear lacritin levels, corneal nerve morphology, and clinical 
measures of ocular surface disease (i.e., OSDI, Schirmer, OSS, 
TBUT, and CST) were compared between SS and age-matched 
controls. Group differences in sex and ethnicity were tested by 
Fisher's exact test; Schirmer score, OSDI, OSS, CST, TBUT, 
percent expression of tear lacritin isoforms, and features of 
nerve fiber morphology were examined by Wilcoxon exact test. 
Differences in age and total tear lacritin assessed by ELISA were 
compared by t-test. Correlations among variables were assessed 
by Spearman correlation and reported as correlation coefficients 
along with their corresponding P values to provide information 
on the strength and reliability of the correlation, respectively. 18 
Of these measures, integer and continuous variables were 
summarized as mean and standard deviation (SD), categorical 
and binary variables as the accounted number of subjects. 
Western blot data were normalized by the three-component sum 
of lacritin species for each sample 19 ; then normalized values 
were presented as percentages. Performance of clinical readouts 
and lacritin-based tear measurements as diagnostic parameters 
to identify patients with the ocular component of SS was 
assessed by receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves using 
the <rs id="software-0" type="software">RStudio</rs> platform (Boston, MA, USA), <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 0.98.1102</rs>. 
Area under the curve (AUC) was estimated by R package pROC 
to determine the 95% confidence intervals (95%CI). 20 The ROC 
cutoff for each of these variables was optimized to maximize the 
sensitivity and specificity. The optimized performances were 
compared to the performance of clinical tests and associated 
cutoffs currently used to diagnose the signs and symptoms of SS-
associated dry eye, including Schirmer score 5, OSS  ‡ 3, OSDI 
 ‡ 20, and TBUT &lt; 10 seconds. The mean values and 95% 
confidence intervals of sensitivity and specificity for each 
clinical test were calculated from 2000 bootstrap runs using 
the R package Boot. 21 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Objective and Subjective Clinical Measures of Dry 
Eye Are Altered in SS Patients </p>

<p>Clinical data were obtained from 10 SS patients and 10 age-
matched controls. There were nine females and one male in 
each group. The average ages were 58.2 (SD ¼ 8.44) and 56.5 
(SD ¼ 8.71) in the control and SS groups, respectively. Most of 
these patients were Caucasians, seven in the control group and 
nine in the SS group. Statistical comparison of demographics 
confirmed that these two groups did not differ significantly 
with respect to sex, age, or ethnicity. Other than TBUT and 
symptoms of dryness (OSDI), each of the clinical tests 
routinely used to assess the signs of ocular surface disease in 
patients with SS was significantly different compared to that in 
control patients (Table 1). </p>

<p>Overall Lacritin and Its Active Isoforms Are 
Reduced in the Tears of SS Patients </p>

<p>As a naturally occurring tear glycoprotein with prominent 
prosecretory, cytoprotective, mitogenic, and bacteriocidal </p>

<p>properties, we hypothesized that lacritin was reduced in the 
tears of SS patients with aqueous-deficient dry eye. Using tear 
proteins collected by Schirmer strips and eluted using PBS, we 
quantified overall lacritin levels using ELISA, as well as the 
relative expression of a fully active cleaved fragment of lacritin 
(~15 kDa), active lacritin monomer (~23-25 kDa), and larger 
molecular weight inactive lacritin species complexed with 
tissue transglutaminase (~40-75 kDa) using Western blot 
analysis (Fig. 1). As shown in Figure 1, the total amount of 
lacritin visualized in Western blots using anti-lacritin antibodies 
was significantly greater in control samples compared to SS 
patients when the same concentration of total tear protein was 
run in each lane. The observation of reduced lacritin in 
Western blots of SS tears was supported by quantitation of total 
tear lacritin using ELISA (reported as ng lacritin/100 ng total 
tear protein, bottom row of Fig. 1). Interestingly, a number of 
tear samples from SS patients showed higher molecular weight 
(inactive) complexes of lacritin by Western blot while the 
ELISA analysis did not detect these complexes (last two lanes of 
Fig. 1), suggesting that they may not be accessible to anti-
lacritin antibodies under conditions used for the ELISA. </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Subjective and Objective Measures of 's Syndrome 
(SS) Dry Eye </p>

<p>Clinic Characteristics </p>

<p>Control 
Mean (SD) </p>

<p>SS 
Mean (SD) P Value </p>

<p>Schirmer tear test (STT) 
21.57 (8.64) 
5.89 (4.20) 
&lt;0.001 
Tear breakup time (TBUT) 
5.86 (2.67) 
3.44 (3.54) 
0.14 
Ocular staining score (OSS) 
1.43 (0.98) 
6.11 (3.02) 
0.001 
Corneal sensitivity testing 
(CST) 
5.58 (0.38) 
3.22 (1.30) 
&lt;0.001 
Ocular Surface Disease 
Index (OSDI) 
17.12 (13.95) 39.23 (28.58) 
0.07 </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Western blot and ELISA analysis of human tear samples for 
lacritin. Human tear samples from patients with 's Syndrome 
(SS) and age-matched controls (C) were eluted from Schirmer tear test 
strips and total protein was determined by the BCA assay. Schirmer tear 
test (STT) values measured in millimeters (mm) were recorded prior to 
elution. Tear protein samples were normalized to 200 lg/mL, and 4 lg 
of each sample was loaded on SDS PAGE, transferred to nitrocellulose, 
challenged with anti N-terminal lacritin antibodies, and developed by 
chemiluminescence. Tear lacritin concentrations determined by ELISA, 
as described in Materials and Methods, are presented as ng lacritin per 
100 ng total protein. WB15 is the proteolytically cleaved fragment of 
lacritin; WB26 is lacritin monomer; and WB40 represents the tissue 
transglutaminase-generated dimers, trimers, and larger polymers of 
lacritin above 40 kDa. Representative data from five eyes are shown. </p>

<p>Dry Eye Alters Tear Lacritin and Corneal Nerves 
IOVS j October 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 13 j 5239 </p>

<p>Western blot results indicated that the level of the cleaved 
fragment, migrating at approximately 15 kDa (WB15), was 
12.93% (P &lt; 0.01) lower in SS versus control tears while 
lacritin monomer, migrating at approximately 26 kDa on 
Western blots (WB26), was 21.02% lower than in control eyes 
(P &lt; 0.01). Perhaps most compelling, inactive lacritin cross-
linked by tissue transglutaminase in tears 7 and migrating as 
multiple bands at and above 40 kDa on Western blots (WB40) 
was 33.95% higher in SS patients compared to controls (P &lt; 
0.01) (Table 2). Thus, in contrast to reduced levels of active 
cleaved fragment, monomer, and total tear lacritin in SS 
patients, complexes of inactive lacritin were significantly 
increased. </p>

<p>Deficiency in Tear Lacritin Predicts the Severity of 
Nerve Damage and Ocular Surface Disease </p>

<p>Studies exploring the effects of dry eye on corneal innervation 
are gaining momentum, in part due to the technological 
advancements of IVCM. We used images of the central cornea 
captured using IVCM to assess NFD, NFL, NBD, and tortuosity. 
Among these features, NFD and NFL were significantly reduced 
in the corneas of SS patients, with nerves consistently noted to 
be less dense and shorter than those of control patients (Table 
3). Interestingly, both the density and length of nerves were 
significantly correlated with ocular surface staining (Spearman 
correlation coefficients ¼ À0.62 [P ¼ 0.01] and À0.66 [P &lt; 
0.01], respectively), supporting the hypothesis that nerves 
provide an essential function to maintain corneal epithelial 
integrity. 
Along with the association between corneal nerve loss and 
ocular surface disease, corneal innervation was similarly 
correlated with reduced levels of tear lacritin (Fig. 2). Among 
the readouts of tear lacritin, overall levels assessed by ELISA 
were the most highly correlated with NFD and NFL (Spearman 
correlation coefficients ¼ 0.70 [P &lt; 0.01] and 0.74 [P &lt; 0.01], 
respectively). In contrast, the inactive component, WB40, was 
negatively correlated with fiber density and length (r ¼ À0.61 
and À0.62, P ¼ 0.01 and &lt; 0.01, respectively). 
We also noted strong correlations between tear lacritin and 
many of the traditional, objective, diagnostic measures of dry 
eye (Fig. 3). Specifically, reduced lacritin measured by ELISA 
was positively correlated with Schirmer score (Spearman r ¼ 
0.77, P &lt; 0.01), negatively correlated with OSS (Spearman r ¼ 
À0.80, P &lt; 0.01), and positively correlated with CST 
(Spearman r ¼ 0.81, P &lt; 0.01). In contrast, reduced TBUT 
(Spearman r ¼ 0.49, P ¼ 0.05) and subjective symptoms of 
dryness OSDI (Spearman r ¼ À0.52, P ¼ 0.06) were poorly 
correlated with a low overall level of lacritin. Similarly, the 
increased presence of inactive lacritin complexes (WB40) was 
highly correlated with low Schirmer score (Spearman r ¼ 
À0.87, P &lt; 0.01), increased OSS (Spearman r ¼ 0.78, P &lt; 0.01), 
and reduced CST (Spearman r ¼ À0.92, P &lt; 0.01), whereas </p>

<p>correlations with TBUT (Spearman r ¼ À0.59, P ¼ 0.02) and 
OSDI (Spearman r ¼ 0.42, P ¼ 0.14) were minimal or 
insignificant. Together, these results demonstrated a profound 
decrease in overall levels of lacritin in tears of SS patients that 
occurred in conjunction with an equally significant decrease in 
the ratio of active to inactive lacritin. These changes in tear 
lacritin are highly correlated to objective measures of clinically 
significantly dry eye but minimally correlated with symptoms 
of dryness and TBUT. To our knowledge, these results are the 
first to demonstrate statistically significant associations be-
tween ocular surface disease severity, altered corneal innerva-
tion, and decreased levels of tear lacritin in a cohort of SS 
patients versus age-matched controls. </p>

<p>Tear Lacritin Levels Are Equivalent to or Better 
Than Standard Clinical Measures for Diagnosing 
SS-Associated Dry Eye </p>

<p>Compared to current clinical readouts used to assess the signs 
and symptoms of SS dry eye, lacritin and its isoforms 
performed as well as or better than traditional diagnostic tests 
to differentiate SS dry eye from controls. For example, using 
optimized cutoff values for total lacritin, lacritin monomer, and 
inactive lacritin species, the patients were correctly identified 
with a sensitivity of 100.00% (set by bootstrap) and specific-
ities of 85.71% (95% CI, as reported in Table 4). The OSS, 
currently the primary objective clinical test used to diagnose 
the ocular component of SS, had a sensitivity of 88.89% 
(95%CI: 66.67-100.00%) and a corresponding specificity of 
85.71% (95% CI: 57.14-100.00%) when using the cutoff of  ‡3, </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Comparison of Total Lacritin and Percent Expression of 
Lacritin Species </p>

<p>Lacritin </p>

<p>Control 
Mean (SD) </p>

<p>SS 
Mean (SD) 
P Value </p>

<p>ELISA* 
18.17 (4.57) 
3.72 (5.62) 
&lt;0.01 
WB15 † 
14.65 (7.54) 
1.72 (5.15) 
&lt;0.01 
WB26 † 
34.31 (10.84) 
13.29 (10.95) 
&lt;0.01 
WB40 † 
51.04 (12.03) 
84.99 (11.15) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>* Total tear lacritin measured by ELISA and expressed as ng/100 ng 
total protein. 
 † Percent expression of 15-kDa, 26-kDa, and &gt;40-kDa lacritin 
species assessed by Western blot (WB) and quantified by densitometry. </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Comparison of Corneal Nerve Fiber Morphology </p>

<p>Nerve Features </p>

<p>Control Cohort 
Mean (SD) </p>

<p>SS Cohort 
Mean (SD) P Value </p>

<p>Nerve fiber density (NFD) 
31.80 (9.35) 21.70 (18.93) &lt;0.05 
Nerve fiber length (NFL) 
6.54 (2.47) 
4.18 (3.44) &lt;0.05 
Nerve branch density (NBD) 10.20 (7.22) 
6.07 (13.01) 
0.07 
Tortuosity coefficient (TC) 
21.05 (9.35) 22.04 (15.77) 
0.99 </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Correlation between tear lacritin levels and corneal nerve 
features. Spearman correlation coefficients and corresponding P values 
are provided. Data points represent a single eye of each patient. </p>

<p>Dry Eye Alters Tear Lacritin and Corneal Nerves 
IOVS j October 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 13 j 5240 </p>

<p>as specified by the current American College of Rheumatology 
diagnostic criteria. As such, the sum of sensitivity and 
specificity for OSS was 11.11% lower than that of total tear 
lacritin and its inactive isoform (WB40), which had sums equal 
to 185.71%. It was also noted that the AUCs of lacritin ELISA 
(AUC ¼ 0.98) and inactive lacritin WB40 (AUC ¼ 0.97) were 
slightly higher than any of the clinical parameters used to 
differentiate SS patients from the healthy controls. 
Finally, it was found that clinically defined cutoff values for 
traditional diagnostic tests (standard cutoffs) were different 
from the values optimized by the sum of sensitivity and 
specificity through ROC curve analysis (optimized cutoff). For 
example, 5 mm of wetting in 5 minutes on the Schirmer tear 
test (a classification criterion proposed by SICCA and others) 
provided a sensitivity of 50% and specificity of 100%. 
Alternatively, an optimized cutoff of 14 mm provided a 
sensitivity of 78% and specificity of 86%, suggesting that a 
higher Schirmer score may substantially improve the sensitivity 
of Schirmer testing with minimal compromise to its specificity. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We found significantly reduced levels of total tear lacritin, 
lacritin monomer, and the active cleaved fragment of lacritin in 
the aqueous-deficient eyes of SS patients compared with age-
matched controls. Reduced levels of total tear lacritin were 
highly correlated with altered morphology of corneal nerves, 
low Schirmer scores, increased corneal staining, and reduced 
corneal sensitivity in SS patients. These data demonstrate an 
important association between the level of tear lacritin and 
altered homeostasis of the chronically inflamed cornea where 
reduced tear secretion and altered innervation contribute to 
ocular surface damage. 
Interestingly, loss of active lacritin in SS samples was 
complemented by an equally profound increase in lacritin's 
inactive form that exists in higher molecular weight forms 
cross-linked by tissue transglutaminase. Tissue transglutamin-
ase is a negative regulator of monomeric lacritin bioactivity, 7 </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Correlation between total tear lacritin levels and clinical 
parameters used to assess dry eye. Spearman correlation coefficients 
and corresponding P values are provided. Data points represent a 
single eye of each patient. </p>

<p>TABLE 4. Diagnostic Performance of Tear Lacritin and Clinical Test Using Standard and Optimized Cutoffs </p>

<p>Tested Variables </p>

<p>Diagnostic Performance of Tear Lacritin </p>

<p>AUC (95%CI) 
Cutoff (95%CI) </p>

<p>Sensitivity, % 
(95%CI) </p>

<p>Specificity, % 
(95%CI) 
Sensitivity þ Specificity </p>

<p>Lacritin 
ELISA 
0.98 (0.94-1.00) 
14.50 (5.05-16.50) 
100.00 (--)* 
85.71 (57.14-100.00) 
185.71 
WB15 
0.94 (0.80-1.00) 
2.64% (2.62%-6.90%) 
88.89 (66.67-100.00) 100.00 (--) 
188.89 
WB26 
0.94 (0.84-1.00) 29.82% (10.76%-34.07%) 100.00 (--) 
85.71 (57.14-100.00) 
185.71 
WB40 
0.97 (0.89-1.00) 62.72% (61.05%-79.26%) 100.00 (--) 
85.71 (60.00-100.00) 
185.71 </p>

<p>Diagnostic performance of traditional clinical tests 
OSDI 
Standard 
0.80 (0.55-1.00) 
20 
57.14 (20.00-100.00) 
85.71 (57.14-100.00) 
142.85 
Optimized 
18.05 (12.03-53.10) 
71.43 (37.50-100.00) 
71.43 (42.86-100.00) 
142.86 
Schirmer 
Standard 
0.96 (0.89-1.00) 
5 
50.00 (26.32-71.41) 
100.00 (--) 
150.00 
Optimized 
14.00 (7.50-16.50) 
77.78 (44.44-100.00) 
85.71 (57.14-100.00) 
179.47 
OSS 
Standard 
0.95 (0.87-1.00) 
3 
88.89 (66.67-100.00) 
85.71 (57.14-100.0) 
174.60 
Optimized 
2.50 (1.50-4.50) 
88.89 (66.67-100.00) 
85.71 (57.14-100.00) 
174.60 
TBUT 
Standard 
0.72 (0.45-0.99) 
10 
100.00 (--) 
0.00 (--) 
100.00 
Optimized 
3.00 (1.00-9.00) 
66.67 (33.33-100.00) 
85.71 (57.14-100.00) 
152.38 
CST 
Optimized 
0.89 (0.67-1.00) 
4.00 (3.25-5.55) 
77.78 (55.00-100.00) 100.00 (--) 
177.78 </p>

<p>(--) Sensitivity or specificity kept constant for resampling of 2000 runs by bootstrap. </p>

<p>Dry Eye Alters Tear Lacritin and Corneal Nerves 
IOVS j October 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 13 j 5241 </p>

<p>and the dramatic increase in lacritin's inactive crossed-linked 
forms suggests that tear tissue transglutaminase may play an 
important role in SS-associated dry eye disease. It is also 
interesting to note that tear lacritin ELISA analysis does not 
detect the inactive forms of lacritin observed in Western blot 
analysis. One possible explanation for this observation is that 
the ELISA is done under nondenatured conditions while the 
Western blot analysis denatures proteins prior to SDS gel 
electrophoresis, thereby exposing antigen-binding sites that 
may be inaccessible in the cross-linked native state. This 
observation suggests that the ELISA analysis detects only active 
forms of tear lacritin, thus extending the use of Schirmer strips 
and ELISA to quantify lacritin tear levels as a diagnostic 
biomarker for aqueous tear deficiency. 
Data from our lab and others indicate that 95% of dry eye 
patients are selectively deficient in lacritin, 13-15 suggesting that 
its replacement may have therapeutic benefits. Using the 
autoimmune regulator knockout (AIRE KO) mouse model of 
SS-associated, aqueous-deficient dry eye, we have published 
data demonstrating significant improvements in tear secretion 
and ocular surface integrity of the cornea following 33 daily 
topical application of recombinant lacritin for 3 weeks. 15 
Although the exact mechanism by which topical lacritin 
promotes tearing is not understood, our recent investigation 
in the AIRE KO mouse suggests that corneal sensory nerves are 
directly or indirectly involved (McNamara NA, et al. IOVS 
2015;56:ARVO E-Abstract 4808). Lacrimal tear secretion is 
tightly regulated through corneal innervations, 22 and loss of 
epithelial integrity in dry eye provides tear lacritin direct 
access to syndecan 1-expressing neuronal cells within the 
corneal epithelium and subbasal nerve plexus. 11 Signaling via 
lacritin's receptor syndecan-1 has been shown to regulate 
neuron growth in Caenorhabditis elegans, 23 further support-
ing a functional link between lacritin tear levels, corneal 
innervations, and neuronal stimulation of lacrimation in the 
setting of dry eye. 
Measurements of corneal nerves using IVCM have been 
successfully employed for the diagnosis and stratification of 
corneal neuropathy due to diabetes 24 and other conditions of 
the eye such as postcorneal transplantation, refractive 
surgeries, 25 and contact lens-associated disorders. 26-28 How-
ever, studies examining corneal sensitivity and corneal 
nerves by IVCM in SS patients have presented conflicting 
results. 27,29 Studies have reported SS patients as having 
reduced, 1,30 similar, 31,32 or increased 33 subbasal nerve 
density when compared to controls with variable levels of 
corneal sensation. 1,31 This variability may be attributed to 
use of different instruments and/or selection of patients at 
various stages of disease severity where nerves might be in 
different phases of damage or compensatory regeneration. 
While this interpretation remains to be validated, it is 
conceivable that IVCM could provide a clinical measure of 
corneal denervation that indicates the physiological state of 
nerves and predicts the symptoms and severity of disease. 
Our results demonstrated significant decreases in corneal 
NFD and NFL in SS patients compared to age-matched 
controls. Moreover, fiber density and fiber length were both 
highly correlated with the traditional clinical parameters 
used to diagnose and assess the severity of dry eye in human 
patients (data not shown). 
The current study provides evidence to support the use of 
tear lacritin measured by ELISA as a diagnostic marker for SS-
associated dry eye. Compared to standard clinical tests, the 
diagnostic performance of tear lacritin was similar or superior 
to Schirmer testing and ocular surface staining as assessed 
using the optimized AUC. Tear lacritin was also highly 
correlated to altered morphology of corneal nerves, with 
levels of inactive lacritin in complex with tissue transgluta-</p>

<p>minase proving to be the form most significantly altered in SS 
patients compared to controls. Further investigation of the 
mechanisms and consequences associated with reduced tear 
lacritin and altered innervation may provide significant clinical 
implications for maintaining or restoring ocular surface health 
in autoimmune-mediated dry eye. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Supported by National Eye Institute Grants EY025980 (NAM), 
EY02162 (University of California-San Francisco Ophthalmology 
Core), and P30EY003176 (University of California-Berkeley Vision 
Science Core). </p>

<p>Disclosure: N.A. McNamara, None; S. Ge, None; S.M. Lee, None; 
A.M. Enghauser, None; L. Kuehl, None; F.Y.-T. Chen, None; M. 
Gallup, None; R.L. McKown, Biomanufacturing for EyeRx 
Research, Inc. (S) </p>



<p>Dry Eye Alters Tear Lacritin and Corneal Nerves 
IOVS j October 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 13 j 5242 </p>



<p>Dry Eye Alters Tear Lacritin and Corneal Nerves 
IOVS j October 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 13 j 5243 </p>

</text></tei>