<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5321344" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: There is an urgent need to understand </p>

<p>how to improve targeting of artemisinin combination 
therapy (ACT) to patients with confirmed malaria 
infection, including subsidised ACTs sold over-the-
counter. We hypothesised that offering an antimalarial 
subsidy conditional on a positive malaria rapid 
diagnostic test (RDT) would increase uptake of testing 
and improve rational use of ACTs. </p>

<p>Methods: We designed a 2×2 factorial randomised </p>

<p>experiment evaluating 2 levels of subsidy for RDTs and 
ACTs. Between July 2014 and June 2015, 444 
individuals with a malaria-like illness who had not 
sought treatment were recruited from their homes. We 
used scratch cards to allocate participants into 4 groups 
in a ratio of 1:1:1:1. Participants were eligible for an 
unsubsidised or fully subsidised RDT and 1 of 2 levels 
of ACT subsidy (current retail price or an additional 
subsidy conditional on a positive RDT). Treatment 
decisions were documented 1 week later. Our primary 
outcome was uptake of malaria testing. Secondary 
outcomes evaluated ACT consumption among those 
with a negative test, a positive test or no test. </p>

<p>Results: Offering a free RDT increased the probability </p>

<p>of testing by 18.6 percentage points (adjusted 
probability difference (APD), 95% CI 5.9 to 31.3). An 
offer of a conditional ACT subsidy did not have an 
additional effect on the probability of malaria testing 
when the RDT was free (APD=2.7; 95% CI −8.6 to 
14.1). However, receiving the conditional ACT subsidy 
increased the probability of taking an ACT following a 
positive RDT by 19.5 percentage points (APD, 95% CI 
2.2 to 36.8). Overall, the proportion who took ACT 
following a negative test was lower than those who took 
ACT without being tested, indicated improved targeting 
among those who were tested. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Both subsidies improved appropriate </p>

<p>fever management, demonstrating the impact of these </p>

<p>costs on decision making. However, the conditional ACT 
subsidy did not increase testing. We conclude that each 
of the subsidies primarily impacts the most immediate 
decision. </p>

<p>Trial registration number: NCT02199977. </p>

<p>Key questions </p>

<p>What is already known about this topic? </p>

<p>▸ While the overwhelming view from the literature 
is that availability of subsidised ACTs quickly 
and effectively increases access, studies have 
demonstrated poor targeting of antimalarial 
drugs to malaria cases and overuse of ACTs in 
the retail sector. 
▸ Evidence regarding use of RDTs in the retail 
sector, whether subsidised or unsubsidised, 
shows adherence to the results is inconsistent. </p>

<p>What are the new findings? </p>

<p>▸ This is the first study that makes an ACT subsidy 
conditional on diagnostically confirmed malaria 
infection, and provides new guidance to policy-
makers on consumer-directed subsidy pro-
grammes for malaria diagnosis and treatment. 
▸ Our results show that both RDT and ACT sub-
sidies can independently improve individuals' 
choices about malaria testing and treatment, 
demonstrating the price sensitivity of these deci-
sions. Adding a conditional ACT subsidy to the 
RDT subsidy did not increase testing likelihood, 
but paying for an RDT does correlate with 
increased adherence to the RDT results. 
▸ Information from an RDT can improve targeting 
of ACTs among those seeking treatment 
over-the-counter. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>However, there is little evidence to guide policymakers 
in the implementation of diagnostic testing within a 
subsidy framework in the retail sector. Existing evidence 
indicates that subsidising treatments such as ACTs can 
lead to overuse 
3 but subsidising preventive health inter-
ventions can expand uptake without compromising 
usage. 
7 It is not clear whether subsidies for diagnostic 
testing would follow the latter trend and what effect they 
might have on ACT consumption. In addition, the inter-
action between ACT and rapid diagnostic test (RDT) 
subsidies and how the price of each could be manipu-
lated to increase the value of both interventions has not 
been explored. One example from a cancer screening </p>

<p>and treatment experiment demonstrates that advanced 
information about availability of subsidised treatment, 
conditional on diagnostic testing, can improve uptake of 
testing. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Here, we sought to study the relationship between a 
subsidised diagnostic test and a conditionally subsidised 
treatment intervention in order to understand how 
ACTs can be targeted to malaria cases in the retail 
sector. We designed an individually randomised experi-
ment to determine the effect of a conditional subsidy 
for ACT on the decision to be tested for malaria when 
the test is subsidised or not, and the subsequent effect 
of the test on drug purchasing decisions. Our primary 
hypothesis was that clients who learn they will receive an 
ACT subsidy conditional on a positive test are more 
likely to opt for testing before deciding which drug to 
buy. Secondary end points include the effect of the diag-
nostic test subsidy on uptake of testing, and the effect of 
testing and antimalarial subsidy on subsequent drug pur-
chasing decisions. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study design 
We conducted a 2×2 factorial randomised experiment to 
test two levels of subsidy RDT for malaria (fully subsi-
dised and free to the participant vs an unsubsidised test 
for which the participant paid ∼US$0.50) and two levels 
of ACT subsidy (current retail price equivalent to no 
additional subsidy vs an additional subsidy of US$0.60 at 
the point of sale) on testing and treatment decisions of 
patients ill with malaria-like symptoms. The study was 
conducted in a rural division of Bungoma County in 
western Kenya. </p>

<p>Participants 
Over the course of the study period, from July 2014 to 
June 2015, 3 of the 11 sublocations in the eastern part 
of Bungoma subcounty were randomly selected for par-
ticipation. In each of these sublocations, field teams can-
vassed in every household to identify eligible 
participants. Individuals were eligible for enrolment if 
they were older than 1 year and had a malaria-like 
illness or history of symptoms during the last 24 hours. 
Any individual who had already taken or purchased 
medicine or sought treatment for their illness was 
excluded. Anyone exhibiting danger signs, symptoms of 
severe disease or other problems requiring immediate 
referral to a health facility were also excluded and 
referred to the nearest facility with the help of the local 
community health worker (CHW). If more than one 
individual was found to meet the inclusion criteria in a 
single household, all of the individuals were enrolled in 
the same study group, but only one individual (selected 
by alphabetical ordering of their given names) provided 
information for the analysis. Participants gave verbal 
informed consent for entry into the study. Written 
informed consent was obtained for those who chose to </p>

<p>Key questions </p>

<p>Recommendations for policy </p>

<p>▸ RDT subsidies at the community level greatly improve uptake of 
diagnostic testing. Reducing the price of an RDT is critical for 
improving testing before treatment outside of the formal health-
care sector. 
▸ ACT prices under the current government subsidy are still too 
high to ensure that all malaria-positive cases can afford treat-
ment. However, conditional subsidies linked to a positive test 
may be more sustainable and improve ACT targeting compared 
to unrestricted subsidies. </p>



<p>Prudhomme O'Meara W, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2016;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000101 </p>

<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>have an RDT after enrolment. Parent or guardian 
consent was required for participants &lt;18 years and 
child assent was required for children older than 8 years. 
Thirteen shops that sold medicines were identified 
within the communities from which participants were 
enrolled. Any shop that stocked WHO prequalified 
(green-leaf branded) ACT was eligible to participate in 
the study. Shops gave written consent for participation. </p>

<p>Randomisation and study groups 
We randomly assigned half the participants to receive a 
fully subsidised (free) RDT test, relative to the price of 
∼US$0.50 that other participants would have to pay. 
Orthogonally, we also randomly assigned participants to 
one of two levels of ACT subsidy (current retail price 
including subsidies from government equivalent to ∼US 
$1.25 per adult dose, vs a further subsidised price of 
∼US$0.65 per adult dose which was only available follow-
ing a positive RDT). The ACT subsidy levels were chosen 
to compare the prevailing retail price under partial gov-
ernment subsidy to the previous highly subsidised 
Affordable Medicines Facility-malaria (AMFm)s price. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Study participants were randomly allocated to the four 
groups in a ratio of 1:1:1:1 (figure 1) using scratch 
cards. </p>

<p>Procedures 
Prior to initiation of enrolment in each sublocation, 20 
CHWs from each sublocation attended a 3-day training 
programme to learn how to perform malaria RDTs. 
After consenting, the participant was offered a scratch 
card that had a group assignment to be revealed by the 
participant. The research assistant explained the indivi-
dual's group assignment and that the period of validity 
for the CHW RDT testing was 3 days. The group assign-
ment identified which of the two subsidies (one, both or 
neither) the participant was entitled to, but the partici-
pant was free to choose whether or not to seek testing 
or treatment regardless of their group assignment. 
Contact information for the nearest CHW was provided, 
but fieldworkers avoided health education messages 
about the intervention. All participants could obtain an 
RDT (free or US$0.50, depending on the group) by 
reporting to the CHW, who provided the conditional 
ACT voucher when applicable. RDT-negative partici-
pants or those not tested could still access ACTs at the 
normal retail price. Participants could also choose to 
seek care at the nearest health facility where they would 
be treated according to normal patient protocols. 
Government facilities charged US$0.65 for a microscopy 
test but ACTs are free. 
The voucher was redeemable at participating local 
drug shops. Eleven shops were enrolled in the study and 
remained active throughout participant recruitment. 
The only WHO 'green-leaf' branded ACT available in 
the retail sector in Kenya at the time of the study was 
artemether-lumefantrine (AL), which is also the first-
line therapy used in the formal health sector. Therefore, </p>

<p>the study voucher could only be used for purchase of 
green-leaf branded AL. 
Fieldworkers collected participant data at the time of 
enrolment and each participant was visited 1 week after 
enrolment to record information about action taken for 
the illness. Data were collected on Android tablets using 
customised electronic forms. 
CHWs recorded information about clients who 
requested an RDT on standard forms, which were 
scanned and digitised using a web-based automated data 
capture system (Captricity, Oakland, California, USA). 
CHWs regularly provided used RDTs to a field super-
visor, who checked the recorded results against the RDT 
to make sure the CHW correctly interpreted the test. </p>

<p>Outcomes 
Treatment seeking for an acute illness in our study can 
be conceptualised as a series of steps and decisions: (1) 
decision to use RDT, (2) receive information from a test 
( positive or negative) and (3) decision to use ACT. The 
study intervention acts at steps one and three by allocat-
ing 
participants 
to 
different 
subsidy 
levels. 
Randomisation occurs before step one. Although group 
assignment includes the ACT subsidy assignment, partici-
pant groups are no longer randomly distributed on 
reaching step three since some will have opted not to be 
tested. 
Study end points are measured at multiple decision 
points of the health-seeking process. Our primary end 
point is uptake of malaria testing defined as the partici-
pant's decision to be tested for malaria regardless of the 
source of the test (CHW or health facility) and the type 
of test (RDT or microscopy). The primary outcome of 
interest is the effect of offering a conditional ACT 
subsidy on uptake of testing when the RDT is free 
(Group A vs Group B). The secondary outcomes include 
the effect of RDT subsidy on the uptake of testing (free 
vs paid RDT, Group B vs Group D), and the effect of a 
conditional ACT subsidy on uptake of testing when the 
RDT is not free (Group C vs Group D). Other secondary 
end points in all four of the study groups included drug 
purchasing decisions following a positive test, a negative 
test and with no test. We defined two additional binary 
end points that combined drug purchasing decisions of 
test-positives and test-negatives: 'appropriate ACT use' 
was defined as taking ACT if positive or not taking ACT 
if negative among those who took a malaria tests and 
'targeted ACT use' was defined as taking ACT if positive 
or not taking ACT if negative among all participants. All 
outcomes are based on self-report during the follow-up 
interview conducted 1 week postenrolment. CHW 
records and patient records from the health facility were 
used to confirm the self-reported malaria testing results 
whenever possible. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
We calculated the sample size to achieve 90% power to 
detect a difference in proportions of a prespecified </p>

<p>Prudhomme O'Meara W, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2016;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000101 </p>



<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>magnitude based on Pearson's χ 
2 test with a two-sided α 
of 5% for each of our primary and secondary outcome 
measures. We estimated that 20% of those randomised 
to Group D (no subsidy), 40% of Group C (ACT subsidy 
only), 50% of Group B (RDT subsidy only) and 75% of 
Group A (ACT and RDT subsidy) would opt in for 
malaria testing. Of all our outcomes of interest, the sec-
ondary outcome of the effect of an ACT subsidy when 
RDT testing was not free (Group C vs Group D) 
required the largest sample size at 436 (109 per arm). 
We intended to recruit a total of 500 participants in 
order to account for up to 12% loss before the 1-week 
follow-up visit. In practice, this loss to follow-up was only 
2%, thus recruitment ceased at 444 individuals. </p>

<p>All 
analyses 
were 
conducted 
using 
the 
intention-to-treat principle. Analyses were conducted in 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata SE</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.14</rs> (College Station, Texas, USA). We com-
pared baseline covariates to examine the balance 
between intervention and control arms using count and 
percentages for categorical variables and median and 
IQR for continuous variables. We compared the same 
set of baseline covariates to determine whether loss to 
follow-up differed according to observed variables, 
including the study group. Proportions of participants 
who opted in for testing, were tested positive/negative, 
and took an ACT were compared by the study group. All 
primary end points are individual-level binary outcomes, 
modelled using a linear probability model (LPM), </p>

<p>Figure 1 CONSORT diagram of participant enrolment, refusal, group assignment and follow-up. The intervention available to 
each group (A-D) in this factorial experiment is detailed at the bottom of the diagram. </p>



<p>Prudhomme O'Meara W, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2016;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000101 </p>

<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>allowing us to interpret model parameters as probability 
differences. The LPM was specified as a generalised 
linear model for a binomial outcome with an identity 
link function. We summarised testing choice by the four 
randomised study groups by regressing the binary 
outcome on two factors (RDT subsidy and ACT subsidy) 
and their interaction to match the randomised 2×2 fac-
torial study design. 
9 In addition to unadjusted group 
effects, we specified models with a full set of prespeci-
fied predictors: gender and age of the client, occupation 
and education level of the client or guardian (if client 
&lt;18 years), household size, wealth, and sublocation. 
Wealth was assessed as a composite score based on prin-
cipal component analysis of ownership of basic house-
hold assets, using a polychoric correlation matrix to 
account for the categorical nature of the included 
assets. 
10 The poorest 40% of participants were used as 
the comparator group. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>For the secondary end point of ACT consumption (an 
individual-level binary outcome) we used the same LPM 
modelling approach as for the testing-related outcomes. 
Models were stratified by test results for the subsample 
of clients who opted for a test. Since the interaction 
term was not significant in any of these models or in the 
primary testing outcome models, we excluded it in 
order to gain power and to improve model interpret-
ation. Similarly, because we had not powered our study 
for these secondary end points, we reduced the set of 
prespecified predictors included in the primary 
outcome to the most parsimonious model with the best 
fit. To do so, we performed likelihood ratio tests and 
compared Akaike information criterion for subsets of 
the prespecified predictors. 
12 The reduced set included 
wealth index only. Therefore, we only present the adjust-
ment for the parsimonious model for the secondary end 
points and provide results from this parsimonious set for 
the primary outcome for comparison. Since testing out-
comes relied on self-reports of testing behaviour, we con-
ducted sensitivity analyses to determine whether model 
results persisted when the outcome was malaria testing 
at the CHW only (rather than the broader definition of 
any malaria test, including those conducted in a health 
facility) and when there was documented proof of the 
malaria test. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Study participants 
Four hundred and forty-four participants were enrolled 
across the four groups (figure 1) between 31 July 2014 and 
24 June 2015. Overall, 63% were women and 62% were 
&gt;18 years (table 1). The majority of households owned an 
insecticide treated net (ITN) (86%) and 63% of patients 
reported sleeping under the ITN on all the last seven 
nights. On average, the nearest participating medicine 
retailer was half a kilometre nearer than the closest health 
facility (1.6 vs 2.2 km). There was no evidence of differ-
ences in patient demographics between the four study </p>

<p>groups. Ninety eight per cent of patients had a follow-up 
interview 1 week after enrolment. There were very low 
rates of dropouts in all the study groups (2%). </p>

<p>Effect of subsidies on testing 
Sixty two per cent of participants underwent a malaria 
diagnostic test for their illness from either source (CHW 
or health facility, table 2). The proportion receiving a 
test differed substantially between study groups. After 
adjusting for the full set of prespecified covariates, the 
RDT subsidy resulted in an 18.6 percentage point 
increase (95% CI 5.9 to 31.3; table 3) in the probability 
of malaria testing over unsubsidised RDTs, in the 
absence of conditional ACT subsidies. Uptake of malaria 
testing was not affected by the offer of a conditional 
ACT subsidy when the RDT was subsidised (Group A vs. 
Group B, 2.7 percentage points, 95% CI −8.6 to 14.1). 
The interaction between RDT and ACT subsidy was not 
significant in any of the fitted models, indicating that 
there is no evidence of a statistically significant differen-
tial effect of ACT subsidy on the uptake of testing when 
the RDT test is free versus when the RDT test is not sub-
sidised (see online supplementary table S1). 
Of those who were tested, 89.9% were tested by a 
CHW, although this proportion was slightly lower in the 
groups that had to pay for RDT testing by the CHW 
(unsubsidised groups) and higher in the subsidised 
RDT groups (84.1% vs 93.8%, see online supplementary 
table S2). The difference in proportion of people tested 
at a facility across the groups was very small, suggesting 
that the subsidised RDTs were probably not diverting 
people who would normally be tested at the facility to 
the CHW testing, although we did not test this formally. 
The primary analysis is based on self-report; however, 
the uptake of testing and test results could be confirmed 
only from records kept by the CHW or by observing 
facility records in the patients' possession for 87% of 
participants. Excluding those without confirmation of 
testing did not substantively change the estimate of the 
effect of the RDT subsidy on uptake of testing. </p>

<p>ACT consumption 
Thirty nine per cent of the 267 participants who were 
tested had a positive malaria result; the proportion was 
higher in the groups who had to pay for their test 
(table 2: 45.9% vs 33.8%). Among those who tested 
positive for malaria, 74.8% took ACT. In the adjusted 
analysis, malaria-positive participants who received con-
ditional ACT subsidy were 19.5 percentage points more 
likely to receive recommended ACT treatment, irrespect-
ive of whether they received an RDT subsidy (table 4, 
95% CI 2.7% to 36.8%). In contrast, there was no evi-
dence of an effect of RDT subsidy on ACT purchasing 
after a positive test (4.2% more purchasing ACT with the 
RDT subsidy, 95% CI −1.2% to 20.4%). 
Among those with a negative malaria test, ACT con-
sumption was lowest in the groups that had to pay for 
their test. Only 2 of 27 participants (7.4%) with a negative </p>

<p>Prudhomme O'Meara W, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2016;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000101 </p>



<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>test in the no subsidy group (Group D) took ACT. In con-
trast, 27.5% of participants in the double subsidy group 
took ACT following a negative test (table 2). In the 
adjusted analysis, malaria-negative participants who 
underwent free RDT testing were 12.8 percentage points 
more likely to consume ACT (95% CI 1.7 to 23.9; table 4) 
than those who paid for their RDT. 
Twenty six per cent of the 163 participants who were 
not tested took ACT (table 2). ACT consumption among 
malaria-negative patients was lower than among those not 
tested in all four study groups (18.9% vs 25.8%; table 2). </p>

<p>Targeting and appropriate use of ACT 
Appropriate use of ACTs among those who are tested 
requires malaria-positive individuals to receive ACT and 
malaria-negative individuals to refrain from taking ACT. 
Targeting ACT to malaria-infected patients is maximised 
when all potential malaria fevers are tested and the </p>

<p>results of the test are adhered to; patients with a positive 
test receive ACT and those with a negative test abstain. 
In our study, appropriate ACT use following a test was 
highest when clients paid for their RDT and were given 
a conditional voucher for their ACT (Group C). 
However, uptake of testing in groups with access to 
unsubsidised RDTs was low compared to those who 
received a subsidised RDT. Therefore, overall targeting 
of ACTs in all participants was highest in the groups that 
received a free, fully subsidised RDT (42.5% and 39% in 
Groups C and D, respectively, compared to 56.1% and 
57.3% in Groups A and B, respectively, table 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Consumption of first-line antimalarials has increased, 
partly due to the availability of subsidised ACTs in the 
retail sector in many malaria-endemic countries. The 
vast majority of ACTs paid for in the retail sector are </p>

<p>Table 1 Participant characteristics by study group </p>

<p>Group A: ACT 
subsidy 
RDT subsidy 
N=116 </p>

<p>Group B: RDT 
subsidy 
N=107 </p>

<p>Group C: ACT 
subsidy 
N=114 </p>

<p>Group D: no subsidy 
(reference) N=107 </p>

<p>Total 
N=444 </p>

<p>Female 
71 (61%) 
63 (59%) 
76 (67%) 
69 (64%) 
279 (63%) </p>

<p>Patient age (years) </p>

<p>0 to 5 
38 (33%) 
28 (26%) 
35 (31%) 
23 (21%) 
124 (28%) </p>

<p>&gt;5 to &lt;18 
41 (35%) 
32 (30%) 
32 (28%) 
45 (42%) 
150 (34%) </p>

<p>18 to &lt;35 
22 (19%) 
23 (21%) 
21 (18%) 
15 (14%) 
81 (18%) </p>

<p>35+ 
15 (13%) 
24 (22%) 
26 (23%) 
24 (22%) 
89 (20%) </p>

<p>Household size </p>

<p>Median (IQR) 
6 (5-7) 
6 (4-8) 
6 (5-7) 
6 (5-8) 
6 (4-7) </p>

<p>Highest level of education completed </p>

<p>&lt;Primary or 
none </p>

<p>3 (3%) 
2 (2%) 
5 (4%) 
3 (3%) 
13 (3%) </p>

<p>Primary 
69 (59%) 
67 (63%) 
71 (62%) 
72 (67%) 
279 (63%) </p>

<p>Secondary 
44 (38%) 
38 (36%) 
38 (33%) 
32 (30%) 
152 (34%) </p>

<p>Occupation </p>

<p>Farming 
73 (63%) 
64 (60%) 
69 (61%) 
69 (64%) 
275 (62%) </p>

<p>Unemployed 
11 (9%) 
13 (12%) 
16 (14%) 
13 (12%) 
53 (12%) </p>

<p>Employed 
13 (11%) 
10 (9%) 
8 (7%) 
9 (8%) 
40 (9%) </p>

<p>Self-employed/ 
other </p>

<p>19 (16%) 
20 (19%) 
21 (18%) 
16 (15%) 
76 (17%) </p>

<p>Wealth category </p>

<p>Poorest 40th 
centile </p>

<p>45 (40%) 
36 (36%) 
45 (40%) 
46 (44%) 
172 (40%) </p>

<p>Distance to facility (km) </p>

<p>Median (IQR) 
2.1 (1.5-2.8) 
2.2 (1.6-2.7) 
2.2 (1.5-2.9) 
2.0 (1.4-2.8) 
2.2 (1.5-2.8) </p>

<p>Distance to enrolled shop (km) </p>

<p>Median (IQR) 
1.4 (1.0-2.1) 
1.6 (0.9-2.2) 
1.6 (1.0-2.1) 
1.7 (1.0-2.1) 
1.6 (1.0-2.2) </p>

<p>Has 1 week 
follow-up </p>

<p>116 (100%) 
103 (96%) 
114 (100%) 
104 (97%) 
437 (98%) </p>

<p>ACT, artemisinin combination therapy; RDT, rapid diagnostic test. </p>



<p>Prudhomme O'Meara W, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2016;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000101 </p>

<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>taken presumptively without parasitological confirmation 
of malaria infection. It is not well understood how to 
improve the uptake of diagnostic testing among those 
seeking treatment over-the-counter. In order to maxi-
mise targeting of ACTs to confirmed malaria cases, we 
sought to test whether the RDT should be subsidised 
and whether ACT subsidy, conditional on a positive RDT 
test result, could improve appropriate use of ACTs. We 
find that both the RDT and ACT subsidies in this study 
had significant positive effects on appropriate fever man-
agement, indicating that price is still a major driving 
force behind these decisions. Fully subsidised RDTs 
made available in the community greatly improve uptake 
of testing before treatment. Although making a small 
payment for an RDT (ie, unsubsidised RDT) seemed to 
reduce inappropriate ACT use among malaria-negative 
participants, this benefit was negated by the large reduc-
tion in testing rates in the unsubsidised RDT groups. 
Providing an additional discount on an ACT drug, 
which is conditional on a positive RDT, improves the use 
of ACT by those with confirmed infection and increases 
targeting of ACTs overall. The percentage of malaria 
infections receiving appropriate treatment was 20 per-
centage points higher in the ACT subsidy group, suggest-
ing that at the current retail prices, a significant number 
of malaria-positive individuals would decide not to pur-
chase an ACT even after confirmation that they have 
malaria. However, the prior offer of a conditional ACT 
subsidy at the time of enrolment did not improve uptake 
of testing, regardless of the price of the RDT, indicating 
that study participants did not project future drug </p>

<p>discount in a manner that influenced testing behaviour. 
We conclude that both subsidies are important, but only 
in determining the next immediate action. 
Overall, the randomised design of our study mitigates 
many concerns about bias. However, there are some lim-
itations that should be considered when interpreting the 
results. First, it was somewhat difficult to find partici-
pants who were feeling ill, but had not yet sought treat-
ment during our door-to-door canvassing. It is possible 
that the group we identified for enrolment had some sys-
tematic differences from the overall population of 
people who might experience a febrile illness. Second, 
our results are based on self-report at follow-up, which 
introduces concerns about recall bias and social desir-
ability bias. Our 1-week follow-up window was short 
enough to minimise recall bias 
13 and we were able to 
confirm testing results by documentation of the test 
result in nearly 90% of cases. However, we were not able 
to confirm the drug purchases for most individuals 
unless they used a study voucher. We note that despite 
introducing an extra step into the treatment-seeking 
sequence (CHW and then a shop), uptake of testing was 
high when the test was offered at no charge to the par-
ticipant. This possibly reflects the ease of accessing 
testing through a community member. However, 
response to the testing intervention may have been moti-
vated partly out of curiosity or desire to interact with a 
novel experience or opportunity. This may have biased 
the RDT treatment effect and it may have reduced 
adherence to the RDT results, which could partially 
explain the high non-adherence to the RDT in the </p>

<p>Table 2 Sample proportions for testing and treatment outcomes and behaviour for N=444 study participants by study group </p>

<p>Group A: ACT 
subsidy and RDT 
subsidy 
N=116 </p>

<p>Group B: RDT 
subsidy 
N=107 </p>

<p>Group C: ACT 
subsidy 
N=114 </p>

<p>Group D: no subsidy 
(reference) N=107 </p>

<p>Total 
N=444 
% 
% 
% 
% 
% </p>

<p>Had a malaria test* 
73.7 (n=84) 
73.8 (n=76) 
49.6 (n=56) 
51.0 (n=51) 
62.1 (n=267) </p>

<p>Positive 
39.3 (n=33) 
27.6 (n=21) 
44.6 (n=25) 
47.1 (n=24) 
38.6 (n=103) </p>

<p>No ACT 
18.2 
28.6 
16.0 
41.7 
25.2 </p>

<p>ACT 
81.8 
71.4 
84.0 
58.3 
74.8 </p>

<p>Negative 
60.7 (n=51) 
72.4 (n=55) 
55.4 (n=31) 
52.9 (n=27) 
61.4 (n=164) </p>

<p>No ACT 
72.5 
80.0 
87.1 
92.6 
81.1 </p>

<p>ACT 
27.5 
20.0 
12.9 
7.4 
18.9 </p>

<p>Appropriate ACT use † 
76.2 (n=84) 
77.6 (n=76) 
85.7 (n=56) 
76.5 (n=51) 
78.7 (n=267) </p>

<p>Did not have a test 
26.3 (n=30) 
26.2 (n=27) 
50.4 (n=57) 
49.0 (n=49) 
37.9 (n=163) </p>

<p>No ACT 
70.0 
70.4 
78.9 
73.5 
74.2 </p>

<p>ACT 
30.0 
29.6 
21.1 
26.5 
25.8 </p>

<p>Targeted ACT use ‡ 
56.1 (n=116) 
57.3 (n=107) 
42.5 (n=114) 
39.0 (n=107) 
48.8 (n=444) </p>

<p>Observations 
N=114 
N=103 
N=113 
N=100 
N=430 </p>

<p>*Self-report of any malaria test (RDT or slide) at health facility or tested by the CHW. 
 †Defined as taking ACT if positive or not taking ACT if negative among those who had a malaria test. 
 ‡Defined as taking ACT if positive or not taking ACT if negative among all participants. 
ACT, artemisinin combination therapy; RDT, rapid diagnostic test. </p>

<p>Prudhomme O'Meara W, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2016;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000101 </p>



<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>double subsidy group. It is also possible that information 
about subsidies offered to other groups influenced indi-
vidual behaviour. Since it was not possible for partici-
pants to be blinded to the intervention (theirs or 
others'), we are unable to estimate placebo effects or 
rule out potential behavioural responses to individuals 
getting information about other treatment arms or 
subsidy levels. Finally, although our initial group alloca-
tion was random, the decision to get tested and the sub-
sequent information received from testing are no longer 
random due to selection effects. This imbalance across 
arms subsequent to the first action (whether to get 
tested or not) could introduce bias in the estimation of 
treatment effects on ACT consumption. Although we did 
not observe systematic differences between subgroups 
(tested or not, those taking ACT or not) it is possible 
that the groups differ on unobserved characteristics such 
as preferences or beliefs about their illness or percep-
tions derived from previous experience with RDTs or 
ACTs. 
In previous studies it has been shown that between 
36% and 77% of fever treated in the retail sector do not 
have malaria. 
14 15 A study in Tanzania estimated that 
80% of ACTs are sold to patients without parasitaemia 
and only 70% of parasitaemic patients paid for ACT. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>The discordance between malaria and ACT consump-
tion demonstrates the need for improved targeting of 
antimalarials sold in the retail sector. Recent studies that 
introduced RDTs into retail shops alongside subsidised 
ACTs have had mixed results. A study in Uganda 
reported low uptake of RDTs by retail shop owners and 
their customers and low adherence to test results. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Other studies have demonstrated higher uptake when 
the tests are highly subsidised and much less expensive 
than the available ACT. 
18 There is some tension between 
motivation of the shop owner to make a profitable drug 
sale versus the expectation in most studies that an indi-
vidual with a negative test would not be sold an antimal-
arial and would be referred to a health facility without a 
drug. This may even compromise the integrity of the 
testing; two studies documented high rates of false posi-
tives by RDT at the shops compared to a reference 
blood smear. 
19 20 Offering testing at the community 
level through agents who are independent of the subse-
quent drug sale and who are known to the patient may 
mitigate this concern. Furthermore, in our study, shop 
participation was high and we encountered no major 
problems in administering targeted drug subsidies in 
this manner. We observed fairly high ACT use among 
untested clients, but not as high as other studies. In 
reports from other countries where subsidised ACTs are 
available over-the-counter; between 60% and 100% of 
untested clients paid for ACTs. 
19-21 It is possible that the 
current price of ACTs in the retail sector in Kenya is pro-
hibitive for some families. At the end of the AMFm 
pilot, the average price of ACT in Kenya was US$0.58 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>but the subsidy level has declined since the conclusion 
of the pilot and the current cost of an adult dose is 
about three times higher than the AMFm subsidised 
price. In support of this view, we note that our results 
agree with Cohen et al 
22 who reported that 25% of 
untested clients purchasing ACT in Uganda where the 
price of ACT was four times higher than AMFm target 
prices. 
2 Importantly, in all of our study groups, ACT </p>

<p>Table 3 Linear probability model estimates* of the effect of RDT and ACT subsidies on malaria testing behaviour, defined as 
self-report of taking any malaria test †, for N=444 study participants </p>

<p>Unadjusted 
Adjusted (parsimonious) 
Adjusted (full ‡) </p>

<p>Prespecified comparisons of interest (% differences) </p>

<p>RDT-only subsidy (Group B vs 
Group D) </p>

<p>21.4% 
(8.5% to 34.2%) </p>

<p>18.8% 
(5.9% to 31.6%) </p>

<p>18.6% 
(5.9% to 31.3%) </p>

<p>ACT-only subsidy (Group C vs 
Group D) </p>

<p>−2.9% 
(−16.2% to 10.5%) </p>

<p>−3.5% 
(−16.9% to 9.9%) </p>

<p>−2.8% 
(−16.5% to 11.0%) </p>

<p>ACT subsidy when RDT is 
subsidised (Group A vs Group B) § </p>

<p>0.35% 
(−11.3% to 12.0%) </p>

<p>1.5% 
(−10.1% to 13.2%) </p>

<p>2.7% 
(−8.6% to 14.1%) </p>

<p>Covariate effects (% differences) </p>

<p>Wealth: poorest 40th centile 
-
−13.0% 
(−22.3% to −3.7%) </p>

<p>−14.5% 
(−24.1% to −4.9%) </p>

<p>Reference level (%) (Group D-no 
subsidies) </p>

<p>52.4% 
(42.8% to 62.1%) </p>

<p>58.2% 
(47.8% to 68.7%) </p>

<p>62.0% 
(32.8% to 91.3%) </p>

<p>Sample size 
435 
427 
427 </p>

<p>*LPM models specified as a generalised linear model for a binomial outcome with an identity link function. All models include two factors (RDT 
subsidy and ACT subsidy) and their interaction to match the randomised 2×2 factorial study design in order to estimate the prespecified effects 
of interest. 
 †Self-report of any malaria test (RDT or slide) at CHW or health facility. 
 ‡Fully adjusted model includes age (of patient), gender (of patient), education level (of patient or guardian if patient &lt;18 years), occupation (of 
patient or guardian), household size, wealth, sublocation of residence, and an interaction term between ACT and RDT subsidies. Only wealth was 
significant and is the only covariate retained in the parsimonious model. Full model results can be found in the online supplementary table 1. 
 §Defined as the coefficient of the main effect of the ACT subsidy plus the coefficient of the ACT×RDT interaction term. 
ACT, artemisinin combination therapy; RDT, rapid diagnostic test. </p>



<p>Prudhomme O'Meara W, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2016;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000101 </p>

<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>consumption among malaria-negative participants was 
lower than among untested participants, demonstrating 
targeting of ACTs as a result of testing. Malaria-negative 
participants in the double-subsidy group took an ACT 
more frequently than malaria-negative participants in 
any other group, and nearly as often as those untested, 
an observation for which we do not have a satisfying 
explanation. 
This is the first study that implements an antimalarial 
subsidy that is conditional on confirmatory testing. 
Antimalarial subsidies in the retail sector have improved 
access to effective treatment but may also increase 
inappropriate use of the drugs. Confirmatory diagnostic 
testing for malaria prior to treatment could improve tar-
geting of subsidised ACTs, reducing their unnecessary 
use and lowering the per patient costs of a subsidy pro-
gramme. In our study, both RDT subsidy and ACT 
subsidy ( provided conditional on a positive RDT) were 
independently linked to increases in appropriate fever 
management decisions, but adding the conditional ACT 
subsidy on top of the RDT subsidy did not influence the 
likelihood of malaria testing. We conclude that both sub-
sidies are independently important, but only in relation 
to decision making on the next immediate treatment 
action targeted by the subsidy. A drug subsidy which is 
conditional on confirmatory testing is a promising 
approach for improving sustainability of publicly funded 
subsidies. However, more work is required to define the 
optimal relationship between diagnostic testing and sub-
sidised ACTs sold over-the-counter, both in terms of the 
level of subsidy of each commodity as well as the mech-
anism of delivery. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Division of Infectious Diseases and International Health, Duke University 
Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina, USA </p>

<p>2 Duke Global Health Institute, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, USA 
3 Moi University School of Public Health, College of Health Sciences, Eldoret, 
Kenya 
4 Sanford School of Public Policy, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, 
USA 
5 Department of Economics, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, USA 
6 Academic Model Providing Access to Healthcare (AMPATH), Eldoret, Kenya 
7 Moi University School of Medicine, College of Health Sciences, Eldoret, 
Kenya 
8 Department of Biostatistics and Bioinformatics, Duke University, Durham, 
North Carolina, USA </p>

<p>Handling editor Valery Ridde </p>

<p>Acknowledgements This study could not have been carried out without the 
exceptional attention to detail and commitment of our field team; L Abel, I 
Khaoya, I Kunusia, E Mukeli, E Nalianya, J Namae, L Nukewa E Wamalwa and 
A Wekesa. The authors are grateful to the study participants and the 
community health workers as well as the local community leadership that 
supported this work. </p>

<p>Contributors WPO participated in study design, execution, data analysis, and 
wrote the first draft of the manuscript. MM participated in study design, 
execution and data analysis. JL participated in study design and execution. 
ELT participated in study design, data analysis and drafting of the manuscript. 
AL participated in study design, study execution and drafting of the 
manuscript. AP participated in study design, data analysis, and drafting of the 
manuscript. EM participated in study design and data analysis. DM 
participated in study design and oversaw execution of study activities. All 
authors approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding This study received funding from award number R01AI110478 from 
the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases of the National 
Institutes of Health (USA). The content is solely the responsibility of the 
authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National 
Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases or the National Institutes of Health. 
The study sponsor had no influence on the study design; data collection, 
analysis or interpretation; content of the manuscript, nor the authors' decision 
to submit this manuscript. The researchers operated independently from the 
funder in these matters. All authors had full access to all data and took 
responsibility for the integrity and accurate analysis of the data. </p>

<p>Competing interests All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform 
disclosure form at http://www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf and declare: all 
authors had financial support from the National Institute of Allergy and </p>

<p>Table 4 Linear probability model estimates* of the effect of RDT and ACT subsidies on ACT consumption among study 
participants who were tested for malaria, stratified by test results (N=267) </p>

<p>Estimated effects 
Malaria negative 
Malaria positive </p>

<p>Unadjusted </p>

<p>Adjusted 
(parsimonious) 
Unadjusted </p>

<p>Adjusted 
(parsimonious) 
Comparisons of interest (% differences) </p>

<p>RDT subsidy (irrespective of ACT 
subsidy group) </p>

<p>13.4% 
(2.4% to 24.4%) </p>

<p>12.8% 
(1.7% to 23.9%) </p>

<p>2.9% 
(−13.6% to 19.4%) </p>

<p>4.2% 
(−1.2% to 20.4%) </p>

<p>ACT subsidy (irrespective of RDT 
subsidy group) </p>

<p>6.4% 
(−4.7% to 17.6%) </p>

<p>8.2% 
(−3.3% to 19.6%) </p>

<p>17.8% 
(0.4% to 35.1%) </p>

<p>19.5% 
(2.2% to 36.8%) </p>

<p>Covariate effects (% differences) </p>

<p>Wealth: poorest 40th centile 
2.9% 
(−9.0% to 14.8%) </p>

<p>4.2% 
(−12.2% to 20.6%) </p>





<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

<p>Infectious Diseases of the National Institutes of Health (USA) for the submitted 
work; no financial relationships with any organisations that might have an 
interest in the submitted work in the previous 3 years; no other relationships or 
activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work. </p>

<p>Ethics approval The study was reviewed and approved by Moi University 
Institutional Research and Ethics Committee (approval number 0001198) and 
Duke University Health System Institutional Review Board (Pro00052602). 
Permission was also sought and granted from the Bungoma East subcounty 
Health Management Team and the chiefs and assistant chiefs of the 
participating administrative areas. Informed consent was obtained from all 
participants prior to their enrolment. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement Individual-level data can be requested from the 
corresponding author. Consent was not obtained for data sharing, but the 
presented data are anonymised and risk of identification is very low. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Prudhomme O'Meara W, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2016;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000101 </p>

<p>BMJ Global Health </p>

</text></tei>