<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5445908" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: 
Morphological changes repaired by icariin and autologous concentrate growth factors (ACGF) in critical-sized 
cranial defect were observed and their promoting effects were investigated. 
Material/Methods: 
Seventy-two New Zealand white rabbits weighing 1.8~2.0kg were used to build a critical-sized cranial defect 
model and were randomly divided into 3 groups. X-ray, HE staining, general and histological observation, and 
immunohistochemistry were used to describe the changes caused by normal saline, icariin, and ACGF. 
Results: 
Cranial defects were covered with newly formed bone tissue at the 12 th week in icariin and ACGF groups, with 
red color, hard surface, and no obvious boundary. Densities were the same in 2 groups at 4 timepoints. HE 
staining showed defects filled with a large amount of fibrous connective tissue, thick collagen fibers, and abun-
dant osteoclasts. No new bone matrix appeared in any of the 3 groups. Trabecular area, trabeculae width, and 
osteoblast number in 2 groups were more than that of the control group, and osteoclast number was lower. 
However, osteoclast number among the 3 groups at the 12 th week had no significant difference, which was the 
same with 4 indicators between the icariin and ACGF groups. From the 4 th to 12 th week, regenerated cartilage 
was formed and showed positive reaction with BMP-2 and TGFb1 from primary bone, which also was demon-
strated by granulation tissue and uniform dyeing. 
Conclusions: 
ACGF and icariin both can increase new bone quantity and improve bone quality, which can also promote heal-
ing. The effects and mechanisms of icariin and ACGF on the expression of gene are not exactly the same. </p>

<p>Bone defects caused by various causes, especially oral and 
maxillofacial defects, have a serious impact on patient qual-
ity of life [1]. Bone healing is an extremely complex process 
of biological repair, and has been a major problem in clinical 
practice. How to promote the healing of bone defect is a cur-
rent focus of medical research. Scholars in China and other 
countries have done many experiments and widely discussed 
the bone healing mechanism with the help of histology, his-
tochemistry, histology, ultrastructure, and biomechanics [2]. </p>

<p>Chinese herbal medicine has a history of 7000 years in China. 
Icariin (C 33 H 40 O 15 , molecular weight 676.67), is an active com-
ponent of Epimedium, and was reported to have physiolog-
ical activities such as improving cardiovascular and cerebral 
vessels, enhancing the sexual glands and the immune system, 
delaying aging, resisting tumors and viruses, inhibiting osteo-
clast formation, and promoting osteoblast growth [3-6]. The 
mechanism of promoting bone repair and regeneration by icar-
iin is well understood. Autologous concentrated growth factor 
(ACGF), a new type of biological material, was first proposed by 
Sacco [7]. ACGF contains transfer growth factor b (TGF-b), bone 
morphogenetic protein (BMP), insulin-like growth factor (IGF), 
vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), epidermal growth 
factor (EGF), platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF), and fibro-
blast growth factor (bFGF) [8,9]. Recent studies have shown 
that ACGF has the ability to promote new bone formation and 
implant bone bonding, and shortens the time required for this 
process [10]. In a certain sense, ACGF can enhance the repair 
and regeneration of bone defects. </p>

<p>Using a critical-sized cranial defect model, we observed the 
effect of normal saline, icariin, and ACGF pellicle on bone de-
fects. At 4 time points, the effects, characteristics, and speeds 
of osteoclast and osteoblast formation were compared to ex-
plore the mechanism of promoting healing of bone defects by 
general observation, X-ray, HE staining, and bone histomor-
phometry and immunohistochemistry. </p>

<p>Material and Methods </p>

<p>We randomly divided 72 healthy female New Zealand white 
rabbits weighing 1.8~2.0kg (12 months old, supplied by 
the Laboratory Animal Center of Hebei Medical University, 
SCXK(JI)2013-1-003, 1406115) into 3 groups and housed 
them individually. </p>

<p>Building a critical-sized cranial defect model </p>

<p>After rabbits were conventionally raised for a week, skull hair 
of the surgical area between the eyes and ears was removed </p>

<p>with 8% Na 2 S the day before surgery. Under general anesthesia 
with 10% hydrate (0.15 mg/kg, FUYU Chemical, China), rabbits 
were fixed on the operating table in prone position. A 15-mm 
diameter cranial defect was made and the integrity of the dura 
mater was preserved to produce a cranial full-thickness defect 
(Figure 1). Gentamicin sulfate and sterile saline were used to 
wash the wound, preserving the integrity of the periosteum 
and covering the bone defect area. After the surgery, rabbits 
were returned to their cages after resuscitation and allowed 
free access to food and water. Each rabbit was injected with 
80 000 units of gentamicin sulfate for 3 consecutive days. </p>

<p>Groups </p>

<p>Group A, the icariin group, was given intragastric administra-
tion of icariin in equal daily doses from the first day after su-
turing periosteum and skin. Icariin was administered daily 
as a 100-mg/ml solution (CY121120, Ciyuan Biotech Co., Ltd, 
China) and dosage was 100 mg/kg per day. In group B, the 
ACGF group, the local bone defect was covered with ACGF pel-
licle and then periosteum and skin were sutured. Group C, the 
control group, was given normal saline by gastric lavage be-
fore eating and dosage was 1 ml/kg once daily from the first 
day after suturing periosteum and skin. </p>

<p>ACGF pellicle </p>

<p>Venous blood of rabbits was collected into 9-ml blood collection 
tubes (Vacuette, Austria) without shaking. After centrifugation 
with 30-s acceleration, 2700 r/min for 2 min, 2400 r/min for 
4 min, 2700 r/min for 4 min, 3000 r/min for 3 min, and 36 s 
deceleration (ZilaDent, Italy), a middle layer of yellow jelly ma-
terial formed. Which was the ACGF gel layer. An ACGF pellicle 
was produced using a mold. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Rabbit skull full-thickness defect with the integrity of 
the dura mater. </p>

<p>2374 </p>

<p>Indexed in: [Current Contents/Clinical Medicine] [SCI Expanded] [ISI Alerting System] 
[ISI Journals Master List] [Index Medicus/MEDLINE] [EMBASE/Excerpta Medica] 
[Chemical Abstracts/CAS] [Index Copernicus] </p>

<p>Li G. et al.: 
Morphological observation by icariin and ACGF 
© Med Sci Monit, 2017; 23: 2373-2381 </p>

<p>ANIMAL STUDY </p>

<p>This work is licensed under Creative Common Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) </p>

<p>Indicators </p>

<p>At 2, 4, 8, and 12 weeks after surgery, all rabbits in the 3 groups 
were killed. Under sterile conditions, the skull was taken out 
and an X-ray was taken to observe bone defect healing. The 
new bone tissue was intercepted by 5 mm along the edge of 
the defect region and fixed for 48 h in 4% polyformaldehyde. 
A 4-μm decalcified bone tissue section was made for HE (he-
matoxylin and eosin) staining. HE-stained tissue section was </p>

<p>photographed under a light microscope to compare trabecu-
lae width (TW), trabecular area (TA), osteoblast number (OBN), 
and osteoclast number (OCN). </p>

<p>Expression of BMP-2 and TGF-1 protein detected by 
streptavidin-peroxidase (SP) immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Paraffin sections was made, routinely dewaxed in water, and 
soaked in 3% H 2 O 2 for 10 min and washed with PBS 3 times </p>

<p>Figure 2. Repairing situation of bone defect at 4 time points. First column is A group; second column is group B; third column is 
group C. </p>

<p>2375 </p>

<p>Indexed in: [Current Contents/Clinical Medicine] [SCI Expanded] [ISI Alerting System] 
[ISI Journals Master List] [Index Medicus/MEDLINE] [EMBASE/Excerpta Medica] 
[Chemical Abstracts/CAS] [Index Copernicus] </p>

<p>Li G. et al.: 
Morphological observation by icariin and ACGF 
© Med Sci Monit, 2017; 23: 2373-2381 </p>

<p>ANIMAL STUDY </p>

<p>This work is licensed under Creative Common Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) </p>

<p>for 5 min each time. Samples were blocked at 37°C with sheep 
serum for 30 min to reduce nonspecific adsorption and then 
washed with PBS 3 times. With monoclonal antibody BMP-2 
(diluted concentration 1: 50) and TGFb1 (diluted concentra-
tion 1: 50) (ZSGB-BIO, Beijing, China), immunohistochemical 
staining was done with biotin-labeled goat anti-mouse IgG 
(ZSGB-BIO, Beijing, China) and horseradish peroxidase-labeled 
streptavidin (ZSGB-BIO, Beijing, China) for 30 min and 20 min, 
respectively. 3,3'-diaminobenzidine (ZSGB-BIO, Beijing, China) 
was used to display color. Samples were stained again with </p>

<p>hematoxylin and then washed with water. After being pack-
aged with neutral gum, samples were observed under a light 
microscope. In addition, PBS instead of antibody I was used 
as a negative control. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">19.0</rs> software was used to analyze data. All data are ex-
pressed as mean ±SD. Variance analysis was used to compare </p>

<p>Figure 3. General observation of skull at 4 time points. First column is group A; second column is group B; third column is group C. </p>

<p>2376 </p>

<p>Indexed in: [Current Contents/Clinical Medicine] [SCI Expanded] [ISI Alerting System] 
[ISI Journals Master List] [Index Medicus/MEDLINE] [EMBASE/Excerpta Medica] 
[Chemical Abstracts/CAS] [Index Copernicus] </p>

<p>Li G. et al.: 
Morphological observation by icariin and ACGF 
© Med Sci Monit, 2017; 23: 2373-2381 </p>

<p>ANIMAL STUDY </p>

<p>This work is licensed under Creative Common Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) </p>

<p>the data between 2 groups. P values less than 0.05 were con-
sidered significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The general observation of bone defect was done and the 
changes are shown in Figures 2 and 3. There were no differ-
ences among the 3 groups at the 2 nd week, with central local 
depression and blurred boundary. A small amount of soft, thin, 
translucent new bone tissue appeared in groups A and B from 
the 4 th week. Bone fusion with normal bone tissue was obvi-
ous (smooth surface, uniform thickness, slightly red color) at </p>

<p>the 8 th week in groups A and B, but not group C. At 12 weeks, 
bone defects were covered with newly formed bone tissue with 
red color, hard surface, and no obvious boundary between the 
edges, forming normal physiological curvature of skull tissue. 
X-rays showed homogeneous low-density images with sharp 
edges of the bone defect at the 2 nd week in all 3 groups, and 
in groups A and B this changed to cloud-like low-density shad-
ow at the 4 th week. Local high-density bone was found in the 
defect area and the defect area was obviously smaller with 
edges blurred. There was no significant difference between 
groups A and B (P&gt;0.05, Figure 4). </p>

<p>Figure 4. X-ray result of skull at 4 time points. First column is A group; second column is group B; third column is group C. </p>

<p>2377 </p>

<p>Indexed in: [Current Contents/Clinical Medicine] [SCI Expanded] [ISI Alerting System] 
[ISI Journals Master List] [Index Medicus/MEDLINE] [EMBASE/Excerpta Medica] 
[Chemical Abstracts/CAS] [Index Copernicus] </p>

<p>Li G. et al.: 
Morphological observation by icariin and ACGF 
© Med Sci Monit, 2017; 23: 2373-2381 </p>

<p>ANIMAL STUDY </p>

<p>This work is licensed under Creative Common Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) </p>

<p>Results of HE staining revealed bone defects were filled with 
fibrous connective tissue and no new bone tissue appeared at 
the 2 nd week in all 3 groups. OCN was abundant. Two weeks lat-
er, in groups A and B, fibrous connective tissue decreased but 
collagen fibers became thick, with a few scattered inflammato-
ry cells. A small amount of new fibrous bone tissue was found 
and osteoblasts began to appear and neatly arrange around fi-
brous bone-like structure. In the control group, inflammatory </p>

<p>cells were widely distributed in fibrous tissue with some os-
teoclasts (Figure 5). TW, TA, OBN, and OCN are shown in Table 
1; there was no statistical difference between A and B group 
at all 4 time points among these 4 indicators. </p>

<p>Brown granules appeared in cells after intracellular stain-
ing and brown flakes in intercellular substance during ex-
tracellular staining were both regarded as positive staining. </p>

<p>Figure 5. HE staining results of skull at 4 time points (HE ×400). New bone was not observed at the 2 nd week. A few osteoblasts 
gathered around trabecular bone in groups A and B at the 4 th week. A large number of osteoblasts gathered around 
trabecular bone in groups A and B after 8 weeks. A few osteoblasts gathered around trabecular bone in group C. Mass of 
new bone was observed in groups A and B at 12 weeks, while masses of fibrous tissue gathered around trabecular bone in 
group C. First column is group A, second column is group B, third column is group C. </p>

<p>2378 </p>

<p>Indexed in: [Current Contents/Clinical Medicine] [SCI Expanded] [ISI Alerting System] 
[ISI Journals Master List] [Index Medicus/MEDLINE] [EMBASE/Excerpta Medica] 
[Chemical Abstracts/CAS] [Index Copernicus] </p>

<p>Li G. et al.: 
Morphological observation by icariin and ACGF 
© Med Sci Monit, 2017; 23: 2373-2381 </p>

<p>ANIMAL STUDY </p>

<p>This work is licensed under Creative Common Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical staining results of BMP-2 and TGF-b1 
were almost the same and are displayed in Figure 6. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Previous research showed that an experimental bone defect 
should be larger than the area an animal can self-heal [11]. 
This can realistically and effectively reflect the repair situa-
tion by materials or growth factor, and reduce the influence 
of factors such as species, age, and site [12]. Critical-sized de-
fect (CSD) was first proposed by Schmitz et al., who defined it 
as the minimal defect that cannot be repaired and healed in 
a lifetime by itself in a specific bone [13]. CSD models of rats, 
dogs, and rabbits have been widely used, and the rabbit crit-
ical-sized cranial defect model is 15 mm in diameter and is a 
round bone defect [11,12,14]. In our study, the rabbit cranial 
defect was 15×15 mm and cannot self-repair, which has been </p>

<p>confirmed in preliminary experiments and can realistically re-
flect the repairing situation using icariin and ACGF. </p>

<p>Epimedium is a genus of flowering plants in the family 
Berberidaceae and is a typical representative of Chinese herb-
al medicines (Yang) used to repair strengthen bone. Icariin, 
as the active component of Epimedium, was reported to have 
many physiological activities, which not only stimulate new 
bone formation and increase bone mass, but also promotes 
bone marrow stromal stem cell differentiation to osteoblasts 
and inhibits osteoclast differentiation [15-17]. In addition, ex-
cept for promoting the expression of TGF-b in rat osteoblasts, 
icariin also can inhibit the expression of IL-6 and TNF-a, which 
can inhibit bone resorption and promote bone formation [18]. 
Thus, icariin has been widely used and is a highly developed 
method to repair bone defects. </p>

<p>Indicator 
C group 
A group 
B group </p>

<p>2 th week </p>

<p>TA (%) 
9.12±3.02 
17.67±3.55* 
17.33±3.95* </p>

<p>TW (µm) 
186.11±24.53 
290.32±24.89* 
291.45±24.52* </p>

<p>OBN 
10.31±5.14 
31.11±5.67* 
31.24±5.22* </p>

<p>OCN 
5.19±0.55 
4.03±0.50* 
4.02±0.53* </p>

<p>4 th week </p>

<p>TA (%) 
19.04±3.94 
37.88±4.10* 
37.81±3.91* </p>

<p>TW (µm) 
225.17±28.53 
312.13±27.69* 
311.02±27.72* </p>

<p>OBN 
20.11±4.45 
49.74±4.67* 
47.55±4.53* </p>

<p>OCN 
4.88±0.78 
3.19±0.80* 
3.17±0.78* </p>

<p>8 th week </p>

<p>TA (%) 
28.12±3.56 
45.55±3.66* 
46.01±3.58* </p>

<p>TW (µm) 
299.36±13.58 
419.10±37.10* 
417.90±38.15* </p>

<p>OBN 
29.64±8.41 
60.12±7.36* 
58.17±8.38* </p>

<p>OCN 
4.53±0.66 
1.75±0.47* 
1.77±0.55* </p>

<p>12 th week </p>

<p>TA (%) 
43.16±5.45 
67.00±5.60* 
66.97±5.58* </p>

<p>TW (µm) 
377.97±29.17 
579.88±30.23* 
580.03±29.91* </p>

<p>OBN 
20.35±4.91 
35.71±4.87* 
36.03±4.77* </p>

<p>OCN 
1.99±0.74 
1.94±0.88 
1.95±0.79 </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparisons of bone histomorphometric indicators among three groups (Mean ±SD, n=3). </p>

<p>A group means icariine group; B group means ACGF group; C group means the control group. TA -means trabercular area; 
TW -means traberculae width; OBN -means osteoblast number; OCN -means osteoclast number. * When this group compared with 
the control group, P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>2379 </p>

<p>Indexed in: [Current Contents/Clinical Medicine] [SCI Expanded] [ISI Alerting System] 
[ISI Journals Master List] [Index Medicus/MEDLINE] [EMBASE/Excerpta Medica] 
[Chemical Abstracts/CAS] [Index Copernicus] </p>

<p>Li G. et al.: 
Morphological observation by icariin and ACGF 
© Med Sci Monit, 2017; 23: 2373-2381 </p>

<p>ANIMAL STUDY </p>

<p>This work is licensed under Creative Common Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) </p>

<p>Figure 6. Immunohistochemical staining results of BMP-2 and TGF-b1 at 4 time points (Polymer ×400). First column is group A; second 
column is group B; third column is group C. Left 3 pictures are BMP-2, and right pictures are TGF-b1. BMP-2 and TGF-b1 were 
positive in intercellular substances among the 3 groups at the 2 nd week, which was the same at the 4 th week. BMP-2 and 
TGF-b1 were positive in intercellular substance and bone matrix at the 8 th week, and osteoblasts also showed positive at the 
12 th week. </p>

<p>At present, there are 2 kinds of plasma extract in the field of 
oral and maxillofacial surgery: platelet-rich plasma (PRP) and 
platelet-rich fibrin (PRF) [19,20]. ACGF is isolated from venous 
blood, just like PRF. However, ACGF is completely without addi-
tives such as calcium chloride and bovine thrombin, and is saf-
er than PRF in the control of infection. Studies had confirmed 
that ACGF can speed the reconstruction of new bone and does 
not cause viral infections [7]. Due to its fibrous framework com-
posed of various high-concentration growth factors and fibrous 
protein, ACGF is successfully used as a healing biological ma-
terial. TGF-b can promote mitotic division of osteogenic pre-
cursor cells and fibroblast cells [21]. PDGF can increase OBN, 
stimulate mitotic division of bone marrow stromal stem cells, 
and promote capillary regeneration [22]. IGF is involved in the 
development and differentiation of bone, skin, and nerves, and 
also has the function of promoting mitosis [23]. VEGF can pro-
mote differentiation of osteoblasts, fracture healing, forma-
tion of new blood vessels, and enhances permeability [24]. In 
addition, the polymerization of fibrinogen molecules can cap-
ture fiber protein blocks to form a 3-dimensional polymer grid 
structure, which is thin, soft, osmotic, and rich in elastin. In 
bone repair and regeneration, fibrin coagulation plays an im-
portant role in mechanical support. </p>

<p>Osteoblasts determine the formation, development, reconstruc-
tion, and repair of bone [25]. The change in OBN is an impor-
tant factor that affects the balance of bone metabolism. TGF-b </p>

<p>is a secreted protein that controls proliferation, cellular differ-
entiation, and other functions in most cells and is widespread 
in animal bone tissue and platelets [26]. Because of its exten-
sive biological activity and variety of regulatory function, TGF-b 
can promote osteoblast proliferation and differentiation, in-
hibit the activity of osteoclasts, and promote fiber cells to se-
crete fiber mucin and collagen, which has an important regu-
latory role in bone cell growth, immunity, and differentiation. 
TGF-b is an important biological transmitter in injury. TGF-b1 
is an important subtype of TGF-b, which can induce the differ-
entiation of primary mesenchymal stem cells into cartilage tis-
sue, and promote the proliferation and maturation of cartilage 
cells during the process of embryonic cartilage formation [27]. 
BMP is a multifunctional growth factor in the TGF-b family; it 
is a highly conserved and functional protein with structure 
similar to that of other members of the family [28]. Because it 
can induce bone and cartilage formation in vivo, BMP is called 
"osteogenin" or "bone morphogenetic protein". BMP-2 is the 
most widely studied BMP and is the most active in inducing 
osteogenesis. BMP-2 was widely found to be highly expressed 
in cartilage cells, osteoblasts, and their precursor cells [28]. </p>

<p>In the present study, we compared the 2 methods of repairing 
rabbit cranial defect by icariin and ACGF pellicle. The results 
showed that, from the 4 th week, osteoblasts began to gather 
around the cranial edge with a cubic shape, a large and obvi-
ous nucleus, abundant cytoplasm, and regular arrangement. </p>



<p>Indexed in: [Current Contents/Clinical Medicine] [SCI Expanded] [ISI Alerting System] 
[ISI Journals Master List] [Index Medicus/MEDLINE] [EMBASE/Excerpta Medica] 
[Chemical Abstracts/CAS] [Index Copernicus] </p>

<p>Li G. et al.: 
Morphological observation by icariin and ACGF 
© Med Sci Monit, 2017; 23: 2373-2381 </p>

<p>ANIMAL STUDY </p>

<p>This work is licensed under Creative Common Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) </p>

<p>This illustrates that the osteoblasts were significantly more 
active than in the control group. Osteoblast activity reached 
a peak at the 8 th week, with a single, large, and clear nucleus, 
1-nucleolus, and a fence-like arrangement around bone and 
trabecular bone. At the 12 th week, trabecular bone thickened 
and OBN stabilized, which was significantly higher than in 
the control group. There was no significant difference in new 
bone formation or new bone density in the icariin and ACGF 
groups, but they were both higher than in the control group, 
indicating that icariin and ACGF both can accelerate the qual-
ity and speed of bone healing and achieve almost the same 
effect. X-ray, HE staining, histological observation, and immu-
nohistochemistry almost showed the same results. Positive ex-
pression of BMP-2 and TGF-b1 gradually increased after cra-
nial defects were repaired by icariin and ACGF pellicle for 2, 
4, 8, and 12 weeks, suggesting that icariin and ACGF pellicle 
can quickly and effectively initiate formation of various cyto-
kines related to osteogenesis, promote the formation of car-
tilage matrix and the proliferation and differentiation of os-
teoblasts, inhibit the formation of osteoclasts, and accelerate 
the repair and healing of bone defects. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>ACGF and icariin both can increase new bone quantity and im-
prove the quality of healing. They also can promote the qual-
ity and rate of healing. The effect of ACGF and icariin on heal-
ing of bone defects was nearly identical (P&gt;0.05). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We acknowledge the assistance of investigators and all sub-
jects in this study. </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests. In 
addition, this research received no specific grant from any fund-
ing agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors. </p>





<p>Indexed in: [Current Contents/Clinical Medicine] [SCI Expanded] [ISI Alerting System] 
[ISI Journals Master List] [Index Medicus/MEDLINE] [EMBASE/Excerpta Medica] 
[Chemical Abstracts/CAS] [Index Copernicus] </p>

<p>Li G. et al.: 
Morphological observation by icariin and ACGF 
© Med Sci Monit, 2017; 23: 2373-2381 </p>

<p>ANIMAL STUDY </p>

<p>This work is licensed under Creative Common Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) </p>

</text></tei>