<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5143422" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Fatty acid biosynthesis (FAS) is a vital process in cells. Fatty acids are essential for cell assembly and cellular me-
tabolism. Abnormal FAS directly correlates with cell growth delay and human diseases, such as metabolic syndromes 
and various cancers. The FAS system utilizes an acyl carrier protein (ACP) as a transporter to stabilize and shuttle 
the growing fatty acid chain throughout enzymatic modules for stepwise catalysis. Studying the interactions between 
enzymatic modules and ACP is, therefore, critical for understanding the biological function of the FAS system. How-
ever, the information remains unclear due to the high flexibility of ACP and its weak interaction with enzymatic mod-
ules. We present here a 2.55 Å crystal structure of type II FAS dehydratase FabZ in complex with holo-ACP, which 
exhibits a highly symmetrical FabZ hexamer-ACP 3 stoichiometry with each ACP binding to a FabZ dimer subunit. 
Further structural analysis, together with biophysical and computational results, reveals a novel dynamic seesaw-like 
ACP binding and catalysis mechanism for the dehydratase module in the FAS system, which is regulated by a critical 
gatekeeper residue (Tyr100 in FabZ) that manipulates the movements of the β-sheet layer. These findings improve 
the general understanding of the dehydration process in the FAS system and will potentially facilitate drug and ther-
apeutic design for diseases associated with abnormalities in FAS. 
Fatty acid biosynthesis (FAS) is one of the most im-
portant processes in cells and organisms on earth. Fatty 
acids are essential for the cellular membrane assembly, 
energy storage, cell signal transduction and regulation 
of gene expression [1-5]. Deficiency in the FAS system 
causes delays in bacterial development and triggers pro-
grammed cell death in plants [2, 3, 6]. In human, dereg-
ulated FAS system has been correlated with metabolic 
syndrome (MetS) diseases, including obesity and type-
II diabetes [7-11]. Moreover, human fatty acid synthase </p>

<p>(hFASN) has been considered as an oncogene because it 
is significantly overexpressed in several human cancers 
with poor prognosis and survival, particularly, including 
prostate and breast cancers [12-17]. 
The chemical logic of FAS system is highly conserved 
between eukaryotes and bacteria except for the arrange-
ment of functional enzymatic modules. It utilizes a series 
of enzymatic modules to iteratively carry out fatty acid 
elongation, which is divided into two stages: synthesis 
initiation and elongation (Figure 1). The initiation stage 
covalently attaches a short acetyl (or malonyl) group to 
the terminal sulfhydryl of the 4-phosphopantetheine arm 
(4′-Pan-arm, hereafter) on the substrate carrier protein, 
which is a holo-acyl carrier protein (holo-ACP). Subse-
quently, ACP shuttles among approximately four enzy-
matic modules in the elongation cycle to process fatty 
acid extension; and two additional carbons are added </p>

<p>Lin Zhang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>to the substrate chain in each cycle until the product is 
released. On the basis of the enzymatic module arrange-
ment, the FAS system is divided into associative and dis-
sociative architectural types. The associative architecture 
(FAS-I) exists in some bacteria (e.g., CMN-FAS) and 
eukaryotes, including mammals and fungi [1, 18]. All the 
enzymatic modules function as domains on a large poly-
peptide (one or two polypeptide(s) in fungi), which is en-
coded by a single gene (one or two gene(s) in fungi). The 
dissociative architecture (FAS-II) exists in plants, mito-
chondria and bacteria, whereas the enzymatic modules 
function as a series of individual soluble enzymes en-
coded by discrete genes [2]. So far, crystal structures of 
FAS-I synthases (FASN) from Sus scrofa and fungi [19- 23] and FAS-II individual enzymes from various bacteri-
al species have been reported [2, 24-28], which provided 
detailed insights into the biochemical mechanism at an 
atomic level. However, due to the high flexibility and </p>

<p>diffusible characteristics of ACP, the interactions be-
tween ACP and enzyme modules in FASN or individual 
enzymes in FAS-II have rarely been investigated except 
for an incomplete enoyl reductase (FabI)-ACP structure 
and a covalently crosslinked β-hydroxyacyl-ACP dehy-
dratase (FabA)-ACP structure [25, 29]. Hence, the key 
mechanisms underlying the recognition and processing 
of ACP by enzymatic modules for substrate catalysis re-
main unclear, especially in the elongation cycle. 
The elongation cycle predominantly consists of four 
catalytic steps (Figure 1). Dehydration of β-hydroxya-
cyl-ACP is the third step, which is processed either by 
the dehydratase (DH) domain of FAS-I synthase or two 
individual DH homologs, FabA and FabZ, in FAS-II 
(Figure 1) [1, 2]. FabA appears as a homodimer and cat-
alyzes the dehydration of short fatty acids (≤ 10-carbon) 
as well as the isomerization of trans-2-acyl-ACP to cis-
2-acyl-ACP. In contrast, FabZ appears as a hexamer in </p>

<p>Figure 1 Schematic diagram of fatty acid biosynthesis process. The catalytic process is divided into initiation and elongation 
stages. In the initiation stage, apo-form of acyl carrier protein (apo-ACP, green) is covalently installed with a 4′-phosphop-
antetheine moiety (4′-Pan-arm) by holo-ACP synthase (AcpS), forming holo-ACP. Subsequently, a short acetyl (or malonyl) 
group is covalently attached to the terminal sulfhydryl of the 4′-Pan-arm by malonyl-CoA-/acetyl-CoA-ACP transacylase (MAT 
domain in FAS-I; FabD in FAS-II). The elongation cycle mainly includes four catalytic steps to process fatty acid extension 
successively. The first step is decarboxylative condensation to form β-ketoacyl-ACP by β-ketoacyl synthase (KS domain in 
FAS-I; FabH, FanB and FabF in FAS-II); the second step is NADPH-dependent reduction of β-ketoacyl-ACP to β-hydroxya-
cyl-ACP by β-ketoacyl reductase (KR domain in FAS-I; FabG in FAS-II); the third step is β-hydroxyacyl-ACP dehydration to 
β-enoyl-ACP by β-hydroxyacyl-ACP dehydratase (DH domain in FAS-I; FabA and FabZ in FAS-II); the last step is β-enoyl-
ACP reduction by NADPH-dependent β-enoyl reductase (ER domain in FAS-I; FabI, FabK and FabL in FAS-II). After four 
steps, two carbons are added to the fatty acid chain, and the fatty acid chain either re-enter the elongation cycle for further exten-
sion or is released from ACP by thioesterase (TE domain in FAS-I; TE in FAS-II) once the length reaches 16-18 carbons. </p>



<p>Crystal structure of FabZ-ACP complex </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 26 No 12 | December 2016 </p>

<p>most cases (dimer is also observed besides hexamer in 
Plasmodium falciparum) and preferentially catalyzes the 
dehydration of long-chain fatty acids [2] (Supplementary 
information, Figure S1). In addition, FabZ is involved in 
the balance maintenance of fatty acid and lipid A biosyn-
thesis by regulating deacetylase LpxC [30]. Due to their 
indispensable functions and ubiquitous distributions, 
FabA and FabZ are regarded as important drug targets 
against pathogenic microbes. The enzymatic characteris-
tics of FabA and FabZ, as well as their structures in vari-
ous bacterial species have been well studied, and several 
lead compounds have been developed [31-35]. In 2014, 
Nguyen et al. [29] reported the first FabA-ACP complex 
structure, in which a mechanism-based synthetic alkyne 
probe was employed to covalently crosslink two ACP 
molecules to the FabA homodimer. The complex struc-
ture reveals ACP binding and the substrate accommo-
dation mechanism of FabA for the first time. A putative 
ACP binding mechanism was proposed based on the sig-
nificant conformational changes of ACP helices α2 and 
α3 observed during binding to FabA. Nevertheless, this 
structural model has not provided adequate insights into 
how the DH module recognizes and regulates ACP mole-
cules for enzymatic catalysis in the FAS system and what 
determines the distinct substrate length preference and 
isomerization mechanism between FabA and FabZ. The 
DH module (FabZ)-ACP complex structure in the FAS 
system presented in current study illustrates a dynamic 
seesaw-like ACP binding and regulation mechanism of 
FabZ, representing a novel substrate selection and catal-
ysis mechanism for the DH module in the FAS system. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Overall structure of the FabZ-ACP complex 
The recombinant FabZ and ACP from Helicobacter 
pylori were expressed and purified as described previ-
ously [36, 37]. Instead of using an alkyne probe attached 
to ACP (which was used in FabA-ACP structure [29]), 
holo-ACP was directly employed in crystallization to 
obtain the natural conformation of the DH module bound 
with ACP. The purified FabZ and holo-ACP proteins 
were mixed with a molar ratio of 1:7, and further puri-
fied by using Superdex 200 gel-filtration column. The 
crystals appeared within 30 days under 277 K in hang-
ing drop, and the complex structure was determined by 
molecular replacement (MR) at a resolution of 2.55 Å 
(Supplementary information, Table S1). The asymmet-
ric crystallographic unit contains a FabZ dimer subunit 
bound with a holo-ACP molecule. However, the gel-fil-
tration results indicated that the complex appears to have 
a stable hexamer conformation that reflects native FabZ </p>

<p>in complex with ACP (Supplementary information, Fig-
ure S2). As shown in Figure 2A, the overall structure of 
the FabZ-ACP hexamer generated by crystallographic 
symmetry operation displays a turbine-like shape with 
six FabZ monomers arranged in a ring-like contact topol-
ogy to form a classic FabZ "trimer of dimers" hexameric 
turbine core [26]. Each FabZ dimer subunit is bound by 
one holo-ACP, resulting in a stoichiometry of (FabZ di-
mer-ACP) 3 . 
In the dimer subunit, an unexpected 2:1 (FabZ mono-
mer:ACP) stoichiometric binding ratio is observed, 
where only one ACP molecule binds to a FabZ dimer. 
FabZ monomers A and B within the dimer subunit adopt 
a typical β + α "hot dog" fold in which a layer consisting 
of six anti-parallel β-sheets (β1-β6 strands, hereafter) 
wraps around the long, central six-turn α-helix (α3) (Fig-
ure 2B) [2, 26]. The β-sheet layer from each monomer 
further interacts with each other through their β3 strands 
to form a stable FabZ homodimer subunit. Next to the 
dimer interface, there are two L-shaped substrate-bind-
ing and catalysis tunnels, which are ~20 Å away from 
each other. Each tunnel consists of residues from both 
monomers. The entrance of the tunnel is located on the 
β3 strand near the dimer interface, and protected by a 
gatekeeper residue Tyr100 from bulk solvent. Here we 
named the two tunnels of the dimer subunit tunnels A (the 
gatekeeper residue Tyr100 is from monomer A) and B 
(Tyr100 is from monomer B). The holo-ACP binds to the 
β-sheet layer right on the FabZ dimer interface through 
its conserved α2 helix, occupying the monomer A and B 
surface areas of 148.82 Å 
2 and 335.03 Å 
2 , respectively, 
and inserts the 4′-Pan-arm into tunnel B (Figure 2B). The 
FabZ-ACP interactions are established through multiple 
hydrogen bonds (H-bonds) between a list of conserved 
residues, including those between positively charged res-
idue Arg110′ on FabZ β3 strand (the prime indicates the 
residue from FabZ monomer A in the dimer, otherwise 
from monomer B) and two negatively charged residues 
Asp35 and Asp38 on the N-terminus of ACP α2 helix, 
between Lys129 on the loop between FabZ β4 and β5 
strands and Glu47 on the C-terminus of ACP α2 helix, 
and between Lys152 on FabZ β6 strand and Glu41 on the 
C-terminus of ACP α2 helix (Figure 2B, Supplementary 
information, Figures S3, S4 and Table S2). In addition 
to H-bonds, the sidechains of Leu37, Val40 and Met44 
on ACP α2 helix form hydrophobic contacts with the 
hydrophobic patch composed of Met102, Thr103, Ile132 
and Lys152 from FabZ (Figure 2B). These hydrophobic 
and electrostatic interactions orient the ACP α2 helix 
precisely with the entrance of the FabZ tunnel B. Mean-
while, the sidechain of the gatekeeper residue Tyr100 in 
FabZ monomer B points toward Lys62′ to form an open </p>

<p>Lin Zhang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>Figure 2 Crystal structure of the FabZ-ACP complex. (A) Overall structure of the FabZ-ACP complex. FabZ dimer subunits 
are colored in green/cyan, and ACP is colored in magenta. The cartoon was generated by Pymol. (B) Interactions between 
ACP and FabZ dimer subunit. White surface of FabZ active tunnel was generated by Pymol plugin Caver. Residues involved 
in the interactions are shown as sticks, and the prime indicates the residues from FabZ monomer A, otherwise from B. 
H-bond network is shown as yellow dashes, and secondary structural elements are labeled as well. </p>

<p>conformation so that the ACP 4′-Pan-arm can comfort-
ably enter tunnel B (Figure 2B). Inside tunnel B, the arm 
displays a nearly extended conformation (Supplementary 
information, Figure S5). The conformation is stabilized 
by H-bonds between the backbone oxygen of Arg110′ 
from FabZ and ACP 4′-Pan-arm hydroxyl group (atom 
O 
33 ) and the first -NH group (atom N 
36 ) (Figure 2B), 
which indicates that the role of Arg110 in ACP binding 
is indispensable, consistent with results from previous 
reports [2, 38]. </p>

<p>Fatty acyl chain length preference of FabZ 
Previous studies indicate that the L-shaped FabZ ac-
tive tunnel is not adequate for accommodating a long fat-
ty acid substrate (&gt; 12-carbon), although FabZ enzymat-
ically prefers long substrates [2, 26-28]. In the current 
structure, ACP binding and insertion of the 4′-Pan-arm 
expand the active tunnel by pushing the β-sheet layer 
toward β4 (Figure 3A), which evokes a novel Y-shaped 
tunnel with extended potential for long fatty acid accom-
modation. The extension of the classical L-shaped tunnel 
B starts around residue Gly79 by forming two tunnel </p>

<p>branches (designated tunnels I and II; Figure 4A). Tunnel 
I consists of hydrophobic residues Gly78, Gly79, Trp133, 
Val135, Leu151 and Ala153 (Figure 4B), whereas tunnel 
II consists of hydrophobic residues Leu21, Phe83, Ile93, 
Ala94, Lys97 and Ile98 from monomer B (Figure 4C). 
Accordingly, the hydrophobic nature of both tunnels I 
and II is suitable for accommodation of fatty acids. 
To investigate the selectivity of two tunnels for differ-
ent lengths of fatty acid substrates, we docked 4-, 6-, 8-, 
10-, 12-, 14-and 16-carbon fatty acid chains into the ac-
tive tunnel structure (Supplementary information, Table 
S3) [39]. As shown in Figure 4, short fatty acid chains 
(4-, 6-, 8-, 10-and 12-carbon chains) extend to tunnel I, 
whereas tunnel II is blocked by the sidechain of Phe83 
(closed conformation, pointing toward Ile98). In con-
trast, longer fatty acid chains (14-and 16-carbon chains) 
extend to tunnel II by switching the sidechain of Phe83 
toward Ile93 to form an open conformation [26]. Nota-
bly, the exit of tunnel II is a loop area between β3 and α4 
(residues Ala94-Lys97), which was reported to be disor-
dered in previously determined FabZ structures [27, 28], 
suggesting that this exit has flexibility and compatibility </p>

<p>1334 </p>

<p>Crystal structure of FabZ-ACP complex </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 26 No 12 | December 2016 </p>

<p>Lin Zhang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>for threading out long substrates. </p>

<p>Distinct isomerization behavior between FabA and FabZ 
The FabZ dimer shares high structural similarity with 
the FabA dimer. Nevertheless, unlike FabA, FabZ does 
not function as an isomerase [2]. Comparison of the 
structures of FabZ-ACP and FabA-ACP complexes, both 
docked with an 8-carbon trans-2 fatty acid chain, shows 
that the ACP 4′-Pan-arms adopt a similar conformation 
in the two structures, whereas the conformation of the 
fatty acid substrate appears to be significantly different 
(Supplementary information, Figure S6). The carbon 
chain displays a nearly U-shape conformation in FabZ 
tunnel I compared with the L-shape in FabA because the 
tunnel leading to a U-shape in FabA is blocked by Val90 
and Val162. Interestingly, the fatty acid chain adopts a 
cis conformation in FabA, whereas it remains the trans 
configuration in FabZ, which is consistent with a hypoth-
esis proposed by Kimber et al. [27] that the L-shape tun-
nel has much less steric hindrance for the carbonyl chain 
isomerization compared with the U-shape. </p>

<p>The dynamic seesaw-like catalytic mechanism of FabZ 
Unlike two ACPs covalently binding to the FabA di-
mer, only one ACP binds to the FabZ dimer subunit. The 
superposition of holo-ACP from the FabZ-ACP complex 
with native apo-and holo-ACP structures displays high 
structural similarity except for the 4′-Pan-arm orientation 
(Supplementary information, Figure S7), suggesting that 
the conformation of ACP itself does not interfere with the 
stoichiometric binding. In contrast, significant conforma-
tional changes in both FabZ monomers were observed. 
In FabZ monomer B, the anti-parallel β-sheet layer 
moves ~2.8 Å toward β4 due to ACP binding and 4′-Pan-
arm insertion (Figure 3A). The narrow L-shaped active 
tunnel is, therefore, expanded to a Y-shape to accommo-
date a long fatty acid substrate. In addition, the phenol 
ring of Tyr100 sidechain points toward Lys62′ to allow </p>

<p>the 4′-Pan-arm inserting into the catalytic tunnel (Figure 
3C). Surprisingly, FabZ monomer A also has similar con-
formational changes upon ACP binding to monomer B. 
The β-sheet layer in monomer A moves 1.0-1.7 Å farther 
toward β4 compared with that in monomer B and the 
specific loop between β4 and β5 is extruded by a distance 
of ~4.8 Å (Figure 3B). The extruded loop introduces 
clashes into most of interactions between the β-sheet lay-
er of FabZ and ACP α2 helix, especially the hydrophobic 
contacts between FabZ Lys129′ and Glu47/Glu53 from 
ACP, as well as FabZ Ile132′ and Val40/Met44 from 
ACP (Supplementary information, Figure S8), forming a 
conformation unfavorable for ACP binding. To support 
such conformational movements, the Tyr100′ sidechain 
adopts an abnormal closed conformation by further rotat-
ing ~30° clockwise along the C α -C bond from the regular 
closed conformation (in the native FabZ hexamer struc-
ture [26]) and pointing toward the backbone carbonyl 
oxygen of Phe109 to generate additional H-bond (Figure 
3D). These structural observations strongly argue that 
FabZ regulates ACP binding and releasing through alter-
nating movements of the β-sheet layer. 
Indeed, these β-sheet layer movements have been 
observed in our previous study of the native FabZ struc-
ture, in which three monomers (defined as monomers 
A-C) adopt a close conformation, while the other three 
(monomers D-E) adopt an open conformation [26]. 
These movements directly correlated with the sidechain 
position of the gatekeeper residue Tyr100. Tyr100 is lo-
cated on the β3 strand next to the active tunnel entrance 
and adopts two distinct conformations in the native 
FabZ hexamer structure either by pointing the phenol 
ring toward Lys62′ to form an open conformation (the 
tunnel entrance is opened to substrate; e.g., monomer 
E) or rotating the phenol ring along the C α -C β bond for 
~120° to interact with Pro112′ to form a closed confor-
mation (the tunnel entrance is blocked by the sidechain 
of Tyr100; e.g., monomer A) (Figure 3E). In the native </p>

<p>Figure 3 Superposition of FabZ monomer subunits. In the structure of a FabZ-ACP dimer subunit, only one monomer is as-
sociated with ACP, termed monomer B; the other is termed monomer A. In the structure of the ACP-unbound FabZ hexamer 
(PDB code: 2GLL), three monomers adopt open conformation (monomers D, E and F), and the other three adopt close con-
formation (monomers A, B and C). (A) Superposition of FabZ monomer B (cyan) from FabZ-ACP complex with monomer E 
(yellow) from native FabZ hexamer structure (PDB code: 2GLL). The β-sheet layers from monomer B and E are colored in 
blue and orange, respectively. holo-ACP is colored in magenta, and the 4′-Pan-arm is shown in sticks. (B) Superposition of 
FabZ monomers A (green) and B (cyan) from the FabZ-ACP complex. The β-sheet layers from monomers A and B are col-
ored in forest green and blue, respectively. (C-F) Superposition of FabZ β-sheet layers. Residues around the entrance are 
shown and labeled. (C) Superposition of monomer A (green) with monomer B (cyan) from FabZ-ACP complex. (D) Superpo-
sition of monomer A (yellow) from the native FabZ hexamer (PDB code: 2GLL) with monomer A (green) from the FabZ-ACP 
complex. (E) Superposition of monomer A (yellow) with monomer E (wheat), both from native FabZ hexamer structure. Atoms 
of Tyr100 and Pro112′ involved in the interactions are presented as transparent spheres. (F) Superposition of monomer E 
(wheat) from the native FabZ hexamer with monomer A (blue) from FabZ (Y100A) mutant hexamer (PDB code: 2GLV). </p>



<p>Crystal structure of FabZ-ACP complex </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 26 No 12 | December 2016 </p>

<p>FabZ hexamer structure, the hydrophobic interaction 
between the Tyr100 sidechain and Pro112′ in the closed 
conformation pushes the β-sheet layer further toward β4 
compared with the open conformation (Figure 3E). In the 
FabZ-ACP complex structure, the abnormal conforma-
tion of Tyr100′ sidechain further pushes the β-sheet layer 
toward β4 (Figure 3D), likely causing ACP releasing. 
Previous studies suggested that the gatekeeper residue 
commonly exists in the DH across species in the FAS </p>

<p>Figure 4 Side view of FabZ active tunnel B surface with fatty acids of different lengths modeled to ACP. The electrostatic 
surface and ribbons were generated by Pymol. The color range from red (negative) to blue (positive) represents the surface 
electrostatic potentials of −75 e/kT to +75 e/kT. ACP is colored in magenta. Fatty acid chains with 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14 and 16 
carbons are colored in hot pink, purple blue, yellow, salmon, gray, slate and orange, respectively. Secondary structural ele-
ments, tunnels I and II are labeled. (A) Side view of FabZ active tunnel B surface with fatty acids of different lengths modeled 
to ACP. Catalytic residues His58′ and Glu72, and residue Gly79 in the Y-shaped tunnel fork are shown as sticks. (B) Side 
view of FabZ active tunnel surface with short fatty acid chains (4-12 carbons). Short fatty acid chains and residues involved 
in the interactions are shown as sticks, and long chains with 14 and 16 carbons are shown as lines. The closed conformation 
of backdoor residue Phe83 (pointing toward Ile98) shown here is replaced by the corresponding residue from native HpFabZ 
structure (PDB code: 2GLL). It blocks long fatty chain (shown as a line) stretching to tunnel II. (C) Side view of FabZ active 
tunnel surface with long fatty acid chains (14 and 16 carbons). Long fatty acid chains and residues involved in the interactions 
are shown as sticks, and short chains are shown as lines. Phe83 adopts an open conformation (pointing to Ile93) and allows 
long fatty chains (shown as sticks) to stretch into tunnel II. </p>

<p>system for protecting the hydrophobic catalytic tunnel 
from bulk solvent [2, 27, 28]. Multiple sequence align-
ments of FabZ among 72 bacterial species indicate that 
tyrosine is the predominant gatekeeper (61%), whereas 
some other residues with hydrophobic sidechains, such 
as phenylalanine (22%) and leucine (17%), are also ob-
served (Supplementary information, Figure S3C). Our 
studies suggest that the absence of the Tyr100 sidechain 
in FabZ Y100A mutant completely abolishes the move-</p>

<p>Lin Zhang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>ments of the β-sheet layer within the FabZ hexamer 
(Figure 3F) and significantly reduces FabZ enzymatic ac-
tivity to ~10% by interfering with the release of ACP [26]. 
Together with structural observations, these results indi-
cate that the hydrophobic sidechain of such a gatekeeper 
is indispensable for the maintenance of FabZ enzymatic 
activity not only for simply protecting the hydrophobic 
catalytic tunnel from bulk solvent but also for regulating 
ACP binding and releasing by rotating its sidechain to 
manipulate the movements of the β-sheet layer in an al-
ternating manner like a seesaw. </p>

<p>Biophysical studies of FabZ-ACP binding 
The structural packing analysis indicates that the 
N-terminus of holo-ACP from the crystallographic 
neighbor FabZ-ACP molecule has contacts with the 
ACP-unbound FabZ monomer A to form a potential 
large tetramer complex with a stoichiometry of (FabZ 
hexamer-ACP 3 ) 4 or an even larger aggregated mass 
due to the linkage effect (Supplementary information, 
Figure S9). To investigate whether the crystal packing 
force from the neighbor ACP molecule contributes to 
the conformational changes in monomer A observed in 
our crystal structure, we carefully examined the contacts 
between monomer A and the neighbor ACP. The contacts 
are contributed by hydrophobic interactions between the 
sidechains of Met102′ and Met154′ from FabZ mono-
mer A and the backbones of a cloning-generated extra 
residue Gly(-2) at the N-terminus of ACP, as well as 
the sidechain of Arg110 from FabZ monomer B and the 
sidechain of another cloning-generated extra residue 
Tyr(-1) of ACP (Supplementary information, Figure 
S9A and S9B). Among the interactions, Tyr100′ from 
FabZ monomer A interacts weakly through its hydroxyl 
group to the backbone N atom of ACP Ser(-4) residue 
(~4.0 Å distance). As Ser(-4) is the very first residue at 
the N-terminus of ACP, the interaction between Ser(-
4) and Tyr100 is even weaker than normal hydrophobic 
interaction due to the high flexibility of the residue. The 
superposition of FabZ monomers A and B suggests that 
the sidechains of Met102 and Met154 are slightly bend-
ed, and the sidechain of Arg110 is extended due to the 
packing forces (Supplementary information, Figure S9C 
and S9D). Obviously, the packing forces tend to push 
the sidechain of Tyr100′ from monomer A anticlockwise, 
forming an open conformation rather than the current 
"super-close" conformation, and push the β-sheet layer to 
move backward rather than toward β4. Hence, the crystal 
packing has little influence on the observed conforma-
tional changes in monomer A in the complex structure. 
As these interactions, potentially induced by crystal-
lographic packing, occur close to the entrance of FabZ </p>

<p>tunnel A, steric hindrance of the neighbor holo-ACP 
may block the FabZ tunnel entrance, thus preventing the 
binding of a second holo-ACP in solution (Supplemen-
tary information, Figure S2). To eliminate this concern, 
the oligomeric state of the FabZ-ACP complex in solu-
tion was evaluated by size-exclusion chromatography 
coupled with multi-angle light scattering (SEC-MALS). 
Compared with native FabZ, the molecular weight of the 
complex is almost exactly that of a FabZ hexamer plus 
three holo-ACPs (Figure 5A and 5B). The stoichiometry 
was further confirmed by synchrotron-based small-angle 
X-ray scattering (SAXS) (Figure 5C-5E). The low-reso-
lution particle model reconstructed from the SAXS ex-
perimental profiles fits well with the respective complex 
structure (χ 
2 = 0.922), which suggests that the FabZ-ACP 
complex adopts the same stoichiometry in solution as 
observed in the crystal structure. Subsequently, a titra-
tion-based microscale thermophoresis assay (MST) was 
employed to identify the binding affinities of holo-ACP 
to FabZ (Figure 5F and 5G) [40]. On the basis of the 
stoichiometry, the binding curve appears in triphasic 
phases with binding affinities of 0.354 ± 0.056, 16.2 ± 
1.5 and 297 ± 22.1 µM (Figure 5F). The distinct binding 
affinities also indicate that the binding of ACP to FabZ 
hexamer involves a complicated allosteric crosstalk, not 
only between monomers within a FabZ dimer subunit 
observed from the structure, but also between dimers 
within the FabZ hexamer. It is likely that the binding of 
each ACP induces significant conformational changes 
of ACP-unbound and -bound FabZ dimer subunits, thus 
influencing the subsequent ACP binding (lower binding 
affinities). Such conformational changes are most like-
ly regulated by the gatekeeper residue Tyr100, as ACP 
binding as well as FabZ enzymatic activity are abolished 
by FabZ Y100A mutagenesis (Figure 5G) [40]. Although 
the allosteric crosstalk between FabZ dimer subunits in-
duced by successive ACP binding could not be observed 
from the current structure as the crystal was obtained 
under the condition of saturated ACP binding of FabZ 
hexamer (ACP:FabZ = 7:1 before gel-filtration purifica-
tion), the solution-based biophysical results uncovered 
the existence of such allosteric crosstalk. Nevertheless, 
the current structure shows monomer-monomer allosteric 
crosstalk upon the asymmetric binding of ACP on FabZ 
dimer subunit, and reveals the dynamic seesaw-like cat-
alytic mechanism of DH FabZ in the FAS system for the 
first time, which is regulated by the critical gatekeeper 
residue Tyr100. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>To date, there is little structural information for the </p>



<p>Crystal structure of FabZ-ACP complex </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 26 No 12 | December 2016 </p>

<p>Lin Zhang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>interaction of ACP with enzymatic modules in the FAS 
system, except for an incomplete FabI-ACP structure 
and the covalently crosslinked FabA-ACP structure [25,  29]. Our study presents the first native high-resolution 
enzymatic module-ACP complex structure of a FAS sys-
tem. The complex exhibits a highly symmetrical FabZ 
hexamer-ACP 3 stoichiometry with each ACP binding to a 
FabZ dimer subunit. Further structural analysis suggests 
that FabZ contacts ACP through H-bonds between a con-
stellation of conserved Arg/Lys residues near its active 
tunnel entrance and negatively charged residues along 
an ACP α2 helix as well as hydrophobic interactions 
between residues located in the hydrophobic patch near 
the tunnel entrance of FabZ and residues in the ACP α2 
helix. Remarkably, the conserved Arg110 of FabZ con-
tributes to the FabZ-ACP interactions, suggesting an im-
portant role in recognizing and binding of ACP to FabZ. 
The binding of ACP to FabZ also induces the movements 
of the β-sheet layer, which enlarges the narrow L-shaped 
active tunnel to a Y-shape for long fatty acid substrate 
accommodation. This Y-shaped tunnel has significantly 
more steric hindrance in reversion of trans-2-acyl-ACP to 
cis-3-acyl-ACP during isomerization compared with the 
L-shaped tunnel of FabA, which explains the absence of 
isomerase activity in FabZ. More importantly, the move-
ments of the β-sheet layer not only occur on ACP-bound 
FabZ monomers but also on ACP-unbound monomers 
with even larger conformational changes, forming an un-
favorable conformation for ACP binding by introducing 
clashes between FabZ and ACP. Additional biophysical </p>

<p>methods, including SEC-MALS, SAXS and MST, con-
firmed these observations, and the corresponding binding 
affinities of ACP toward FabZ were determined. These 
findings suggest a novel dynamic seesaw-like continuous 
catalytic mechanism of DH FabZ with ACP in the FAS-II 
system, in which ACP's alternate binding is regulated by 
a FabZ gatekeeper residue Tyr100 through manipulating 
the movements of FabZ's β-sheet layer (Figure 6, and 
Supplementary information, Movie). Furthermore, the 
MST titration result suggests that the binding of ACP to 
FabZ involves a series of complicated allosteric crosstalk 
both between monomer subunits and between dimer sub-
units. The current crystal structure successfully shows 
the monomer-monomer crosstalk due to the asymmetric 
binding of ACP on FabZ dimer subunit. The current 
study mainly focuses on the structural changes within a 
single FabZ dimer subunit as well as the corresponding 
seesaw-like allosteric crosstalk mechanism on regulating 
ACP binding; and thus the current structural information 
is not adequate to explain entire allosteric changes be-
tween dimer subunits. 
The superposition of FabZ-ACP structure, FabA-ACP 
structure (PDB code: 4KEH) and the mammalian DH 
module from S. scrofa FASN (PDB code: 2vz8) exhibits 
high overall structural similarity, indicating that these 
DH (module) may employ a conserved mechanism to 
regulate ACP catalysis (Supplementary information, 
Figure S6A-S6C and S10). The major difference among 
the structures is the numbers of ACP bound to the DH 
(module). In FabA-ACP structure case, two ACP mole-</p>

<p>Figure 5 Biophysical studies of FabZ-ACP complex in solution. (A) Size-exclusion chromatography (SEC) coupled with 
multi-angle light scattering (MALS) analysis. FabZ protein (black curve) or holo-ACP (blue curve) was separated using a 
Wyatt Technology WTC-030S5 column. The running buffer contains 20 mM HEPES (pH 8.0), 500 mM NaCl and 10 mM DTT. 
500 mM NaCl, instead of 150 mM NaCl was used due to the instability of FabZ protein in a low-salt buffer. Corresponding 
average molecular weight of the fraction peaks marked with stars was evaluated and analyzed using Wyatt Technology SEC-
MALS system. The chromatogram shows the readings of UV detector, and 280 nm absorption scaling is shown in Y axis 
on the left. The yellow and green curves indicate the calculated molecular masses of FabZ and holo-ACP throughout the 
peaks. The molecular mass scaling is shown in the Y axis on the right. (B) SEC-MALS analysis of FabZ-ACP complex. The 
FabZ-ACP complex saturated with excess amounts of holo-ACP (red curve) was separated using a Wyatt Technology WTC-
030S5 column. The running buffer for separating the complex contains 20 mM HEPES (pH 8.0), 150 mM NaCl and 10 mM 
DTT. The magenta curves indicate the calculated molecular masses of FabZ-ACP complex and holo-ACP throughout the 
peaks. (C) SAXS scattering data from FabZ-ACP complex in solution. Curve-1 (black dots): SAXS scattering experimental 
data. Curve-2 (red line): scattering pattern calculated from the crystal structure. Curve-3 (green line): smooth curve back 
transformed from the p(r) and extrapolated to a zero scattering angle for the complex in solution. (D) SAXS data analysis: 
distance distribution functions for the complex. (E) SAXS modeling: low-resolution envelope for the complex was shown as a 
particle model and was superposed with the complex crystal structure. (F) Microscale thermophoresis (MST) measurements 
of holo-ACP binding to wild-type FabZ. Data points colored in black, red and blue indicate the differences in normalized fluo-
rescence generated by various concentrations of holo-ACP binding to FabZ. Curves colored in black, red and green indicate 
the calculated fits according to the data points, and the corresponding Kd values are shown. (G) MST measurements of ho-
lo-ACP binding to FabZ (Y100A) mutant. Data points in black indicate the difference in normalized fluorescence generated by 
various concentrations of holo-ACP binding to FabZ (Y100A). Curves colored in black indicate the calculated fits according to 
the data points. </p>



<p>Crystal structure of FabZ-ACP complex </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 26 No 12 | December 2016 </p>

<p>Figure 6 Schematic diagram of the dynamic seesaw-like continuous catalytic mechanism model of FabZ during fatty acid bio-
synthesis. Monomers A and B within a FabZ dimer subunit and two ACP molecules are colored in green, light blue, wheat and 
purple, respectively. Four critical β-strands from the β-sheet layer are shown as oval rafts. Key gatekeeper residues Tyr100 
and Phe83 from FabZ monomer B (cyan) and monomer A (green) are shown as sticks. The 4′-phosphopantetheine arm (ma-
genta) attached with a long fatty acid chain (orange) from ACP are shown as lines. In the native conformation of FabZ, the 
sidechains of Tyr100 and Phe83 adopt close conformation to protect the hydrophobic catalytic tunnel from bulk solvent (step 
1). When the first ACP molecule (wheat) binds to FabZ monomer B, the L-shaped active tunnel is expanded to a Y-shape due 
to movement of the β-sheet layer toward 4. The sidechains of Tyr100 and Phe83 flop ~120° to an open conformation, which 
allows the substrate chain carried by the 4′-Pan-arm to insert into the active tunnel for catalytic dehydration. Meanwhile, the 
β-sheet layer in the ACP-unbound FabZ monomer A moves further toward β4 due to a ~30° rotation of the Tyr100 sidechain 
from its normal closed conformation to form an abnormal conformation unfavorable for ACP binding (purple) (steps 2 and 3). 
When the dehydration reaction is finished on monomer B, the β-sheet layer moves further toward β4 to release ACP, whereas 
the β-sheet layer on monomer A moves back with a ~150° rotation of the Tyr100 sidechain to a normal open conformation 
to accept binding and catalysis of the second ACP (steps 4 and 5). By doing so, the catalysis core is exchanged from FabZ 
monomer B to monomer A. When the second dehydration reaction is finished, the catalysis core is exchanged to B again 
like a see-saw due to the movements of the β-sheet layer (steps 4-6), which causes the high-efficiency catalytic dehydration 
mechanism of FabZ in the FAS system. </p>

<p>cules bind to a FabA dimer, whereas in our structure, one 
ACP molecule binds to a FabZ dimer subunit. This could 
be caused by the covalent crosslinking of ACP to FabA. 
In the DH domain case, it is a pseudo-dimer with distinct 
differences between the two subdomains, and can only </p>

<p>catalyze one ACP at a time rather than two. However, 
the DH domain shares a highly structurally conserved 
β-sheet layer with FabZ, where ACP molecule binds to, 
suggesting that the DH domain is very likely to utilize 
similar mechanism to regulate ACP by manipulating the </p>

<p>Lin Zhang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>

<p>conformational changes of the β-sheet layer. Hence, our 
finding also contributes to the understanding of mamma-
lian FAS catalytic mechanism, and provides a potential 
drug discovery strategy against human diseases associat-
ed with FAS by inhibiting its enzymatic activity through 
interfering ACP-enzymatic module interactions. Collec-
tively, our results illustrate a novel and dynamic ACP 
binding and regulation mechanism for the DH module in 
the FAS system, which provides a plausible explanation 
for previously established phenomenon and facilitates a 
general understanding of the biological functions of the 
FAS system. 
Increasing evidence suggests that overproduction of 
fatty acids by the FAS system is correlated with MetS 
and various cancers [12-17, 41]. Inhibition of FAS activ-
ity significantly induces tumor cell apoptosis, suppresses 
tumor cell metastasis and improves insulin sensitivity [33,  42, 43]. Hence, hFASN is considered to be a promising 
anti-MetS and anti-tumor drug target for clinical therapy, 
and several specific inhibitors for interfering with the en-
zymatic activity of hFASN have been developed [3, 41- 46]. Unfortunately, most of these compounds have lim-
ited applications in clinical scenarios due to severe side 
effects or modest potency [23, 33]. The dynamic ACP 
binding and regulation mechanism of the DH module in 
the FAS system provides a potential novel drug design 
strategy for interfering with ACP-enzymatic module in-
teractions rather than the enzymatic activities in the FAS 
system, which may significantly reduce side effects. Our 
findings may benefit clinical drug and therapy devel-
opment against pathogenic infection, as well as human 
diseases associated with the deregulation of this pathway, 
including obesity, diabetes, and prostate and breast can-
cers. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Protein subcloning, expression and purification </p>

<p>Expressions and purifications of apo-ACP, holo-ACP, FabZ 
and FabZ (Y100A) from H. pylori were expressed and purified as 
described previously [36, 37]. Briefly, FabZ gene was subcloned 
to PQE30 plasmid and expressed in Escherichia coli strain M15 
cells. QuikChange Site-Directed Mutagenesis (Stratagene) strat-
egy was used to perform the FabZ (Y100A) mutagenesis. FabZ 
and FabZ (Y100A) protein were purified by using Ni-NTA and 
Gel-filtration column. ACP gene was subcloned to pET32a vector 
and expressed in E. coli BL21 cells. The protein was purified by 
using Ni-NTA, and the N-terminal thioredoxin-His tag was re-
moved by recombinant enterokinase protease cleavage at 4 °C for 
overnight. Subsequently, ACP protein was further purified by GE 
HiLoad 16/600 Superdex 75 prep grade gel-filtration column. The 
final concentration was quantified by Bradford reagent purchased 
from Bio-Rad. For the FabZ-holo-ACP complex, the purified FabZ 
and holo-ACP protein were mixed in molar ratio 1:7, and dialyzed </p>

<p>against 20 mM HEPES, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl and 10 mM DTT. 
The mixture was concentrated and loaded to HiLoad 16/600 Su-
perdex 200 prep grade column for further purification. The com-
plex peak was pooled and concentrated to10 mg/ml. </p>

<p>Apo-ACP, holo-ACP and FabZ-ACP complex crystallization </p>

<p>Approximately 10 mg/ml apo-ACP, holo-ACP and complex 
protein were mixed with an equal volume of reservoir solution 
containing 1.0-3.0 M sodium chloride and 0.1 M sodium acetate, 
and 1.0-3.0 M lithium sulfate and 0.5 M ammonium sulfate, and 
10%-30% PEG3350, 0.05 M tri-sodium citrate dehydrate, respec-
tively, and equilibrated against 500 µl of the reservoir solution at 
277 K. Crystals appeared within 30 days. The crystals were then 
flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen with 20%-30% glycerol (v/v) as the 
cryoprotectant solution. </p>

<p>Data collection and structure determination </p>

<p>Crystal diffraction data of apo-ACP and FabZ-ACP complex 
were collected at beamline BL19U1 at the National Center for 
Protein Sciences Shanghai and Shanghai Synchrotron Radiation 
Facility, China. Significant decay of the complex crystals during 
data collection caused the resolution cut off at 2.55 Å. While the 
crystal diffraction data of holo-ACP were collected at 100 K using 
CuKα X-ray with a Rigaku R-AXIS IV++ image plate. The data 
were further processed using <rs type="software">HKL2000</rs> software package [47] and 
<rs type="software">CrystalClear</rs> software. The structures were solved by MR with the 
published structure of apo-EcACP (PDB code: 1T8K) and Hp-
FabZ (PDB code: 2GLL) as search models, and refined by using 
programs <rs type="software">Phenix</rs> [48] (complex) and <rs type="software">CNS</rs> (apo and holo-ACP). 
The crystallographic statistics are summarized in Supplementary 
information, Table S1. Electron density interpretation and model 
building were performed using the computer graphics program 
<rs type="software">Coot</rs> [49]. Final structures were visualized by PyMol software. </p>

<p>Covalent docking </p>

<p><rs id="software-16" type="software">SYBYL</rs> package (<rs corresp="#software-16" type="url">www.tripos.com</rs>) was used to prepare the 
fatty acid chains and the protein structures used in docking. Initial 
structures of fatty acid chains in different lengths (4-to 16-carbon 
chain) were sketched using the <rs type="software">SYBYL</rs> program with standard 
geometric parameters, and Gasteiger-Hucker charge was added. 
All fatty acids were then optimized using the standard TRIPOS 
force field with Gasteiger-Hückel charges until the energy gradient 
converged to below 0.05 kcal/mol. Waters in the crystal structure 
of FabZ were removed, and all hydrogens were added. Kollman 
all-atom charges were assigned for FabZ and Gasteiger-Hückel 
charge was computed for residue 36 with 4′-Pan-arm. 
Genetic algorithm-based docking program <rs type="software">GOLD</rs> was used 
for molecular docking simulations [50]. Fatty acid chain-binding 
site for docking was defined as a collection of all atoms within 25 
Å around the midpoint of the terminal S of the 4-Pan-arm and O 
atom of Lys97, so the active site would be big enough to include 
the possible binding sites of variable length fatty acid chains. The 
GOLDScore fitness function was employed in scoring conforma-
tions. The parameters for GOLD were as follows: numbers of GA 
ran 50, no early termination was allowed and all other parameters 
were used as default (Supplementary information, Table S3). </p>

<p>Size-exclusion chromatography coupled with multi-angle 
light scattering measurements </p>



<p>Crystal structure of FabZ-ACP complex </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 26 No 12 | December 2016 </p>

<p>Approximately 10 µl, 0.5 mg/ml purified FabZ-ACP complex 
saturated with excess amount of holo-ACP sample was injected 
into HPLC system (Agilent Technologies) and separated by using 
Wyatt Technology WTC-030S5 column with running buffer con-
taining 20 mM HEPES, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl and 10 mM DTT. 
The native FabZ or holo-ACP protein was separated with running 
buffer containing 20 mM HEPES, pH 8.0, 500 mM NaCl and 10 
mM DTT due to the instability of FabZ protein under low salt (150 
mM NaCl) buffer. Corresponding molecular weight of the fraction 
peaks was evaluated and analyzed by using Wyatt Technology 
SEC-MALS system, which was calibrated by using 2 mg/ml 
standard BSA sample. As shown in Figure 5A and 5B, FabZ-ACP 
MW calculated = 145 KDa, MW observed = 143 (± 2.0%) kDa; FabZ 
MW calculated = 117 kDa, MW observed = 112.7 (± 0.66%) kDa; holo-ACP 
MW calculated = 9382 Da, MW observed = 9331 (± 4.3%) Da. </p>

<p>Synchrotron solution small angle X-ray scattering measure-
ments </p>

<p>FabZ-ACP complex purified from gel-filtration in the solution 
containing 20 mM HEPES, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl and 10 mM 
DTT was used in the Synchrotron SAXS experiment. The mea-
surement was performed in a vacuum cuvette with exposure time 
of 1 s to diminish the parasitic scattering under wavelength 1.03 Å 
at National Center for Protein Sciences Shanghai (NCPSS) beam-
line BL19U2, China. The scattering was recorded in the range 
of the momentum transfer 0.015 &lt; s &lt; 0.420/Å, where s = (4π × 
sinθ)/λ and 2θ is the scattering angle. SAXS data were subsequent-
ly processed and analyzed by using the <rs type="software">ATSAS</rs> program suite 
[51]. Briefly, program <rs type="software">PRIMUS</rs> [52] was employed to process the 
experimental scattering data and correct the solvent background 
scattering. Program <rs type="software">CRYSOL</rs> was used to generate the theoretical 
scattering from the FabZ-ACP complex crystal structure [53]. Pro-
gram <rs type="software">GNOM</rs> was employed to calculate the distance distribution 
function p(r) (Figure 5C and 5D) [54]. Subsequently, programs 
<rs type="software">DAMMIN</rs> [55], <rs type="software">GASBOR</rs> [56] and <rs type="software">DAMAVER</rs> [57] were used 
to reconstruct the low-resolution shapes to a dummy atom particle 
model, and superpose to the crystal structure (Figure 5E). The 
figure was generated by using <rs corresp="#software-26" type="creator">GraphPad</rs> <rs id="software-26" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-26" type="version-number">5</rs> and <rs type="software">PyMol</rs> soft-
ware. </p>

<p>Microscale thermophoresis assays </p>

<p>MST assay is a new immobilization-free and titration-based 
technology for biomolecule interaction determination [58]. The 
assay was performed with a NanoTemper Monolith NT.115 instru-
ment (NanoTemper Technologies GmbH). Briefly, FabZ or FabZ 
(Y100A) was labeled with fluorescence dye NT-647 (amine-re-
action) according to manufacturer's protocol. Subsequently, 50 
nM of labeled protein was mixed with various concentrations of 
holo-ACP in the reaction buffer containing 20 mM HEPES, pH 8.0, 
150 mM NaCl, 5 mM fresh DTT and 0.05% Tween 20. After in-
cubation for 5 min under room temperature, 10 µl of the mixtures 
were loaded into premium coated capillaries for measurement. The 
MST data were then collected under 40% infrared laser power and 
20% light-emitting diode power. Nanotemper analysis software 
(1.5.41) was used to fit the independent experimental data and de-
termine Kd and standard deviation value. The figure was generated 
by using <rs corresp="#software-29" type="creator">GraphPad</rs> <rs id="software-29" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-29" type="version-number">5</rs>. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This project was supported by the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (21572133 to LZ, 21210003 to HJ and 
91413102 to XS), the Program for Professors of Special Appoint-
ment (Eastern Scholar) at the Shanghai Institutions of Higher 
Learning (to LZ), the National Great Basic Science Project of 
China (2010CB529806 to HC), the Ministry of Science and Tech-
nology of China (2015CB910304 to HJ). We thank the staff of 
beamlines BL19U1 and BL19U2 at the National Center for Protein 
Sciences Shanghai (NCPSS) and Shanghai Synchrotron Radiation 
Facility (SSRF, China) for assistance with crystal diffraction and 
SAXS data collection. We thank professors Jianping Ding and Ji-
amu Du from Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, Chinese 
Academy of Sciences for data analysis and discussion. We thank 
Mr Jing Lan from WYATT Technology for SEC-MALS technical 
support, Mr Fenfei Wang from Quantum Design China &amp; Nano-
Temper Technologies GmbH for MST technical support, and Dr 
José Ramón Andrade Candelario for production of the animation 
(http://www.3dciencia.com/). </p>

<p>Author Contributions </p>

<p>HJ and LZ designed the experiments; LZ, TRF and ZWC 
performed protein purification; LZ and LZ performed the crystal-
lization as well as SEC-MALS, SAXS and the MST biophysical 
experiments; JFX and JRX performed the computational analysis; 
HJ, LZ, LZ and JFX wrote the paper. All authors discussed and 
commented on the manuscript. </p>

<p>Competing Financial Interests 
The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>



<p>Lin Zhang et al. </p>

<p>
www.cell-research.com | Cell Research | SPRINGER NATURE </p>





<p>Crystal structure of FabZ-ACP complex </p>

<p>SPRINGER NATURE | Cell Research | Vol 26 No 12 | December 2016 </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 Unported 
License. The images or other third party material in this article are 
included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated 
otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the 
Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from 
the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>© The Author(s) 2016 </p>

</text></tei>