<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5042035" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Evaluation of the radio-transmission pH-measurement system for monitoring the ruminal pH and subacute ruminal acidosis 
(SARA) in cattle is described. This is done in order to reveal the possible application of this system for detection and pathophys-
iological research of SARA by continuous ruminal pH measurement. The possibility of using this system for assessment of the 
ruminal pH in SARA cattle, and the presence of negative correlation between the ruminal pH and ruminal temperature in heathy 
and SARA cattle were determined. In addition, the 16S rRNA gene pyrosequencing analysis showed that the ruminal microbial 
community was simpler in SARA cattle, and the bacterial numbers in SARA cattle were lower than those in healthy hay-fed 
cattle. Concentrate feeding might have reduced the diversity of the ruminal microbial community. Changes in the ruminal 
microbial community of SARA cattle might be related to the changes in ruminal pH followed by the decrease in the number 
of some bacteria. Continuous monitoring of the ruminal pH using the radio-transmission pH-measurement system would be 
applied for detection and prevention of SARA in the field and pathophysiological research of SARA, including ruminal zymology 
and bacteriology, which have been determined previously by sampling of the ruminal fluid and measuring of ruminal pH. </p>

<p>Cows with subacute ruminal acidosis (SARA) often 
develop complications of laminitis, reduced and erratic 
feed intake, low body condition score, low milk fat 
syndrome, abomasal displacement, ulceration and 
ruminitis (Enemark 2008; Plaizier et al. 2009). Further-
more, SARA is associated with immunosuppression 
(Kleen et al. 2003) and inflammation (Khafipour et al. 
2009a,2009b; Plaizier et al. 2009). Free lipopolysaccha-
ride (LPS) increases in the rumen during SARA (Gozho 
et al. 2007; Emmanuel et al. 2008), and the LPS translo-
cates from the rumen into blood circulation, which 
activates an inflammatory response (Khafipour et al. 
2009a,2009b) affecting peripheral leukocyte populations 
and production of pro-inflammatory cytokines. There-
fore, monitoring ruminal pH and prevention of acidic 
pH are very important challenges in the dairy industry. 
SARA is characterized by repeated bouts of low rumi-
nal pH (Enemark et al. 2004; Enemark 2008; Plaizier 
et al. 2009), but accurate measurement of the ruminal 
pH is very difficult. In order to obtain the ruminal fluid 
for pH measurement, oro-ruminal probe and rumeno-
centesis are used (Duffield et al. 2004; Bramley et al. 
2008). Recently, an indwelling ruminal pH system was </p>

<p>developed and placed in the rumen of fistulated cattle 
(Marden et al. 2005; AlZahal et al. 2007; Penner et al. 
2006, 2009). Although an indwelling ruminal pH system 
has made continuous recording of ruminal pH possible 
(Keunen et al. 2002; Nocek et al. 2002a,2002b; Rustome 
et al. 2006), this system can be used only for experimen-
tally fistulated cows. Therefore, this system does not 
allow the field application of SARA evaluation. Based 
on these backgrounds, we recently have invented a 
new radio-transmission pH-measurement system, and 
assessed its performance and usefulness in a continuous 
evaluation of ruminal pH (Sato et al. 2012a, b). 
In the cows exposed to SARA challenge, the ruminal 
pH remained very low during the first day of SARA 
challenge, but mid-lactating cows fed a 60% forage diet 
recovered to the normal pH more quickly than early lac-
tating cows fed a 45% forage diet (Dohme et al. 2008). 
Decrease in ruminal pH on the day of SARA challenge 
was getting severer with each successive challenge. </p>

<p>Correspondence: Shigeru Sato, Cooperative Department of 
Veterinary Medicine, Faculty of Agriculture, Iwate University, 
Morioka, Iwate 020-8550, Japan. (Email: sshigeru@iwate-u.ac.jp) 
Received 28 December 2014; accepted for publication 
27 February 2015. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. Animal Science Journal published by 
Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Animal Science. </p>

<p>doi:10.1111/asj.12415 
Animal Science Journal (2016) 87, 168-177 </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which 
permits use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no 
modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>bs_bs_banner </p>

<p>Authors speculated that the increased severity of SARA 
with repeated challenges might be due to short recovery 
time provided to the experimental cows between 
challenge periods. However, changes in the ruminal 
pH and volatile fatty acid (VFA) of cattle with repeated 
acidosis challenges are not adequately known. Further-
more, several studies have been conducted on the 
rumen microbial community in cows with SARA (Chen 
et al. 2012; Hernandez-Sanabria et al. 2012; Mao et al. 
2013; Golder et al. 2014). The most common bacteria 
detected in the rumen of cattle with SARA are Lactobacil-
lus spp. and Streptococcus bovis (Nagaraja &amp; Titgemeyer 
2007). The dominant bacterial phyla include Firmicutes, 
Bacteroidetes and all subgroups of Proteobacteria. Recently, 
pyrosequencing has been used for assessment of micro-
bial composition in the rumen of cattle (Jami &amp; Mizrahi 
2012; Rice et al. 2012). These studies supported the 
notion that pyrosequencing facilitated greater under-
standing of microbial diversity. Most of the studies about 
microbial communities in SARA cattle are based on 
single induction of SARA. The microbial community in 
cattle with repeated induction of SARA is unknown. 
In this review, our radio-transmission pH-mea-
surement system for continuous monitoring of ruminal 
pH and SARA in cattle is reported, to reveal the possible 
application of this system for detection and patho-
physiological research of SARA. In addition, our recent 
research about the changes in the ruminal pH, VFA 
and microbial communities in cattle associated with 
repeatedly induced SARA, as well as the effects of 
Propionibacterium-based probiotics on the ruminal pH 
and VFA in cattle are presented. The experimental 
designs described in this review were approved by the 
Iwate University Laboratory Animal Care and Use 
committee. </p>

<p>CONTINUOUS MONITORING OF 
RUMINAL PH BY A RADIO 
TRANSMISSION MEASUREMENT 
SYSTEM </p>

<p>The radio-transmission pH-measurement system con-
sists of a wireless pH sensor, a data measurement 
receiver, a relay unit and a personal computer with spe-
cial software (<rs type="software">YCOW-S</rs>; DKK-Toa Yamagata) (Sato et al. 
2012b) installed. The wireless system utilized a specified 
low-power radio transmission system (429 MHz band), 
which could be operated without a license in accordance 
with Japanese Radio Law. The mean variations of the 
measurements by the glass pH electrode were + 0.20 
after 2 months of continuous recording, compared to 
the values confirmed by a standard pH solution at the 
start of the recording. The mean lifetime of the internal 
battery was 3 months when measurements were 
continuously transmitted every 10 min. There was a 
good correlation between continuous recording and spot 
sampling (r = 0.986, P &lt; 0.01), when the ruminal pH </p>

<p>recorded by our new system was compared to that of 
the spot sampling of ruminal fluid (Sato et al. 2012b). 
We have demonstrated the possible application of the 
radio-transmission pH-measurement system for assess-
ment and monitoring of the ruminal pH in cows. Our 
new system might contribute to accurate assessment 
and prevention of SARA. In this chapter, our experi-
mental results of basic tests for performance of radio-
transmission pH-measurement system are described. </p>

<p>CHANGES IN RUMINAL PH IN CATTLE 
FED DIFFERENT DIETS </p>

<p>The ruminal pH was measured continuously by the 
radio-transmission pH-measurement system in cattle, 
which were fed three kinds of diets, 1 week for each. 
Four rumen-cannulated Holstein steers, aged 7 months, 
were used. Cattle were fed orchard grass mixed hay and 
concentrate (50% flaked barley and 50% corn). The 
ratios of roughage and concentrate were 10:0 (A-diet), 
2:8 (B-diet) and 5:5 (C-diet), respectively. The pH sensor 
was placed in the ventral sac of the rumen through 
rumen-fistula, and pH was measured at 10-min intervals 
for 4 weeks. 
The ruminal pH decreased markedly and rapidly 
when feeding changed from A-to B-diet, but it returned 
to the basal level when feeding changed from B-to 
C-diet (Fig. 1). Thereafter, another pattern of the rumi-
nal pH changes was observed when B-diet was fed the 
second time showing moderate decrease in pH com-
pared to that of the first B-diet feeding. Within 1 week 
of B-diet feeding, the decreased ruminal pH recovered 
slightly. In addition, the changes in the ruminal pH after 
feeding the same diet varied among individual cows. 
These results indicated that the SARA could be 
induced successfully by feeding the B-diet. Changes of 
the pH values after the morning feeding in this study 
were similar to previous studies (Krause &amp; Oetzel 
2005; Keunen et al. 2002). These results demonstrated 
the possible use of the radio-transmission pH-
measurement system for the assessment and monitoring 
of ruminal pH of cows in field conditions. It is suggested 
that the ruminal pH could be recoverable after rapid 
feeding changes by adaptation of ruminal fermentation. </p>

<p>RELATIONS BETWEEN PH AND 
TEMPERATURE, VFA IN RUMINAL FLUID </p>

<p>Ruminal temperature rises during the early phase of 
disease, estrus and onset of calving (Cooper-Prado et al. 
2011; Rose-Dye et al. 2011). In addition, the ruminal 
temperature exceeds rectal temperature presumably 
due to accelerated microbial fermentation (AlZahal 
et al. 2008, 2009). Ruminal temperature is negatively 
correlated with the ruminal pH in cows with SARA, 
and a predictive equation for aiding the diagnosis of 
SARA has been sought based on the negative correlation 
between the lowest ruminal pH and high rumen </p>

<p>SARA EVALUATION BY RUMINAL PH MONITORING 169 </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. Animal Science Journal published by 
Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Animal Science. </p>

<p>Animal Science Journal (2016) 87, 168-177 </p>

<p>temperature (AlZahal et al. 2008, 2009). However, it is 
still controversial with regard to whether an accurate 
ruminal pH can be predicted by measuring ruminal 
temperature because it is not clear when the lowest pH 
and the highest temperature appear. 
To assess the relationship between pH and tempera-
ture in the ruminal bottom fluid, circadian changes were 
monitored using cattle fed a control diet (C-diet) or 
rumen acidosis-inducing (RAI) diet by using the radio-
transmission pH-measurement system (Kimura et al. 
2012a). Eight primiparous non-lactating, rumen-
cannulated Holstein cattle weighting 620-720 kg were 
used. Both diets were composed of orchard grass and 
timothy mixed hay and concentrate (equivalent amount 
of flaked barley and corn). Each cow was given 
5.5-6.5 kg twice daily on a dry matter (DM) basis for 2 
weeks. The ratios of roughage to concentrate for C-diet 
and RAI-diet were 9:1 and 2:8. The pH sensor was placed 
in the ventral sac of the rumen, and two parameters 
were measured simultaneously at 10-min intervals for 
14 days after commencement of feeding. 
Compared to the mean ruminal pH for 60 min imme-
diately after the morning feeding (0 h), significantly 
lower pH was noted 3-13 h later (P &lt; 0.05) and 4-19 h 
later (P &lt; 0.01) in cattle fed C-and RAI-diets, respec-
tively, although the reduction in the latter was much 
higher than that in the former (Fig. 2). In contrast, 
significantly higher ruminal temperature was found at 
8 and 12 14 h later (P &lt; 0.05) and 6, 8 and 10-19 h later 
(P &lt; 0.01) in cattle fed C-and RAI-diets, respectively. A 
significant negative correlation was observed between 
the lowest ruminal pH and its corresponding ruminal 
temperature in cattle fed C-and RAI-diets (r = -0.722 
and -0.650, respectively, P &lt; 0.01), suggesting active </p>

<p>fermentation and VFA production in the rumen. How-
ever, the ruminal pH profiles may not be predictable by 
measuring only ruminal temperature because decreases 
in pH were preceded by increases in temperature, and 
the circadian changes in pH and temperature were asso-
ciated with ruminal fermentation. Meanwhile, ruminal 
lactic acid and total VFA concentrations increased signif-
icantly or tended to increase in cattle fed an RAI-diet, </p>

<p>Figure 1 Continuous changes in ruminal pH of cattle fed a different diet 1 week for each. The ruminal pH was measured continuously 
at 10 min intervals. Ratio of roughage and concentrate in the three diets were 8:2 (A-diet), 2:8 (B-diet) and 5:5 (C-diet), respectively. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Circadian changes in 1-h mean ruminal pH (black 
circles) and temperature (white circles) in cattle fed the control 
diet (C-diet, A) or the rumen acidosis-inducing diet (RAI-diet, B). 
Arrows indicate the feeding times. Values represent mean ± SE 
(n = 8). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05, </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01 (significant difference compared to 
the 1-h mean at 08.00-09.00 hours in each group). </p>



<p>© 2015 The Authors. Animal Science Journal published by 
Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Animal Science. </p>

<p>Animal Science Journal (2016) 87, 168-177 </p>

<p>whereas ruminal ammonia N concentrations decreased 
significantly in cows fed an RAI-diet, although there 
was variation. Significant (P &lt; 0.05) negative correla-
tions were observed between the ruminal pH and con-
centrations of total VFA (r = À0.681) or its components 
such as acetic acid (r = À0.699), propionic acid (r = 
À0.575) and butyric acid (r = À0.638) in cows fed a 
C-diet. A significant (P &lt; 0.05) negative correlation was 
observed between the ruminal temperature and lactic 
acid concentration (r = À0.582) in cows fed an RAI-diet. 
Ruminal lactic acid is not the cause of pH reduction in 
SARA model cows (Keunen et al. 2002). Some SARA 
cows have normal ruminal lactate concentrations, indi-
cating that elevated VFA concentration is one of the 
main causes of low ruminal pH. In our study, a negative 
correlation has been observed between the ruminal pH 
and ruminal temperature in cattle fed the RAI-diet, as 
previously described (AlZahal et al. 2008). In addition, 
significant negative correlations were observed between 
the ruminal pH and VFA concentrations in cattle fed the 
C-diet. The negative correlation was also observed 
between the ruminal temperature and lactic acid con-
centration in cattle fed the RAI-diet. Elevated total VFA 
concentration is the main cause of low ruminal pH in 
cows with SARA (Keunen et al. 2002). Therefore, the 
ruminal temperature might increase and the ruminal 
pH might decrease simultaneously by rapid fermentation 
and VFA production after RAI-diet feeding. </p>

<p>SIMULTANEOUS ESTIMATION OF PH IN 
THE RUMEN AND RETICULUM </p>

<p>The reliability of ruminal pH depends on the sampling 
site (bottom vs. middle of the rumen and rumen vs. 
reticulum) and sampling procedure (rumenocentesis 
vs. an oro-ruminal probe) (Duffield et al. 2004; Tafaj 
et al. 2004; Bramley et al. 2008). An indwelling wired 
system has been used to measure pH at the bottom of 
the rumen (Marden et al. 2005; AlZahal et al. 2007; 
Penner et al. 2009), but there have been no reports on 
simultaneous pH measurements of fluids at the bottom 
and in the middle of the rumen and in the reticulum 
(i.e. three sites) of cows. Furthermore, a few reports 
had examined the pH of reticulum fluid (Bryant 1964; 
Lane et al. 1968). In these reports the highest pH in the 
reticulum and the lowest pH at the top or middle of the 
rumen were reported (Lane et al. 1968). 
To assess the site difference of pH in the rumen and 
reticulum, circadian pH changes in the fluid of the 
rumen (bottom and middle) and reticulum were 
assessed simultaneously using wireless and wired 
radio-transmission pH-measurement systems in cattle 
fed the control diet (C-diet) or the RAI diet (Kimura 
et al. 2012b; Sato et al. 2012c). Cattle (n = 8) and diets 
(C-diet and RAI-diet) used in this study were the same 
as a previous study, which investigated the relation be-
tween ruminal pH and temperature. Wireless pH sensor </p>

<p>was placed in the ventral sac at the bottom of the rumen 
and in the reticulum. Wired pH sensor was fixed 
10-20 cm below the ruminal mat surface (middle of the 
rumen) by a stout wire through a rumen cannula. 
The pH in the three sites decreased following the 
morning and evening feedings (Fig. 3). In cattle fed the 
C-diet, the bottom-rumen and reticular pH reverted to 
the basal level by the next morning, while the middle-
rumen pH did not recover completely, suggesting that 
active fermentation occurred in the middle of the 
rumen. The mean pH at 1-h intervals was higher in 
the reticulum than at the bottom and in the middle of 
the rumen. The relatively stable reticular pH may result 
from dilution due to salivation and drinking water, as 
previously described (Dado &amp; Allen 1993). In cows fed 
the RAI-diet, the bottom-rumen pH fell to approxi-
mately 5.2 after the evening feeding, but returned to 
the basal level by the next morning. In contrast, the 
middle-rumen pH did not return to the basal level 
(6.5) within 24 h, presumably owing to continuous and 
vigorous fermentation. Significant (P &lt; 0.01) positive 
correlations were observed in the pH of cattle fed the 
RAI-diet between in the middle and at the bottom of 
the rumen (r = 0.894), in the middle of the rumen and 
in the reticulum (r = 0.764) and at the bottom of the 
rumen and in the reticulum (r = 0.797). </p>

<p>Figure 3 Circadian pH changes at the bottom (closed circles) 
and in the middle (open triangles) of the rumen and in the 
reticulum (open squares) of cattle fed control diet (C-diet, A) or 
the rumen acidosis-inducing diet (RAI-diet, B). Arrows show the 
feeding times. Values are expressed as mean ± SE (n = 4). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P &lt; 
0.05, </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01 (significant difference compared to the 
corresponding basal pH (taken at 09.00 hours)). </p>

<p>SARA EVALUATION BY RUMINAL PH MONITORING 171 </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. Animal Science Journal published by 
Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Animal Science. </p>

<p>Animal Science Journal (2016) 87, 168-177 </p>

<p>PATHOPHYSIOLOGICAL EVALUATION 
OF SARA BY CONTINUOUS 
MONITORING OF RUMINAL PH </p>

<p>SARA is characterized by ruminal pH (Enemark 2008; 
Plaizier et al. 2009) lower than 5.6, and pH 5.8 is consid-
ered as the marginal threshold for SARA (Kleen et al. 
2003; Gozho et al. 2005, 2007). In an experiment of 
successive SARA induction, decreased ruminal pH was 
much severer in the day of challenge feeding (Dohme 
et al. 2008). Increased severity of SARA might have been 
induced by instability of the ruminal microflora 
(Nagaraja &amp; Titgemeyer 2007), and decreased absorptive 
capacity of the ruminal epithelium might also have 
contributed to VFA accumulation in the rumen. A 
short-term, severe insult of acute acidosis decreased 
ruminal VFA absorption, presumably caused by damage 
to the ruminal wall (Krehbiel et al. 1995). Decreased ru-
minal absorptive capacity as a result of acidosis challenge 
may increase the severity of subsequent acidosis chal-
lenges. However, changes in the ruminal pH and VFA 
of cattle with repeated acidosis challenges are unknown. 
In addition, molecular techniques have shown that the 
ruminal microbial community is highly diverse (Mao 
et al. 2013), but the factors influencing its composition 
remain unknown. The ruminal microbial community 
in SARA cows has been reported (Chen et al. 2012; 
Hernandez-Sanabria et al. 2012; Golder et al. 2014), but 
the relationship between the ruminal pH, VFA and 
microbiota composition in SARA cattle is unclear. 
Bacteria-based probiotics are known to have positive 
implications on animal health and performance. Bacte-
rial probiotics have been shown to improve the rumen-
predominant microorganisms (Ghorbani et al. 2002; 
Chiquette et al. 2012; Qadis et al. 2014a) and ruminal 
performance in cattle (Qadis et al. 2014b,c). Steers that 
received probiotics containing both lactate-utilizing 
Propionibacterium and lactate-producing Enterococcus had 
higher ruminal concentrations of acetate, and the blood 
variables indicated a reduced risk of metabolic acidosis 
(Ghorbani et al. 2002). However, little information is 
available about the effect of probiotics containing 
Propionibacterium on ruminal pH and VFA in cattle. 
Changes in the ruminal pH, VFA and microbial commu-
nity in cattle with repeatedly induced SARA and effects 
of Propionibacterium-based probiotics on the ruminal 
pH and VFA in SARA cattle should be assessed 
pathophysiologically for the possible association with 
SARA by continuous monitoring of ruminal pH. </p>

<p>CHANGES IN RUMINAL PH, VFA AND 
MICROBIOTA COMPOSITION IN CATTLE 
WITH REPEATEDLY INDUCED SARA </p>

<p>The ruminal pH, VFA and microbial composition in 
cattle with repeatedly induced SARA were investigated 
to reveal the ruminal adaptation to acute and short-term </p>

<p>changes in feeding. The 16S rRNA gene pyrosequencing 
and real-time PCR were used to analyze the ruminal 
microbial community in SARA cattle, and to compare 
the composition of microbial community in cattle fed 
hay or high-concentrate diet. 
Eight rumen-cannulated Holstein steers (age, 8-10 
months; body weight, 180-200 kg) were used and fed 
hay or RAI diet (20% hay and 80% concentrate) each 
for 7 days. Each steer was fed either hay or the RAI-diet 
for 7 days, 2-3 kg of feed twice daily on a DM basis, 
followed by the other diet for an additional 7 days with-
out a resting period. This experiment was continuously 
performed twice. The pH sensor was placed in the 
ventral sac of the rumen and pH was measured every 
10 min. Ruminal fluid was collected three times (08.00, 
14.00 and 20.00 hours) at 7 days after starting each 
feeding period. Total VFA and VFA components were 
separated and quantified by gas chromatography. The 
microbial community of the ruminal fluids was analyzed 
by 16S rRNA arrangement analysis (four of eight cattle 
in the first experimental period) and real time PCR (four 
of eight cattle in both experimental periods) using bacte-
rial DNA extraction from fluids collected at 20.00 hours. 
The 24-h mean ruminal pH values in the concentrate-
fed (CF) period were significantly (P &lt; 0.05) lower than 
those in the hay-fed (FF) period, and the pH values 
obtained at 3 days after concentrate feeding were slightly 
lower in the first experiment compared to the second 
experiment (Fig. 4). The 1-h mean pH values of the 
ruminal fluids decreased gradually following morning 
and evening feedings in both FF and CF periods, and 
the pH values in the CF period were lower overall than 
those in the FF period. Ruminal total VFA, propionic 
acid and butyric acid concentrations, and LPS activity 
in the CF period were slightly higher than those in the 
FF period (Fig. 5). However, no significant difference 
was observed in the ruminal total VFA, concentration 
of each VFA and lactic acid, as well as LPS activity 
between the first and second experiments. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Changes in 24-h mean ruminal pH of cattle fed hay 
and concentrate at the first (black circles) and second (black 
squares) experiment. Values represent mean ± SE (n = 8). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P &lt; 
0.05 (significant difference compared to the 24-h mean at 7 days 
after hay feeding in the first experiment). </p>



<p>© 2015 The Authors. Animal Science Journal published by 
Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Animal Science. </p>

<p>Animal Science Journal (2016) 87, 168-177 </p>

<p>The 16S rRNA gene pyrosequencing analysis showed 
that the ruminal microbial community was simpler in 
the CF period than in the FF period. Detected numbers 
of the bacterial phylum, genus and species in the CF pe-
riod were significantly (P &lt; 0.05) lower than those in the 
FF period (Table 1). At the phylum level, Firmicutes, 
Bacteroidetes and Actinobacteria were dominant in during 
both FF and CF periods (Fig. 6). The percentages of 
Bacteroidetes and Proteobacteria were reduced by concen-
trate feeding, whereas Firmicutes was more abundant in 
the CF period than the FF period. At the genus level, 
Prevotella, Clostridium, Butyrivibrio, Eubacterium and 
Ruminococcus were dominant in both feeding periods. 
As compared with the FF period, the ratios of Prevotella 
and Eubacterium were lower, while the percentages of 
Ruminococcus, Clostridium and Butyrivibrio increased in </p>

<p>the CF period. The real-time PCR analysis showed 
that the bacterial numbers of total methanogens, 
Fibrobacter succinogenes and Selenomonas ruminantium, 
significantly (P &lt; 0.05) decreased, and those of Strep-
tococcus bovis and Megasphaera elsdenii significantly 
(P &lt; 0.05) increased in the CF period compared to the FF 
period (Fig. 7). In the FF period, the bacterial numbers of 
total bacteria, total methanogens and Selenomonas 
ruminantium in the second experimental period were 
significantly (P &lt; 0.05) lower than those in the first 
experiment. 
In the CF period, both ruminal pH and bacterial diver-
sity were lower and the rumen microbial composition 
was simpler than those in the FF period. Concentrate 
feeding might have reduced the diversity of the rumen 
microbial community. Changes in the rumen microbial </p>

<p>Figure 5 Circadian changes in total volatile fatty acids (VFA), each VFA component, ammonia N and lactic acid concentrations, and 
lipopolysaccharide (LPS) activity of cattle fed hay and concentrate in the first and second experiment. Values represent mean ± SE 
(n = 8). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05, </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01 (significant difference compared to the value at 08:00 hours in each feeding group). </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05, </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 
(significant difference compared to the value of first experiment in each feeding). </p>

<p>Table 1 Number of bacterial phylum, genus and species in cattle fed hay and concentrate in the first experiment by the 16S rRNA gene 
pyrosequencing </p>

<p>Phylum 1 
Genus 1 
Species 1 </p>

<p>Cattle No. 
Hay-fed 
Concentrate-fed 
Hay-fed 
Concentrate-fed 
Hay-fed 
Concentrate-fed </p>

<p>1 
16 
11 
144 
97 
371 
229 
2 
16 
7 
145 
75 
325 
165 
3 
11 
9 
132 
77 
317 
177 
4 
10 
5 
97 
81 
237 
163 
mean 
13.3 
8 a 
129.5 
82.5 a 
312.5 
183.5 a 
SE 
1.6 
1.3 
11.2 
5.0 
27.8 
15.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Bacterial number detected by 16S rRNA pyrosequence </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 (significant difference compared to the hay-fed period </p>

<p>SARA EVALUATION BY RUMINAL PH MONITORING 173 </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. Animal Science Journal published by 
Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Animal Science. </p>

<p>Animal Science Journal (2016) 87, 168-177 </p>

<p>composition of SARA cattle might be related to the 
marked changes in ruminal pH followed by the rapid 
decrease in numbers of bacteria. Changes in ruminal 
pH and rumen microbial community were observed 
markedly by acute and short-term change in feeding, 
which indicated ruminal adaptation (Mao et al. 2013). 
However, further research is needed to reveal the rela-
tion between ruminal pH and microbial community. </p>

<p>EFFECTS OF PROPIONIBACTERIUM-
BASED PROBIOTIC ON RUMINAL PH 
AND VFA IN CATTLE </p>

<p>Propionibacteria are natural inhabitants of the rumen 
and they produce propionate, a major precursor for 
glucose production, through hepatic gluconeogenesis 
(Sauer et al. 1989). Feeding of propionibacteria may </p>

<p>Figure 6 Comparison of rumen microbial community in cattle (n = 4) fed hay and concentrate in the first experiment by the 16S rRNA 
gene pyrosequencing. The microbial composition was analyzed by the 16S rRNA arrangement analysis using bacterial DNA extraction 
from fluids collected at 20.00 hours. </p>

<p>Figure 7 Comparison of rumen bacterial numbers in cattle (n = 4) fed hay and concentrate (Con) in the first and second experiment by 
real-time PCR. The bacterial number was analyzed using bacterial DNA extraction from fluids collected at 20.00 hours. Values represent 
mean ± SE (n = 4). </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05, </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01 (significant difference compared to the first experiment in the same feeding), </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05, </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01 
(significant difference between the hay-and concentrate-feeding within the same experimental period). </p>



<p>© 2015 The Authors. Animal Science Journal published by 
Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Animal Science. </p>

<p>Animal Science Journal (2016) 87, 168-177 </p>

<p>increase hepatic glucose production and positively influ-
ence host metabolism (Francisco et al. 2002). The effects 
of propionibacteria feeding on the lactational perfor-
mance of dairy cows in early lactation have been 
reported (Stein et al. 2006; Lehloenya et al. 2008; Weiss 
et al. 2008), and the cattle that received probiotics 
containing lactate-utilizing Propionibacterium had higher 
ruminal concentrations of acetate (Ghorbani et al. 
2002). However, little information is available regarding 
the effect of probiotics containing Propionibacterium on 
the ruminal pH and VFA in cattle. To evaluate the 
preventive effect of Propionibacterium on ruminal pH 
and SARA, changes in the ruminal pH and VFA of cattle 
administered Propionibacterium-based probiotic were 
investigated. 
Four primiparous non-lactating, rumen-cannulated 
Holstein cattle weighing 620-700 kg were used, and the 
experiment was performed three times at 4-week inter-
vals. Cattle were fed hay over the 2 weeks before the 
experiment. Thereafter, the RAI-diet consisting of 20% 
hay and 80% concentrate was fed for 2 weeks. Each 
cow was given 6-7 kg feed twice daily on a DM basis. 
During the RAI-died feeding, two groups of cattle were 
fed simultaneously either with a Propionibacterium-based 
probiotic (5×10 10 colony forming units) (A-diet), or with 
a Propionibacterium-based probiotic plus fermented prod-
ucts of Lactobacillus (10 g) and lactose (23.5 g) (B-diet) 
once a day. Cattle fed the RAI-diet without probiotic </p>

<p>served as the control. The ruminal pH was measured at 
10-min intervals using the pH sensor, and the ruminal 
fluids for VFA analysis were collected at 14 days after 
RAI-diet feeding. 
The mean 24-h ruminal pH values decreased mark-
edly and showed significantly (P &lt; 0.01) low levels after </p>

<p>Figure 8 Changes in 24-h mean ruminal pH of cattle fed the 
rumen acidosis-inducing diet (RAI)-diet (Control), RAI-diet plus 
Propionibacterium-based probiotic (A-diet), or RAI-diet plus 
Propionibacterium-based probiotic, fermented products of 
Lactobacillus, and lactose (B-diet) once a day. Values represent 
mean ± SE (n = 4). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01 (significant difference compared to 
the control on the same day), </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01 (significant difference 
compared to the day -1 within the same group). </p>

<p>Figure 9 Circadian changes in total volatile fatty acids (VFA), each VFA component, lactic acid and ammonia N concentrations of cattle 
fed the rumen acidosis-inducing diet (RAI)-diet (Control), RAI-diet plus Propionibacterium-based probiotic (A-diet), or RAI-diet plus 
Propionibacterium-based probiotic, fermented products of Lactobacillus, and lactose (B-diet) once a day. Values represent mean ± SE 
(n = 4). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01 (significant difference compared to the 08.00 hours within the same group). </p>

<p>SARA EVALUATION BY RUMINAL PH MONITORING 175 </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. Animal Science Journal published by 
Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Animal Science. </p>

<p>Animal Science Journal (2016) 87, 168-177 </p>

<p>RAI-diet feeding in the control and two probiotic feeding 
groups. However, the pH values in the B-diet group at 
1-3 and 11 days after RAI-diet feeding were significantly 
(P &lt; 0.01) higher than those of the control (Fig. 8). No 
significant difference was observed in the ruminal VFA 
concentrations between both feeding groups and the 
control, whereas the ruminal total VFA and VFA con-
centrations including propionic acid in cattle fed 
Propionibacterium-based probiotic (A-and B-diet) were 
slightly higher than those in the control (Fig. 9). 
These results indicate that the decreased ruminal pH 
resulting from feeding the RAI-diet was relieved by the 
administration of Propionibacterium-based probiotic, 
fermented products of Lactobacillus and lactose. 
Propionibacterium-based additive might improve the 
ruminal fermentation and reduce ruminal pH in SARA 
cattle. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Continuous monitoring of the ruminal pH using a newly 
invented radio-transmission pH-measurement system 
could be applied for detection and prevention of SARA 
in the field and pathophysiological research of SARA, 
including the ruminal zymology and bacteriology, which 
have been determined previously by sampling of the 
ruminal fluid and measuring of ruminal pH. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The author would like to express sincere thanks to Meiji 
Feed CO., LTD for the kind gift of Propionibacterium-
based probiotic and fermented products of Lactobacillus. </p>



<p>SARA EVALUATION BY RUMINAL PH MONITORING 177 </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. Animal Science Journal published by 
Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd on behalf of Japanese Society of Animal Science. </p>

<p>Animal Science Journal (2016) 87, 168-177 </p>

</text></tei>