<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5367605" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Computer-assisted orthopaedic surgery was born in the 
1990s. Nowadays, computer-assisted orthopaedic surgery 
is used for transpedicular screw fixation and for total knee 
arthroplasty. </p>

<p>Patient-specific instrumentation is one type of computer-
assisted surgery based on volumetric images, such as 
computed tomography or magnetic resonance imaging. </p>

<p>In this article, possible applications of patient-specific 
instruments in paediatric orthopaedics are described. The 
use of patient-specific instrumentation for the correction 
of cubitus varus is given as an example with complex oste-
otomy. Another application for tarsal coalition resection 
is shown. </p>

<p>A last example of using patient-specific instrumentation 
for both tumour resection and allograft reconstruction is 
illustrated. </p>

<p>Patient-specific instruments based on computed tomogra-
phy of the bone can increase peri-operative accuracy and 
decrease operative time. They are very helpful for the sur-
geon. Other applications are possible and will be probably 
developed in the future. </p>

<p>Computer-assisted surgery (CAS) is the term used to 
describe the concept of applying computers to enable pre-
operative planning and provide intra-operative assistance 
or guidance. CAS is also known as computer-aided sur-
gery, computer-assisted intervention, image-guided sur-
gery and surgical navigation. CAS applied to orthopaedic 
surgery is termed 'computer-assisted orthopaedic surgery' 
(CAOS). The first rudimental CAS systems were developed 
in the early 1970s. These systems gave feedback on instru-
ment positioning in stereotaxic neurosurgery. 1 In ortho-
paedic surgery, the first CAOS application was in 1995 for </p>

<p>transpedicular screw fixation in the spine. 2 In orthopae-
dic oncology, the first reported application was for pelvic 
sarcoma resection in 2004 3 and the first use for both sar-
coma resection and reconstruction with an allograft was 
in 2010. 4 In paediatric orthopaedic surgery, CAOS sys-
tems have been developed for complex osteotomies, 5 for 
tumour resection 6,7 and for tarsal coalition resection. 8 
Navigation and robotic systems are the most advanced 
parts of CAOS. 9 Surgical navigation is a visualisation sys-
tem that gives positional information about surgical tools 
or implants relative to a target organ (bone). There are 
three types of surgical navigation systems: </p>

<p>1. Volumetric image-based navigation uses volumet-
ric images, such as computed tomography (CT), 
magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), or ultrasound 
echograms (US). These modalities are most often 
used to extract bone surface. 
2. Fluoroscopic navigation makes use of intra-
operative fluoroscopic images to reconstruct a 
three-dimensional (3D) model of the bone. 
3. Imageless navigation makes use of kinetic information 
about joints or morphometric information regarding 
the target bones obtained intra-operatively. </p>

<p>There are three types of robotic systems developed to 
overcome the inaccuracy of hand-controlled positioning 
of surgical tools: 9 </p>

<p>1. The first type locates a cutting guide block or a drill-
ing guide sleeve to allow the surgeon to slide a 
bone saw or a drill bit into the guide. 
2. Another type constrains the range of movement of 
a surgical tool held by a robot arm. 
3. The last type is an active system which directs a mill-
ing device automatically, according to pre-operative 
planning. </p>



<p>Surgical navigation in paediatric orthopaedicS </p>

<p>appearance. When the limitation interferes with normal 
everyday life, corrective surgery is indicated. The required 
correction is often a complex bi-planar bone section. 
Using a conventional manual method, the obtained 
correction is often sub-optimal, leading to an over-or 
under-correction. A 3D simulation of the levels of bone 
section is very helpful to visualise the initial position and 
estimate the appropriate correction. </p>

<p>Cubitus varus </p>

<p>Cubitus varus is a good example of a complex 3D deform-
ity in children. Malunion in cubitus varus most often 
occurs resulting from inadequate reduction of a supra-
condylar fracture of the humerus. Cubitus varus does not 
always impair elbow function or elbow range of motion, 
but the cosmetic deformity may lead parents to request 
an operation to improve the appearance of the elbow. 
Planning based on conventional radiology may be a 
source of inaccuracy because of important errors in the 
angular measurement. 18 During the surgery, it is very dif-
ficult to orientate the saw blade correctly. Accurate correc-
tion of a cubitus varus needs to take into account the 
deformity in three dimensions and not only in the frontal 
and sagittal projections, in order to obtain a good result 
in terms of appearance and function. 19 </p>

<p>Pre-operative 3D-planning and PSI </p>

<p>A pre-operative humerus CT scan is obtained with a mini-
mal resolution of 1 mm spacing between slices and 2 mm 
slice thickness. A 3D reconstruction of the bone is made 
from the CT scan. The varus deformity and the flexion or 
extension deformity are assessed on the 3D reconstruction 
of the distal humerus. The closing wedge is planned accord-
ing to frontal/sagittal angle measurement. The transverse 
rotation plane is corrected as well to restore an optimal 
joint line (Fig. 1). No bony hinge is left at the opposite side 
in order to medially translate the distal fragment and 
decrease the residual condylar prominence (Fig. 2). 
The PSI is designed based on the 3D computer simula-
tion and is manufactured using a biocompatible material 
(polyamide) by SLS. The PSI consists of three different parts: </p>

<p>A first main PSI to place four 2 mm K-wires (Figs 3a 
and 4a); 
A second set of cutting guides placed on the K-wires 
(Figs 3b and 4b); 
A final external fixator (Figs 3c and 4e), which imposes 
the final position but with a freedom in translation. </p>

<p>Surgical technique </p>

<p>During the surgery, the patient is positioned in the supine 
position with the arm placed on an arm board with a tourni-
quet. A 4 cm to 5 cm lateral approach is used. After soft-tis-
sue dissection, the periosteum is incised longitudinally and 
the distal humeral metaphysis is exposed subperiosteally. </p>

<p>manufacturer. An engineer processes the data to identify 
specific anatomical landmarks and creates a computer-
generated, customised surgical plan. Once the surgeon 
approves the plan, a corresponding set of disposable cut-
ting blocks or pin guides is manufactured to help the sur-
geon in the positioning and alignment tasks of the surgical 
tool. The goal is to correctly position the implant during 
surgery. Salako et al used guided intrapedicular screws to 
decrease the rate of misplaced screws. 11 Leiggener et al 12 
manufactured a guide by additive manufacturing using 
selective laser sintering (SLS) for mandible reconstruction 
with free fibula osseous flap. They were able to perform a 
complex reconstruction by choosing the best position on 
the donor (fibula) and recipient (mandible) sites, avoiding 
important structures like dental nerve and respecting vas-
cular anatomy. Modabber et al 13 have concluded that this 
technique significantly decreased the shaping time during 
surgery, and should in addition have an impact on the sur-
vival of the flap. </p>

<p>Advantages of CAOS </p>

<p>The principal idea behind CAOS is that operative outcomes 
will be improved through the use of computer technology. 
CAOS helps the surgeon to more accurately pinpoint ana-
tomical landmarks, and guides the surgeon through differ-
ent bone cuts. Three main advantages of CAOS and PSIs 
have been found. PSIs have been widely tested to assess 
their accuracy and impact on time during the surgery. The 
early reported results on accuracy of PSIs were encourag-
ing. Positioning measurements have shown angulation 
error below 0.6° in the spine and the tibia and 1° in the 
femur. 14 Cadaveric experiments showed clinically accepta-
ble results in the spine 15 with few errors above 2 mm when 
compared with the conventional method. On the question 
of time, studies have shown a shorter duration of surgery 
by using PSIs in three different applications. This improve-
ment is easily understandable because of the 'plug and 
play' characteristic of the instrument. The user places the 
instrument in the correct position and connects standard 
devices to achieve the desired task. A cadaveric experiment 
has demonstrated that PSIs decreased the time to find the 
entry point for drilling in a vertebra pedicle. 15 For triple pel-
vic osteotomies on actual patients, the whole surgery time 
decreased by 23%, to gain 35 minutes. 16 The decrease of 
intra-operative irradiation thanks to a lesser use of fluoros-
copy is also an added value of the technology. It has been 
shown that it is significantly decreased when using PSIs. 17 
In this report we will demonstrate the use of PSI tech-
nology in paediatric orthopaedics by describing three pos-
sible clinical applications. </p>

<p>Application for complex osteotomies </p>

<p>A non-anatomical bone malunion or a congenital malfor-
mation can limit the leg function or give a poor aesthetic </p>



<p>a) 
b) </p>

<p>The PSI is displaced until the unique position is reached. Four 
2 mm K-wires are inserted in the distal humerus by following 
the PSI (Figs 4a and 5a). The PSI is cut into two parts, and </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Images showing the planning of the closing wedge 
(in red) to correct both a) frontal and b) sagittal planes. </p>

<p>a) 
b) </p>

<p>these sections are removed. Two other PSIs are inserted (Fig. 
4b) following the K-wires to perform the closing wedge with 
oscillating saw (Fig. 4c). The wedge fragment is removed 
(Fig. 4d). The planned correction is directly obtained by 
aligning the four K-wires in a third guide used as a temporary 
external fixator (Figs 4e and 5b). A medial translation of the 
distal fragment along the wires is still possible to decrease 
the prominence. Final osteosynthesis is obtained by two 
crossed 2 mm K-wires (Fig. 5b). The four initial K-wires are 
finally removed. In the post-operative period, the child is 
immobilised in a long-arm posterior splint with the elbow 
flexed at 90° for three weeks without change. </p>

<p>Application for tarsal coalition resection </p>

<p>Tarsal coalition or congenital tarsal synostosis is character-
ised by an abnormal bony, cartilaginous or fibrous junction 
between two or more hind-and/or mid-foot bones. It occurs 
with an incidence of about 1% of the general population 
and is bilateral in 50% of cases. 8,20 Talocalcaneal and calca-
neonavicular coalitions are the most frequent forms. It is a 
frequent cause of foot and ankle pain, with onset during the 
second decade of life or later. Subtalar motion (inversion 
and eversion) may be impaired and iterative ankle sprain, 
flat-foot and tarsal tunnel syndrome may occur. Diagnosis is 
given by radiograph for calcaneonavicular coalition (AP, 
oblique and lateral views) and by CT for talocalcaneal coali-
tion. Surgery is indicated only in cases of symptomatic tarsal 
coalition resistant to conservative management. One 
favoured technique is triple arthrodesis (talocalcaneal, talo-
navicular and calcaneocuboid), but long-term follow-up 
has shown onset of secondary tibiotarsal osteoarthritis in 
58% to 77% of cases. 21,22 An alternative method consists of 
resecting the synostosis, providing good results in terms of 
pain alleviation and prevention of osteoarthritis, 23,24 
although not in all reports. It is not always straightforward 
during actual surgery to determine precise location and ori-
entation of the saw blade for bone bridge resection, and it is 
also difficult to stop sawing before breaching the healthy 
talocalcaneal joint. Fluoroscopy is often not useful for taloc-
alcaneal coalition. Arthroscopic resection has also been 
reported, 24,25 but involves a long learning curve, 26 longer 
operating time, 27 , risk of posterior tibial pedicle neurovascu-
lar lesion 28 and difficulty in positioning. 29 </p>

<p>Pre-operative 3D-planning and PSI </p>

<p>A pre-operative CT scan of the coalition is performed with 
a minimal resolution of 1 mm spacing between slices and 
2 mm slice thickness. Using 3D planning software, the PSI 
is virtually designed, then manufactured, comprising one 
reusable standardised titanium component and a second 
patient-specific polyamide component (Fig. 6). </p>

<p>Surgical technique </p>

<p>The patient is positioned in dorsal decubitus, with a pneu-
matic tourniquet on the thigh. In talocalcaneal coalition, </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Images showing that no hinge is left at the opposite side 
to allow medialisation of the distal fragment in the a) frontal 
and b) sagittal planes. </p>

<p>a) 
b) </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Photographs of the different parts of the patient-specific 
instrument used for cubitus varus correction. </p>

<p>a) 
b) 
c) </p>



<p>Surgical navigation in paediatric orthopaedicS </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Images showing patient-specific instrument compound of two components: the titanium component is standardised and 
reusable, while the polyamide component is made by rapid prototyping. There is metal-metal contact between the guide and the 
Kirschner wires and saw blade, avoiding soft-tissue contamination by potential polyamide debris. </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Radiograph of the surgical steps showing a) the four Kirschner wires (K-wires) inserted following the first patient-specific 
instrument (PSI); b) the four K-wires are aligned in the last PSI giving the desired correction; and c) two crossed K-wires fix the 
correction and the four K-wires are removed. </p>

<p>a) 
b) 
c) </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Photographs of the successive surgical steps showing how a) the patient-specific instrument (PSI) is placed at the surface of the 
bone and four 2 mm Kirschner wires (K-wires) are inserted; b) the first PSI is removed and replaced by two other PSIs that present a flat 
surface to guide the saw blade; c) the saw blade is guided by the PSI; d) the closing wedge is removed; e) a final PSI brings the four K-wires 
into alignment (as an external fixator). The targeted correction is automatically obtained (according to the pre-operative planning). </p>

<p>a) 
b) 
c) 
d) 
e) </p>

<p>the approach is medial, with an incision over the susten-
taculum tali. The posterior tibial and flexor hallucis longus 
tendons are retracted respectively forward and backward 
to expose the bone bridge. In calcaneonavicular coalition, </p>

<p>the incision is anterolateral, forwards of the sinus tarsi; the 
extensor digitorum brevis muscle is reclined distally, 
exposing the coalition. The PSI is positioned on the bone 
surface, having been designed so as to give a perfect fit in </p>



<p>Fig. 7 Photographs showing how a fascia lata allograft is folded to obtain a 'concertina' effect. </p>

<p>a single possible position. It is fixed using two K-wires to 
ensure stability, and can then guide the direction of the 
saw blade. It is further designed to ensure correct resec-
tion depth, the blade being introduced fully into the PSI so 
as to reach but not damage the healthy subtalar joint. To 
reduce recurrence risk, a frozen fascia lata allograft is 
folded several times before positioning, to obtain a 'con-
certina' effect between the talus and calcaneum (Figs. 7 
and 8). At the end of the surgery, the capsular and tendi-
nous planes are carefully closed. Walking is systematically 
resumed as soon as pain allows. Physical therapy for mid-
and hind-foot mobilisation is initiated at one week. Sport 
is authorised at six months. The technique has the advan-
tages of increasing accuracy and reducing surgery time, 
and the surgical approach is smaller. 8 </p>

<p>Application for tumour resection and 
allograft reconstruction </p>

<p>Osteosarcoma and Ewing's sarcoma are the most fre-
quent malignant primary bone tumours in children, 
while chondrosarcoma is the most frequent in adults. 
Improvements in diagnosis and therapeutic techniques 
increased the possibility of limb-salvage surgery. The 
function of the reconstructed limb is a major factor, espe-
cially in young and physically active patients who place 
high demands on their limb. The limb reconstruction 
must also be durable because life expectancy for many of </p>

<p>Fig. 8 Photographs showing how a distractor opens the resection area and the fascia lata allograft is inserted and then sutured with 
the capsule. </p>

<p>these patients is several decades. However, several stud-
ies suggest that limb-salvage surgery increases the local 
recurrence, in cases of inadequate margin excision. 30 To 
achieve local control of the disease and improve onco-
logical results, wide resection margins are mandatory. 
This wide surgical excision results in a large residual bone 
defect that needs restoration. By using PSI the width of 
the margins may be decreased. 7 The resection is carefully 
planned before surgery, based on MRI and CT scans that 
are used to define the trajectories of the resection. Limb 
reconstruction for such large defects can be performed 
by different techniques, including: endoprosthetic recon-
struction, osteoarticular allograft, vascularised autograft, 
bone transport with distraction osteogenesis or re-
implantation of the tumour-bearing bone segment after 
devitalisation of the tumour cells (by heating, freezing or 
extracorporeal irradiation). Massive bone allografts pre-
sent some drawbacks, including relatively long rehabilita-
tion due to immobilisation and partial weight-bearing, 
difficulties in obtaining size-matched allografts for small 
patients, the absence of expandability, and the relatively 
high incidence of complications. 31 Despite these draw-
backs, allografts offer several advantages, including the 
ability to re-attach host ligamentous and tendinous struc-
tures to the graft. Others advantages are the biological 
incorporation of the graft (at least partially) and the pres-
ervation of the joint, the juxta-articular bone and the 
growth-plates. 32 These advantages make massive bone </p>



<p>Surgical navigation in paediatric orthopaedicS </p>

<p>allografts convenient for intercalary, osteoarticular or 
arthrodesis operations, and for allograft-prosthetic com-
posite reconstruction in an extra-articular resection. Bone 
allograft is the most common option for intercalary 
reconstruction, with survival rates as high as 75% to 89% 
at ten years. 31,33,34 </p>

<p>Example of Ewing sarcoma resection of the pelvis (zones I, II 
and IV of Enneking) </p>

<p>Pre-operative planning for tumour resection. Pre-operative 
bone CT and MRI scans are obtained respectively for 
CT with 0.5 mm spacing between slices and 1 mm 
slice thickness, and for MRI according to the resolution 
needed for diagnosis. The open-source software <rs id="software-3" type="software">ITK-
Snap</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">2.0.0</rs> 35 is used to manually delineate the tumour 
on each MRI slice where it is visible. </p>

<p>Multi-modal registration allows merging of the MRI 
and the delineated tumour volume with the CT, making 
both studies share the same co-ordinate system (Figs 9 
and 10). The cutting planes are initially brought into con-
tact with the tumour and then translated back with a sur-
geon-defined security margin of at least 5 mm. PSIs are 
virtually designed and made by additive manufacturing 
using a biocompatible material (Figs 11 and 12). </p>

<p>Pre-operative planning for allograft preparation. To 
select the best-fitting allograft amongst those avail-
able from the local bone bank, CT scans of all available </p>

<p>corresponding allografts are acquired (0.35 mm slice 
thickness, 0.7 mm spacing between slices). A CT-based 
registration is performed between the patient's bone 
and the available allografts. Once the optimal allograft 
is chosen, the CT-to-CT registration permits the trans-
fer of the cutting planes of the tumour resection to the 
co-ordinate system of the allograft's CT (Fig. 13). This 
procedure ensures that the target planes for the patient 
and allograft are identical. In this case, the patient was 
11 years old. The allograft, being harvested from an 
adult donor, was over-sized. It had been planned to 
cut the superior iliac crest to adjust its size and to be 
able to close the surgical approach (Fig. 13). A second </p>

<p>Fig. 9 MRIs of an 11-year-old girl with Ewing's sarcoma of the left iliac wing involving zones I, II and IV of Enneking. Left, CT of the 
pelvis; middle, merging of CT and MRI; right, tumour delineated on the MRI merged with CT. </p>

<p>Fig. 10 Images of the CT of the patient's pelvis with the tumour 
delineated (red). </p>



<p>instrument specific to the graft was designed and 
manufactured to assist the allograft cutting (Fig. 13). 
The obtained virtual reconstruction was a good fit 
with the normal anatomy (Fig. 14). The operating time 
was seven hours. No femoral or sciatic nerve palsy was 
encountered. The patient observed a six-week non-
weight-bearing period before walking with crutches for 
six additional weeks. </p>

<p>Cost implications of PSIs in paediatric 
orthopaedics </p>

<p>The cost of the planning and manufacturing of a single 
PSI, for example for a complex 3D-osteotomy, is about 
€800, and for two PSIs for both tumour resection and allo-
graft cutting, the cost is in the region of €1600. </p>

<p>Summary </p>

<p>Three examples of computer-assisted surgery using PSIs 
(patient-specific instruments) in paediatric orthopaedics 
have been presented. With PSIs, we have found an increase 
in accuracy and a reduction in operating time. Another 
advantage is that fluoroscopy is no longer needed during 
the surgery. These advantages represent a benefit for the 
patient and for the surgeon at an acceptable cost. </p>

<p>Author informAtion </p>

<p>1 Cliniques universitaires Saint-Luc, Brussels, Belgium. 
2 3D Side, Belgium. </p>

<p>Correspondence should be sent to Pierre-Louis Docquier, Cliniques Universitaires 
Saint-Luc, Service de Chirurgie Orthopédique et Traumatologique, 10, Avenue 
Hippocrate, B-1200 Brussels, Belgium. 
Email: Pierre-Louis.Docquier@uclouvain.be </p>

<p>ConfliCt of interest </p>

<p>Paul Laurent and Khanh TranDuy are founders of 3D Side, a patient-specific surgical 
technology manufacturer. </p>

<p>Fig. 11 Images showing how a first patient-specific instrument 
is created to guide the horizontal cut in the upper part of the 
acetabulum and the vertical cut in the pubis. </p>

<p>Fig. 12 Images showing how a second PSI is created to guide 
the vertical cut in the posterior iliac crest and the sacral ala. </p>

<p>Fig. 13 Left: simulated reconstruction: allograft (red) inserted 
in the gap obtained after tumour resection. The allograft was 
harvested from a female adult but is oversized by comparison 
with the iliac wing of the 11-year-old girl. Matching and 
positioning of the allograft aim to obtain congruency in the 
acetabulum. Middle: a specific instrument is created to obtain 
the appropriate cutting. Right: the allograft has been cut to 
decrease its size. </p>

<p>Fig. 14 Radiograph of the reconstruction. </p>



<p>Surgical navigation in paediatric orthopaedicS </p>

<p>funding </p>

<p>This research received a grant from Fondation Contre le Cancer (GrantSCIE2010-184) 
(www.cancer.be). </p>

<p>liCenCe </p>

<p>© 2016 The author(s) 
This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) licence (https://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution 
of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed. </p>

<p>referenCes </p>



</text></tei>