<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5419080" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>For therapeutic monoclonal antibodies (mAbs), detailed analysis of the structural integrity and 
heterogeneity, which results from multiple types of post-translational modifications (PTMs), is relevant to 
various processes, including product characterization, storage stability and quality control. Despite the 
recent rapid development of new bioanalytical techniques, it is still challenging to completely characterize 
the proteoform profile of a mAb. As a nearly indispensable tool in mAb analysis, mass spectrometry (MS) 
provides unique structural information at multiple levels. Here, we tested a hybrid strategy for the 
comprehensive characterization of micro-heterogeneity by integrating 2 state-of-the-art MS-based 
approaches, high-resolution native MS and targeted glycan profiling, to perform complementary analysis 
at the intact protein level and released glycan level, respectively. We compared the performance of these 
methods using samples of engineered half-body IgG4s and a panel of mAbs approved for human use. The 
glycosylation characterization data derived from these approaches were found to be mutually consistent 
in composition profiling, and complementary in identification and relative-quantitation of low-abundant 
uncommon glycoforms. In addition, multiple other sources of micro-heterogeneity, such as glycation, lack 
of glycosylation, and loss of light chains, could be detected by this approach, and the contribution of 
multiple types of modifications to the overall micro-heterogeneity could be assessed using our 
superposition algorithm. Our data demonstrate that the hybrid strategy allows reliable and thorough 
characterization of mAbs, revealing product characteristics that would easily be missed if only a single 
approach were used. </p>

<p>Therapeutic monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) are inherently het-
erogeneous in structure due to numerous factors, including post-
translational modifications (PTMs), incomplete processing, sus-
ceptibility to degradation, and disulfide shuffling. 
1-4 In particular, 
the glycosylation at Asn297 in the Fc-region contributes greatly 
to the micro-heterogeneity, affecting the conformation, half-life 
in serum, efficacy and safety of mAbs. 
5-7 The glycan chains stabi-
lize the CH2 domain, and removal of certain carbohydrate resi-
dues often leads to conformational changes, a decrease in 
thermal stability, and loss of effector functions. 
8 For instance, 
removal of terminal galactose reduces complement-dependent 
cytotoxicity (CDC), 
9,10 while a decreased level of core fucosyla-
tion enhances antibody-dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity 
(ADCC). 
11-13 Other modifications made to the protein backbone, 
such as C-terminal lysine clipping, 
14 deamidation, and oxidation 
also contribute to the heterogeneity of mAb products. 
15,16 In 
some cases, more substantial changes in the protein scaffold can </p>

<p>be introduced by either incomplete processing or degradation, </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>influencing the antigen binding capability 
18 or the in vivo clear-
ance rate of mAbs. 
19 These biologic consequences make compre-
hensive characterizations of heterogeneity critical for the design, 
production and clinical use of mAbs. 
Currently, mass spectrometry (MS)-based techniques are 
widely used for the analysis of mAb heterogeneity with special 
emphasis on glycosylation. It is technically possible to charac-
terize mAb glycosylation at several levels: the intact protein 
level, the glycopeptide level and the released glycan level. </p>

<p>20-24 </p>

<p>MS analysis of released glycans is still the method of choice for 
obtaining structural information on the glycome. Glycan analy-
sis allows for rapid, high-throughput characterization of mAb 
samples by matching the light chain retention time and accu-
rate mass, providing in-depth structural information on the 
glycans, including even linkage details. 
25 Glycopeptide analysis 
provides simultaneous identification of the glycoproteins and </p>

<p>CONTACT Albert J. R. Heck 
A.J.R.Heck@uu.nl 
Biomolecular Mass Spectrometry and Proteomics, Utrecht University, Kruytgebouw, Padualaan 8, Utrecht 3584CH, 
The Netherlands. 
*These authors equally contributed to this work. 
**Present Address: Nanjing Normal University, 1 Wenyuan Rd, Nanjing, Jiangsu Province 210023, China. </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Present Address: Amgen, Thousand Oaks, CA 91320, USA. 
Supplemental data for this article can be accessed on the publisher's website. </p>

<p>Published with license by Taylor &amp; Francis Group, LLC © Yang Yang, Guanbo Wang, Ting Song, Carlito B. Lebrilla, and Albert J. R. Heck 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits unre-
stricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The moral rights of the named author(s) have been asserted. </p>

<p>MABS 
2017, VOL. 9, NO. 4, 638-645 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/19420862.2017.1290033 </p>

<p>their glycans, and localization, occupancy and micro-heteroge-
neity can be evaluated by using tandem mass spectrometry 
(MS/MS) techniques. </p>

<p>20,24,26 </p>

<p>Recently, site-specific glycosylation analysis of mAbs was 
shown to benefit from the sensitivity and specify achievable by 
targeted approaches using multiple reaction monitoring 
(MRM). 
27 At the other end of the spectrum, by directly analyz-
ing the intact protein, it is possible to simultaneously and quanti-
tatively profile the distribution of the main glycoproteoforms, 
which is an important indication for product integrity and con-
sistency. 
28-30 Although these approaches have proven powerful 
in providing structural information, no single approach is suffi-
cient for an in-depth characterization of all aspects of heteroge-
neity. In a recent comprehensive analysis of cetuximab, Ayoub 
et al. combined multiple schemes (intact analysis, middle-down, 
middle-up and bottom-up) to reveal distinct glycosylation pro-
files on the Fab and Fc region, as well as a sequence error in the 
reported sequence of the light chain. 
31 This study provided a 
good example of the benefit of integrating information at multi-
ple levels in dissection of a mAb product. 
Here, we combined 2 cutting-edge MS-based approaches, i. 
e., high-resolution native MS for the global profiling of co-exist-
ing proteoforms and targeted glycan analysis of released N-gly-
cans for the structural analysis of individual glycoforms, to 
characterize 12 therapeutic mAbs, 7 of which are marketed. 
Combining the data obtained at the intact protein level and 
released glycan level, we were able to better resolve the overall 
heterogeneity exhibited by a mAb and quantitatively profile 
them with satisfactory confidence. In addition, other sources of 
micro-heterogeneity, such as incomplete lysine clipping, lack of 
glycosylation, loss of could be inferred simultaneously from the </p>

<p>native MS data. The complementary structural information 
provided by the 2 approaches allow the micro-heterogeneity 
and structural integrity of mAbs to be characterized in unprece-
dented detail, useful for pharmaceutical development and mAb 
quality control, especially when these differentiated proteo-
forms exhibit difference in potency. In addition, our strategy 
can be used to detect structural alterations induced by storage-
induced degradation of biopharmaceuticals. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Comparative analysis of IgG4-Dhinge half-body N-
glycosylation at the intact protein and released glycan 
levels </p>

<p>To evaluate the performance of native MS and targeted glycan 
profiling in the analysis of N-glycosylation at the intact protein 
level and released glycan level, we compared the data provided 
by these 2 approaches. Three IgG4-Dhinge mutants, i.e., F405T/ 
Y407E, Y407Q and Y407K, were selected as model analytes 
because their defined half-molecule state harbors only one N-gly-
cosylation site and thus allows unpaired glycan chains to be 
characterized at the intact protein level. Moreover, as suggested 
by previous studies, 
32 each of these 3 mutants exhibits high levels 
of galactose, sialic acids and branching, providing a wide range 
of glycoforms valuable for our method validation. 
In the native MS measurements, signals corresponding to 
various glycoproteoforms could be baseline-resolved based on 
their unique molecular weight (MW) accurately measured 
using the Orbitrap EMR mass analyzer (Fig. 1A). Then, the 
composition of the corresponding species, i.e., the </p>

<p>Figure 1. N-glycosylation on 3 IgG4-Dhinge mutants are quantitatively profiled at the intact protein and the released glycan level. (A) Deconvoluted native mass spectra 
of the intact IgG4-Dhinge proteins with all glycoproteoforms baseline-resolved, separated by their MW. Asterisks indicate observed glycine truncations in the mAb back-
bone. (B) Total ion current (TIC) chromatograms of the released glycans that are separated based on their chromatographic elution time. Signal peaks are color-coded 
using the same scheme as in (A). (C) Direct comparison of the relative abundances of glycans with different compositions determined by the 2 individual approaches, 
whereby the consistency between the 2 methods was evaluated using Pearson correlation scores. Quantification data of native MS has been adjusted for glycine 
truncation. </p>

<p>MABS </p>

<p>
stoichiometry of carbohydrate residues, was calculated using 
the MW of individual residues. In targeted glycan profiling 
(Fig. 1B), the glycans released from the glycoproteins were 
identified by mapping their chromatographic elution profiles to 
those of the common glycosylations on commercial mAb prod-
ucts covered by a library. 
25 The glycan compositions were then 
further verified by the MW measured using the MS coupled 
with LC. Both approaches yielded results in aspects of accurate 
MW, glycan composition and relative abundance. To quantita-
tively compare the 2 data sets, for each mutant we plotted the 
relative abundances of detected glycans against their MW in a 
mirror-like fashion (Fig. 1C). Illustratively for IgG4-Dhinge-
Y407Q, with 25 and 24 glycoforms mass-assigned by native MS 
and targeted glycan profiling, respectively, 14 species could be 
assigned by both approaches, accounting for 92% of the total 
glycan abundance (Fig. 1C; Table S2). The Pearson correlation 
coefficient (R) of the full-range mirror-plots is 0.84. In addition 
to the common glycoforms, the more sophisticated di-and tri-
sialylated species such as 6,5,1,2 (annotated as numbers of Hex, 
HexNAc,Fuc,Sia incorporated, sic passim) and 6,5,1,3 were also 
detected in similar abundances by both approaches. Similar 
observations were made in analysis of Y407K and F405T/ 
Y407E (see also Fig. 1). These distribution maps and the R val-
ues calculated for the comparisons suggest an overall good 
agreement between the 2 approaches in terms of detection and 
identification of the predominant glycoforms, as well as many 
low abundant ones. 
Between the 2 data sets, the discrepancies in abundances of 
certain glycoforms may partially be attributed to artifacts 
induced by either approach. Particularly, native MS reported 
higher abundances of most of the glycoforms containing 5 Hex-
NAc residues compared with glycan profiling (Table S2), sug-
gesting the potential presence of a systematic bias. In native 
MS, all glycoforms are separated and assigned solely based on 
MW, and thus the accuracy of quantitation for certain species 
may be compromised by the occasional overlapping of signals 
of different glycoforms whose MW difference is smaller than 
the peak widths, in spite of the instruments' resolving power. 
Roughly, in our native MS analysis a minimum MW difference 
of 20 Da is necessary for unambiguous assignments of different 
glycoforms. For instance, since the MW of glycoform G1 
(4,4,0,0) is only 16 Da heavier than that of G0F (3,4,1,0), in the 
native MS data the signal peak of G1 are merged into that of 
G0F, resulting in an overestimated abundance of G0F, and false 
negative detection of G1 (Fig. 1; Table S2). In sharp contrast, 
targeted profiling provides the released glycans with more effi-
cient separation (based on the chromatographic elution time 
and MW) and composition verification based on tandem MS 
patterns when necessary, allowing signals to be assigned with 
higher confidence. However, biases in the released glycan anal-
ysis may exist, for instance due to difference in ionization and 
detection response that may affect quantitation. 
36 Moreover, 
MS analysis of released glycans can result in undesired frag-
mentation, 
37 leading to diminished quantitative detection of 
the species of origin and false positive detection of fragments, 
especially if these fragment species are not covered by the refer-
ence library. As exemplified by the elution profiles of glycans 
released from F405T/Y407E (Fig. 1B), while 2 of the 5,4,1,2 spe-
cies were eluted at 25.08 and 25.91 min, respectively, 2 minor </p>

<p>species mass-assigned as 5,4,1,1 were observed at the same elu-
tion positions, implying that these 5,4,1,1 species were yielded 
by loss of a sialic acid residue from a subpopulation of 5,4,1,2 
at the MS detection stage. 
The efficient separation provided by the glycan profiling also 
allows the exact linkages of carbohydrate residues to be 
assigned, benefiting from the distinguishable LC-retention and 
gas-phase fragmentation behaviors exhibited by the structural 
isomers. As exemplified by the glycan G2FS (5,4,1,1), 3 struc-
tural isomers could be identified by matching with the accurate 
masses and the calibrated chromatographic retention times 
from the library (Table S3). </p>

<p>Resolving other types of modification enhancing mAb 
micro-heterogeneity </p>

<p>Next, using a similar workflow, we characterized 7 mAbs 
approved for human use with high resolution native MS to 
complement previously performed analyses of their released 
glycans. 
25 Use of intact protein samples instead of the released 
glycans increases not only the total MW of the analytes, but 
also increases the overall heterogeneity of the sample molecules 
due to the presence of other modifications, as exemplified in 
Fig. 2. To best extract the non-N-glycosylation-induced hetero-
geneity, we additionally measured the N-deglycosylated format 
of these intact mAbs. As illustrated by 3 examples, mAb back-
bones can undergo different types of modification that can 
occur to various extents (Fig. 2). Upon removal of the N-gly-
can, trastuzumab exhibits a quite uniform MW, suggesting 
minimal other modifications, and complete C-terminal Lys 
processing (Fig. 2A). In sharp contrast, both infliximab and 
bevacizumab exhibit a broad range of intact masses, resulting 
largely from incomplete C-terminal Lys processing and multi-
ple glycation events, respectively (Fig. 2B, C). 
Taking advantage of its relatively monodisperse protein 
backbone, the glycosylation profiling for trastuzumab appears 
to be nearly as straightforward as for the IgG4-Dhinge mutants. 
However, as the carbohydrate content of the intact IgG1 mole-
cule originates from 2 glycan chains, the analysis at the glycan 
level is needed to determine the detailed glycan composition. 
Based on the MW and relative abundances of individual N-gly-
can chains determined at the released glycan level, we simu-
lated the distribution of MW of the intact mAb assuming 
random pairing of the 2 glycan chains, and compared it with 
the experimentally measured native MS spectrum. In this spec-
trum 14 unique MWs corresponding to different glycan com-
positions could be assigned (Fig. 2A, Fig. S1), including both 
abundant glycans, such as 6,8,2,0 (G0F/G0F), 7,8,2,0 (G0F/ 
G1F), 8,8,2,0 (G0F/G2F or G1F/G1F), and lower abundant gly-
cans, such as 6,6,0,0 to 10,8,2,2. As illustrated in Fig. 3A, a high 
correlation coefficient (R D 0.92) was obtained between the 2 
sets of data, demonstrating the validity of direct profiling of the 
paired glycan composition on IgGs by native MS. However, 
since in the native MS data a single composition may originate 
from multiple possible combinations of glycan pairs, analysis at 
the intact protein level alone is insufficient to determine the 
contribution of each pair. Also, it is noteworthy that the 
assumption of random glycan pairing we made for the simula-
tion may not represent the actual situation, 
38 which could </p>

<p> 
Y. YANG ET AL. </p>

<p>contribute to the remaining differences in abundance between 
the measured and simulated data sets. 
Clipping of the C-terminal Lys occurs to a variable extent in 
most mAb products. Although manufacturers usually consider 
these variants to have no considerable effect on the potency or 
safety profile, a recent study demonstrated that C-terminal Lys 
may interfere with the ordered oligomerization of IgG at the 
cell surface, leading to suboptimal C1q binding and CDC of 
opsonized cells. 
14 Providing an alternative to charge-based sep-
aration techniques such as isoelectric focusing (IEF) electro-
phoresis (either capillary-or slab-based) and ion exchange 
chromatography, 
39,40 MS analysis of deglycosylated mAb 
allows simple evaluation of the amount of C-terminal Lys 
retained (0, 1 or 2, annotated as K0, K1 and K2, respectively). 
Unlike trastuzumab whose C-terminal Lysine residues were 
completely processed (i.e., only K0), infliximab displayed K0, 
K1 and K2 variants in comparable abundances (Fig. 2B, lower 
panel), resulting in a relatively complicated mass spectrum 
even in its deglycosylated form (Fig. 2B, upper panel). Based on 
the MW and distribution of the K0, K1 and K2 backbones, we 
were able to determine the compositions and abundances of 
the N-glycan chain pairs attached to infliximab, by subtracting </p>

<p>the contributions of K0, K1 and K2 backbones according to 
their ratios (Fig. 2B, upper panel). The extracted quantitative 
profile of infliximab is consistent with a previous study using 
capillary electrophoresis (CE), 
41 demonstrating the comparable 
effectiveness of native MS in separating charge variants of 
mAbs. 
Glycation caused by exposure of mAb to reducing sugars is 
another common type of modification that occurs either under 
physiologic conditions or during cell culture. 
42,43 In many cases, 
glycation alters the charge profile of pharmaceutical products 
and may thus affect its quality. 
44,45 Because the net contribution 
of a monosaccharide to the total MW of protein is equivalent 
regardless of its site of attachment through a glycan chain or to 
the backbone, in the intact-MW analysis the removal of N-glyco-
sylation is required to distinguish the glycation from the 
extended N-glycosylation. Indeed, although the glycosylated for-
mat of bevacizumab showed a profile similar in heterogeneity to 
trastuzumab, removal of the N-glycans demonstrated a signifi-
cantly higher extent of glycation for bevacizumab (»1.3 copies 
of hexose residues on average) (Fig. 2C, lower panel). 
As a non-enzymatic process, glycation introduces a reducing 
sugar at a primary amine on the protein, either the lysine (Lys) 
side-chain epsilon amino group or the a-amino N-termi-
nus. 
46,47 While the precise localization of glycation sites </p>

<p>Figure 2. Resolving N-glycosylation and other types of modification increasing 
mAb micro-heterogeneity on therapeutic mAbs. (A) Deconvoluted native MS spec-
tra of N-glycosylated and deglycosylated trastuzumab, revealing only minor modi-
fications besides N-glycosylation. (B) Deconvoluted native MS spectra of infliximab 
revealing incomplete C-terminal lysine processing of this mAb. The annotations of 
the glycoforms are color-coded according to the number of clipped Lysine resi-
dues. (C) Deconvoluted native MS spectra of bevacizumab suggesting 1-4 hexose 
residues are still attached after N-deglycosylation revealing the occurrence of 
extensive glycation (annotated with the green dots). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Comparison of experimental and simulated spectra. For trastuzumab (A) 
and bevacizumab (B), the experimental deconvoluted intact protein mass spectra 
(blue) are compared with the simulated spectra, based on the detected quantita-
tive profile of N-glycosylation and/or other backbone modifications (red). The cor-
relation between data sets is evaluated by means of Pearson Correlation and is 
0.92 for trastuzumab and 0.95 for bevacizumab. For bevacizumab, simulation 
excluding the contribution of glycation (white) results in a significantly lower cor-
relation coefficient (R D 0.69). </p>

<p>MABS </p>

<p>
requires the analysis at the peptide level using a bottom-up 
approach, 
48-51 the distribution of glycated mAbs and the aver-
age glycation level are unique information provided by analysis 
at the intact protein level. Based on the distribution of glycan 
chains profiled at the glycan level, the MW of protein backbone 
and the glycation profile measured at the intact protein level, 
we simulated a profile reflecting the overall heterogeneity 
including contributions from both glycosylation and glycation, 
and compared the simulated profile with the experimental pro-
file (Fig. 3B). The consistent patterns of the profile envelopes 
(R D 0.95) demonstrates the accuracy of profiling results of 
individual types of modifications, and the validity of reconstitu-
tion of overall heterogeneity using these data. We made another 
simulation, now excluding glycation, as shown in Fig. 3B. The 
resulting simulated spectrum exhibited a distinct peak distribu-
tion compared with the experimental MS data and the correla-
tion decreased from 0.95 to 0.69, demonstrating the effect of 
glycation on the overall heterogeneity of this mAb molecule. </p>

<p>Monitoring the global structural integrity of mAbs </p>

<p>Because some of the studied mAbs had been stored for 
extended periods and their expiration date had passed, we 
examined the global stability and structural integrity of the 
samples, using native MS as primary read-out. Next to the full 
mAb structures (denoted L(2)H(2)g(2) where L, H and g 
denote the light, heavy, and glycan chains, respectively) we also 
detected mAb-like products lacking the light chains or one or 2 
glycan chains. Even for the structurally most stable trastuzu-
mab, which exhibited the least structural heterogeneity of the 
mAbs studied here, we detected a low abundant species lacking 
one full N-glycan chain (L(2)H(2)g(1); Fig. 4A). The profile of 
the retained N-glycan chain resembles the distribution of the 
ensemble of glycan chains profiled for the overall population of 
trastuzumab (Fig. S2). Such single site-glycosylation was 
detected for all investigated mAbs, with the relative abundance </p>

<p>ranging from 0.8% to 2.8% (Table 1). Singly glycosylated IgGs 
have been shown to display a decrease in thermal stability, C1q 
binding affinity, Fc gamma receptors (FcgRs) binding affinity 
and ADCC. </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>Among the mAb samples stored for long periods, bevacizu-
mab and ofatumumab exhibited additional partial loss of their 
light chains. For bevacizumab, we detected species missing 
both light chains, with 2, 1 or 0 N-glycan chains attached. 
Notably, in both cases, no mAb molecules lacking only one 
light chain were observed, suggesting the removal of the light 
chains is not a random or sequential process (Fig. 4B). Species 
of low abundance lacking both light chains were also detected 
in ofatumumab, yet no further glycan loss was observed 
(Fig. S3). In healthy mammals, failure of light chain association 
usually results in rapid intracellular degradation of the heavy 
chains due to the inefficient transport from ER to Golgi, </p>

<p>53,54 </p>

<p>preventing the expression of heavy chain antibodies (L(0)H 
(2)). The production of natural L(0)H(2) with VH/CH1 
domains partially removed was found in humans with H chain 
disease. 
55 All the L(0)H(2) species observed in this work 
retained heavy chain integrity, implying that the absence of 
light chains is likely the result of degradation. The exact nature 
of the reactions responsible for such release of the light chain 
remains to be investigated. We rule out in-source dissociation 
of the products during the MS measurement, since no free light 
chain ions were detected under the gentle ionization conditions 
of data acquisition. In addition, the charge density carried by 
the L(0)H(2) species is in line with the empirical expectation, </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>suggesting these species are not the products of gas phase frag-
mentation. 
57 Native MS provides a convenient means to char-
acterize the heterogeneity-inducing degradation products of 
proteins in solution without any front-end separation. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Here, we demonstrated that glycoprotein analysis at the intact 
protein and released glycan level using high-resolution native 
MS and targeted glycan profiling, respectively, can provide 
mutually consistent information on the composition and abun-
dance of glycoprotein proteoforms. However, careful </p>

<p>Figure 4. mAb structural integrity probed by native MS at the intact protein level. 
(A) Native mass spectrum of trastuzumab, which populates predominantly the 
intact format L(2)H(2)g(2) (blue; L, H and g denote light chain, heavy chain and N-
glycan chain, respectively, with numbers indicated in the parentheses) and margin-
ally the single site-glycosylated format L(2)H(2)g(1) (orange). (B) For bevacizumab, 
in addition to the 2 formats detected in (A), the light-chain-free species with 2, 1 
and 0 N-glycan chains attached (green, red and purple, respectively) are detected. 
Relative abundances of each species are estimated using summed ion intensities 
corresponding to all detected charge states, with data normalized to the ensemble 
of species and plotted on a logarithmic scale in the insets. </p>

<p>Table 1. Key characteristics of the therapeutic mAbs investigated. </p>

<p>ID </p>

<p>Number 
of glycan 
chains </p>

<p>Number of 
glycoforms 
assigned </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Single site-
glycosylation 
(%) </p>

<p>Light 
chain 
loss </p>

<p>C-
terminal 
K 
retained </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>Glycation 
level </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Panitumumab 
2 
12 
2.8 
ND 
ND 
&lt; 0.05 
Rituximab 
2 
19 
1.6 
ND 
ND 
&lt; 0.05 
Bevacizumab 
2 
-
1.6 
17.3 
ND 
1.3 
Trastuzumab 
2 
14 
2.0 
ND 
ND 
&lt; 0.05 
Infliximab 
2 
-
0.8 
ND 
54.7 
&lt; 0.05 
Ofatumumab 
2 
12 
1.9 
17.7 
ND 
&lt; 0.05 
Eculizumab 
2 
11 
1.6 
ND 
ND 
&lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>a Number of glycoforms assigned by the complementary approaches. Confident 
assignments of Bevacizumab and Infliximab via measurements at the intact level 
are hampered by the co-occurence and interference with other backbone 
modifications. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Calculated as </p>

<p>A K1 
ð ÞC 2£A K2 
ð Þ 
2£ A K0 
ð ÞC A K1 
ð ÞC A K2 
ð Þ 
ð </p>

<p>Þ , where A K n 
ð Þis the abundance of K n species. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Reported as the average copies of monosaccharide residues attached to the mAb. 
A minimum abundance of 5% of the singly glycated species (relative to the non-
glycated species) was set as the threshold for calculation. </p>

<p> 
Y. YANG ET AL. </p>

<p>optimization and proper data processing are needed to mini-
mize the artifacts induced in either approach. Both methods 
provide highly complementary data, but also have their own 
niche. The multiple-dimensional separation of glycoforms and 
the tandem MS data gathered by targeted profiling of released 
glycans enables the differentiation of structural isomers, as well 
as elucidation of the linkages within carbohydrate residues. 
Native MS analysis at the intact protein level provides a global 
snapshot of the glycoform distribution with high confidence, 
and can concomitantly reveal co-occurring modification on the 
protein, such as truncations and glycations. 
In the combined analysis of a sample panel of model pro-
teins that included aged therapeutic mAbs, we demonstrated 
the power of using these hybrid MS-based approaches concom-
itantly. The combined analysis provided detailed structural 
information, both qualitative and quantitative, and better 
resolved the overall heterogeneity caused not only by N-glyco-
sylation, but also by C-terminal Lys processing, glycation, sin-
gle site-glycosylation, and loss of specific polypeptide chains. A 
comparison of simulated and experimental data, using dedi-
cated mathematical algorithms, allowed the heterogeneity to be 
further assessed and cross-validated. Both approaches provide 
reasonable high-throughput because they are compatible with 
automated sampling, and neither of them requires any time-
consuming stages. Therefore, we conclude that the combination 
of these 2 workflows will provide an ideal platform to measure 
micro-heterogeneity, not only in IgGs, but also in all other kind 
of industrial and plasma glycoproteins. </p>

<p>Materials &amp; methods </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>The monoclonal hinge-deleted IgG4 antibody (IgG4-Dhinge-
WT) and its mutants (Y407A, Y407E, Y407Q and Y407K) used 
in this study were gifts from Genmab (Utrecht, The Nether-
lands). These proteins were expressed in HEK-293F cells and 
purified as described previously. 
32 The 7 therapeutic mAbs used 
in this work (with specifications are listed in Table S1) were 
kind gifts from the UC Davis Medical Center, all representing 
expired batches (lot number unknown). PNGase F was obtained 
from Roche (Indianapolis, USA). Dithiothreitol (DTT) was pur-
chased from Sigma-Aldrich (Steinheim, Germany). </p>

<p>High-resolution native MS analysis using an Orbitrap EMR </p>

<p>Prior to native MS measurement, the aqueous environment of 
all mAb stock solutions (IgG4-Dhinge antibodies were pre-
pared in PBS; the powder of therapeutic mAbs was reconsti-
tuted in Milli-Q water) were substituted with 150 mM aqueous 
ammonium acetate (pH adjusted to 7.5 using ammonium 
hydroxide) by ultrafiltration using a 10 kDa cut-off filter 
(Merck Millipore, Germany). Protein concentrations were mea-
sured by UV absorbance at 280 nm and adjusted to 2-3 mM for 
native MS injection. PNGase F was used to remove the N-gly-
cans following the procedure supplied by the manufacturer. 
1-3 uL of samples loaded in home-made gold-coated boro-
silicate capillaries were directly infused into an Exactive Plus 
Orbitrap instrument with extended mass range (EMR) </p>

<p>(Thermo Fisher Scientific, Germany) using an m/z range of 
500-10,000 Th. The voltage offsets on transport multi-poles 
and ion lenses were manually tuned to achieve optimal trans-
mission of protein ions at elevated m/z. Nitrogen was infused 
in the higher-energy collisional dissociation (HCD) cell at a gas 
pressure of 6-8 £ 10 
¡10 bar. MS parameters were adjusted as 
follows: spray voltage 1.2-1.3 V; source fragmentation 30 V; 
source temperature 250 
C; collision energy 30 V; resolution (at 
m/z 200) 17,500. The instrument was mass-calibrated using CsI 
clusters, as described previously. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>The raw mass spectra were deconvoluted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Protein 
Deconvolution</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v2.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Thermo Fisher Scientific</rs>, Germany) and 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">BioAnalyst</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">v1.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">AB/Sciex</rs>, Canada). The deconvoluted data 
were further processed as described previously to solve the com-
position of glycosylation and other possible PTMs. 
29 Average 
MW values of individual carbohydrate residues used for MW 
calculation include: hexose/mannose/galactose (Hex/Man/Gal) -
162.1424 Da; N-acetylhexosamine/N-acetylglucosamine (Hex-
NAc) -203.1950 Da; deoxyhexose (Fuc) -146.1430 Da; N-ace-
tylneuraminic acid (Neu5Ac, Sia) -291.2579 Da; N-
glycolylneuraminic acid (Neu5Gc) -307.2573 Da. </p>

<p>Targeted N-glycan profiling using nanoLC-Chip-Q-TOF MS </p>

<p>N-glycans were released from the proteins before the analysis 
using a nanoLC-chip-Q-TOF MS system. The release, purifica-
tion, injection, data acquisition and analysis of N-glycan were 
performed following the described previously protocols. 
25 In 
brief, N-glycans were released from reduced mAb by PNGase F 
digestion, followed by solid phase extraction (SPE) purification, 
chemical reduction by NaBH 4 , and SPE again for the removal 
of reductant. Purified N-glycans were then loaded to Agilent 
nanoLC-chip-Q-TOF analyzed with the exact same condition 
of a previously reported human serum N-glycan structural 
library. A mixture of serum N-glycans standard was prepared 
and analyzed together with mAb N-glycans to calibrate chro-
matographic retention times in the serum N-glycan library as 
described previously. 
34 Structures of N-glycan were identified 
by matching with accurate masses and calibrated chro-
matographic retention times from the library. </p>

<p>Intergrative data construction of pseudo native MS 
spectrum </p>

<p>We perform in silico data construction to simulate a zero-
charge, native MS spectrum based on the masses and relative 
abundances of glycans identified using targeted glycan profil-
ing, the basic principle of which has been described previ-
ously. 
35 The data construction is achieved based on the 
following 3 elements: 1) the mass of the mAb backbone; 2) the 
masses and relative abundance of the glycans identified by tar-
geted glycan profiling; and 3) extra modifications on mAb 
backbone. 
To compare the simulated result with the native MS spectra, 
the native MS spectra (acquired in profile mode) are pre-proc-
essed by convoluting the ESI spectrum to a zero-charge state 
spectrum using the <rs id="software-2" type="software">Protein Deconvolution</rs> package (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Thermo Fisher Scientific</rs>). Subsequently, the standard Pearson </p>

<p>MABS </p>

<p>
correlation is performed to evaluate the data generated from 
the 2 platforms. </p>

<p>Disclosure of potential conflicts of interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>Y.Y. and A.J.R.H. are supported by the EU funded ITN project ManiFold, 
grant 317371. A.J.R.H. is further supported by the European Union Hori-
zon 2020 program FET-OPEN project MSmed, grant 686547, and the 
research and innovation program RELENT, grant 668036. This work was 
further supported by The Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research 
(NWO) via the Roadmap Initiative Proteins@Work (project number 
184.032.201), and the TOP-Punt Grant 718.015.003 for A.J.R.H. </p>

<p>ORCID </p>

<p>Guanbo Wang 
http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5468-8993 
Albert J. R. Heck 
http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2405-4404 </p>



<p> 
Y. YANG ET AL. </p>



<p>MABS </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>