<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5400067" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The integrated chronic disease management (ICDM) model was introduced as a response to the 
dual burden of HIV/AIDS and non-communicable diseases (NCDs) in South Africa, one of the first 
of such efforts by an African Ministry of Health. The aim of the ICDM model is to leverage HIV pro-
gramme innovations to improve the quality of chronic disease care. There is a dearth of literature 
on the perspectives of healthcare providers and users on the quality of care in the novel ICDM 
model. This paper describes the viewpoints of operational managers and patients regarding quality 
of care in the ICDM model. 
In 2013, we conducted a case study of the seven PHC facilities in the rural Agincourt sub-district in 
northeast South Africa. Focus group discussions (n ¼ 8) were used to obtain data from 56 purpos-
ively selected patients 18 years. In-depth interviews were conducted with operational managers 
of each facility and the sub-district health manager. Donabedian's structure, process and outcome 
theory for service quality evaluation underpinned the conceptual framework in this study. 
Qualitative data were analysed, with <rs id="software-1" type="software">MAXQDA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">2</rs> software, to identify 17 a priori dimensions of 
care and unanticipated themes that emerged during the analysis. 
The manager and patient narratives showed the inadequacies in structure (malfunctioning blood 
pressure machines and staff shortage); process (irregular prepacking of drugs); and outcome (long 
waiting times). There was discordance between managers and patients regarding reasons for long 
patient waiting time which managers attributed to staff shortage and missed appointments, while 
patients ascribed it to late arrival of managers to the clinics. Patients reported anti-hypertension 
drug stock-outs (structure); sub-optimal defaulter-tracing (process); rigid clinic appointment system 
(process). Emerging themes showed that patients reported HIV stigmatisation in the community 
due to defaulter-tracing activities of home-based carers, while managers reported treatment of </p>

<p>chronic diseases by traditional healers and reduced facility-related HIV stigma because HIV and 
NCD patients attended the same clinic. 
Leveraging elements of HIV programmes for NCDs, specifically hypertension management, is yet 
to be achieved in the study setting in part because of malfunctioning blood pressure machines and 
anti-hypertension drug stock-outs. This has implications for the nationwide scale up of the ICDM 
model in South Africa and planning of an integrated chronic disease care in other low-and middle-
income countries. </p>

<p>Many low-and middle-income countries (LMICs) are witnessing an 
increasing burden of chronic non-communicable diseases (NCDs) 
(WHO 2010). Chronic conditions include all health problems that 
require ongoing management for at least six months encompassing 
NCDs (e.g. hypertension), but also expanding to include HIV 
(WHO 2002). This is due to the growing recognition of the trans-
formation of HIV to a chronic condition as a result of rapidly ex-
panding Antiretroviral Treatment (ART) resulting in increasing life 
expectancy (UNAIDS 2011). 
Chronic non-communicable diseases are responsible for two-
thirds of all mortalities worldwide with 80% of these deaths occur-
ring in LMICs (WHO 2014a). It is estimated that the annual number 
of deaths from NCDs will increase to 55 million by 2030 (WHO 
2013b) and Africa will have the greatest increase by 27% (WHO  2008b). Since the beginning of the HIV/AIDS epidemic, over 78 mil-
lion people have been infected with the virus and 39 million people 
have died of HIV-related causes (WHO 2015). In 2011, nearly 70% 
of the 34 million people living with HIV (PLWHIV) worldwide 
resided in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) (WHO, 2015). Thirty six mil-
lion deaths due to chronic diseases could have been averted globally 
by 2015 if health systems were strengthened and small set of inter-
ventions were directed towards whole populations and high-risk in-
dividuals (Beaglehole et al. 2007). 
In 2008, NCDs accounted for 29% of all deaths in South Africa 
(WHO 2011) and in 2012, mortalities due to NCDs had increased 
to 43% (WHO 2014b). The increase in NCD-related mortalities in </p>

<p>South Africa may be attributed to the rising prevalence of NCDs 
which is an outcome of improved life expectancy (Mayosi et al.  2009) in part due to the increased roll-out of Antiretroviral 
Treatment (ART). The increasing burden of NCDs in South Africa 
(Tollman et al. 2008) is occurring against the background of the 
gradually declining but persisting HIV infection with a prevalence 
rate estimated at 10% in the general population in 2014 (Statistics 
South Africa 2014), one of the highest in Africa. These numbers pre-
sent the urgent necessity to address the dual burden of HIV and 
NCDs in South Africa. 
Chronic disease services are fragmented with the HIV pro-
gramme vertically controlled and administered in a 'silo' within the 
health system (Kawonga et al. 2013). Although the achievements of 
vertical programmes have been widely acknowledged (the smallpox 
eradication programme is a case in point) (Unger et al. 2003), these 
programmes address only a fraction of the need for healthcare; cre-
ate duplication; lead to inefficient facility utilisation by recipients; 
and may lead to gaps in care (Brown 2001). In confronting the chal-
lenges posed by vertical programmes, Margaret Chan, the Director 
General of the World Health Organization (WHO) stated emphatic-
ally: 'We need a comprehensive, integrated approach to service de-
livery. We need to fight fragmentation' (Chan 2007). 
The WHO defines integrated healthcare as 'the organisation and 
management of health services so that people get the care they need, 
when they need it, in ways that are user-friendly, achieve the desired 
results and provide value for money' (WHO 2008a). Following evi-
dence that integrated chronic disease care improves patient health </p>

<p>Key Messages </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>An integrated chronic disease management (ICDM) model was initiated as a national pilot in 2011 in selected primary 
health care (PHC) facilities in South Africa to leverage an established HIV treatment programme for improving quality 
of care for non-communicable diseases (NCDs). This study was a novel evaluation of a major initiative of the national 
department of health, one of the first of such efforts by an African ministry of health. </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>An in-depth perspective of the quality of care in the ICDM model was assessed from the viewpoints of healthcare pro-
viders and users using Avedis Donabedian's structure, process, and outcome theoretical framework for evaluating the 
quality of healthcare. The manager and the patient narratives showed the inadequacies in structure (malfunctioning 
blood pressure machines and staff shortage); process (irregular prepacking of drugs); and outcome (long waiting 
times). Patients reported anti-hypertension drug stock-outs; sub-optimal defaulter-tracing; and rigid clinic appointments. 
Managers thought there was reduced HIV stigma because HIV and NCD patients attended the same clinic. </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>These findings suggest that the purpose for which the ICDM model was initiated -to use the HIV programme as lever-
age for scaling up services for NCDs -is yet to be achieved. This has implications for the nationwide scale up of the 
ICDM model in PHC facilities in South Africa and planning of an integrated chronic care of communicable and non-
communicable conditions in other low-and middle-income countries. </p>

<p> 
Health Policy and Planning, 2017, Vol. 32, No. 2 </p>

<p>outcomes (Janssens et al. 2007), the Joint United Nations 
Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS) recommended an integrated 
approach for chronic disease management. This approach leverages 
the innovations of the HIV programme to support or scale up ser-
vices for NCDs (UNAIDS 2011) using the building blocks described 
in the Innovative Care for Chronic Conditions (ICCC) framework 
(WHO 2002). 
In line with this recommendation, the National Department of 
Health (NDoH) in South Africa initiated the Integrated Chronic 
Disease Management (ICDM) model which uses a diagonal ap-
proach to health systems strengthening (Mahomed et al. 2014). The 
diagonal approach integrates the vertical HIV programme with the 
horizontal general health system (Knaul et al. 2015). The national 
pilot of the ICDM model commenced in June 2011 in selected PHC 
facilities in three of South Africa's nine provinces, i.e. Gauteng,  North West and Mpumalanga (NDoH 2014). This is one of the first 
of such efforts by an African ministry of health. 
The ICDM model has health facility, community and population 
components. Services in health facilities have been reorganised to im-
prove operational efficiency and quality of care. In the communities, 
ward-based PHC outreach teams provide 'assisted' self-management 
to promote individual responsibility. The population component in-
volves health promotion and screening (NDoH 2014). The priority 
areas of facility reorganization include coherence of care; reduced 
waiting time; defaulter-tracing activities; appointment systems; supply 
of critical medicines; prepacking of medication; and appropriate 
referral. In community-oriented integrated chronic disease care, an 
outreach team consisting of one professional nurse, three staff nurses 
and six community health workers operates within the community 
the clinic serves. The outreach team is responsible for 6000 individ-
uals in 1500 households (250 households per 1 community health 
worker), and is expected to manage at least 80% of defined health 
problems of the catchment population (NDoH 2014). </p>

<p>Quality of care and quality assessment </p>

<p>Several frameworks have been recommended for evaluating quality 
of care (Donabedian 1988a;WHO 2006; Hulton et al. 2000;  Parasuraman et al. 1985). However, Avedis Donabedian's model has 
been used extensively in evaluating quality of healthcare and is re-
garded as a classic conceptual framework. Avedis Donabedian 
described seven elements of quality of medical care: efficacy, effective-
ness, efficiency, equity, optimality, acceptability and legitimacy 
(Donabedian 2003). He argued that the choice and relative prioritiza-
tion of these elements should be contextual and guided by the circum-
stances in which quality of care is assessed (Donabedian 2003). 
Donabedian described the quality assessment as a triad of structure, 
process, and outcome (SPO) constructs. He defined structure as the 
factors that affect the context in which care is provided (e.g. availabil-
ity and functionality of equipment); process as the actions that make 
up healthcare (e.g. examination of patients); and outcome as the ef-
fects of healthcare on patients (e.g. waiting time). He postulated the 
relationships between SPO constructs based on the premise that good 
structure should promote good process, and good process should in 
turn promote good outcome. The SPO framework often represented 
by a chain of three boxes depicting the relationships between SPO 
constructs (Donabedian 2003) can be used to draw inferences about 
the quality of healthcare (Donabedian 1988a). 
Integrated healthcare programmes have been well researched 
quantitatively (Huntington and Aplogan 1994; Briggs and Garner  2006) from the perspective of healthcare providers and relatively 
less so from a user perspective (Briggs and Garner 2006). </p>

<p>Furthermore, differing views of healthcare providers and users have 
been reported in few quantitative surveys that assessed provider-
user perspectives and interactions on quality of integrated healthcare 
programmes (Briggs and Garner 2006). However, little is known 
about the use of a qualitative method to assess the quality of care in 
the ICDM model from the perspectives of and interactions between 
healthcare providers and users. The aim of this study was to assess 
the perspectives of healthcare providers and users and their inter-
actions regarding the quality of care in the ICDM model in PHC 
facilities in a rural South African setting, using qualitative research 
to operationalise Donabedian's theoretical framework. </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>Study setting </p>

<p>This research was conducted in PHC facilities in the rural Agincourt 
sub-district of Mpumalanga province, northeast South Africa. At the 
time of the study, the ICDM model was being implemented in 17 of 
the 38 PHC facilities in the sub-district. Seven of the 17 facilities im-
plementing the ICDM model are situated in an area covered by the 
Agincourt Health and Demographic Surveillance System (HDSS), 
which has been monitoring the population in the area for two dec-
ades. The population under surveillance in July 2011 was 90 000 peo-
ple in 16 000 households in 27 villages in which Tsonga is the most 
widely spoken language (Kahn et al. 2012). Government's develop-
ment initiatives have led to improved housing and access to potable 
water, electricity and social security grants. However, infrastructure 
in the area is still limited and unemployment rates remain high (Kahn  et al. 2007). All PHC health facilities in the Agincourt HDSS were se-
lected for the study. Three referral public hospitals that serve these 
PHC health facilities are situated 25 km to 45 km from the study area 
(Kahn et al. 2007). These primary and secondary public health facili-
ties serve socio-economically vulnerable populations in the study 
area. </p>

<p>Study design and study population </p>

<p>This qualitative study was a component of a broader mixed methods 
research project which evaluated the quality of care in the ICDM 
model and assessed the effectiveness of the model in improving pa-
tients' health outcomes in the study setting (Ameh et al. under re- view). This research was a case study of the seven PHC facilities 
implementing the ICDM model in the study area. The study popula-
tion consisted of patients 18 years and above receiving treatment for 
chronic diseases at the health facilities; seven operational managers 
(nurses-in-charge) of the selected PHC facilities; and the sub-district 
health manager. Focus Group Discussions (FGDs) were conducted 
to obtain in-depth data from multiple patients to capitalise on group 
interactions and communication regarding lived experiences based 
on provider-user interface. In-depth interviews were held for the 
seven operational managers of the health facilities and the sub-
district health manager to get the depth and breadth of providers' 
perspective on the quality of integrated chronic care and policy en-
vironment for implementing the ICDM model, respectively. </p>

<p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria for research participants </p>

<p>The ICDM model addresses the following disease categories: HIV/ 
AIDS, tuberculosis, hypertension, diabetes, chronic obstructive pul-
monary disease, asthma, epilepsy and mental health illnesses that are 
to be managed at PHC level (NDoH 2014). Considering the burden 
of chronic diseases in the study area, patients with markers of chronic 
diseases for HIV, hypertension, and diabetes in the health facilities </p>

<p>Health Policy and Planning, 2017, Vol. 32, No. 2 </p>

<p>
were eligible to participate in the study. The criteria for recruiting pa-
tients for FGDs were i) having commenced treatment for the markers 
of chronic conditions in the study area six months before the imple-
mentation of the ICDM model; ii) having participated in the exit 
quantitative interviews organised by the research team before the 
FGDs and iii) willingness to participate. Participation in the exit 
quantitative interview was a criterion for recruiting patients for FGDs 
because the broader mixed methods research was designed for the 
quantitative and qualitative components to be conducted in series 
with the exit interviews preceding the FGDs. The purpose was to use 
the exit interviews as a means of identifying patients who overwhelm-
ingly reported satisfaction or dissatisfaction with the quality of care 
in the priority areas of the ICDM model and purposively selecting 
these patients for FGDs to further explore their in-depth perspectives 
on the quality of care in the ICDM model. Patients receiving treat-
ment six months before the ICDM model was implemented were se-
lected to assess their levels of (dis)satisfaction with the quality of 
chronic disease care before and after the implementation of the 
ICDM model in efforts to gauge possible changes in the quality of 
chronic disease care that can be attributed to the ICDM model. 
Out of the 435 randomly selected patients who responded to the 
exit interviews, 70 were purposively selected for seven FGDs (i.e. 10 
patients per clinic). Ten (10) clinic defaulters were identified and 
purposively selected for FGD with at least one patient from each of 
the seven health facilities. Clinic defaulters were defined as those 
who missed three consecutive clinic appointments as was observed 
through the review of clinical records. Of the 70 selected patients, 
56 participated in the FGDs and five of the 10 defaulters partici-
pated in the FGD for clinic defaulters. Sixty one of the 80 patients 
selected for discussions participated in the FGDs giving a response 
rate of 76%: 80% for the seven FGDs and 50% for the defaulter 
FGD (Figure 1). The Exit interviews were conducted from August to 
October 2013 and preceded the FGDs to make it easy to recruit pa-
tients for the FGDs and to provide a large sampling frame from 
which prospective FGD participants were to be purposively selected. 
Prospective FGD participants were selected from all clinics during 
official working hours (8.00 am -4.30 pm local time) from Monday 
to Friday when the exit interviews were held. The FGDs were con-
ducted in November and December 2013 and were held on a 
Saturday at a time that was convenient for most of the patients. </p>

<p>The operational managers, who were also professional nurses, 
were selected for the in-depth interviews because of their roles and 
responsibilities as managers of the health facilities. These roles were 
perceived to be critical to better understanding the quality of care in 
the ICDM model than other nurses who often rotated their clinical 
duties at predetermined intervals in other service provision areas 
such as acute care, antenatal clinic, postnatal clinic and child welfare 
clinics. The sub-district health manager was interviewed in order to 
understand the policy environment for the operational implementa-
tion of the ICDM model. </p>

<p>Conceptual framework for assessing quality of care in 
the ICDM model </p>

<p>This study utilized Donabedian's SPO framework, used in Sweden 
(Kunkel et al. 2007), as it is a classic framework for evaluating the 
quality of medical care (Mitchell et al. 1998), and because the 
NDoH in South Africa adopted this framework for the ICDM im-
plementation (NDoH 2014). 
Figure 2 shows the conceptual framework for this study. In this 
article, the relationships between structure, process and outcome 
constructs are non-predictive. The postulated relationships are the-
matically assessed using qualitative analytical techniques to generate 
recommendations for policy and practice. The conceptual frame-
work indicates that, for instance, the provision of good structure 
(e.g. equipment and critical medicines) leads to a good process, (e.g. 
examination of patients) which in turn leads to good outcome (e.g. 
reduced waiting time). </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>The FGDs were preceded by the health facility patient exit inter-
views, which were conducted as a component of the broader study. 
After the exit interviews, the patients were briefed about the purpose 
and scheduled dates of the upcoming FGDs. Those who volunteered 
to participate in the FGDs were invited to do so based on the inclu-
sion criteria previously described. Seven FGDs were held for 5-9 
participants of similar age recruited from within the seven PHC 
facilities, with each session lasting 60-90 min. The purpose of inter-
viewing participants of similar age was to gain collective rather than 
individual accounts and to provide a conducive environment for the </p>

<p>Figure 1. Sampling of patients for focus group discussions </p>

<p> 
Health Policy and Planning, 2017, Vol. 32, No. 2 </p>

<p>participants to freely discuss their experiences with the health system 
without fear of being intimidated. One FGD was also held for five 
clinic defaulters from within the seven health facilities; hence, a total 
of eight FGDs were conducted. The FGDs were held in a centrally 
located neutral venue within the catchment area of the health facility 
to enable the patients to freely express and communicate their lived 
experiences with healthcare services. Finally, eight in-depth inter-
views lasting 30-40 min were conducted with the seven operational 
managers and the sub-district health manager in designated health 
facilities. 
A priori identification of the 17 dimensions of care (Figure 2) for 
which the SPO constructs were intended was undertaken by experts 
on quality of care in the study team to reflect Donabedian's defin-
itions of SPO domains and the theory of the relationships between 
SPO constructs; henceforth, referred to as themes. This approach was 
used to develop the respective topic guides. 
Of the 17 dimensions of care assessed and categorised under 
SPO themes, ten were adapted from the Patient Satisfaction 
Questionnaire (PSQ-18) (Ware et al. 1976) used as a study tool in 
the exit interviews. The remaining seven dimensions were identified 
by the study team as priority areas for improving quality in ICDM: 
supply of critical medicines, hospital referral, defaulter tracing, pre-
packing of medicines, clinic appointments, reducing patient waiting 
time, and coherence of integrated chronic disease (NDoH 2014). 
These priority areas (Figure 2) are the key components of the tools 
and systems used in the successful HIV programme that is being 
leveraged to support or scale-up services for improving the quality 
of care for NCDs (NDoH 2014). The FGD and interview guides for 
operational managers contained statements on the 17 dimensions 
that were intended to elicit healthcare providers' and users' perspec-
tives of quality of care in ICDM. The study participants were asked 
to raise their concerns about unanticipated dimensions of care not 
originally included in the topic guides. 
The first author (S.A.) ran a two-day training session with two 
experienced qualitative field workers, with at least 10 years of field 
experience in the HDSS. During the training, the field workers were </p>

<p>briefed about the purpose of the study and on how to administer the 
structured topic guide to the patients. One field worker audiotaped 
and moderated the discussions while the other took notes during the 
FGDs which were held in Tsonga. The first author conducted and 
audiotaped the in depth interviews with the operational managers 
and sub-district health manager according to the respective topic 
guides written in English language. </p>

<p>Quality assurance </p>

<p>The FGD audio recordings were translated and transcribed into 
English by two qualitative field workers. A third qualitative field 
worker in the Agincourt HDSS validated the transcriptions by listen-
ing to two of the eight audiotapes and also translated them into 
English. A comparison of the early and latter transcriptions showed 
no major differences in the participants' experiences and opinions 
regarding the dimensions of quality of care in the ICDM model. 
Similar procedures were used to assure data quality for the in-depth 
interviews. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>The transcribed FGDs and interviews were thematically analysed 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">MAXQDA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">2</rs> software. A combined deductive and inductive 
approach was used for data analysis. The deductive analysis was 
based on the pre-identified themes focusing on the in-depth inquiry 
of the dimensions of care in the ICDM model. Inductive analysis 
was undertaken for an emerging theme that was not anticipated at 
the outset and not included among the 17 dimensions of care cov-
ered in the topic guide. The data were coded by S.A. and verified by 
the co-authors through the reading and re-reading of the quotes. 
A code book was developed based on recurring pre-identified 
themes and emerging themes. Reliability of the coded data was veri-
fied through discussions of inconsistent codes among co-authors 
until agreement was reached. </p>

<p>Ethical considerations </p>

<p>Written informed consent was obtained from the study participants 
after reading out the content of the information sheet and explaining 
the purpose of the FGD. Because confidentiality during the FGDs 
could not be guaranteed, participants chose whether to disclose the 
chronic disease(s) for which they were receiving treatment in the 
health facilities and were urged to respect the privacy of fellow dis-
cussants who voluntarily disclosed this information. Anonymity was 
guaranteed by removing all identifiable information from the narra-
tives reproduced in study reports. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Healthcare provider and user perspectives on the quality of care in 
the ICDM model are discussed below using Donabedian's structure, 
process and outcome framework for health service evaluation. 
Verbatim quotes are used to illustrate the analysis. </p>

<p>Socio-demographic characteristics </p>

<p>There were 61 black adult South African participants (43 females 
and 18 males) in the eight FGDs. The race of the FGD participants 
reflects the dominance of black people in the study setting. The gen-
der imbalance of the 61 participants in the FGDs (43 (70%) females 
and 18 (30%) males) corroborates the gender constitution of the par-
ticipants of a population-based research in the study setting (female 
vs. male: 70% vs. 30%) to determine the predictors of health care </p>

<p>Figure 2. Conceptual framework of quality of care in the ICDM model* </p>

<p>*The 17 dimensions of care and their intended constructs used to operation-
alise Avedis </p>

<p>Donabedian's theory in the ICDM model in Bushbuckridge sub-district in 2013 </p>

<p>(The dimensions in red colour are the priority areas of the ICDM model) </p>

<p>Health Policy and Planning, 2017, Vol. 32, No. 2 </p>

<p>
utilisation (Ameh et al. 2014) and the gender composition of the 
345 patients who participated in the exit interviews from which the 
FGD participants were recruited (female vs. male: 81% vs. 19%) 
(Ameh et al. under review). 
All seven operational managers who participated in the in-depth 
interviews were female professional nurses with an age range of 40-
55 years and 15-20 years of nursing experience. A 55-year-old male 
senior sub-district health staff was interviewed on behalf of the sub-
district health manager because the latter could not be reached due 
to busy administrative schedules. </p>

<p>Structure-related dimensions of care </p>

<p>Critical medicines </p>

<p>Hypertension patients reported receiving monthly prescribed medi-
cation. However, there were occasional drug stock-outs in some 
health facilities and participants expressed frustration with irregular 
supplies of anti-hypertension medicines. </p>

<p>When my treatment is not available at the clinic they do tell me 
that this month my treatment is not available; then they gave me 
the one that is available that day. When the treatment is not out 
of stock, they do give me all the treatment that I am getting every 
month [Respondent 2 (man), Clinic 1]. </p>

<p>Equipment </p>

<p>Hypertension patients expressed concerns about the lack of func-
tioning blood pressure (BP) machines in the facilities. Patients re-
ported expectations of BP checks by nurses while taking anti-
hypertensive drugs. They also described their experiences of travel-
ling to other health facilities to assess their BP. </p>

<p>We have stayed for two to three months without BP machine. 
They were just giving us treatment without knowing whether our 
BP was high or not. . . . It gives us problem when we have to 
travel to another clinic to check our BP [Respondent 1 (woman), 
Clinic 7]. </p>

<p>An operational manager acknowledged that her facility did not 
have functioning BP cuffs (a component of BP equipment) and other 
medical equipment. This nurse expressed frustration in her ability to 
provide quality care to patients due to lack of equipment. She fur-
ther indicated that a project manager working in a non-
governmental research institution donated BP cuffs to her health fa-
cility to enable nurses to monitor patients' BP more effectively. </p>

<p>[Laughs] what can I say? I think three weeks back Mr. X [a pro-
ject site manager at institution Y] was here to give us different 
kinds of BP cuffs because we didn't have them. I really can't say 
that the clinic has all the different medical equipment to take 
care of all those patients or bring quality nursing care to the pa-
tients [Operational Manager, clinic 3]. </p>

<p>Process-related dimensions of care </p>

<p>Prepacking of drugs </p>

<p>The ICDM manual stipulates that nurses prepack patients' medi-
cines before their arrival at the facilities to reduce patient waiting 
times during consultations. Nurses' inability to regularly prepack 
medicines was reported as a factor militating against their ability to 
effectively deliver services. An operational manager reported that 
prepacking of drugs before appointments was sometimes done, but 
that staff shortage and unavailability of prepacking bags were </p>

<p>obstacles to regular prepacking of drugs. Hence, prepacking was 
sometimes done during or after consultations or was not done in in-
stances when there were no prepacking bags. </p>

<p>Sometimes we do prepacking the day before clinic appointment. 
Sometimes when we are short-staffed, we are unable to do it. 
Another challenge is that we don't have prepacking bags 
[Operational Manager, Clinic 4]. </p>

<p>Appointment system </p>

<p>Patients reported a rigid appointment system in which they were un-
able to access services for sudden-onset illnesses occurring outside 
scheduled appointment dates. </p>

<p>When your date is still far you can't go to the clinic even when 
you have other illnesses [Respondent 2 (woman), Clinic 3]. </p>

<p>In the ICDM model, patients with chronic diseases are given ap-
pointment dates for their next clinic visits. These predetermined 
scheduled appointments are usually on a monthly basis for unstable/ 
uncontrolled cases [e.g. BP &gt; 140/90 mmHg for hypertension pa-
tients and CD4 count &lt; 350 cells/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>for HIV patients] or two 
monthly for stable/controlled cases [e.g. BP &lt; 140/90 mmHg for 
hypertension patients and CD4 count &gt; 350 cells/mm 
3 for HIV </p>

<p>patients]. 
Patients also reported that missing clinic appointments led to 
punishment through being made to wait in queues during subse-
quent visits until the nurses had attended to patients who were on 
the appointment list for that day. This resulted in long patient wait-
ing times. </p>

<p>When they [nurses] shout at us it is because . . . they tell you to 
come today at nine, you find that you miss your appointment 
date and come at another day. When I missed my appointment 
and went there the other day, they [nurses] delayed me even 
when I arrived at the clinic early. All the patients that came after 
my arrival collected their treatment and went home and left me 
at the clinic. And I don't think they [nurses] are wrong because 
you [patient] are the one who missed your appointment 
[Respondent 2 (woman), Clinic 1]. </p>

<p>Unprofessional behaviour of clinical staff </p>

<p>Patients recognised the role of home-based carers [HBCs] in patient 
management such as assisting patients with domestic chores and de-
livering drugs from the facilities. However, some patients reported 
that HBCs breached confidentiality by disclosing their clinical infor-
mation to persons other than those entrusted with patient care and 
management. </p>

<p>I told them [HBCs] not to come to my house any more. When I 
tell them something, I expect them to report it to their seniors 
and not to tell the whole community. So when I'm sick, I will go 
to the clinic [Respondent 5 (woman), Clinic 2]. </p>

<p>Patients reported how the behaviours of healthcare providers 
influenced their perception of quality of care in the health facilities. 
In the quote below, a patient expressed dissatisfaction with the pro-
fessional conduct of a nurse. </p>

<p>Eish! [A popular exclamation in South Africa often used to de-
scribe a frustrating or appalling experience] there is a new nurse 
that arrived at the clinic. She is fat and tall [Man 1 and 2 nod in 
agreement]. When you are in the consulting room with her [refer-
ring to the new nurse], she will send you to go and take the tablets 
in the locker [referring to where drugs are kept]. Do I know the </p>

<p> 
Health Policy and Planning, 2017, Vol. 32, No. 2 </p>

<p>tablets I have to use? Sometimes she will send a cleaner to go and 
take the tablets; does the cleaner know the treatment? I have seen 
it several times and am saying that these nurses are going to kill us 
[Respondent 2 (woman), Clinic 4]. </p>

<p>Outcome-related dimensions of care </p>

<p>Reduced stigma in the health facilities </p>

<p>An operational manager reported that the ICDM model conferred 
an advantage on PLWHIV because of the reduced stigma due to 
non-segregation of patients managed for chronic disease in the same 
clinic. Non-separation of patients or consultation rooms in the clin-
ics implied that it may not have been easy for patients to identify 
who was being managed for HIV/AIDS; hence, the reduced HIV-
related stigma. </p>

<p>Previously we were grouping them according to their diseases, 
but now they are put together. Patients living with HIV/AIDS are 
satisfied because they are mixed with those who are having 
hypertension and diabetes (Operational Manager, Clinic 6). </p>

<p>Waiting time </p>

<p>Patients and operational managers attributed long patient waiting 
time in facilities to several factors. Patients noted the late arrival of 
filing clerks and nurses; long morning prayer sessions before com-
mencement of clinical duties; staff meetings; prolonged tea or lunch 
breaks; nurses giving preferential treatment to friends or relatives 
who skip the queues; and nurses engaging in trading activities (e.g. 
buying and selling of household products) in the consultation room 
during consultation hours. </p>

<p>We arrive at six in the morning and stay outside the gate and 
they will open the gate at eight o'clock. Sometimes they will start 
to check you at one o'clock. You will get your treatment very late 
despite early arrival at the clinic [Respondent 2 (man), Clinic 7]. </p>

<p>Operational managers by contrast reported long waiting times 
due to staff shortage and patients missing appointments. </p>

<p>We are booking a certain number of patients and if that number 
becomes extra because of those who didn't come on their ap-
pointment dates, you find that we have a lot of patients and they 
[who missed previous appointments] have to wait (Operational 
Manager, Clinic 1). </p>

<p>The overall findings show that the aim of leveraging the HIV 
programme for NCD care, such as hypertension, may be yet to be 
achieved due to anti-hypertension drug stock-outs; malfunctioning 
blood pressure machines; sub-optimal defaulter tracing activities; 
rigid clinic appointments; and a dysfunctional prepacking system. 
Long patient waiting time was also reported as problematic by the 
service providers and users. </p>

<p>Emerging themes </p>

<p>Staff shortage </p>

<p>Both users and providers identified staff shortage as a key challenge 
impacting the delivery of quality care in facilities. A manager 
described making mistakes due to work overload arising from staff 
shortage, and a patient described how staff shortage led to work-
related exhaustion and 'complicated' behaviour of nurses, negatively 
impacting the provision of quality services. </p>

<p>I'm alone and I have to do all the programmes with the staff 
nurse. I'm to manage the deliveries, antenatal clinics, integrated 
chronic disease clinic, minor illness, immunization and all those 
programmes. I can't! . . . . Sometimes if I am forced to do the 
work alone I end up making some stupid mistakes (Operational 
Manager, clinic 3). </p>

<p>Today, they [referring to nurses] are two and they get tired and 
become complicated [Respondent 1 (woman), Clinic 6]. </p>

<p>Unaffordable transportation costs </p>

<p>Patients reported unaffordable transportation costs as a barrier to 
accessing clinics or when referred by nurses from clinics to doctors 
in the hospitals. In a rural South African setting with high 
unemployment levels, people's reliance on paid jobs as a means of 
livelihood affects health-seeking behaviour. </p>

<p>If I am working for someone and that person doesn't pay me, I 
have to wait until the person pays me before I have to go to the 
clinic or hospital [Respondent 4 (woman), Clinic 1]. </p>

<p>HIV stigmatisation due to home visits by 
home-based carers </p>

<p>An operational manager described a situation in which community 
members stigmatised ill people who were visited by HBCs. 
Community members were said to have perceived persons visited by 
HBCs to have HIV/AIDS, and that patients responded by not allow-
ing HBCs visit their homes. This reported stigma constitutes a bar-
rier to accessing home-based health services. </p>

<p>Home-based carers are not accepted. They [patients] are thinking 
that other people [community members] will think that they are 
HIV positive and that is why the HBCs are coming to visit them 
[Operational manager, Clinic 1]. </p>

<p>Use of traditional healers </p>

<p>An operational manager noted that patient behaviours presented 
challenges for HBCs to trace clinic defaulters who use traditional 
medicine in places far away from where they [patients] received bio-
medical care. Furthermore, the use traditional medicine for the treat-
ment of chronic diseases could potentially interfere with the use of 
modern pharmaceuticals. </p>

<p>We [nurses] have tried our level best even to trace patients who 
missed their appointment using HBCs and by telephone calls. 
Some of our patients move around seeking care in many places 
because they believe in both western civilization treatment and 
traditional healers. You find that a patient is receiving treatment 
in village X and the next thing you will hear from the relative 
that he (the patient) is at village Y (about 50 Km away from vil-
lage X) because there is a traditional healer there who is busy 
treating him. That gives us a problem in tracing them 
[Operational manager, Clinic 3]. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study shows that the innovative ICDM model provides non-
segregated services for chronic disease patients and appears to have 
benefited PLWHIV due to reduced HIV-related stigma. This was 
also reported in a pilot study in Cambodia (Janssens et al. 2007;  UNAIDS 2011). However, the ICDM model did not show benefits 
for patients receiving treatment for hypertension as a result of occa-
sional stock-outs of anti-hypertension drugs and malfunctioning BP </p>

<p>Health Policy and Planning, 2017, Vol. 32, No. 2 </p>

<p>
machines. This was corroborated in the quantitative component of 
the broader study which showed suboptimal blood pressure (BP) 
control (Ameh et al. under review). The widely reported suboptimal 
BP control could impact the WHO's target for the 25% reduction in 
premature mortality (i.e. deaths among persons 30-69 years of age) 
due to NCDs by 2025 (WHO 2013a). 
The inability to deliver effective hypertension services in the 
ICDM model can be attributed to policy and health system factors. 
Notable among these is the failure of the Innovative Care for Chronic 
Conditions (ICCC) framework to significantly incorporate the com-
plexities associated with multiple morbidities; (Oni et al. 2014) South 
Africa's public health sector vertical HIV programme not being ad-
ministratively integrated with the horizontal general health system; 
(Kawonga et al. 2013) and the lack or breakdown of equipment to 
measure blood pressure (Thorogood et al. 2004). Most chronic dis-
eases are presently managed in separate disease-specific public health 
facilities in South Africa (Oni et al. 2014) and suboptimal care has 
been reported for hypertension patients receiving treatment in these 
facilities (Steyn et al. 2008). This justifies the prioritization of optimal 
management of non-communicable diseases in the ongoing PHC re-
engineering and ICDM model implementation (NDoH 2013) within 
the ICCC framework forming the cornerstone of these reforms 
(NDoH 2013). 
Defaulter-tracing activities in the study setting were not done by 
the ward-based PHC outreach teams, but by volunteer HBCs who 
receive little or no remuneration. This was because the pilot of the 
PHC outreach team was being implemented in other communities in 
the Bushbuckridge Municipality at the time this study was con-
ducted. Although the HBCs visited homes to do domestic chores 
and trace clinic defaulters, they were not generally accepted because 
the patients feared lack of confidentiality often arising from the dis-
closure of their disease status to community members by HBCs. 
Unprofessional conduct of some nurses was identified as a bar-
rier to the effective implementation of the ICDM model. Some pa-
tients reported nurses were involved in buying and selling of 
household products during official working hours. These illicit trad-
ing activities which are not related to professional work could po-
tentially contribute to long patient waiting time in the clinics. 
Furthermore, preferential treatment to health workers' friends and 
relatives could also lead to patient dissatisfaction with services and 
prolonged waiting time. Therefore, educational programmes need to 
be targeted at healthcare workers to change their attitudes and be-
haviours regarding provision of quality services to patients. 
Emerging theme were staff shortage and patients' inability to 
afford the cost of transportation to the PHC health facilities and hos-
pitals on referral as previously reported in our study setting (Goudge  et al. 2009). Therefore, financial constraint remains a barrier to ac-
cessing free services and treatment in public PHC facilities in South 
Africa. Other emerging themes were HIV stigmatization due to home 
visits by HBCs and use of traditional healers. Ill persons did not wel-
come HBCs into their homes because of the stigma attached to such 
visits which is often associated with chronic illness specifically HIV/ 
AIDS. These practices have been reported in the literature in an inte-
grated HIV/TB programme elsewhere in South Africa (Uwimana  et al. 2012). The reported HIV-related stigma in the communities is a 
barrier to accessing home-based health services and has the potential 
to negatively impact the effectiveness of the model in improving pa-
tients' health outcomes. Defaulter tracing was reportedly challenging 
because of combined use of PHC facilities and traditional healers in 
communities far away from where they received biomedical care. 
This pattern of health-related migration in the study setting has been 
attributed to the use of plural healing such as use of biomedicine, </p>

<p>traditional healers, prophets and churches as viable alternatives 
for the treatment of stroke-like symptoms and other diseases 
(Thorogood et al. 2007). The use of traditional healers may interfere 
with pharmaceutical treatment which could result in poor health out-
comes of patients. 
The healthcare provider-user interface reported in this study cor-
roborates the multi-and bi-directional relationship between struc-
ture, process, and outcome constructs postulated by Donabedian 
(Mitchell et al. 1998). Staff shortage and the lack of prepacking bags 
(structure factors) made it challenging for nurses to prepack patients' 
drugs (process factor) which in turn led to long patient waiting time 
(outcome factor). Patients who missed clinic appointments (process 
factor) felt nurses were unfriendly (process factor) to them during 
their subsequent clinic visit, and punished them by delaying their 
consultation process (outcome factor). These dynamics contributed 
to avoidable long waiting periods (outcome factor), aside from other 
health facility-related factors, such as the late arrival of staff; long 
morning prayer sessions before commencement of clinical duties; 
morning staff meetings; and prolonged tea/lunch breaks. Healthcare 
providers and users consistently reported long waiting periods in the 
health facilities as has been described in other resource-constrained 
LMICs (Babirye et al. 2014). This could be a reflection of operational 
challenges such as performance of multiple tasks, staff shortage, and 
work overload (Briggs and Garner 2006). 
A substantive finding in terms of how quality of care is concep-
tualised relates to the diverging views of providers and patients. 
Constraints experienced by each group (e.g. providers working under 
pressure due to chronic staff shortage and patients struggling to ac-
cess services or their lack of trust in service providers) result in pro-
nounced provider-patient disconnect. Hulton's framework of quality 
of care, which incorporates the user's experience of care with care 
provided (Hulton et al. 2000, Hulton et al. 2007) is an interactional 
notion of quality of care and underscores the need to address these 
challenges through people-centred health systems research. 
The purpose of leveraging HIV programme for NCDs, especially 
hypertension, is yet to be achieved in PHC health facilities in the 
study setting due to malfunctioning blood pressure machines and 
anti-hypertension drug stock-outs. This has implications for the na-
tionwide scale up of the ICDM model in South Africa and planning 
of integrated chronic care of communicable and non-communicable 
conditions in Swaziland and Ethiopia (Rabkin et al. 2012) and 
Uganda (Schwartz et al. 2015). </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations </p>

<p>The limitations of our study have been categorised as general and 
specific. Although qualitative methods do not necessarily require 
probability sampling techniques, the patients were not randomly se-
lected and may not be representative of the chronic disease sub-
population in the selected health facilities. Furthermore, the qualita-
tive methods used to preclude the establishment of cause and effect 
relationship as would be established in quantitative research. 
Instead, explanations of phenomena are developed through eliciting 
lived experiences and systematising these into valid forms of know-
ledge on the relationships between problems and their causes. 
Specifically, this study was conducted in a rural sub-district of South 
Africa and our findings may not be generalized to PHC facilities in 
semi-urban and urban areas in the provinces where the pilot of the 
ICDM model is ongoing. Future research is needed to understand 
how the ICDM model works in urban PHC facilities. 
Although the qualitative methods used do not establish cause and 
effect relationships, they help to identify contextual factors that </p>

<p> 
Health Policy and Planning, 2017, Vol. 32, No. 2 </p>

<p>could contribute to understanding the quality of care in the ICDM 
model for the purpose of generating recommendations for policy and 
practice. Despite these limitations, our methodology was well suited 
for the study because of the dearth of contextual qualitative data on 
provider and patient perspectives on the quality of care in the ICDM 
model. To our knowledge, this is the first application of 
Donabedian's theory, using qualitative methods, to assess the quality 
of care in the ICDM model in Africa. The use of a combined deduct-
ive and inductive approach in data collection was a major strength. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>A key finding was that patients reported anti-hypertension drug 
stock-outs (structure); sub-optimal defaulter-tracing activities (pro-
cess); and a rigid clinic appointment system (process). Nurse and pa-
tient narratives showed the inadequacies in structure 
(malfunctioning blood pressure machines and staff shortage); pro-
cess (irregular prepacking of drugs); and outcome (long waiting 
times). There was discordance between managers and patients re-
garding reasons for long patient waiting time which managers 
attributed to staff shortage and missed appointments, while patients 
ascribed it to late arrival of managers to the clinics. Emerging 
themes showed that patients reported HIV stigmatization in the 
community due to defaulter-tracing activities of home-based carers, 
while managers reported treatment of chronic diseases by traditional 
healers in the community and reduced facility-related HIV stigma 
because HIV and NCD patients attended the same clinic. </p>

<p>Acknowledgement </p>

<p>This work was supported by (i) Medical Research Council/Wits Rural Public 
Health and health Transitions Research Unit (Agincourt) South Africa, 
through the Wellcome Trust, UK (Grant Numbers 058893/Z/99/A, 069683/ 
Z/02/Z); (ii) Fogarty International Centre of the National Institutes of Health 
fellowship (Grant number 1D43TW008330-01A); and (iii) African Doctoral 
Dissertation Research Fellowship. The content is solely the responsibility of 
the authors and does not necessarily represent the official view of the 
National Institutes of Health and other funders. This paper was facilitated by 
attending the Wits School of Public Health Thanda Ukubhala writing retreat 
funded by the Faculty of Health Sciences Research Office. The authors ac-
knowledge the contributions of Chimaraoke Izugbara, Rachel Caesar, Lenore 
Manderson, Faith Mambulu and Latonya Wilson for writing support. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was pro-
vided by the Fogarty International Centre of the National Institutes of Health 
fellowship (Grant number 1D43TW008330-01A). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Health Policy and Planning, 2017, Vol. 32, No. 2 </p>



<p>
 
Health Policy and Planning, 2017, Vol. 32, No. 2 </p>

</text></tei>