<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5476471" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Interleukins have been well described in mice and humans. In large domestic </p>

<p>animals the situation is drastically different and there is still a need for further 
researches aiming at identifying all the homologous interleukins and comparing </p>

<p>their functions among species. We performed here a bibliometric analysis of all </p>

<p>interleukins described in the literature in various large animal species to identify 
what is known so far and to underline where there is a need for new studies. Using </p>

<p>indicators such as H index but also M quotient, A index, G index, GH ratio, and 
HG index we ranked 39 interleukins identified so far in bovine, caprine, equine, </p>

<p>ovine, and porcine, the main large domestic animals. Indexes and ratio under </p>

<p>investigations were higher for IL1, IL2, IL4, IL5, IL6, IL8, IL10, IL12, and IL18 
than for other interleukins, particularly in bovine and porcine species and to a </p>

<p>certain extent in equine species. Recently discovered interleukins presented low 
values for the different indexes, quotient, and ratio. Even some "old" interleukins </p>

<p>showed low values highlighting the need for further developments in comparative </p>

<p>immunology. For instance an interleukin such as IL4 demonstrated variation in its 
functions between species. In conclusion, this study provides the first bibliometric </p>

<p>analysis dedicated to large domestic animal interleukins and underlines the need 
for more studies to fully determine the structure and the functions of interleukins in </p>

<p>other mammal species. </p>

<p>Immunology has known major developments in the last years. In mammals, most </p>

<p>of our knowledge comes from the murine model and human. Besides, in large </p>

<p>domestic animals the situation is quite different (Montoya and Meurens, 2015; 
Summerfield, 2009). Indeed, basic or applied immunology studies dealing with </p>

<p>large domestic animals constitute less than 5% of the publications in major 
immunology journals. However, some specialized journals like Veterinary </p>

<p>Immunology and Immunopathology, Veterinary Microbiology and Developmental </p>

<p>and Comparative Immunology are dedicated to animal immunology and infectious 
diseases and several studies about large domestic animal immunology were </p>

<p>published in the last years. </p>

<p>Interleukins are proteins enabling communications between the various cell </p>

<p>populations. Some of them such as interleukin 1 (IL-1) and IL-6 have pro-
inflammatory actions while some other ones such as IL-4, IL10 and IL-37 are </p>

<p>clearly anti-inflammatory compounds making them interesting targets to diagnose </p>

<p>or treat various conditions (Carinci et al., 2016; Conti et al., 2017; Lin et al., 2016; 
Mahdavi-Roshan et al., 2016; Wu et al., 2016). The word interleukin, created in </p>

<p>1979, derives from Latin Inter-("between, amid") and −leukin because many 
interleukins are produced by leukocytes and stimulate these cells (di Giovine and </p>

<p>Duff, 1990). Logically the first interleukin to be identified was interleukin 1 (di </p>

<p>Giovine and Duff, 1990). Since then many interleukins were described in various 
species including human, mouse and large domestic animals. However, papers </p>

<p>related to specific interleukins in a determined species are not so frequent and there 
are significant variations in the knowledge of interleukins between species. </p>

<p>The measure of the scientific productivity and quality of a particular researcher has 
been widely used by managers, research institutions, and funding agencies to </p>

<p>evaluate professional promotions or to rank projects and grants. Created in 2005 </p>

<p>(Hirsch, 2005), the H index, which is the number of published papers (N) that have 
been cited N or more times, became quickly popular to assess researchers at </p>

<p>different stages of their career. Originally used to assess scientists the H index was 
then proposed to evaluate countries (Csajbók et al., 2007), journals (Braun et al., </p>

<p>2006), and even, more recently, animal and human pathogens (Cox et al., 2016; </p>

<p>Díaz et al., 2016; Ducrot et al., 2016; McIntyre et al., 2011). Regarding pathogens 
these studies were particularly interesting in identifying the hot and/or neglected </p>

<p>topics. Because H index has some drawbacks most of these studies also used other 
bibliometric indicators such as A index, G index, HG index, GH ratio, M quotient, </p>

<p>and Deciphering Citations Organized by Subject (Dcos) index which measure the 
contribution that a given author, institute or country would have in a specific </p>

<p>research area or subject (Díaz et al., 2016; Ducrot et al., 2016). A simultaneous use </p>

<p>of the various indicators could provide a more accurate view of the situation for a </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>specific subject. So far, no studies applied bibliometric indexes to immune </p>

<p>mediators such as cytokines, interleukins, and chemokines. With the development 
of comparative immunology there is a need for complementary approaches to </p>

<p>assess what has been done and what needs to be done. </p>

<p>In the current study, interleukins were compared using H index scores and other </p>

<p>indexes in 5 large domestic animals including four artiodactyls (bovine, caprine, 
ovine, and porcine) and one perissodactyl (horse). This bibliometric analysis </p>

<p>enabled us to globally assess the present situation regarding research on </p>

<p>interleukins in large animals. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Selection of interleukins and animal species </p>

<p>The current study comprises all identified interleukins so far in mice and humans 
(IL1 to IL39). Because some interleukins, especially the first ones, have been </p>

<p>described under various names, searches were done using several names, 
synonymous, and acronyms used for every interleukins. Most of these alternative 
"names" are listed in Table 1. Some interleukins such as IL12 and IL23 required </p>

<p>further bibliometric analyses as they are heterodimeric and share the subunit p40. 
Furthermore, other interleukins such as IL1 or IL17 are described as families of </p>

<p>compounds instead of unique molecules. Indeed, IL1 family includes, amongst 
others, IL1α, IL1β, and IL1Ra and IL17 family IL17A to F. Because in many </p>

<p>publications, especially the oldest ones, there was no information regarding the </p>

<p>exact nature of the considered interleukin we did not distinguish between 
themselves the different members of the interleukin families and instead </p>

<p>considered the families as a whole. Regarding selected animal species we focused 
especially on large domestic animal which are mostly livestock animal (see </p>

<p>Table 2). </p>

<p>2.2. Calculation of the H index for the interleukins in the 
selected species </p>

<p>To calculate H index we used the software package developed by Web of Science </p>

<p>(WOS). The work was carried out from May 2016 to June 2016 included 
("Thomson Reuters: Overview-Web of Science v.5.22.2," 2016). All searches were </p>

<p>restricted to the title of articles published in English between 1956 and 2016. </p>

<p>Because there are multiple synonyms, names, and acronyms for interleukins and 
large domestic animal names, the selection of the terms used in the multiple </p>

<p>searches had to be done very carefully. Various sources such as general English 
dictionaries, NCBI databases, Immunology text books were used to generate a list </p>

<p>of terms (see Tables 1 and 2). For instance, for pig we used the terms: "porcine or </p>

<p>pig or Sus scrofa or swine or boar or piglet or sow" and for IL2: IL2 or IL-2 or </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Table 1. Interleukin names or abbreviations used to perform the analysis. </p>

<p>IL1 or IL-1 or interleukin 1 or lymphokine activating factor or lymphocyte-activating factor or B-cell activating factor or catabolin or endogenous pyrogen or epidermal cell-derived thymocyte-
activating factor or mononuclear cell factor </p>

<p>IL2 or IL-2 or interleukin 2 or T cell growth factor or T cell stimulating factor </p>

<p>IL3 or IL-3 or interleukin 3 or multipotential CSF or mast cell growth factor or P cell stimulating factor or histamine-producing cell stimulating factor or hematopoietic growth factor </p>

<p>IL4 or IL-4 or interleukin 4 or B cell growth factor 1 or B cell stimulatory factor 1 </p>

<p>IL5 or IL-5 or interleukin 5 or T cell-replacing factor or BCGF II or eosinophil colony stimulating factor or eosinophil differentiation factor </p>

<p>IL6 or IL-6 or interleukin 6 or IFN B2 or BSF2 or hybridoma growth factor or plasmocytoma growth factor or myeloid blood cell differentiation-inducing protein or hepatocyte stimulating factor </p>

<p>IL7 or IL-7 or interleukin 7 or LP-1 or lymphopoetine 1 </p>

<p>IL8 or IL-8 or interleukin 8 or neutrophil activating factor or neutrophil chemotactic factor or NAP-1 or GCAP or CXCL-8 or CXCL8 </p>

<p>IL9 or IL-9 or interleukin 9 or TCF III or TCF3 </p>

<p>IL10 or IL-10 or interleukin 10 or CSIF or cytokine synthesis inhibitory factor </p>

<p>IL11 or IL-11 or interleukin 11 </p>

<p>IL12 or IL-12 or interleukin 12 or NKSF or natural killer cell stimulatory factor or CLMF or cytotoxic lymphocyte maturation factor </p>

<p>IL13 or IL-13 or interleukin 13 or P600 </p>

<p>IL14 or IL-14 or interleukin 14 or HMW-BCGF </p>

<p>IL15 or IL-15 or interleukin 15 </p>

<p>IL16 or IL-16 or interleukin 16 or LCF </p>

<p>IL17 or IL-17 or interleukin 17 or CTLA-8 or CTLA8 </p>

<p>IL18 or IL-18 or interleukin 18 or IGIF or interferon gamma inducing factor </p>

<p>IL19 or IL-19 or interleukin 19 </p>

<p>IL20 or IL-20 or interleukin 20 </p>

<p>IL21 or IL-21 or interleukin 21 </p>

<p>IL22 or IL-22 or interleukin 22 or IL-TIF </p>

<p>IL23 or IL-23 or interleukin 23 </p>

<p>IL24 or IL-24 or interleukin 24 or IL-10B or MDA7 or melanoma differentiation association protein 7 </p>

<p>IL25 or IL-25 or interleukin 25 or IL-17E or SF20 </p>

<p>IL26 or IL-26 or interleukin 26 </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 
2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>IL27 or IL-27 or interleukin 27 </p>

<p>IL28 or IL-28 or interleukin 28 or IFNλ2 or IFNλ3 or interferon lambda </p>

<p>IL29 or IL-29 or interleukin 29 or IFNλ1 or interferon lambda </p>

<p>IL30 or IL-30 or interleukin 30 or IL27p28 or IL27 p28 </p>

<p>IL31 or IL-31 or interleukin 31 </p>

<p>IL32 or IL-32 or interleukin 32 or NK4 </p>

<p>IL33 or IL-33 or interleukin 33 or NF-HEV </p>

<p>IL34 or IL-34 or interleukin 34 </p>

<p>IL35 or IL-35 or interleukin 35 </p>

<p>IL36 or IL-36 or interleukin 36 </p>

<p>IL37 or IL-37 or interleukin 37 </p>

<p>IL38 or IL-38 or interleukin 38 </p>

<p>IL39 or IL-39 or interleukin 39 or IL-23p19/Ebi3 </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>





<p>interleukin 2 or T cell growth factor or T cell stimulating factor. Consequently, 
especially for interleukins, possible changes in the terminology have been taken </p>

<p>into consideration. The Boolean options "AND", "NOT", and "OR" were used to </p>

<p>organize the terms of the search. For instance, in pigs, "NOT" option was 
necessary to exclude all the papers related to the guinea pig. Besides H index, the </p>

<p>first year of publication and the total number of citations were also collected. 
Searches were performed twice by two independent operators. </p>

<p>2.3. Comparisons of the H index with others indices </p>

<p>To assess and challenge H index other indicators − M quotient, A index, G index, </p>

<p>GH ratio, and HG index-were generated for all the interleukins in the different 
species. M quotient was created to overcome the fact that H index was directly </p>

<p>proportional to the career length of the scientists who were assessed. Hirsch </p>

<p>proposed that index to enable a comparison of scientists with different scientific 
career length (Hirsch, 2005). To calculate this indicator H index is divided by the </p>

<p>number of years of research activity. Since there are also significant differences 
regarding the year of the first description of interleukins, M quotient was also </p>

<p>applied to interleukins to evaluate "research productivity outcome" of interleukins. </p>

<p>To do that, H index of a given interleukin was divided by the number of years since 
publication for the oldest paper included in the H index. A index is the mean </p>

<p>number of citations of the papers included in H index (Jin et al., 2007). This 
indicator was generated simultaneously to H index using <rs type="software">WOS</rs> software package. </p>

<p>To calculate the G Index a new list of publications for each interleukins was 
required. This list was generated applying same terms than for H Index </p>

<p>calculations. G index is as described by his creator: "For a set of papers, ranked </p>

<p>in decreasing order of the number of citations they received, G index is the highest 
number of papers that received H or more citations" (Egghe, 2006). Then, using G </p>

<p>and H indexes, the HG index was established (HG = √(HxG)) (Alonso et al., 
2010). This index reduces the influence a highly cited paper has on the G index. </p>

<p>The GH ratio (GH = G/H) shows the relative increase of G index with respect to H </p>

<p>(Egghe, 2006). </p>

<p>Table 2. Terms used to describe the different large animal species. </p>

<p>Bovine 
or Bos Taurus or calf or cow or cattle or bull or heifer </p>

<p>Caprine 
or goat or billies or kids or wethers or Capra hircus or Capra aegagrus </p>

<p>Equine 
or horse or Equus ferus or mare or stallion or foal or yearling </p>

<p>Ovine 
or sheep or ewe or Ovis aries or mouton or lamb or ram </p>

<p>Porcine 
or pig or Sus scrofa or swine or boar or piglet or sow </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>2.4. Statistical analyses </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were done using computer software <rs id="software-3" type="software">Prism 6</rs> for Windows </p>

<p>(version <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">6.02</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA</rs>). One-Way ANOVA was </p>

<p>used to detect differences amongst the groups. To account for the non-normal 
distribution of the data, all data were sorted by rank status prior to ANOVA </p>

<p>statistical analysis. Tukey's test was used to compare the means of the ranks among 
the groups. P values less than 0.05 were considered significant. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Article selection and first analyses </p>

<p>Fig. 1 presented the number of articles found for every interleukin and animal </p>

<p>species. The number of articles is highly variable between interleukins (Fig. 1) and 
within them between species (supplementary Table 1). Because of this high </p>

<p>variation, no statistically significant differences were identified between the 39 
interleukins. However, it can still be observed that a higher number of articles were </p>

<p>found for interleukins 1-18 than for other interleukins. After an analysis of the </p>

<p>found articles, we identified several articles which were not linked to the 
interleukin assessed in the search. These articles can be considered as false positive </p>

<p>results and were consequently excluded for further analyses. A list of selected 
articles was then constituted for each interleukins and each species (supplementary </p>

<p>Table 1). In some cases, the difference in the number of articles was quite </p>

<p>important. For instance, in bovine IL1, from 271 articles, 223 were kept. These 
differences illustrate the necessity to check articles one by one. </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 1 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Number of articles found for all the interleukins considered in our study. Variable numbers of 
articles were identified for the 39 interleukins. For each interleukin, all the selected species were </p>

<p>considered together. The search was carried out in titles and was based on specific terms listed in </p>

<p>Tables 1 and 2. Median values +/− SD are presented. </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>3.2. Top 9 interleukins in terms of selected papers </p>

<p>The 9 interleukins showing the highest number of selected papers are presented in </p>

<p>Fig. 2. For each interleukin, the total number of selected papers is provided at the </p>

<p>centre of the circles and the contribution of each species is illustrated using 
different colours. Additionally, for each species, the year of publication of the first </p>

<p>published paper is identified. Except for IL5, most of the time bovine and porcine 
species are dominating. The number of selected papers rapidly decreased from IL1-</p>

<p>IL2-IL6 to IL12-IL18-IL5 and only 26 articles were kept for IL5, essentially from </p>

<p>equine and ovine species. The first articles were published in the seventies for IL1 
in small ruminants and less than ten years ago in the caprine species for IL18. </p>

<p>Globally interleukins were first studied in the pigs and in the bovine species and 
later in ovine, caprine and equine species. </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 2 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Total number of papers and first years of publication in the different species for the 9 
interleukins (IL1, IL2, IL4, IL5, IL6, IL10, IL12, IL18) presenting the highest numbers of selected </p>

<p>articles. For the 9 interleukins, the contribution of every species is visualized using different colours and </p>

<p>for every single species the first year of publication of an article dealing with the interleukin is provided. </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>3.3. Interleukin ranking by H index </p>

<p>Regarding H index, the distribution of the interleukins was similar to the one observed </p>

<p>for the number of selected papers. Highest H indexes were observed in IL1, IL2, IL4, </p>

<p>IL6, IL8, IL10, IL12, and IL18 with again a strong variation between species (Fig. 3 
and supplementary Table 1). The two highest H indexes were calculated for IL1 in </p>

<p>bovine (36) and porcine species (32) meaning that 36 papers about bovine IL1 were 
cited more than 36 times and 32 papers dealing with porcine IL1 were cited more than </p>

<p>32 times (supplementary Table 1). For recently identified interleukins, H indexes </p>

<p>were low or equal to 0. For instance, for IL23, H index was 3 in horse, 2 in sheep and 1 
in bovine. Again and similarly to previous observations with the number of selected </p>

<p>papers, the variation between species within interleukins H index was high preventing 
statistical comparisons to reach significance. </p>

<p>3.4. Assessment of H index, M quotient, A index and G index for 
the main interleukins in domestic large animal species </p>

<p>In Fig. 4, the different indexes and M quotient are presented for the most studied </p>

<p>interleukins in the different species. H index is high in all the species, especially in 
porcine and bovine species, except caprine species (Fig. 4). IL5 was one of the only </p>

<p>interleukins where H index was higher (5) in the horse than in other species (Fig. 4 
and supplementary Table 1). Horse IL4 H index was also quite high compared to </p>

<p>other species H indexes. Regarding IL18, it can be observed there is no H index for </p>

<p>ovine species. With the calculation of M quotient, the ranking of the interleukins is 
modified and IL6 and IL10 have globally higher values than IL2 and IL4 for instance </p>

<p>(Fig. 4). The differences between species are lower regarding M quotient than H 
index. For instance, ovine IL1 M quotient or equine IL10 M quotient are very similar </p>

<p>to their bovine and porcine counterparts. Moreover, some interleukins such as IL22, </p>

<p>IL23, and IL29 showed values ≥0.4 in bovine, ovine, and porcine species </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 3 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Global H index for the 39 interleukins in the different species. A global H index for all the 
species is illustrated for every interleukins. Median values +/− SD are presented. </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>(supplementary Table 1). A index is the mean number of citations of the papers 
included in H index. Using that index, IL6, IL8, and IL12 in the different species show </p>

<p>increased values compared to H index graph. Differences between H and A indexes </p>

<p>within one species are important. For instance, bovine IL5 H index is low (2) 
compared to ovine or horse (4 and 5, respectively) but IL5 A indexes are similar </p>

<p>between these 3 species (24 to 25.75). On the contrary the profile of G index graph is 
extremely similar to what was observed with H index graph showing the same </p>

<p>ranking for the main interleukins (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>3.5. GH ratio and HG index for the main interleukins in 
domestic large animal species </p>

<p>GH ratio shows the relative increase of G index with respect to H. Using that ratio, 
the main change is observed for caprine and ovine species which are presenting </p>

<p>values similar to the ones observed in other species (Fig. 5). Regarding the HG </p>

<p>index, an index established to reduce the influence of highly cited papers on the G 
index, the profile was very similar to what was observed with G index (Fig. 5) </p>

<p>suggesting a low influence of highly cited papers. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Most of our knowledge about interleukins is coming from studies performed in </p>

<p>rodents and humans. However, several papers dedicated to these important </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 4 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 4. H index, M quotient, A index, and G index in the different species for the 9 interleukins (IL1, 
IL2, IL4, IL5, IL6, IL10, IL12, IL18) presenting the highest numbers of selected articles. For the 9 </p>

<p>interleukins, the contribution of every species is visualized using different colours. </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>mediators in other mammal species such as large domestic animals have been 
published in the last thirty years. In order to get a view of the situation at the front </p>

<p>of the research about interleukins in large domestic animals, it was decided to carry 
out a bibliometric analysis on all the identified interleukins in the five major large </p>

<p>animal species, i.e. bovine, caprine, equine, porcine, and ovine. To perform the </p>

<p>bibliometric analyses, different indicators were measured including H index which 
is generally used to assess researcher productivity (Hirsch, 2005). </p>

<p>The first issue we had to overcome in the bibliometric analysis was related to the </p>

<p>accuracy of the performed search using the selected terms for each individual </p>

<p>interleukin. Indeed several searches in our study generated biased lists potentially 
introducing errors. Some interleukins names have changed since their discovery, </p>

<p>even sometimes repeatedly (see for instance IL1 in Table 1). Consequently in order </p>

<p>[ ( F i g . _ 5 ) T D $ F I G ] </p>

<p>Fig. 5. GH ratio and HG index in the different species for the 9 interleukins presenting the highest 
numbers of selected articles. For the 9 interleukins, the contribution of every species is visualized using </p>

<p>different colours. </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>to obtain accurate results, search terms were modified to include a maximum of </p>

<p>alternative and/or complementary names (Table 1). A second issue was the absence 
of detection of relevant papers caused by a title choice strategy where there is no </p>

<p>mention of the involved species or interleukin. For instance, several very relevant and 
interesting studies about IL17 in bovine have been published in the last years (Rainard </p>

<p>et al., 2013; Roussel et al., 2015). However, because the species of interest was not </p>

<p>mentioned in the titles, the papers failed to be selected in our analysis. It is also 
probably the case in the other selected species of our bibliometric analysis. </p>

<p>Furthermore, molecular techniques such as RT-qPCR and microarray have been 
developed to study interleukin and others molecules involved in immunity. These </p>

<p>techniques allow the simultaneous study of many targets (23 genes in (Magiri et al., </p>

<p>2016)) in a same experiment contrary to older experimental approach like ELISA for 
instance. Thereby, it was not possible to indicate all the interleukins assessed in the </p>

<p>paper title and authors preferred to relate their study as "interleukin expression" 
(Deplanche et al., 2016), "response of immune response genes" (Magiri et al., 2016) </p>

<p>or "immune response" (Zbinden et al., 2015). It is difficult to accurately assess the </p>

<p>impact of this bias as the missed papers are by nature hidden. However, it can be 
assumed that in most of the major articles reporting studies focusing on an interleukin </p>

<p>in a particular species, there is mention of the interleukin name and the animal species 
in the article title. Thus, except for less studied interleukins, the percentage of missed </p>

<p>papers is probably lower than 10 percent. Performing the search not only based on </p>

<p>title but also on abstract and general text could have solved that problem. This 
approach was not selected since it would have generated drastically longer output list </p>

<p>with massive background. </p>

<p>Another possible error is the retrieval of several papers not related to the topic in </p>

<p>the generated list. For instance the paper entitled "Interleukin-22: a sheep in wolf's 
clothing" was dedicated to IL22 in the mouse model and did not use any sheep in </p>

<p>any experiment (Laurence et al., 2008). Similarly, a term such as kids refer to </p>

<p>juveniles of both sexes in goat and can bring many papers unrelated to goat in the 
output list. To improve the database accuracy and to minimize the impact of </p>

<p>potential mistakes all the references in the generated lists were revised one by one 
by both authors and in some searches up to 48 papers were removed (see IL1 in </p>

<p>bovine, supplementary Table 1). Because the amount of work can become quickly </p>

<p>important the research topic has to be well determined from the beginning. After 
analysis of the number of selected articles, it appears clearly that many papers have </p>

<p>been dedicated to the study of most of the first described interleukins in the 
different species assessed in our report. On the contrary when newly described </p>

<p>interleukins are considered a very low number of selected papers or even an </p>

<p>absence of papers is observed (see for instance interleukins IL19 to IL32). Since 
there is a growing interest for the development of more predictive models for the </p>

<p>study of various conditions in human biology (see for instance (Aigner et al., 2010; </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Gerdts et al., 2015; Meurens et al., 2012; Montoya and Meurens, 2015; Perrin, </p>

<p>2014)) it underlines the need for more research in comparative immunology to 
support these alternative models. The case of IL4 in pigs well illustrates the </p>

<p>requirement for further research about interleukins in other mammal species. 
Indeed, studies about porcine IL4 demonstrated a replacement of IL4 by IL13 for </p>

<p>some specific functions related to the development of monocyte derived dendritic </p>

<p>cells (Bautista et al., 2007) and no role as a stimulatory factor in the development 
of B cells for this interleukin (Murtaugh et al., 2009). We can postulate similar </p>

<p>situations for some other interleukins in other large animal species. </p>

<p>As mentioned before there is basically no paper focusing on the newly described </p>

<p>interleukins in large domestic animals. Because our bibliometric analysis was based 
on title information, we could have missed some papers dealing with these recent </p>

<p>interleukins. Indeed, this is the case for instance for porcine IL28B (Interferon λ1) and </p>

<p>IL29A (Interferon λ3) in a recent paper (Delgado-Ortega et al., 2014). In that paper, 
mRNA expressions of these two newly described interleukins were assessed but </p>

<p>because the main topic of the paper was not directly related to these interleukins or 
their characterizations we could not find it in our bibliometric research. As reagents </p>

<p>are available for these two interleukins we can postulate the existence of more </p>

<p>publications reporting data related to it. Regarding interleukins 24 to 39, only 5 papers 
were published in large domestic species, in pig, bovine, and ovine, underlining the </p>

<p>paucity of studies dedicated to new interleukins in these species. IL23 was quite an 
exception with a total of 10 publications available in all the selected animal species. It </p>

<p>is most probably linked to its major role in the Th17 response (Iwakura and Ishigame, </p>

<p>2006) which has been a hot topic recently. Moreover, the number of selected papers 
for IL23 could be slightly underestimated, especially for old papers, as this </p>

<p>heterodimeric interleukin shares p40 subunit with IL12. </p>

<p>Considering the different species separately, various trends are observed (see </p>

<p>supplementary Table 1). Indeed, even if the most studied interleukin is invariably 
IL1, there is a large variation between species regarding other interleukins. In the </p>

<p>pig, IL6 and IL10 have also been highly studied and generated several papers and </p>

<p>numerous citations. When we look at M quotient and A index, we can observe high 
values for IL10 showing the more recent interest for this interleukin particularly </p>

<p>involved in the pathogenesis of a major viral disease of the pig caused by the 
porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus (Díaz et al., 2016; Ducrot </p>

<p>et al., 2016; Lunney et al., 2016). Research on this interleukin started more than ten </p>

<p>years later than research on porcine IL1 and IL2 but accelerated in the last years 
modifying quotient and indexes. In the bovine, IL4, IL6, IL8, IL10 and IL12 were </p>

<p>particularly studied after IL1 and IL2 generating high values for H index, A index, 
and M quotient. In sheep, there are the special cases of IL13 which generated a </p>

<p>high number of citations (102 citations from 2005; A index = 55.5) and IL5 with 
11 selected articles and a A index of 25.75, more than in the others species and the </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>others interleukins (IL1, IL2, IL6, IL8, and IL10). The sheep model has been used </p>

<p>to study asthma and parasite infections which are associated to a Th2 response 
(Bao et al., 1996; Kasaian et al., 2007; Liravi et al., 2015; Pernthaner et al., 2005). </p>

<p>However, only a few papers among the selected articles concentrated most of the 
citations (100 citations for 2 articles for IL13 (Kasaian et al., 2007; Liravi et al., </p>

<p>2015) and 89 citations for 2 articles for sheep IL5 (Bao et al., 1996; Pernthaner </p>

<p>et al., 2005). In goat, highest H indexes are observed for IL2, IL4, IL10, IL1, IL6, 
and more surprisingly IL18. This interleukin has been studied for its role in the </p>

<p>modulation of ovarian steroids in the goat reproductive tract (Lei et al., 2015; Liu 
et al., 2005; Qi et al., 2012). In horses, IL4 and IL6 were particularly high after </p>

<p>IL1. Equine IL4 was associated to pulmonary diseases (Cordeau et al., 2004) and </p>

<p>IL6 to various inflammatory conditions (Barton and Collatos, 1999; Fumuso et al., 
2003). </p>

<p>The indexes, ratios and quotient used in our study illustrate different aspects of the 
bibliometric analyses such as, for instance, the interest for one specific interleukin, </p>

<p>the number of papers dedicated to it, the amount of associated citations, and the 
number of years it has been studied. As for researcher or institution evaluation, </p>

<p>simultaneous use of different indicators was needed to assess the interest of the </p>

<p>scientific community for a specific subject. For example, even if ovine IL13 H 
index was low (2), the A index (55.5) and the GH ratio (3) clearly indicated the </p>

<p>interest developed in the researcher community for this specific interleukin. 
Comparing these indicators enabled interesting observations in old interleukins. </p>

<p>For instance, M quotient revealed an important and quite recent interest for IL18 in </p>

<p>pig with papers having a higher number of citations than papers related to most 
other interleukins. In more recent interleukins, indicators failed to generate </p>

<p>comparisons as the number of selected papers was too low. </p>

<p>To our knowledge this is the first report dedicated to a bibliometric study focusing </p>

<p>on interleukins. The analysis was carried out with large domestic animal 
interleukins to get a first idea of the current situation regarding the study of </p>

<p>these immune mediators in these species. Our analysis emphasizes the need for </p>

<p>more studies dealing with comparative immunology between species. This is of 
high importance today when there are many voices asking for the development of </p>

<p>new alternative and more relevant animal models in biomedical research. </p>

<p>Declarations </p>

<p>Author contribution statement </p>

<p>Emmanuelle Moreau, François Meurens: Conceived and designed the experiments; </p>

<p>Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed </p>

<p>reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Article No~e00321 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Funding statement </p>

<p>François Meurens was supported by an establishment grant from the Région Pays </p>

<p>de la Loire (RFI Food for tomorrow-Cap aliment). </p>

<p>Competing interest statement </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary content related to this article has been published online at http://dx. </p>

<p>doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321. </p>



<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>



<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>



<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>



<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2017.e00321 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

</text></tei>