<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5414856" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Non-human primates (NHPs) are currently considered to be the non-rodent species of choice for the preclinical safety 
assessment of single-stranded oligonucleotide (SSO) drugs. We evaluated minipigs as a potential alternative to NHPs to test 
the safety of this class of compounds. Four different phosphorothioated locked nucleic acid-based SSOs (3 antisense and 1 
anti-miR), all with known safety profiles, were administered to minipigs using similar study designs and read-outs as in 
earlier NHP studies with the same compounds. The studies included toxicokinetic investigations, in-life monitoring, clinical 
and anatomic pathology. In the minipig, we demonstrated target engagement by the SSOs where relevant, and a similar 
toxicokinetic behavior in plasma, kidney, and liver when compared with NHPs. Clinical tolerability was similar between 
minipig and NHPs. For the first time, we showed similar and dose-dependent effects on the coagulation and complement 
cascade after intravenous dosing similar to those observed in NHPs. Similar to NHPs, morphological changes were seen in 
proximal tubular epithelial cells of the kidney, Kupffer cells, hepatocytes, and lymph nodes. Minipigs appeared more sensitive 
to the high-dose kidney toxicity of most of the selected SSOs than NHPs. No new target organ or off-target toxicities were 
identified in the minipig. The minipig did not predict the clinical features of human injection site reactions better than the 
NHPs, but histopathological similarities were observed between minipigs and NHPs. We conclude that there is no 
impediment, as default, to the use of minipigs as the non-rodent species in SSO candidate non-clinical safety packages. </p>

<p>Single-stranded oligonucleotides (SSO) are oligomers of syn-
thetic nucleotides, typically 12-20 bases in length and designed 
to hybridize to complementary RNA. Historically, the first key 
modification of therapeutic SSOs was the introduction of a 
phosphorothioated backbone, and more recent developments 
included modifications of the sugar moieties, eg, locked nucleic 
acids (LNAs). These modifications were shown to improve sta-
bility, target affinity and potency, and to reduce non-specific 
toxicities (Veedu et al., 2010; Vester and Wengel, 2004). Although 
numerous SSOs are currently being evaluated in clinical trials 
for various therapeutic indications, up to now only 2 SSO drugs 
have been approved (FDA Briefing Document, 2012; Perry and 
Balfour, 1999). 
Upon parenteral administration, SSOs distribute broadly and 
are rapidly cleared from the circulation. After repeated dosing, 
they tend to accumulate in tissues, with the highest levels found 
in the kidney and liver, followed by lymphoid and other tissues, 
a characteristic observed across different mammalian species 
(Geary et al., 2015). SSO-mediated toxicities are categorized into 
Watson/Crick hybridization-dependent effects, caused by on-
target effect (exaggerated pharmacology) or off-target (second-
ary) pharmacology, and potential non-hybridization related 
toxicities (Frazier, 2015). SSO accumulation-related effects, pro-
inflammatory effects or protein binding of the SSO may be exam-
ples of those hybridization-independent toxicities. In plasma, 
they may manifest as an acute and transient prolongation of co-
agulation and/or activation of the alternative complement sys-
tem, particularly following intravenous administration in the 
non-human primate (NHP), upon reaching high plasma expo-
sures (Crooke et al., 2016). In addition, renal tubular cell degener-
ation, glomerulonephritis, hepatic toxicity with increased serum 
aminotransferase activities, single cell necrosis of hepatocytes, 
as well as thrombocytopenia and injection site reactions (ISRs) 
after subcutaneous administration may be identified during pre-
clinical and/or clinical investigations (Burdick et al., 2014; 
Engelhardt et al., 2015; Frazier, 2015; Henry et al., 1997; van Meer 
et al., 2016). These toxic effects may be hybridization-dependent 
or -independent and are generally sequence-specific and related 
to tissue exposures. 
Currently, there are no specific guidelines regulating the ap-
proval process of SSO drug candidates. As they are chemically 
synthesized, international guidelines for small molecules are 
followed that require repeat-dose toxicity studies to be con-
ducted in both a rodent and non-rodent species (ICH M3[R2]) for 
advancing SSOs into the clinics. The selection of an appropriate 
animal species is essential in safety studies (Morton, 1998). Due 
to high genomic homology and pharmacokinetic similarities 
with humans, the cynomolgus monkey has been the non-
rodent species of choice for the preclinical assessment of SSO 
safety and is considered predictive for identifying potential tox-
icities in humans. 
Recent investigations have confirmed the minipig as a suit-
able alternative non-rodent model in safety studies, and there 
is evidence supporting the predictive validity of minipigs in the 
preclinical development of pharmaceuticals (Bode et al., 2010; 
Ganderup et al., 2012). The minipig shows many similarities to 
human anatomy, physiology, and biochemistry (Forster et al., 
2010). It is already widely used in the safety assessment of phar-
maceuticals for topical dermal delivery as its skin resembles the 
human skin like no other non-rodent species does (Mahl et al., 
2006). Given the high incidence of ISRs in humans receiving sub-
cutaneous administrations of SSOs (van Meer et al., 2016), and 
the limited predictivity of rats and NHPs for these local effects 
identified clinically, we set out to investigate if the minipig </p>

<p>could be a more predictive model for ISRs. To date only a scarce 
dataset on the use of the minipig in SSO safety assessment is 
publicly available. In single studies, SSOs were administered ei-
ther intradermally (Cai et al., 2012), intravitreally (Danis et al., 
2003), subcutaneously (Iyer et al., 2002), or topically (Mehta et al., 
2000). With the recent sequencing of its genome (Heckel 
et al., 2015; Vamathevan et al., 2013), the minipig may now en-
able the design of cross-species reactive SSOs and the assess-
ment of pharmacology-related adverse effects. 
Here, we aimed to characterize the minipig in comparison to 
NHPs through short-term safety studies using parenteral routes, 
and including pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profil-
ing. These studies were conducted on four LNA-based SSOs (3 
with mRNA targets and 1 targeting a microRNA) that had been 
tested in rodents, NHPs, and humans. Applying the principles of 
3Rs (Russell et al., 1959), only female minipigs were used as 
there were no gender differences in drug response reported nei-
ther in NHPs nor in humans. 
We thus have, for the first time, investigated the toxicity 
profile of these molecules in minipigs following systemic 
administration. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>LNA SSO Selection and Study Design </p>

<p>We selected three different antisense LNA SSOs with a phosphor-
othioate backbone, previously characterized in NHPs and humans 
(Durig et al., 2011; Frieden and Orum, 2008; Lee et al., 2013; 
Lindholm et al., 2012; Straarup et al., 2010; van Poelgeest et al., 2013) 
and a LNA-based microRNA antagonist, with a phosphorothioate 
backbone (Gebert et al., 2014; Hildebrandt-Eriksen et al., 2012). 
The SSOs were administered to female minipigs applying a 
study design similar to the reference NHP studies, including toxi-
cokinetic investigations, in-life monitoring, clinical, and anatomic 
pathology. In addition, immunohistochemistry, in situ hybridiza-
tion, and transmission electron microscopy (TEM) were performed 
in minipig samples to localize the SSOs in target organs, to con-
firm target engagement and evaluate changes ultrastructurally. </p>

<p>Oligonucleotides Design and Synthesis </p>

<p>The four selected molecules are phosphorothioated LNA-based 
SSOs with the following characteristics: 
RTR5001-Targets the proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin 
type 9 (PCSK9) mRNA (NCBI reference sequence: NM_174936.3) 
with the sequence 5 
0 -TGCtacaaaacCCA-3 
0 (uppercase LNA, low-</p>

<p>ercase DNA). It matches the sequence of humans and cynomol-
gus monkeys and has a single, end-standing mismatch to the 
minipig sequence. 
RTR4955-Antagonist of the Apolipoprotein B-100 (APOB) 
mRNA (NCBI reference sequence: NM_000384.2) with the se-
quence 5 
0 -GTtgacactgTC-3 
0 . It matches the sequence of humans </p>

<p>and cynomolgus monkeys and has a single, mid-standing mis-
match to the minipig sequence. 
RTR3649-A mixed LNA/DNA phosphorothioated microRNA 
122 
biogenesis 
modulator, 
with 
the 
sequence 
5 
0 -</p>

<p>CcAttGTcaCaCtCC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>. It has a full match to the human, cyno-
molgus monkey, and minipig sequences. 
RTR2996-Binds and inactivates the B-cell-lymphoma 2 
(BCL-2) oncoprotein mRNA (NCBI reference sequence 
NM_000633.2 and NM_000657.2) with the sequence 5 
0 -</p>

<p>CTcccaacgtgcgCCa-3 
0 (Stein et al., 2010) and has a single, mid-</p>

<p>BRAENDLI-BAIOCCO ET AL. | 113 </p>

<p>standing mismatch to the human, cynomolgus monkey and 
minipig sequences. 
All four LNA SSOs were synthesized according to standard 
protocols as previously described (Lindholm et al., 2012; 
Straarup et al., 2010), were characterized, and ultimately diluted 
with 0.9% NaCl to the required concentrations. LNA SSO formu-
lations contained 7% impurities, and the presence of endo-
toxins was excluded. </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Purpose-bred female Gö ttingen minipigs were supplied by 
Ellegaard (Dalmose, Denmark). The minipigs were aged between 
4 and 6 months at study start and were pair-housed in pens ap-
proximately 9 m 
2 in size. Animals were offered environmental </p>

<p>enrichment and were kept at 20 6 2 
C at a relative humidity of </p>

<p>40-80% with a 12-h light/dark cycle in a facility accredited by 
the Association for Assessment and Accreditation of Laboratory 
Animal Care International (AAALAC). Animals were allocated to 
groups, avoiding sister-sister relationships. Animals were regu-
larly monitored, offered a standard minipig diet, and tap water 
ad libitum. Only female minipigs were used as no gender differ-
ences in drug response had been reported in NHPs or humans. 
All procedures were in accordance with the respective Swiss 
regulations and approved by the Cantonal Ethical Committee 
for Animal Research. 
Clinical observations, body weight development, and food 
consumption were closely monitored throughout the study. </p>

<p>Experimental Groups </p>

<p>RTR5001 and RTR4955-Three animals per group and dose level 
received a subcutaneous dose (inguinal region, left and right al-
ternated) of 6 or 20 mg/kg RTR5001 or 8 or 24 mg/kg RTR4955, re-
spectively, on days 1, 6, 11, and 16 at a dose volume of 0.25 mL/ 
kg. Two females per compound received phosphate-buffered 
saline (PBS) and were used as concurrent controls. 
RTR3649-A subcutaneous dose (caudal to the pinna, left and 
right alternated) was administered to three females per group 
at 3, 12, and 48 mg/kg twice per week (a total of 9 doses over 4 
weeks) at a dose volume of 0.32 mL/kg. Three female minipigs 
received sterile physiological saline and were used as concur-
rent controls. Reversibility of findings was assessed after a 
4-week dosing-free period in two additional control and two 
high-dose minipigs. 
RTR2996-Three minipigs were dosed intravenously at 5, 15, 
and 45 mg/kg RTR2996 for 5 min at 2 mL/kg every other day for 
15 days. Three control females were given sterile physiological 
saline. A 14-day dosing-free period was planned in 2 additional 
control and 2 high-dose minipigs. The RT2996 dose levels for 
the minipig were reduced by 1/3 compared to NHP, aiming for 
comparable liver exposures, based on a preliminary single-dose 
pharmacokinetic study. Drug or saline were administered intra-
venously via a vascular access port (VAP) that was implanted 
approximately 4 weeks prior to the start of the study. The VAP 
was implanted in the external jugular vein, with the catheter tip 
being positioned in the vena cava cranialis. The catheter was tun-
neled subcutaneously and connected to the port chamber lo-
cated caudal to the pinna. Following the procedure, animals 
were closely monitored and received post-operative care. </p>

<p>Exposure Assessment </p>

<p>For RTR5001 and RTR4955, blood was collected for plasma expo-
sure assessment at several time points after dosing on day 1 </p>

<p>and throughout the study. For RTR3649, blood was collected up 
until 72 h and for RTR2966 up until 48 h after the first and last 
doses. In addition, liver and kidney cortex tissue samples were 
collected during necropsy. Samples were analyzed with dedi-
cated, qualified hybridization enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
assays (hELISAs) (Hildebrandt-Eriksen et al., 2012; Straarup et al., 
2010). Plasma exposure data were subjected to non-
compartmental pharmacokinetic evaluation and mean C max 
and area under the curve (AUC) values were determined. </p>

<p>Clinical Pathology </p>

<p>Blood was sampled on different occasions for assessment of a 
full set of hematology, coagulation, and clinical chemistry pa-
rameters as well as cytokines and complement. Cytokines (IFN-
a, IFN-c, IL-1b, IL-2, IL-4, IL-6, IL-8, IL-10, and TNF-a) were as-
sessed prior to dosing and at 2 and 7-8 h after dosing). For 
RTR2996, total complement activity (CH50) was assessed on day 
15 before dosing and at 0.25 h and 24 h after dosing. 
Additionally, urine was collected in a metabolic cage for 16 h 
(RTR5001 and RTR4955) or for 24 h (RTR3649 and RTR2996), be-
fore first dosing and towards the end of the dosing period. 
Hematology parameters were determined using a Sysmex 
V R XT 
instrument (Sysmex, Japan), coagulation parameters with ACL 
TOP500 (Instrumentation Laboratory, USA), and clinical chemis-
try parameters with an Advia 180 (Siemens) automated system. 
Urinary chemistry parameters were measured with an Aution 
Max 
TM AX-4280 instrument (Arkray Clinical Diagnostics, USA) </p>

<p>and an Advia 1800 (Siemens) automated system. Cytokines 
were determined by ELISA using the Porcine Cytokine 
Chemiluminescent 9-plex Array Kit on an AS0034 Imager with 
the SignaturePLUS 
TM imaging system and the <rs id="software-0" type="software">PROarray</rs> analysis </p>

<p>software (all <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Aushon SearchLight</rs>, USA) according to provider's 
instructions. In the results significantly altered parameters 
when compared with control and/or pretest values are 
presented. </p>

<p>Necropsy and Anatomic Pathology </p>

<p>All animals were sacrificed 24 h after the last dose. A complete 
post-mortem examination was performed and an extensive list 
of tissues and organs (limited list for RTR3649) were fixed by im-
mersion in 10% buffered formalin, embedded in paraffin, and 
blocked. The tissue blocks were sectioned at 5 mm, stained with 
hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E). The kidney histologic sections 
were additionally stained with Periodic acid-Schiff (PAS). Slides 
were microscopically evaluated and representative slides or 
scans from slides from NHP studies were reviewed by the same 
toxicologic pathologist. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry, in-Situ Hybridization and 
Transmission Electron Microscopy </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry-Immunohistochemistry to localize SSOs 
was performed using a Ventana Discovery XT 
V R immunostainer 
(Ventana Medical Systems, Tucson, AZ). Formalin-fixed and 
paraffin-embedded tissue sections of kidney, liver, and lymph 
nodes (3-4 lm thick) of selected animals were de-paraffinized 
and an anti-SSO pAb2 rabbit polyclonal antibody (synthesized 
ad hoc by Creative Biolabs) diluted 1:100 was used as a primary 
antibody in a standard protocol using the Ventana Red MAP 
V R kit 
(Ventana, 760-123). A Biotin-SP-conjugated AffiniPure donkey 
anti-rabbit 
IgG 
antibody 
diluted 
1:200 
(Jackson 
ImmunoResearch, 711-065-152) was used as secondary anti-
body. Sections were stained with Fast Red and counterstained </p>



<p>with hematoxylin. Rabbit serum (Dako, X0902) was used as a 
negative control. In addition, lysosome-associated membrane 
glycoprotein-2 (LAMP-2) immunohistochemistry was performed 
on selected kidney histological sections using a polyclonal rab-
bit anti-LAMP-2 antibody (Thermo Scientific, 51-2200) diluted 
1:50 in a standard protocol using the Ventana DAB MAP 
V R kit 
(Ventana, 760-124). A Biotin-SP-conjugated AffiniPure donkey 
anti-rabbit IgG (Jackson Immuno Research, 711-065-152) diluted 
1:100 was used as secondary antibody. Sections were stained 
with 3,3 
0 -diaminobenzidine (DAB) and counterstained with </p>

<p>hematoxylin. 
In-situ hybridization-In-situ hybridization was used to detect 
and localize RTR5001 in kidney, liver, and lymph node tissue 
samples of individual animals. Formalin-fixed and paraffin-
embedded tissue sections (3-4 lm thick) were de-paraffinized 
and pre-treated with protease. A digoxigenin-labelled comple-
mentary LNA probe to RTR5001 was designed and provided by 
Exiqon. Following hybridization, sections were stained with 
DAB and counterstained with hematoxylin. All steps of this pro-
cedure were carried out using a Ventana Discovery Ultra </p>

<p>V R </p>

<p>immunostainer. An unlabeled LNA probe against proprotein 
convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9 (PCSK9) and LNA digoxigenin-
labeled U6 (provided by Exiqon) were used as negative and posi-
tive controls, respectively, for each case. Specific staining 
signals were identified as brown, punctate dots or diffuse stain-
ing present in the cytoplasm. In addition, mRNA in-situ hybridi-
zation was applied to investigate the downregulation of PCSK9 
and APOB mRNA in liver tissue samples after dosing with 
RTR5001 and RTR4955, respectively. PCSK9 and APOB mRNA 
were visualized in formalin-fixed and paraffin-embedded liver 
samples (Wang et al., 2012) using RNAscopeVS 
V R (Advanced Cell 
Diagnostics). Liver tissue sections (3-4 lm thick) were de-
paraffinized and treated with protease. PCSK9-or APOB-specific 
mRNA target probe sets (N ¼ 20) for Sus scrofa were provided by 
Exiqon (gene ID 100620501, targeted bps 2 through 1464 of the 
PCSK9 cDNA sequence; Gene ID 100523371, targeted bps 3564 
through 4553 of the APOB cDNA sequence). Following signal 
amplification, sections were stained with Fast Red and counter-
stained with hematoxylin as previously described (Atzpodien 
et al., 2016). All steps of this procedure were carried out using a 
Ventana Discovery Ultra 
V R immunostainer. Probes to the bacte-
rial gene dapB and the endogenous UBC mRNA were used as 
negative and positive controls, respectively. Specific staining 
signals were identified by light microscopy as red, punctate dots 
in the cytoplasm. 
Transmission electron microscopy-For TEM, kidney samples 
from controls and RTR4955-treated minipigs were fixed in 3.5% 
glutaraldehyde at room temperature, osmicated, and embedded 
in epoxy resin. Ultra-thin sections were cut, collected on grids, 
counterstained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate and exam-
ined using a transmission electron microscope. </p>

<p>Tissue Quantitative PCR Analysis </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted from flash-frozen liver samples using 
the RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen). RNA integrity number (RIN) was 
checked with the Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer System and RNA was 
subsequently transcribed into cDNA. Expression levels of APOB 
and PCSK9 were determined by quantitative PCR using commer-
cially available reagent and TaqMan assays (ThermoFisher). 
Gene expression levels were normalized against the house-
keeping gene beta glucuronidase (GUSB). </p>

<p>Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>Group means and standard deviations (SD) were calculated for 
N ! 3 minipigs per group using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Provantis</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Instem Life Sciences</rs>, Stone, UK). Differences between the control group and 
treated groups were determined using an ANOVA with 
Dunnett's multiple comparison test. Values of P &lt; .05 were con-
sidered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Exposure Assessment and Tissue Biodistribution </p>

<p>After RTR5001, RTR4955, and RTR3649 administration, the 
plasma exposure, AUC and C max values increased roughly or 
slightly more than dose-proportionally. For RTR2996, AUC 0-24h 
and C max values increased less than dose-proportionally between 
15 and 45 mg/kg. Plasma exposure over repeated administrations 
at the high dose increased for RTR4955 and RTR2996 but re-
mained unchanged for RTR5001 and RTR3649. All tested SSOs 
were rapidly cleared from the blood circulation, resulting in a 
concentration 2-3 orders of magnitude lower than the C max after 
24 h. RTR4955 kidney exposure was similar at 8 and 24 mg/kg. 
RTR2996 tissue levels increased with dose from 5 to 15 mg/kg and 
showed a trend for saturation at 45 mg/kg. An exposure satura-
tion in kidney and liver tissue was also identified at 48 mg/kg for 
RTR3649. Liver tissue levels increased dose-dependently after 
RTR5001 and RTR4955 administration, as did kidney levels with 
RTR5001. Generally, the four investigated SSOs partitioned to a 
markedly higher concentration in the kidney cortex than in the 
liver (Supplementary Table 1 and Figs 1-3). </p>

<p>In-Life Observations and Clinical Pathology </p>

<p>RTR5001-All animals survived up to the scheduled sacrifice. 
There were no RTR5001-related clinical signs or ISRs and no 
change in hematology, coagulation parameters and cytokines 
was observed. On day 17 at 20 mg/kg, one minipig had a con-
comitant increase in serum creatinine (1.6-fold) and blood urea 
nitrogen (BUN; (1.8-fold); another minipig showed an increase 
in BUN only (1.2-fold). 
Urinary changes at 20 mg/kg consisted of an increase in uri-
nary volume with concomitant increase of N-acetyl-beta-D-glu-
cosaminidase (NAG) and calcium (Ca) normalized to creatinine. 
There were no changes in urinary protein levels. 
A statistically significant (P &lt; .05) decrease (up to À53%) in 
mean serum low-density lipoprotein (LDL), accompanied by a 
decrease of mean total cholesterol serum (À20 to 30%), was ob-
served on days 12 and 17 and decreased triglyceride levels on 
day 17 in the 20 mg/kg group, which are expected pharmaco-
logic effects. 
RTR4955-One minipig at 24 mg/kg was sacrificed for hu-
mane reasons on day 15 approximately 96 h after the third dose 
and 2 days prior to its scheduled sacrificing. It presented with a 
markedly decreased food consumption, an acute loss in body 
weight (7% decrease vs the highest previously recorded value) 
and clinical signs (hypoactivity and tremors). All other animals 
showed a marginal reduction of body weight gain without con-
comitant changes in food consumption. Neither ISRs nor 
changes in cytokine values were seen in any animal. 
Neutrophil (2-fold) and monocyte (2.7-fold) counts as well as 
fibrinogen (2.2-fold) levels were significantly (P &lt; .001) in-
creased in minipigs at 24 mg/kg on day 17. Serum aspartate ami-
notransferase (AST) and glutamate dehydrogenase (GDH) 
activities were significantly (P &lt; .05) increased by up to 2-fold </p>

<p>BRAENDLI-BAIOCCO ET AL. | 115 </p>

<p>on day 17 at 24 mg/kg. Creatinine and BUN concentrations 
were increased in all RTR4955-dosed minipigs by up to 48% 
and 2-fold, respectively on day 17, starting earlier in animals 
at 24 mg/kg. 
Urinary changes included increases in urinary volume, pro-
tein as well as NAG, sodium (Na), Ca and chloride (Cl) concen-
trations normalized to creatinine, in animals dosed at 24 mg/kg. 
Urinary protein was also increased in one animal dosed at 6 mg/kg. 
Parameters that would indicate a pharmacodynamic effect, eg, total 
cholesterol, LDL or high-density lipoprotein (HDL) concentrations, 
were not altered. 
RTR3649-All animals survived to the scheduled sacrificing. 
There were no RTR3649-related clinical signs, ISRs, or changes 
in hematology and urinary parameters. Marginally increased 
prothrombin time (PT; 10-26%) and activated partial thrombo-
plastin time (APTT; up to 18%) values in minipigs at 12 and 
48 mg/kg were observed after repeated administration on days 
16, 25, and 30. 
On day 16, the total cholesterol level was decreased by 16% 
in minipigs dosed at 48 mg/kg; a decrease was also observed in 
an individual animal on day 30. This was accompanied by a 
minimal decrease in HDL cholesterol at days 16 and 30 (reduc-
tions of 19% and 26% at 12 mg/kg, and 33% and 31% at 48 mg/kg, 
respectively). In addition, serum triglyceride levels were statisti-
cally significantly decreased at days 16 and 30 (decreases of 50% 
and 58% at 12 mg/kg, and 62% and 64% at 48 mg/kg, respectively) 
when compared with control and/or pretest values. After the 
dosing-free period, serum cholesterol concentration was low in 
1 of the 2 animals previously dosed at 48 mg/kg; HDL and </p>

<p>triglyceride levels were low in both minipigs. Decreases in cho-
lesterol, HDL and triglyceride levels were expected pharmacody-
namic effects of RTR3649. There were no relevant changes in 
cytokine levels. 
RTR2996-One of the five minipigs at 45 mg/kg, which was 
originally assigned for evaluation during recovery, was sacri-
ficed for humane reasons three days after the last dose. It pre-
sented a marked acute body weight loss that corresponded with 
reduced food consumption and hypoactivity. The overall condi-
tion of this minipig was likely due to kidney changes, which 
were more severe than in the other animals of this group. In ad-
dition, a discoloration (flushing) of limbs, ears and snout was 
observed shortly after the last dosing which was attributed to 
complement activation. After repeated dosing, the majority of 
minipigs dosed at 45 mg/kg presented with a transient flushing 
of limbs, ears and nose immediately after dosing. A prolonged 
bleeding time after blood collection was also noted. 
Accordingly, transient and statistically significant increases in 
PT and APTT were observed at 45 mg/kg after the first dose, and 
this became more pronounced after the last dose (mean values 
were about 3.5 fold higher than baseline). By 24 h after dosing, 
effects on coagulation parameters had partially or totally re-
solved (Figure 4A). Hematology changes observed at 45 mg/kg at 
day 16 were statistically significant (at least P &lt; .05). A reduc-
tion in red blood cell (RBC; 11%) and lymphocyte counts (35%) 
and an increase in reticulocyte count (2.2-fold) were also 
observed. 
At day 16, animals dosed with 45 mg/kg had slight but statis-
tically significant (P &lt; .05) increases in cholesterol (36%), </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Mean exposure levels in the kidney cortex after repeated subcutaneous (RTR5001, RTR4955, or RTR3649) or intravenous (RTR2996) administration to minipigs or </p>

<p>NHPs (N ¼ 3 or N ¼ 5 with 6SD) at different dose levels. NHPs were dosed intravenously with RTR3649; no kidney samples were collected from NHPs after RTR2996 ad-</p>

<p>ministration. Similar dose:exposure relationships were observed in the kidney cortex with all four tested LNA SSOs. </p>



<p>creatinine (59%), BUN (88%), total proteins (17%), albumin (13%), 
globulin (28%), alanine aminotransferase (ALT; 34%), gamma 
glutamyltranspeptidase (GGTP; 31%) and HDL (45%) levels as 
well as markedly increased aspartate aminotransferase (AST; 
2.8-fold) and sorbitol dehydrogenase (SDH; 9.1-fold) values. 
There were no changes in cytokine values. The total comple-
ment activity (CH50), as measured on day 15, was statistically 
significantly (P &lt; .05) activated 15 minutes post-infusion in the 
45 mg/kg group. CH50 levels returned nearly to baseline at 
24 hours post-infusion (Figure 4B). 
Urinary changes consisted of slightly increased urinary pro-
teins in minipigs dosed at 45 mg/kg while the urinary volume 
was increased in one animal at 15 and 45 mg/kg each. Due to a 
kinked catheter, one minipig dosed at 45 mg/kg was only par-
tially dosed, but presented similar findings as the other animals 
in this dose group. It was the only animal that underwent a full 
14-day dosing-free period and therefore, an assessment of po-
tential recovery of effects was not feasible. </p>

<p>Gross and Anatomic Pathology </p>

<p>At necropsy, increased kidney weights were recorded with in-
creasing dose levels in animals that were administered the dif-
ferent SSOs. A pale discoloration of the kidney was observed in 
animals dosed with RTR5001, RTR4955 and RTR2996. A dose-
dependent increase in liver weights was seen in minipigs dosed 
with RTR3649 and RTR2996; this was still present after the end 
of the treatment-free period for RTR3649. In addition, a red dis-
coloration of the injection site was observed in several minipigs 
dosed with RTR5001, RTR4955, RTR3649, and controls. This </p>

<p>discoloration generally corresponded to histopathologic find-
ings of inflammation and acute hemorrhage. 
RTR5001-Histopathological findings were identified in the 
kidney, liver, lymph nodes, and at the injection sites. In the kid-
ney, mild to moderate dilatation of the proximal renal tubules 
accompanied by mild to moderate tubular degeneration/regen-
eration was seen in 2 of 3 minipigs at 20 mg/kg; this corre-
sponded to increased kidney weights and pale discoloration at 
necropsy. Tubular degeneration consisted of proximal tubular 
cell vacuolation, necrosis of tubular cells and occasional apo-
ptotic/necrotic cells in the lumen. The lesions involved the 
proximal tubules and started at the urinary pole of the glomeru-
lus. Sometimes, the parietal epithelial cells around the urinary 
pole also showed vacuoles. Not all nephrons were affected to 
the same extent. In one of the affected minipigs, dosed at 
20 mg/kg, presence of necrotic cells in the lumen was more 
abundant and, in some tubules, denudation of the basement 
membrane was observed (Figure 5A). Tubular regeneration was 
characterized by basophilic hypertrophied tubular cells with 
prominent enlarged nuclei and nucleoli and rare mitoses (as 
seen for RTR2996, Figure 5B). The subcapsular region of the cor-
tex was more severely affected by the described lesions. The 
medulla was always unchanged. Cytoplasmic PAS negative 
granules were occasionally observed in the proximal tubules of 
minipigs dosed at 20 mg/kg. 
In the liver, minimal single cell necrosis was observed in 1 of 
3 minipigs dosed at 20 mg/kg (as seen for RTR2996, Figure 6A). In 
the mandibular, mesenteric, and inguinal (draining) lymph 
nodes, minimal to mild macrophage vacuolation was observed 
(as seen for RTR2996, Figure 6C). </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Mean exposure levels in the liver after repeated subcutaneous (RTR5001, RTR4955 or RTR3649) or intravenous (RTR2996) administration to minipigs or NHPs </p>

<p>(N ¼ 3 or N ¼ 5 with 6SD) at different dose levels (NHPs were dosed intravenously for RTR3649). Similar dose:exposure relationships were observed in the liver cortex </p>

<p>with all four tested LNA SSOs. </p>

<p>BRAENDLI-BAIOCCO ET AL. | 117 </p>

<p>At the injection site, increased subcutaneous inflammation 
characterized by presence of macrophages, lymphocytes and 
granulocytes was observed in animals dosed at 6 and 20 mg/kg 
when compared with controls. This inflammation was accom-
panied by mild subcutaneous edema, fibrin exudation and ne-
crosis at the left injection site (injected on days 6 and 16) and 
was less severe and not accompanied by edema and necrosis at 
the right injection site (injected on days 1 and 11), demonstrat-
ing a tendency to reversibility of these lesions. In addition, min-
imal to moderate acute hemorrhages were observed at the 
injection sites of RTR5001-dosed animals. 
RTR4955-In the animal prematurely sacrificed on day 15, 
abundant ascites, marked perirenal edema accompanied by 
edema of the mesentery, and hemorrhage in the kidney capsule 
were recorded. 
Histopathologically, in the kidney, a dose-dependent tubu-
lar dilatation, degeneration and regeneration, similar to that 
with RTR5001 and corresponding with increased kidney 
weights and pale discoloration at necropsy, was identified. At 
24 mg/kg, in addition to the severe tubular degeneration and 
regeneration, there were inflammatory cell infiltrates in the 
interstitial space and some hyaline casts in the tubular lumen. 
The animal that was sacrificed for humane reasons on day 15 
also presented with abundant granulocytes in the tubules 
(possibly as a consequence of fibrin exudation in the glomer-
uli) and a mesangioproliferative glomerulonephritis with glo-
merular loop necrosis with fibrin exudation in the Bowman's </p>

<p>space (Figure 5C). In addition, hepatocellular vacuolation and 
minimal single cell necrosis in the liver was also seen in this 
female. 
Similarly to RTR5001, vacuolation of macrophages was ob-
served in the mandibular, mesenteric, and inguinal (draining) 
lymph nodes of minipigs dosed with RTR4955. 
At the injection site, hemorrhages were observed with in-
creased severity in animals dosed with RTR4955 compared to 
controls. There was minimal to mild subcutaneous inflamma-
tion characterized by the presence of macrophages, lympho-
cytes and granulocytes in a few animals, but there was no 
difference in incidence between minipigs dosed with RTR4955 
and controls. 
RTR3649-In the kidney, cytoplasmic basophilic granules 
were observed in the proximal tubules of all animals dosed at 
12 and 48 mg/kg. Tubular degeneration similar to those de-
scribed with the other investigated LNA SSOs but of minimal to 
mild severity was observed in 1 of 3 minipigs at 12 mg/kg and all 
minipigs at 48 mg/kg. The changes were mostly localized at the 
or close to the urinary pole of the glomerulus, were still present 
after the 4-week dosing-free period and corresponded with in-
creased kidney weights at necropsy. 
In the liver, minimal or mild diffuse cytoplasmic rarefac-
tion corresponding to an increased content of glycogen was 
observed in all minipigs at 12 mg/kg and in 2 of 3 minipigs at 
48 mg/kg. Rarefaction of hepatocytes persisted after the 4-
week treatment-free period. In addition, basophilic granules </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Mean plasma exposure with 6SD after single administration at different dose levels. A, RTR5001, B, RTR4955, C, RTR3649, and D, RTR2996 to female minipigs </p>

<p>(blue diamonds), female NHPs (red square) and humans (green triangle). The different species were administered subcutaneously at the indicated dose levels (except 
for RTR3649, where NHPs were dosed intravenously over 5 min while minipig and human subjects were dosed subcutaneously and for RTR2996 administered intrave-</p>

<p>nously). The exposure was measured as AUC of plasma concentrations over a time interval of 0 to 24 h for RTR5001, RTR4955 and RTR2996 and of 0 to 72 h for RTR3649 </p>

<p>(except for RTR3649 and RTR2996 in humans, where the time intervals were 0-96 h and 0-48 h, respectively). For the minipig, NHP and human AUC values increased </p>

<p>roughly or slightly more than dose-proportionally for RTR5001, RTR4955, RTR3649, and RTR2996 (NHP and human only). In the minipig AUC0-24h values increased less 
than dose-proportionally for RTR2996. </p>



<p>were observed in the Kupffer cells of 1 of 3 minipigs dosed at 
48 mg/kg. 
At the injection site, minimal to mild perivascular inflam-
matory cell infiltrate mainly consisting of lymphocytes with 
some eosinophilic granulocytes was observed in 2 of 3 minipigs 
dosed at 3, 12, and 48 mg/kg. In all animals at 48 mg/kg this 
change was accompanied by an increase of inflammatory cell 
infiltrate, mainly lymphocytic in the subcutis. There were mild 
subcutaneous fat necrosis, mild to moderate fibroplasia and in-
creased incidence and severity of hemorrhage. In addition, mac-
rophages with granular basophilic cytoplasm were observed in 
animals at 48 mg/kg. The changes at the injection site were al-
most completely reversible. </p>

<p>RTR2996-Histopathologically, 
in 
the kidney, 
dose-
dependent tubular dilatation, degeneration, and regeneration 
were observed at 15 and 45 mg/kg; these effects were similar to 
those observed with the other investigated LNA SSOs. Hyaline 
casts in the tubules were identified in 2 minipigs dosed at 
45 mg/kg. Basophilic fine granules in the cytoplasm of the proxi-
mal tubular epithelium (Figure 5B) were observed with a dose-
dependently increased severity in animals at 15 and 45 mg/kg. 
In the liver, basophilic granules in Kupffer cells (Figure 6A) 
and mild to moderate hepatocellular hypertrophy were ob-
served in animals dosed at 15 and 45 mg/kg. This was accompa-
nied by single cell necrosis/apoptosis and Kupffer cell 
hyperplasia in animals dosed at 45 mg/kg. In the mandibular </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Coagulation and complement activation data for minipigs (N ¼ 3 or N ¼ 5 with 6SD) dosed intravenously with 0, 5, 15, or 45 mg/kg RTR2996 (5 min infusion </p>

<p>time) every other day for 15 days A, Time course of Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (APTT; dashed lines) and Prothrombin Time (PT; solid lines) levels, on x-axis </p>

<p>time of blood sampling for measurement of coagulation parameters, predose -baseline levels, D -days of study and in brackets hours after dosing. Transient and sta-</p>

<p>tistically significant increase in PT and APTT were observed at 45 mg/kg RTR2996 that were partially or totally resolved at 24 h post dose. B, Total complement (CH50) 
activity measured in minipig serum. Differences between the control group and groups dosed with LNA SSOs were determined using an ANOVA with Dunnett's multi-</p>

<p>ple comparison tests. *P &lt; .05, **P &lt; .01 and ***P &lt; .001 compared to control. CH50 was statistically significantly reduced 15 min post-infusion at 45 mg/kg RTR2996. </p>

<p>BRAENDLI-BAIOCCO ET AL. | 119 </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Histopathologic findings in minipigs. A, Kidney, H&amp;E. Necrosis of tubular cells (arrowheads), tubular degeneration and dilatation with denudation of basal mem-</p>

<p>brane (asterisk); 20 mg/kg RTR5001. B, Kidney, H&amp;E. Basophilic granules in proximal tubular cells (arrowheads and insert) and regeneration of proximal tubular cells (as-
terisk); 45 mg/kg RTR2996. C, Kidney, H&amp;E. Mesangioproliferative glomerulonephritis and fibrin exudation into Bowman's space (asterisk); dilated tubules with many </p>

<p>granulocytes (arrowhead); 24 mg/kg RTR4955. D, Kidney of control minipig, immunohistochemistry for LAMP-2. Presence of LAMP-2 positive structures (lysosomes) in </p>

<p>proximal tubular cells. E, Kidney of dosed minipig, immunohistochemistry for LAMP-2. Increased number and size of positive LAMP-2 structures (lysosomes) in proxi-</p>

<p>mal tubular cells; 8 mg/kg RTR4955. F) Kidney, immunohistochemistry for LNA SSO. Accumulation of LNA SSO into the proximal tubular cells (red staining); 6 mg/kg 
RTR5001. G, Kidney, in-situ hybridization for RTR5001. Accumulation of LNA into the proximal tubular cells (brown staining); 6 mg/kg RTR5001 (scale bars ¼ 100 mm, fig-</p>

<p>ure C scale bar ¼ 50 mm). </p>



<p>and mesenteric lymph nodes, vacuolated macrophages, similar 
to those observed with RTR5001 and RTR4955, were seen in all 
RTR2996-dosed groups (Figure 6C). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry, in-Situ Hybridization and 
Transmission Electron Microscopy </p>

<p>The presence of the different LNA SSOs was demonstrated by 
immunohistochemistry in the cytoplasm of tubular epithelial 
cells of the kidney (Figure 5F for RTR5001), in the Kupffer cells of 
the liver (Figure 6B for RTR4955), and in the cytoplasm of macro-
phages of lymph nodes (not shown). In addition, the localiza-
tion of RTR5001 in the cytoplasm of tubular epithelial cells of 
the kidney (Figure 5G), in the Kupffer cells of the liver (not 
shown) and in the cytoplasm of macrophages of lymph nodes 
(Figure 6D) was confirmed by in-situ hybridization. 
Immunohistochemistry revealed an increased number and 
size of positive LAMP-2 structures (lysosomes) in tubular epithe-
lial cells of animals dosed with RTR4955 when compared with 
controls (Figure 5D and E). This confirmed the lysosomal in-
volvement in the accumulation of the LNA SSOs. 
Proximal tubular changes were similar for all four LNA SSOs 
at histopathologic examination and therefore tissue from one 
animal, dosed with RTR4955 and diagnosed with tubular lesions </p>

<p>and mesangioproliferative glomerulonephritis, was selected for 
further characterization by TEM. Ultrastructurally, an increased 
number and size of lysosomes (Figure 7A), with storage of heter-
ogenous osmiophilic material in the cytoplasm, was observed 
in the proximal tubular cells of this minipig, which was dosed 
with 24 mg/kg RTR4955. In addition, some tubules had variable 
damage from single cell necrosis to necrosis of the whole tubu-
lar cross section (Figure 7B). In the surrounding of highly af-
fected tubules, massive edema was present in the interstitial 
space. Cortical collecting ducts were not affected. The glomeru-
lar structure, the basement membranes, endothelial cells or 
podocytes were not affected by LNA SSO dosing in the examined 
minipigs. One minipig, however, dosed with RTR4955 at 24 mg/ 
kg, histopathologically presented with a mesangioproliferative 
glomerulonephritis. Ultrastructurally, the endothelial cells and/ 
or mesangial cells of the glomeruli of this animal were in-
creased or swollen and showed signs of storage of a homoge-
nous or slightly polymorphic material, or vacuoles (Figure 7C). 
No electron dense deposits were observed. </p>

<p>Target Engagement and Pharmacodynamics </p>

<p>PCSK9 mRNA expression levels in minipig livers were markedly 
and dose-dependently reduced by up to 72% after subcutaneous </p>

<p>FIG. 6. Histopathologic findings in minipigs. A, Liver, H&amp;E. Basophilic granules in Kupffer cells (long arrowheads and insert) and apoptotic hepatocytes (short arrow-</p>

<p>heads); 45 mg/kg RTR2996. B, Liver, immunohistochemistry for LNA SSO. Accumulation of LNA SSO (red staining) in Kupffer cells; 24 mg/kg RTR4955. C, Lymph node, </p>

<p>H&amp;E. Vacuolated macrophages (insert); 15 mg/kg RTR2996. D) Lymph node, immunohistochemistry for LNA. Accumulation of LNA SSO in the vacuolated macrophages 
(brown staining); 20 mg/kg RTR5001 (scale bars ¼ 50 mm). </p>

<p>BRAENDLI-BAIOCCO ET AL. | 121 </p>

<p>dosing with RTR5001, whereas APOB mRNA hepatocellular ex-
pression was not altered when compared with controls (Figure 
8). Correspondingly, after repeated subcutaneous dosing with 
RTR5001, LDL cholesterol levels were decreased by up to 53% 
when compared with controls and pretest levels, thereby con-
firming a direct pharmacodynamic effect of RTR5001 in minipig 
livers. </p>

<p>After dosing with RTR4955, neither an effect on APOB mRNA 
nor PCSK9 mRNA hepatocellular expression (Figure 8) nor cho-
lesterol levels could be identified. 
By in-situ hydridization a reduced PCSK9 mRNA expression after 
RTR5001 dosing was confirmed (Figure 9A and B). No such differ-
ence could be identified for APOB mRNA expression levels when 
compared with control liver tissue samples (Figure 9C and D). </p>

<p>FIG. 7. Electron microscopy of kidney from a minipig dosed at 24 mg/kg RTR4955. A, Part of a tubule with massively increased number and size of lysosomes (bar ¼ 5 
mm). B, Proximal tubular degeneration and necrosis (bar ¼ 10 mm). C, Same kidney as shown by light microscopy in Figure 5C. Mesangioproliferative glomerulonephritis </p>

<p>with prominent mesangial hypercellularity and lysosomal inclusion in mesangial cells. Note: normal basement membranes and podocytes, no osmiophilic immune </p>

<p>deposits. (bar ¼ 10 mm). </p>

<p>FIG. 8. Mean APOB and PCSK9 mRNA gene expression levels in minipig (N ¼ 3 with 6SD) liver relative to the house-keeping gene beta glucuronidase (GUSB) and rela-
tive to mean gene expression of the control group after subcutaneous dosing of RTR4955 or RTR5001. PCSK9 mRNA levels were dose-dependently decreased after ad-</p>

<p>ministration of RTR5001 but not RTR4955. No changes in APOB mRNA levels were observed after administration of RTR5001 or RTR4955. </p>



<p>Minimal to mild cytoplasmic staining for PCSK9 was present in he-
patocytes of control minipigs and no or only minimal staining was 
present in minipigs dosed with 20 mg/kg RTR5001, confirming tar-
get engagement in the minipig. Moderate to marked cytoplasmic 
staining for APOB was present in control minipigs and minipigs 
dosed with RTR4955, indicating no effect of the LNA SSO on the 
APOB mRNA expression. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Administration of the 4 LNA SSOs resulted in similar clinical 
findings in minipigs as in NHPs. An overview of the complete re-
sponse pattern is presented for both non-rodent species, mini-
pig and NHP, for all four different SSO LNAs in Table 1. Trends 
for clinical pathology changes are considered crucial to correlate 
with histopathologic findings. After multiple dosing, two high-
dose animals for both NHPs and minipigs were sacrificed for hu-
mane reasons (Table 1). In addition, minipigs showed similar 
exposure and very good comparability in toxicity profile versus 
NHPs, with no additional on-or off-target pharmacology or tox-
icities (Table 1). Effects on the coagulation, renal, and comple-
ment systems were also similar to those in NHPs. 
Overall, the toxicity profile of the LNA SSOs appears to be 
similar in minipigs and NHPs, and typical of the class-wide tox-
icity profile of SSOs (Frazier et al., 2014; Koch and Ørum, 2008), 
with kidney, liver and lymphoid tissues being the main target 
tissues of toxicity. While some of these effects are 
hybridization-independent (eg, pro-inflammatory or plasma 
protein effects) (Henry et al., 2008), the mechanism for others 
(eg, hepatotoxicity) is still uncertain but may also involve off-
target hybridization (Burel et al., 2016). 
The pharmaco-/toxicokinetic behavior of the different LNA 
SSOs was also similar in the minipig and NHPs. As in other spe-
cies, plasma exposure increased roughly dose-proportionally, 
and SSOs were rapidly cleared from circulation (Levin et al., 
2008). In both species, LNA SSOs are distributed and taken up by 
peripheral tissues such as the liver and kidney. For the majority 
of the investigated LNA SSOs there was an exposure saturation 
in the minipig kidney; generally kidney exposure of the cortex 
was markedly higher than the liver, as shown previously (Geary 
et al., 2015; Straarup et al., 2010). 
In minipigs dosed intravenously with RTR2996, we observed 
a transient increase in PT and APTT, and a decrease in total </p>

<p>complement. Corresponding clinical signs, including prolonged 
bleeding and red discoloration of parts of the body, were also 
transient and reversed within a few minutes after administra-
tion. In NHPs, RTR2996 caused coagulation and complement ac-
tivation; this has been described with other LNA SSOs (Henry 
et al., 2014; Hildebrandt-Eriksen et al., 2012; Koch and Ørum, 
2008) but has not previously been described in minipigs (Henry 
et al., 2016). In NHPs, activation of the complement system was 
reported with threshold SSO plasma levels of 70-80 lg/mL 
(Henry et al., 2014). In our minipig study, activation of the com-
plement system was seen at plasma C max values of approxi-
mately 500 lg/mL RTR2996. Although this warrants more data, 
this finding could suggest a lower sensitivity of minipigs to this 
liability than NHPs and therefore possibly a higher relevance to 
human safety assessment since NHPs are known to be overpre-
dictive (Henry et al., 2016). With the confirmed occurrence of 
acute PT and APTT prolongations after high intravenous doses 
in both species, this effect is likely also relevant in terms of hu-
man safety, even if clinical plasma peak concentrations are of-
ten below NHP thresholds (Crooke et al., 2016). 
One factor for choosing a relevant species for preclinical 
safety studies is its ability to capture pharmacological effects 
(eg, exaggerated pharmacology) of a drug development candi-
date, which has been a factor in the historical preference for 
NHPs for biotechnology-derived and oligonucleotide therapeu-
tics. The recent sequencing of the minipig genome was essen-
tial for considering the minipig as a potential alternative 
non-rodent species. As in NHPs, we showed dose-related target 
engagement, a pharmacodynamic effect and a decrease in LDL 
cholesterol after repeated dosing with RTR5001 in minipigs 
(Lindholm et al., 2012). PCSK9 mRNA expression in minipig livers 
was markedly reduced after RTR5001 administration, confirm-
ing pharmacodynamic activity, despite the single mismatch. In 
contrast, RTR4955 neither altered PCSK9 nor APOB mRNA nor 
cholesterol levels. These differences are likely due to different 
positions of the single mismatch to the minipig genome in the 
LNA SSO sequences. The central mismatch in RTR4955 is ex-
pectedly more detrimental on the target regulation than the 
end-standing mismatch in RTR5001, suggesting that for 
RTR4955, this region is critical for RNaseH recruitment and 
cleavage of target mRNA. 
After clearance from the circulation, SSOs accumulated in 
liver Kupffer cells, lymph nodes and, most significantly, in the </p>

<p>FIG. 9. In situ hybridization for detection of PCSK9 or APOB mRNA expression in minipig liver tissue, indicated as red dots with hematoxylin counterstain. A, Minimal </p>

<p>PCSK9 expression in control minipig B, No PCSK9 expression in minipig dosed at 20 mg/kg RTR5001 (scale bar ¼ 50 mm) C, Medium to marked APOB expression in control 
minipig D, Similar amount of APOB expression in minipig dosed at 24 mg/kg RTR4955 compared to control (scale bar ¼ 100 mm). </p>

<p>BRAENDLI-BAIOCCO ET AL. | 123 </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Overview of Main Observations in Minipig and NHP After Dosing With RTR5001, RTR4955, RTR3649 and RTR2996 (Gebert et al., 2014; Hildebrandt-Eriksen et al., 2012; Koch and Ørum, 2008; </p>

<p>Lindholm et al., 2012; data on file, F. Hoffmann-La Roche Ltd., 2017) </p>

<p>RTR5001 </p>

<p>RTR4955 </p>

<p>RTR3649 </p>

<p>RTR2996 </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Dose levels </p>

<p>0, 6, 20 mg/kg </p>

<p>(s.c.) </p>

<p>0, 6, 20 mg/kg </p>

<p>(s.c.) 
0, 8, 24 mg/kg (s.c.) </p>

<p>0, 8, 24 mg/kg </p>

<p>(s.c.) </p>

<p>0, 3, 12 and 
48 mg/kg (s.c.) </p>

<p>0, 3, 12 and 
48 mg/kg (i.v.) </p>

<p>0, 5, 15, and 
45 mg/kg (i.v.) 
0, 3, 20, and 60 mg/kg </p>

<p>(i.v.) </p>

<p>Dosing days 
1, 6, 11 and 16 </p>

<p>1, 6, 11 and 16 </p>

<p>1, 6, 11 and 16 </p>

<p>1, 6, 11 and 16 </p>

<p>1, 4, 8, 11, 15, 18, 
22, 25, 29 </p>

<p>1, 4, 8, 11, 15, 18, 
22, 25, 28 </p>

<p>1, 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 13, </p>

<p>15 
1, 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 13, 15 </p>

<p>Mortality </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>1 humane killed at 
24 mg/kg with tubu-
lar lesions and 
glomerulonephritis 
1 humane killed 
at 24 mg/kg 
with hemor-
rhages, edema </p>

<p>and necrosis of 
cecum, incl. 
liver and kid-
ney changes </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>1 humane killed 
at 45 mg/kg 
with more se-
vere kidney 
changes 
1 humane killed at 
60 mg/kg due to 
liver and kidney 
changes </p>

<p>Hematology </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>" 
WBC, neutro-
phils, mono-
nocytes at </p>

<p>20 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
Neutrophils and 
monocytes at </p>

<p>24 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
Reticulo-and 
monocytes at </p>

<p>24 mg/kg </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p># 
Rbc, lympho-
cytes and re-
ticulocytes at </p>

<p>45 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
Monocytes at </p>

<p>60 mg/kg </p>

<p>Coagulation </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>" 
Fibrinogen at </p>

<p>24 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
Fibrinogen at </p>

<p>!8 </p>

<p>mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
PT and APTT 
at ! 
12 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
PT and APTT 
at ! 
12 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
PT and APTT at 
45 mg/kg asso-
ciated with 
flushing of 
limbs, ear and 
nose </p>

<p>" 
PT and APTT 
at ! 
20 mg/kg </p>

<p>Clinical 
Chemistry </p>

<p># 
CHOL, LDL, tri-
glyceride at </p>

<p>20 mg/kg; " 
Crea in 1 of 3 
and BUN at 
20 mg/kg </p>

<p># 
CHOL, triglycer-
ide at 20 mg/ 
kg, LDL 
at ! 
6 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
AST, GDH, Crea and 
BUN at 24 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
AST, GGTP, 
Crea and BUN 
at ! 
8 mg/kg, # 
CHOL, LDL, 
HDL, triglycer-
ide at ! 
8 mg/kg </p>

<p># 
CHOL, HDL, LDL 
and triglycer-
ide at ! 
12 mg/kg </p>

<p># 
CHOL, HDL, LDL </p>

<p>at ! 
3 mg/kg; " 
ALP at 48 mg/ 
kg; " 
ALT and </p>

<p>AST during 
recovery </p>

<p>" 
CHOL, CREA, 
BUN, total pro-
tein, albumin, 
globulin, AST, </p>

<p>ALT, GGTP, 
SDH at 
45 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
ALT, AST, CHOL, 
BUN, CREA, tri-
glyceride at 60 mg/ </p>

<p>kg, # 
albumin and </p>

<p>A/G at 60 mg/kg </p>

<p>Urinalysis </p>

<p>" 
Na/Crea &amp; Ca/ 
Crea at 
20 mg/kg </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>" 
Volume, NAG, Na/ 
Crea, Ca/Crea, Cl/ 
Crea at 24 mg/kg </p>

<p>Hematuria, pro-
teinuria, leu-
kocytes </p>

<p>at ! 
8 mg/kg </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>" 
Volume in 1 of </p>

<p>3 at ! </p>

<p>15 mg/ </p>

<p>kg, protein at 
45 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
Volume at 60 mg/ </p>

<p>kg and protein 
at ! 
20 mg/kg </p>

<p>Organ weight </p>

<p>" 
Kidney at </p>

<p>20 mg/kg </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>" 
Kidney at ! 
8 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
Liver and kid-
ney at 
24 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
Liver and kid-
ney at 
48 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
Liver at 
48 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
Liver and kid-
ney at ! 
5 mg/kg </p>

<p>" 
Kidney and spleen </p>

<p>at ! 
6 mg/kg and 
liver at ! 
20 mg/kg </p>

<p>Exposure 
Kidney 
cortex 
0, 164, 555 mg/g </p>

<p>at </p>

<p>0, 6, 20 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 386, 602 mg/g </p>

<p>at </p>

<p>0, 6, 20 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 144, 147 mg/g </p>

<p>at 0, 8, </p>

<p>24 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 120, 154 mg/g </p>

<p>at </p>

<p>0, 8, 24 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 643, 1220, 
1580 mg/g </p>

<p>at 0, </p>

<p>3, 12, 48 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 374, 664, 
1550 mg/g </p>

<p>at 0, </p>

<p>3, 12, 48 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 1217, 4237, 
5703 mg/g </p>

<p>at 0, </p>

<p>5, 15, 45 mg/kg, 
respectively 
Not examined </p>



<p>TABLE 1. (continued) </p>

<p>RTR5001 </p>

<p>RTR4955 </p>

<p>RTR3649 </p>

<p>RTR2996 </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Exposure 
Liver </p>

<p>0, 38, 74 mg/g </p>

<p>at 0, </p>

<p>6, 20 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 65, 177 mg/g </p>

<p>at </p>

<p>0, 6, 20 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 32, 82 mg/g </p>

<p>at 0, 8, </p>

<p>24 mg/kg, 
respectively </p>

<p>0, 46, 85 mg/g </p>

<p>at 0, </p>

<p>8, 24 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 160, 462, 
550 mg/g </p>

<p>at 0, 3, </p>

<p>12, 48 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 68, 293, 551 mg/ 
g at 0, 3, 12, 
48 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 292, 897, 
2283 mg/g </p>

<p>at 0, </p>

<p>5, 15, 45 mg/kg, 
respectively 
0, 203, 500, 1042 mg/g 
at 0, 3, 20, 60 mg/kg, 
respectively </p>

<p>Histopathology </p>

<p>Kidney </p>

<p>PAS negative 
granules, tubu-</p>

<p>lar dilatation, 
degeneration/ 
regeneration </p>

<p>in 2 of 3 at 
20 mg/kg </p>

<p>Basophilic tubu-</p>

<p>lar granules 
at ! 
6 mg/kg, 
tubular dilata-
tion/atrophy in </p>

<p>1 of 3 at 
20 mg/kg </p>

<p>Tubular dilatation, de-
generation/regener-</p>

<p>ation at ! 
8 mg/kg </p>

<p>Tubular single 
cell necrosis 
and tubular di-
latation and 
basophilia </p>

<p>at ! 
8 mg/kg </p>

<p>Basophilic gran-</p>

<p>ules and tubu-
lar degenera-
tion 
at ! 
12 mg/kg </p>

<p>Tubular cell vac-
uolation and </p>

<p>in 1 of 6 tubu-
lar single cell 
necrosis at </p>

<p>48 mg/kg </p>

<p>Basophilic gran-</p>

<p>ules, tubular 
degeneration/ 
regeneration </p>

<p>at ! 
15 mg/kg, 
hyaline casts </p>

<p>at 45 mg/kg </p>

<p>Basophilic granules, 
tubular vacuola-
tion/degenera-
tion/necrosis/hy-</p>

<p>pertrophy, intra-</p>

<p>tubular hemor-
rhages, perivascu-</p>

<p>lar tubular 
necrosis </p>

<p>at ! 
20 mg/kg </p>

<p>Liver </p>

<p>Single cell necro-
sis/apoptosis </p>

<p>in 1 of 3 at 
20 mg/kg </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Hepatocellular vacuo-</p>

<p>lation, single cell 
necrosis in 1 of 3 at </p>

<p>24 mg/kg </p>

<p>Hepatocellular 
vacuolation </p>

<p>at ! 
8 mg/kg, 
hypertrophy </p>

<p>and necrosis 
associated </p>

<p>with mononu-
clear cell 
infiltration </p>

<p>Basophilic gran-</p>

<p>ules in Kupffer 
cells at 48 mg/ 
kg, hepatocel-
lular cytoplas-
mic rarefaction 
at ! 
12 mg/kg </p>

<p>Basophilic gran-
ules/hypertro-</p>

<p>phy in Kupffer 
cells 
at ! 
12 mg/kg, 
hepatocellular 
cytoplasmic </p>

<p>change </p>

<p>at ! 
3 mg/kg; 
and hepatocel-
lular apoptosis 
in 1 of 6 at 
48 mg/kg </p>

<p>Basophilic gran-</p>

<p>ules in Kupffer 
cells and hepa-
tocellular hy-
pertrophy </p>

<p>at ! 
15 mg/kg, 
single cell ne-
crosis/apopto-</p>

<p>sis, Kupffer 
cell hyperpla-
sia at 45 mg/kg </p>

<p>Basophilic granules </p>

<p>in Kupffer cells 
at ! 
6 mg/kg, he-
patocyte degener-</p>

<p>ation in 1 of 6 at 
60 mg/kg and he-
patocellular ne-</p>

<p>crosis in 1 of 6 at </p>

<p>20 mg/kg </p>

<p>Lymph nodes </p>

<p>Vacuolated mac-
rophages </p>

<p>at ! 
6 mg/kg </p>

<p>Sinus histiocyto-
sis (vacuo-
lated/stippled) </p>

<p>at ! 
6 mg/kg </p>

<p>Vacuolated macro-
phages at ! 
8 mg/kg </p>

<p>Sinus histiocyto-
sis (vacuo-
lated/stippled) </p>

<p>at ! 
8 mg/kg </p>

<p>Not examined </p>

<p>Vacuolated mac-
rophages </p>

<p>at ! 
3 mg/kg </p>

<p>Vacuolated mac-
rophages </p>

<p>at ! 
5 mg/kg </p>

<p>Foamy macro-
phages, " </p>

<p>cellular-</p>

<p>ity of paracortex 
at ! 
6 mg/kg </p>

<p>s.c. injection 
sites </p>

<p>" 
Severity of in-
flammation, </p>

<p>necrosis and/ </p>

<p>or edema, 
hemorrhages </p>

<p>" 
Severity of in-
flammation, </p>

<p>edema and 
hemorrhages </p>

<p>" 
Hemorrhages; in-
flammation (similar </p>

<p>to controls) </p>

<p>" </p>

<p>Hemorrhages </p>

<p>and acute 
inflammation </p>

<p>Perivascular infil-
tration (all 
doses), inflam-
matory cell in-
filtrate, " 
hemorrhage </p>

<p>and fibroplasia 
at 48 mg/kg </p>

<p>Not applicable 
(i.v. dosing) </p>

<p>Not applicable 
(i.v. dosing) </p>

<p>Not applicable (i.v. 
dosing) </p>

<p>BRAENDLI-BAIOCCO ET AL. | 125 </p>

<p>kidney. Accumulation of LNA SSOs in the proximal tubular cells 
of the minipig kidney resulted in the presence of cytoplasmic 
basophilic granules, similar to that previously shown in rodents 
and NHPs (Frazier et al., 2014; Hildebrandt-Eriksen et al., 2012; 
Koch and Ørum, 2008). Additionally, in the minipig, we observed 
degenerative changes of the renal tubular cells previously iden-
tified in NHP studies (Henry et al., 2012; Koch and Ørum, 2008; 
Monteith et al., 1999). In the minipig, RTR3649 produced mini-
mal to mild tubular degeneration in the kidney, whereas in 
NHPs, vacuolation of tubular cells was reported (Hildebrandt-
Eriksen et al., 2012). In minipigs, RTR5001 produced degenera-
tive/regenerative changes in the kidney; no adverse biochemical 
or histopathologic findings were observed in NHPs (Lindholm 
et al., 2012; van Poelgeest et al., 2013). In a human trial with 
RTR5001, one case of acute kidney injury was reported in a 
healthy volunteer who received three once-weekly doses of 
5 mg/kg, with multifocal tubular necrosis/degeneration and evi-
dence of drug accumulation (van Poelgeest et al., 2013) on bi-
opsy. These findings were similar to those in minipigs given 
RTR5001. Degenerative/regenerative changes of the renal tubu-
lar cells were similar in minipigs and NHPs dosed with RTR4955 
and RTR2996, although severity was greater with RTR4955 in 
the minipig. In addition, one minipig dosed with RTR4955 
showed a mesangioproliferative glomerulonephritis, a lesion 
not previously observed in NHPs for the four LNA SSOs. 
Although no electron-dense deposits along the basal mem-
branes were observed with TEM investigations, the lesion 
showed similar characteristics to those described previously 
(Frazier et al., 2014). Therefore, the pathogenesis-not fully clari-
fied-may be related to a dysfunction of the alternative comple-
ment pathway. Regardless of the mechanism, minipigs may be 
more sensitive to kidney toxicity at high doses than NHPs. 
As commonly observed in NHPs and rodents, basophilic cyto-
plasmic granules were observed in the Kupffer cells in minipigs 
dosed with RTR3649 and RTR2996. Immunohistochemistry and 
in-situ hybridization showed this was due to SSO accumulation. 
Hepatocellular single cell necrosis/apoptosis, correlating with in-
creased serum transaminase activities, were observed in mini-
pigs administered RTR2996, in one minipig administered 
RTR5001, and another one administered RTR4955. Similar 
changes were seen in NHPs administered RTR4955 and RTR2996 
(Koch and Ørum, 2008; Straarup et al., 2010). In clinical studies, 
RTR4955 caused a mild increase in serum transaminase activities 
in some subjects, and a dose-limiting increase in serum transam-
inase activities occurred in two patients treated with RTR2996 
4 mg/kg 3 times per week for two weeks (Tilly et al., 2007). 
Vacuolated macrophages were observed in minipig lymph 
nodes, including the draining lymph node of the injection site, 
similar to those described in other species (Frazier et al., 2014). 
Immunohistochemistry and in-situ hybridization showed the 
presence of the LNA SSO in these vacuolated macrophages. 
These so-called foamy/stippled macrophages were described 
previously in NHPs (Hildebrandt-Eriksen et al., 2012). 
During clinical trials, and after subcutaneous dosing of SSOs, 
ISRs such as erythema, ulceration, necrosis and hyperpigmen-
tation have been observed (van Meer et al., 2016; van Poelgeest 
et al., 2015). Although minipig skin shows similarities to human 
anatomy, physiology, and biochemistry (Forster et al., 2010; 
Mahl et al., 2006) and has been considered a model to predict hu-
man cutaneous reactions, no acute or gross clinical observa-
tions were made in either the minipig or NHPs. 
Histopathologically, subcutaneous dosing of RTR5001 in mini-
pigs resulted in an increased inflammation in the subcutis, 
characterized by the presence of macrophages, lymphocytes, </p>

<p>TABLE 1. (continued) </p>

<p>RTR5001 </p>

<p>RTR4955 </p>

<p>RTR3649 </p>

<p>RTR2996 </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Minipig </p>

<p>NHP </p>

<p>Additional 
organs </p>

<p>Monunuclear cell 
infiltrate and 
necrosis in 
heart of 1 of 3 </p>

<p>at 24 mg/kg; 
hemorrhages </p>

<p>in cecum, co-
lon and lung 
at ! 
8 mg/kg </p>

<p>Not examined </p>

<p># 
Cellularity of adre-</p>

<p>nal glands 
at ! 
20 mg/kg, </p>

<p>" 
cellularity of PALS </p>

<p>at ! 
6 mg/kg and 
marginal zone of 
spleen at 60 mg/kg, </p>

<p>" 
lymphocytic infil-</p>

<p>tration of the sali-
vary gland 
at ! 
6 mg/kg; </p>

<p># 
cellularity of </p>

<p>thymic cortex at </p>

<p>60 mg/kg </p>

<p>Abbreviations: A/G, albumin/globulin ratio; ALP, alkaline phosphatase; APTT, activated partial thromboplastin time; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; BUN, blood urea nitrogen; Ca, calcium; CHOL, total cholesterol; Cl, chloride; Crea, </p>

<p>creatinine; GDH, glutamate dehydrogenase; GGTP, gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase; Hb, hemoglobin; Hct, hematocrit; HDL, high density lipoprotein; i.v., intravenous; LDL, low density lipoprotein; Na, sodium; NAG, N-acetyl-beta-D-
glucosaminidase; PAS, Periodic acid-Schiff-diastase staining; PALS, periarteriolar lymphoid sheaths; PT, partial prothombin time; Rbc, red blood cells; s.c., subcutaneous; SDH, sorbitol dehydrogenase; WBC, white blood cells. </p>



<p>granulocytes, edema, hemorrhages, and necrosis. A tendency to 
recovery from these ISRs was shown by comparing the previous 
and last injection sites. Inflammatory changes were identified 
at the injection sites of control animals and minipigs adminis-
tered RTR4955. Increased severity and incidence of hemor-
rhages were noted in RTR4955-dosed minipigs. RTR3649 caused 
perivascular inflammatory cell infiltration of mainly lympho-
cytes and eosinophilic granulocytes as well as necrosis at the 
injection sites in the minipig. However, as NHPs were dosed in-
travenously in the duration-matching study, a direct compari-
son cannot be made. Subcutaneous injection of RTR5001 and 
RTR4955 to NHPs caused inflammation, with predominant infil-
tration of neutrophils and formation of edema in the subcutis. 
In humans, SSOs are associated with ISRs of varying severity 
when administered subcutaneously (van Meer et al., 2016); le-
sion severity is dose-dependent, and some SSOs cause persis-
tent lesions (van Meer et al., 2016; van Poelgeest et al., 2015). 
Consequently, although no overt ISRs were evident during the 
in-life phase in our preclinical studies, the histopathological ex-
amination of injection sites should still be considered, as data 
suggest similarities to reactions described in humans (van Meer 
et al., 2016). 
In conclusion, our data from four LNA SSOs support the use 
of the minipig in the preclinical safety assessment of this class 
of molecules. We demonstrated that the minipig shows a simi-
lar safety profile as the NHP for four different molecules upon 
subacute exposure. No additional off-target pharmacological ef-
fects or non-hybridization-dependent toxicities were identified. 
Consequently, the number of NHPs that are currently used in 
preclinical safety assessment of SSOs could be reduced. Finally, 
species selection should always maximize the likelihood of 
identifying responses that are similar to those expected in hu-
mans. Therefore, the design of respective cross-reactive SSOs to 
the minipig genome, as well as the pharmacologic activity and a 
similarity in the target distribution to humans is essential to ul-
timately select the minipig as the non-rodent species in preclin-
ical safety investigation. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at Toxicological Sciences online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This research project would not have been possible without 
the highly skilled technical support of F. Hoffmann-La Roche 
personnel from in vivo, clinical pathology, histopathology, 
bioanalytical, toxicokinetics laboratories as well as compara-
tive medicine which is gratefully acknowledged. Editorial as-
sistance was provided by Meridian HealthComms, funded by 
F. Hoffmann-La Roche Ltd. Special thanks to Michael Winter 
for his expert support in clinical pathology. All authors, 
except MJM acknowledge that they are employed by F. 
Hoffmann-La Roche, Ltd. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>This work was supported and funded by F. Hoffmann-La Roche 
Ltd, Basel, Switzerland. All authors, except MJM, are employed 
by F. Hoffmann-La Roche Ltd. </p>



<p>128 | TOXICOLOGICAL SCIENCES, 2017, Vol. 157, No. 1 </p>

</text></tei>