<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5031952" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>SUMMARY </p>

<p>While Cas9 nucleases permit rapid and efficient generation of gene-edited cell lines, the CRISPR-Cas9 system can introduce undesirable 
''on-target'' mutations within the second allele of successfully modified cells via non-homologous end joining (NHEJ). To address this, we 
fused the Streptococcus pyogenes Cas9 (SpCas9) nuclease to a peptide derived from the human Geminin protein (SpCas9-Gem) to facilitate 
its degradation during the G 1 phase of the cell cycle, when DNA repair by NHEJ predominates. We also use mRNA transfection to facilitate 
low and transient expression of modified and unmodified versions of Cas9. Although the frequency of homologous recombination was 
similar for SpCas9-Gem and SpCas9, we observed a marked reduction in the capacity for SpCas9-Gem to induce NHEJ-mediated indels at 
the target locus. Moreover, in contrast to native SpCas9, we demonstrate that transient SpCas9-Gem expression enables reliable gener-
ation of both knockin reporter cell lines and genetically repaired patient-specific induced pluripotent stem cell lines free of unwanted 
mutations at the targeted locus. </p>

<p>The utility of human pluripotent stem cells (hPSCs) is 
significantly enhanced by an ability to precisely modify a 
chosen locus with minimal impact on the remaining 
genome. Ideally this is achieved by gene targeting, which 
historically has proved challenging in hPSCs due to the 
low frequency of homologous recombination (HR) (Zwaka  and Thomson, 2003). More recently, genetic modification 
of hPSCs has been facilitated through the use of nucleases 
to induce DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs) at a target 
locus, which are subsequently repaired by HR or the er-
ror-prone non-homologous end-joining (NHEJ) pathway. 
Zinc finger nucleases and transcription activator-like endo-
nucleases (TALENs) were the first sequence-specific nucle-
ases employed for gene targeting in hPSCs (Hockemeyer  et al., 2009, 2011; Zou et al., 2009). However, both ap-
proaches require the design, expression, and validation of 
a new pair of proteins for every targeted locus, rendering 
both of these platforms time consuming and labor inten-
sive. Due to its simplicity, ease of manipulation, and high 
efficiency, the clustered regularly interspaced short palin-
dromic repeats (CRISPR)-Cas9 system is fast becoming the 
preferred method for the precise modification of eukaryotic 
genomes (Cho et al., 2013; Cong et al., 2013; Jinek et al.,  2012, 2013; Mali et al., 2013). However, a potential limita-
tion to this system is the introduction of ''on-target'' 
disruptive mutations caused by Cas9-induced NHEJ occur-
ring within the untargeted allele of knockin or gene-cor-</p>

<p>rected hPSC clones (Howden et al., 2015; Merkle et al.,  2015). Although reducing the Cas9 dosage may limit 
both off-target and on-target NHEJ activity (Cradick et al.,  2013), a corresponding decrease in gene-targeting effi-
ciency is also expected. 
Previous studies, including one in normal human fibro-
blasts, have demonstrated that HR activity is virtually ab-
sent during G 1 phase, increases sharply in S phase, and be-
gins to decrease by G 2 /M, whereas NHEJ activity occurs 
throughout the cell cycle (Mao et al., 2008; Saleh-Gohari  and Helleday, 2004). Hence, controlling the presence of 
Cas9 protein during specific stages of the cell cycle could 
minimize the formation of undesirable insertion or dele-
tion mutations (indels) induced by NHEJ. We hypothesized 
that the presence of Cas9 in G 1 would induce DNA DSBs 
that would invariably be repaired by error-prone NHEJ, 
whereas elimination of the nuclease within this phase 
could potentially limit the introduction of disruptive in-
dels at the target locus. 
Previous studies have shown that fusion of fluorescent 
reporters to an N-terminal peptide derived from the human 
Geminin protein resulted in their proteolytic destruction 
in the late M and G 1 phases of the cell cycle (Pauklin and  Vallier, 2013; Sakaue-Sawano et al., 2008), a process medi-
ated by the APCCdh1 E3 ligase complex (Nishitani et al.,  2004). In this study, an identical Geminin-derived peptide 
was fused to SpCas9 (designated SpCas9-Gem) to facilitate 
nuclease degradation during G 1 . We show that the fre-
quency of HR is not impaired by fusion of the Geminin </p>

<p>508 Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 7 j 508-517 j September 13, 2016 j ª 2016 The Author(s). 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>peptide to SpCas9, but observe a significant decrease in 
NHEJ frequency, as evidenced by the absence of indels 
within the target locus. Together, these features of 
SpCas9-Gem permit efficient and reliable generation of 
both knockin cell lines and gene-corrected patient-specific 
induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC) lines that are free of 
disruptive mutations within the untargeted allele. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>SpCas9-Gem mRNA Transfection Results in Transient 
and Cell-Cycle-Dependent Protein Expression 
SpCas9-Gem was generated by fusing the first 110 amino 
acids of Geminin to the C-terminal region of SpCas9, 
following removal of the C-terminal nuclear localization 
signal (Figure 1A). Because levels of Geminin and Cdt1 
oscillate inversely, whereby Cdt1 levels are highest during 
G 1 and Geminin levels are highest during the S and G 2 
phases (Nishitani et al., 2004; Sakaue-Sawano et al.,  2008), we also generated a second variant of SpCas9 
(termed SpCas9-Cdt1) by fusing SpCas9 to amino acids </p>

<p>30-120 of Cdt1. Fusion of this peptide to fluorescent re-
porters has previously been shown to be sufficient for 
marking cells in G 1 (Pauklin and Vallier, 2013; Sakaue-Sa- wano et al., 2008). An upstream T7 promoter was used 
for in vitro transcription of mRNA encoding SpCas9, 
SpCas9-Gem and SpCas9-Cdt1 (Figure 1A). We performed 
intracellular staining and flow cytometric analysis 
following transfection of mRNA encoding each of the 
Cas9 variants in the human embryonic stem cell line, H9, 
to examine their abundance and stability over time. Prior 
to analysis, cells were incubated in the presence of Hoechst 
33342 to distinguish cells in G 0 /G 1 and S/G 2 phases of the 
cell cycle. Although at 6 hr post transfection all three Cas9 
variants were present at similar levels, by 18 hr post trans-
fection a marked reduction in both SpCas9-Gem and 
SpCas9-Cdt1 abundance was observed relative to native 
SpCas9 (Figure 1B). Furthermore, at both time points 
SpCas9-Gem appeared to be expressed at higher levels in 
the S/G 2 subpopulation, which was not observed for the 
native SpCas9 or SpCas9-Cdt1 variant. Although signifi-
cant expression of SpCas9-Gem in the G 0 /G 1 subpopula-
tion was also noted, we hypothesized that this could be </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>104 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>104 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>104 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>104 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>104 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>104 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>104 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>Untransfected 
(no Cas9) </p>

<p>SpCas9 
6 hrs </p>

<p>18 hrs </p>

<p>SpCas9-Gem 
SpCas9-Cdt1 </p>

<p>Cas9 </p>

<p>Hoechst </p>

<p>SpCas9 SpCas9-
Gem </p>

<p>SpCas9-
Cdt1 </p>

<p>50 kDa </p>

<p>35 kDa </p>

<p>150 kDa </p>

<p>225 kDa </p>

<p>anti-ACTIN </p>

<p>anti-CRISPR/Cas9 </p>

<p>G0/G1 S/G2 G0/G1 S/G2 G0/G1 S/G2 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>NLS </p>

<p>Geminin 
(1/110) </p>

<p>Cdt1 
(30/120) </p>

<p>Cas9 </p>

<p>T7 promoter </p>

<p>SpCas9 </p>

<p>SpCas9-Cdt1 </p>

<p>SpCas9-Gem </p>

<p>G0/G1 S/G2 </p>

<p>G0/G1 S/G2 </p>

<p>G0/G1 S/G2 </p>

<p>G0/G1 S/G2 </p>

<p>G0/G1 S/G2 </p>

<p>G0/G1 S/G2 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Analysis of SpCas9-Gem Protein 
(A) Schematic diagram of the Cas9 variants generated in this study. Unmodified SpCas9, and the SpCas-Gem and SpCas9-Cdt1 variants were 
cloned downstream of a T7 promoter to permit their in vitro transcription. NLS, nuclear localization signal. 
(B) Flow cytometric analysis following intracellular staining of Cas9 protein in H9 cells transfected with mRNA encoding SpCas9, SpCas9-
Gem, or SpCas9-Cdt1. Cells were analyzed at 6 hr and 18 hr post transfection and incubated in the presence of Hoechst 33342 prior to 
harvesting. Untransfected H9 cells are shown as a negative control. 
(C) Western blot analysis of Cas9 protein expression 12 hr post transfection of SpCas9, SpCas9-Gem, or SpCas9-Cdt1 in H9 cells. Prior to 
harvesting, cells were incubated in the presence of Hoechst 33342 and the G 0 /G 1 and S/G 2 subpopulations were sorted based on DNA 
content. Anti-actin was included as a loading control. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 7 j 508-517 j September 13, 2016 509 </p>

<p>due to the binding of CRISPR-Cas9 antibody to not just the 
intact Cas9 protein but also fragmented protein that was 
undergoing or had recently undergone proteolytic destruc-
tion. To address this concern we performed western blot 
analysis on the G 0 /G 1 and S/G 2 subpopulations 12 hr after 
the introduction of mRNA encoding each of the Cas9 
variants into H9 cells, which were subsequently sorted by 
fluorescence-activated cell sorting based on DNA content. 
Using this analysis we clearly detected higher SpCas9-
Gem protein levels in the S/G 2 population relative to 
the G 0 /G 1 (Figure 1C), confirming cell-cycle-dependent 
expression of the SpCas9-Gem variant. </p>

<p>Generation of Indel-Free Knockin Reporter iPSCs from 
Human Fibroblasts 
To evaluate the HR and NHEJ activities associated with 
SpCas9-Gem and SpCas9-Cdt1, we used a recently des-
cribed method that permits both rapid and efficient gener-
ation of gene-edited induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC) 
lines following a single electroporation of human fibro-
blasts (Howden et al., 2015). As in the previous study, we 
chose to target the DNMT3B gene with an EGFP reporter 
(Figure 2A), since DNMT3B is highly expressed in pluripo-
tent cells and quickly downregulated following differentia-
tion, allowing targeted iPSC colonies to be easily identified 
by fluorescent microscopy (Figure 2B) and flow cytometry 
(Figure 2C). Episomal reprogramming vectors, a plasmid 
encoding a single-guide RNA (sgRNA) specific to sequence 
spanning the DNMT3B start codon and a plasmid encoding 
an EGFP reporter flanked by 1.1 kb and 0.7 kb and homol-
ogy arms specific to sequences upstream and downstream 
of the DNMT3B start codon (Figure 2A) were co-transfected 
with mRNA encoding SpCas9, SpCas9-Gem, or SpCas9-
Cdt1. No observable difference in cell viability was associ-
ated with transfection of mRNA encoding SpCas9-Gem or 
SpCas9-Cdt1 compared with the native SpCas9 (Fig-
ure S1A). To estimate targeting efficiency associated with 
each of the Cas9 variants, we passaged cells approximately 
3 weeks post transfection using EDTA to selectively remove 
residual fibroblasts from iPSCs (Howden et al., 2015). After 
three passages the total cell population was analyzed by 
flow cytometry. As measured by the number of EGFP-ex-
pressing cells, targeting efficiency was comparable for 
both the SpCas9 and SpCas9-Gem variants (17.1% versus 
16.5%) but slightly lower for the SpCas9-Cdt1 variant 
(9.9%) (Figure 2C). We did not observe any EGFP-express-
ing cells when Cas9 mRNA was omitted from the transfec-
tion (data not shown). At 2-3 weeks post transfection, 
randomly selected EGFP-expressing and EGFP non-ex-
pressing (EGFP 
neg ) colonies were picked and expanded for </p>

<p>further analysis (Figure 2B and Table 1). EGFP-expressing 
clones were further categorized as either having a single 
allele (EGFP 
+ ) or both DNMT3B alleles (EGFP 
++ ) targeted, </p>

<p>based on flow cytometry and PCR analysis (Figures 2D 
and S1). Of 28 EGFP-expressing clones isolated from trans-
fections performed with SpCas9 or SpCas9-Gem mRNA, we 
observed 11 (39%) and 6 (21%) EGFP 
++ clones, respectively </p>

<p>(Table 1). The SpCas9-Cdt1 variant resulted in only a single 
(6%) EGFP 
++ clone out of 17 clones analyzed. Next we </p>

<p>analyzed the untargeted allele of single-targeted EGFP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>clones by Sanger sequencing of the PCR product amplified 
from genomic DNA using primers flanking the DNMT3B 
start codon (Figure 2D). With respect to unmodified 
SpCas9, NHEJ activity could be detected within the untar-
geted allele in all 17 clones analyzed (Figure 2E), as evi-
denced by the presence of indels ranging from 1 bp to 
over 1 kb in size (Table S1). In contrast, of 22 clones 
analyzed, we identified 8 (36%) ''indel-free'' clones derived 
using the SpCas9-Gem variant, which did not contain mu-
tations within the untargeted DNMT3B allele. Interest-
ingly, indel-free clones could also be generated with the 
SpCas9-Cdt1 variant, albeit with a lower efficiency (2 out 
of 16 EGFP 
+ clones [12%] analyzed). We next investigated </p>

<p>the NHEJ activity associated with each of the Cas9 variants 
in EGFP 
neg clones, again by analysis of PCR amplicons en-</p>

<p>compassing the DNMT3B start codon and surrounding 
sequence. Sequencing analysis revealed indels in all 25 
EGFP 
neg clones expanded and analyzed from experiments </p>

<p>performed with SpCas9, with all but one clone carrying dis-
ruptions in both DNMT3B alleles (Figure 2F and Table S2). 
Mutations in DNMT3B could also be found in the vast ma-
jority (95%) of EGFP 
neg clones isolated and expanded from </p>

<p>experiments performed using SpCas9-Cdt1 mRNA; how-
ever, approximately half of these had only one allele dis-
rupted by NHEJ with the other allele remaining intact. 
Conversely, only 35% of EGFP 
neg clones generated with </p>

<p>the SpCas9-Gem variant contained mutations in DNMT3B, 
with single allele and biallelic disruption in 13% and 22% 
of EGFP 
neg clones, respectively. </p>

<p>Generation of Indel-Free Gene-Corrected iPSCs from 
Patient Fibroblasts 
Next we assessed the capacity of SpCas9-Gem to facilitate 
the derivation of gene-corrected iPSCs lacking deleterious 
indels within the second allele. To demonstrate this, we 
chose to correct an autosomal dominant G &gt; A transition 
(R853Q) in exon 14 of the SCN2A gene identified in a pedi-
atric patient with severe epilepsy. We attempted to simulta-
neously reprogram and correct the disease-causing muta-
tion in the patient fibroblasts using our one-step protocol 
and mRNA encoding SpCas9, SpCas9-Gem, or SpCas9-
Cdt1. To facilitate gene repair we used an sgRNA encom-
passing the patient-specific mutation and a plasmid encod-
ing wild-type SCN2A sequence, comprising z0.9-kb arms 
flanking the intended DNA DSB. A silent 3-bp change 
was also included to aid in identification of correctly </p>

<p>510 Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 7 j 508-517 j September 13, 2016 </p>

<p>modified clones and to minimize Cas9 recutting following 
HR with the homologous template (Figure 3A). To assess 
HR and NHEJ activities, we extracted genomic DNA from 
randomly selected iPSC colonies, followed by sequencing 
analysis of the PCR product amplified using primers flank-</p>

<p>ing exon 14 of SCN2A. With respect to the SpCas9-Gem 
variant, gene repair was observed in 5 of 30 clones (17%) 
screened, as evidenced by the loss of the disease-causing 
mutation and gain of the 3-bp synonymous change carried 
by the corrective plasmid (Figures 3B and 3C). Indel </p>

<p>DNMT3B </p>

<p>Ex 23 
Ex 1 
Ex 2 </p>

<p>1.1 kb </p>

<p>pA 3' arm 
5' arm 
EGFP </p>

<p>0.7 kb </p>

<p>Cas9 target site </p>

<p>Phase 
EGFP+ </p>

<p>0 
1 0 3 
10 4 
10 5 </p>

<p>EGFP+ </p>

<p>SpCas9-Gem (16.5%) </p>

<p>SpCas9 (17.1%) </p>

<p>SpCas9-Cdt1 (9.9%) </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>200 μm 
200 μm </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>20 
15 
10 </p>

<p>30 
25 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>%indel-free EGFP+ clones </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>SpCas9 SpCas9-
Gem </p>

<p>SpCas9-
Cdt1 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>% EGFP neg </p>

<p>clones with indel </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>one allele 
both alleles 
total </p>

<p>SpCas9 
SpCas9-
Gem </p>

<p>SpCas9-
Cdt1 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>ATG </p>

<p>Unmodified allele 
1.8 kb 
Targeted allele 
2.9 kb </p>

<p>EGFP </p>

<p>DNMT3B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Double 
EGFP++ 
Single 
EGFP+ 
unmod. 
control </p>

<p>ATG (start) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Figure 2. Generation of Knockin Reporter iPSC Lines Using Cas9 Variants 
(A) Schematic diagram of the DNMT3B locus and the homologous template used for gene targeting. pA, polyA signal; Ex, exon. 
(B) Representative phase contrast and fluorescent images depicting an EGFP-expressing and non-expressing iPSC colony emerging 
approximately 2 weeks after simultaneous reprogramming and gene targeting of DNMT3B in human fibroblasts. 
(C) Targeting efficiency associated with SpCas9, SpCas9-Gem and SpCas9-Cdt1 assessed by flow cytometric analysis of the total iPSC 
population after EDTA passaging, initiated approximately 3 weeks post electroporation. 
(D) Schematic of the DNMT3B locus showing location of PCR primers used to screen EGFP-expressing clones, and representative gel analysis 
of the PCR products amplified from EGFP-expressing clones. These primers preferentially amplify the untargeted allele in monoallelic 
(EGFP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) clones, whereas only the larger 2.9-kb band is visible following PCR analysis of biallelic (EGFP 
++ ) clones. 
(E) Proportion of single-targeted EGFP 
+ clones identified without disruption of the other untargeted DNMT3B allele. 
(F) Proportion of EGFP 
neg (untargeted) iPSC clones with one or both DNMT3B alleles disrupted by NHEJ. EGFP 
+ and EGFP 
neg colonies were 
isolated and expanded from three independent experiments, performed with each version of Cas9. Data represent mean ± SEM from three 
independent experiments. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 7 j 508-517 j September 13, 2016 511 </p>

<p>formation at the second SCN2A allele could not be detected 
in four of the gene-corrected clones, although biallelic HR 
with the repair template was observed, as evidenced by ho-
mozygosity for the plasmid-specific 3-bp change (TCA &gt; 
AGC). Targeted correction of SCN2A was also observed 
with the SpCas9 and SpCas9-Cdt1 variants, although at a 
lower frequency (9.7% and 3.3%, respectively). Further-
more, only one gene-corrected clone out of 31 (3.3%) 
iPSC colonies screened for both the SpCas9 and SpCas9-
Cdt1 variants did not contain a secondary mutation at 
the other SCN2A allele. As seen in the previous DNMT3B 
targeting experiment, sequencing analysis of uncorrected 
iPSC clones revealed a much lower incidence of NHEJ asso-
ciated with the SpCas9-Gem variant compared with un-
modified SpCas9 and the SpCas9-Cdt1 variant (Figure 3D). 
Although our sgRNA was designed to recognize the mutant 
over wild-type SCN2A allele, indels could be detected in 
both alleles for each of the Cas9 variants tested. This is 
not unexpected, since single mismatches in sgRNA are 
often well tolerated, even within the 3 
0 end of the proto-</p>

<p>spacer sequence (Fu et al., 2013; Hsu et al., 2013). However, 
analysis of all clones with only a single allele disrupted by 
NHEJ did reveal a preference for the mutant allele (Fig-
ure 3D and Table S3). </p>

<p>SpCas9-Gem Retains HR Capacity with Reduced NHEJ 
Activity in hPSCs 
To evaluate the SpCas9-Gem variant in a cell type other 
than human fibroblasts, we utilized iPSC lines generated 
in the previous experiments (see Figure S1) that harbor 
EGFP targeted to both DNMT3B alleles. For a homologous 
template we used a plasmid encoding the full-length BFP 
sequence that was identical to EGFP except for C &gt; G and 
T &gt; C transitions, corresponding to two consecutive amino 
acid changes (T67S and Y68H) (Figure 4A). This is sufficient 
for conversion of EGFP to BFP reporter expression (Glaser  et al., 2016). We also included a plasmid encoding an 
sgRNA that specifically recognizes EGFP over BFP. Using 
this system in an iPSC line constitutively expressing </p>

<p>EGFP, we simultaneously estimated both HR (as deter-
mined by the number of BFP 
+ cells) and NHEJ frequencies </p>

<p>(as determined by the number of EGFP 
neg cells) in the total </p>

<p>population of transfected cells after 3 days by flow cytom-
etry (Figure 4B). SpCas9 or SpCas9-Gem mRNA resulted 
in similar levels of HR, as determined by the number of 
BFP 
+ cells, when co-transfected with BFP plasmid DNA </p>

<p>and EGFP-specific sgRNA into two independent EGFP </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>iPSC lines (Figures 4B and 4C). However, a significantly 
reduced proportion of EGFP 
neg cells, caused by disruption </p>

<p>of the EGFP gene, was consistently associated with the 
SpCas9-Gem variant. This approximately 2-fold reduction 
in NHEJ activity was observed in both the presence and 
absence of the BFP donor template (Figure 4C). To deter-
mine whether simply lowering the nuclease dosage could 
also achieve reduced indel formation while maintaining 
HR efficiency, we co-transfected 50, 100, 250, or 500 ng 
of mRNA encoding SpCas9 with the BFP plasmid and 
EGFP-specific sgRNA plasmid into iPSCs constitutively ex-
pressing EGFP. In agreement with previous studies, lower 
concentrations of Cas9 did indeed reduce NHEJ frequency, 
although a consequential decrease in HR efficiency was also 
observed. Specifically, the lowest dose of SpCas9 mRNA 
(50 ng) reduced NHEJ to rates observed with 500 ng of 
the SpCas9-Gem mRNA but resulted in more than 5-fold 
reduction in HR frequency (Figure S2A). A positive correla-
tion between Cas9 mRNA concentration and HR efficiency 
was also observed when targeting EGFP to the DNMT3B 
locus in H9 cells (Figure S2B). Furthermore, no significant 
difference in targeting efficiency was observed following 
co-transfection of mRNA encoding SpCas9 or SpCas9-
Gem with the DNMT3B-EGFP homologous template and 
DNMT3B-specific sgRNA in H9 cells (Figure S3A). We also 
evaluated the ''on-target'' indel frequency of the SpCas9-
Gem variant following targeting of the DNMT3B and 
GAPDH loci in H9 cells. In these experiments, we used tar-
geting constructs that contain a drug-selectable marker to 
facilitate rapid isolation, expansion, and characterization 
of individual colonies (Figures S3B and S3C). Consistent 
with the EGFP-to-BFP conversion assay in the previous ex-
periments, an approximately 2-to 3-fold reduction in NHEJ 
activity was associated with the SpCas9-Gem variant 
compared with native SpCas9. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The recent development of the CRISPR-Cas9 system 
will undoubtedly have an enormous impact on the utility 
of hPSCs for the elucidation of developmental processes, 
disease modeling, or even personalized regenerative medi-
cine. However, the reliable and efficient generation of 
knockin or gene-corrected hPSCs without secondary </p>

<p>Table 1. Number of iPSC Clones Isolated, Expanded, and 
Characterized Following Targeting of the DNMT3B Locus </p>

<p>Targeted (EGFP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) Clones Non-targeted 
(EGFP </p>

<p>neg </p>

<p>) 
Clones </p>

<p>Total Clones 
Analyzed 
One Allele Both Alleles </p>

<p>SpCas9 
17 (0) 
11 
25 
53 </p>

<p>SpCas9-Gem 22 (8) 
6 
23 
51 </p>

<p>SpCas9-Cdt1 16 (2) 
1 
22 
39 </p>

<p>The number of clones with EGFP targeted to one allele without an additional 
mutation in the untargeted allele is shown in parentheses. </p>



<p>deleterious mutations has been somewhat elusive. Because 
cell-cycle phase largely determines the frequency of the 
alternative HR and NHEJ DNA repair pathways, it is reason-
able to expect that controlling the timing of a DNA DSB 
may selectively favor one pathway over the other. Chemi-
cal-mediated cell synchronization followed by timed deliv-
ery of Cas9-guide RNA ribonucleoprotein complexes has 
recently been shown to be effective for increasing HR effi-
ciency in the human cell line HEK-293, although whether 
this led to decreased NHEJ activity in alleles that had not 
undergone HR was not reported (Lin et al., 2014). More-
over, different cell types, such as hPSCs, have distinct re-
quirements for synchronization, which do not always 
translate to effective increases in HR. Recent studies have 
also shown that small molecules such as SCR7 may inhibit 
NHEJ and consequently promote HR (Maruyama et al.,  2015). However, these kinds of approaches are likely to </p>

<p>have variable effects across different cell types and may 
potentially exhibit undesirable cytotoxic effects, rendering 
them unsuitable in therapeutic contexts. In an attempt to 
address some of these issues, we generated a variant of 
the SpCas9 nuclease (SpCas9-Gem) that persists during 
stages of the cell cycle when the HR pathway is active, 
but is degraded during G 1 , when NHEJ activity predomi-
nates. An attractive feature of the SpCas9-Gem variant is 
its potential applicability to different cell types without a 
requirement for cells to be manipulated or specially pre-
pared prior to introduction of the gene-editing factors. In 
the current study we have demonstrated the versatility of 
SpCas9-Gem in primary human fibroblasts and hPSCs, 
two cell types known to exhibit very different cell-cycle 
profiles. Although the lower frequency of NHEJ associated 
with SpCas9-Gem was less pronounced in hPSCs, we hy-
pothesize that this may be attributed to the dramatically </p>

<p>UAGUAAGGUC </p>

<p>T T 
G 
T 
T 
A 
T 
G 
T </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>A 
C 
C 
A 
G </p>

<p>c 
G </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C 
A a </p>

<p>C 
C 
T ATTCC G </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CTG taaattaactgggag 
g 
A </p>

<p>uu </p>

<p>ser 
arg 
phe 
C 
AG 
G </p>

<p>gln </p>

<p>arg </p>

<p>leu 
leu 
val 
ser 
leu </p>

<p>Ex 26 
Ex 1 
Ex 14 
SCN2A </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>9.7% </p>

<p>16.6% </p>

<p>13.3% </p>

<p>3.3% 
3.3% </p>

<p>uncorrected </p>

<p>corrected (heterozygous) </p>

<p>corrected (homozygous) </p>

<p>corrected + indel </p>

<p>total 
indel-free </p>

<p>% gene corrected clones </p>

<p>mutant allele 
wt allele 
both alleles 
total </p>

<p>SpCas9 SpCas9-
Gem </p>

<p>SpCas9-
Cdt1 </p>

<p>SpCas9 SpCas9-
Gem </p>

<p>SpCas9-
Cdt1 </p>

<p>% clones with indel </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Figure 3. Generation of Gene-Corrected 
iPSC Lines Using Cas9 Variants 
(A) Schematic diagram of the SCN2A gene, 
with mutation in exon 14. The crRNA 
sequence used (red), PAM location (bold), 
and the patient-specific autosomal domi-
nant mutation (blue) along with the 3-bp 
synonymous change (green) incorporated 
into the plasmid template used for repair are 
shown. Exon sequences are in uppercase, 
introns in lowercase. 
(B) Sequencing analysis of exon 14 of the 
SCN2A gene from a representative uncor-
rected patient-specific iPSC clone and three 
gene-corrected iPSC clones with either one 
allele targeted (heterozygote), both alleles 
targeted (homozygote), or one allele tar-
geted and the other disrupted by NHEJ. 
(C) Proportion of gene-corrected iPSC clones 
without disruption of the second SCN2A 
allele. 
(D) Proportion of uncorrected iPSC clones 
with one or both SCN2A alleles disrupted by 
NHEJ. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 7 j 508-517 j September 13, 2016 513 </p>

<p>shorter G 0 /G 1 phase that is characteristic of hPSCs, 
compared with somatic cell types such as fibroblasts. 
While this manuscript was in preparation, Gutschner  et al. (2016) also described a version of SpCas9 fused to 
the N-terminal region of human Geminin. Although the 
authors reported a modest increase (28%-87%) in HR 
compared with unmodified SpCas9 in HEK293T cells, their 
Cas9-Geminin fusion provoked similar levels of indel for-
mation. This may be explained by their use of plasmid 
DNA to express Cas9 from a b-actin promoter, resulting 
in sustained levels of nuclease transcription that likely per-
sists over several days and during the course of multiple cy-
cles of cell division. In the study presented here, transfec-
tion of in vitro transcribed mRNA was utilized, enabling </p>

<p>uniform and transient expression of SpCas9-Gem protein 
during S/G 2 . Following degradation during G 1 , nuclease 
levels are drastically reduced, even in subsequent S/G 2 
phases, which can most likely be attributed to the transient 
and unstable properties of mRNA. 
Of note, the SpCas9-Cdt1 variant also enabled the gener-
ation of correctly targeted lines, albeit with a lower effi-
ciency than the unmodified or SpCas9-Gem variants. 
Although this may be due to the fact that proteins fused 
to the Cdt1 peptide can persist during the initial stages of 
S phase, when HR becomes a potential option for DNA 
repair, this may also be the result of incomplete degrada-
tion of SpCas9-Cdt1 during S/G 2 /M (see Figure 1). The 
SpCas9-Cdt1 fusion induced indel formation significantly </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>S p C a s 9 
+ p B F P 
S p C a s 9 -G e m 
+ p B F P </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>EGFP+ </p>

<p>BFP+ </p>

<p>%EGFP++ cells </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>S p C a s 9 
S p C a s 9 -G e m 
p B F P </p>

<p>%BFP+ cells </p>

<p>GACCACCCTGACCTACGGCGTGCAGTGCTTCAGCCG </p>

<p>GACCACCCTGAGCCACGGCGTGCAGTGCTTCAGCCG </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 0 
1 0 0 
1 5 0 
2 0 0 
2 5 0 </p>

<p>0.1% BFP+ </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.4% BFP+ </p>

<p>ser his </p>

<p>thr tyr </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>EGFP </p>

<p>BFP </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>60.4% 
neg </p>

<p>36.5% 
EGFP++ </p>

<p>SpCas9 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>64.0% 
neg </p>

<p>33.1% 
EGFP++ </p>

<p>SpCas9 + pBFP </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>3.1% BFP+ </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>67.3% 
EGFP++ </p>

<p>27.4% 
neg </p>

<p>Cas9-Gem </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 3 
10 4 
10 5 </p>

<p>97.7% 
EGFP++ </p>

<p>0.1% 
neg </p>

<p>pBFP (no Cas9) </p>

<p>EGFP </p>

<p>SSC </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 3 
10 4 
10 5 </p>

<p>34.7% 
neg </p>

<p>60.9% 
EGFP++ </p>

<p>Cas9-Gem + pBFP </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>3.2% BFP+ </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>0.1% BFP+ </p>

<p>BFP </p>

<p>SSC </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
1 0 
1 0 
50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
1 0 
1 0 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
1 0 
1 0 </p>

<p>Figure 4. Evaluation of SpCas9-Gem in Pluripotent Stem Cells 
(A) Schematic summary of EGFP-to-BFP conversion targeting strategy. The location of the two amino acid changes and the Cas9 target site 
(red) are indicated. 
(B and C) Representative flow cytometry plots (B) and graphical plot (C) depicting the proportion of BFP 
+ (targeting efficiency) and 
EGFP 
neg cells (NHEJ frequency) assessed 3 days after the introduction of SpCas9 and SpCas9-Gem with and without a BFP homologous 
template in iPSCs constitutively expressing EGFP. Data represent the average ± SD of four independent experiments in two EGFP 
++ iPSC 
lines. *p &lt; 0.0001, **p &lt; 0.000001. </p>

<p>514 Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 7 j 508-517 j September 13, 2016 </p>

<p>more often than SpCas9-Gem but at a lower frequency 
than unmodified SpCas9, which was particularly evident 
when assessing the total number of alleles disrupted by 
NHEJ. It is difficult to determine whether this is due to 
lower overall levels of SpCas9-Cdt1 or perhaps a reduced 
nuclease activity relative to unmodified SpCas9. 
Although any off-target effects associated with the Cas9 
variants generated in this study were not analyzed, the 
lower NHEJ activity of SpCas9-Gem would likely translate 
to a reduction in unwanted mutations across the genome. 
Nonetheless, the incorporation of the Geminin peptide 
into the recently described high-fidelity versions of SpCas9 
(SpCas9-HF1 and eCas9) (Kleinstiver et al., 2016; Slaymaker  et al., 2016) may reduce the likelihood of off-target NHEJ 
further. 
In conclusion, the SpCas9-Gem variant described here fa-
cilitates efficient and reliable generation of knockin and 
gene-corrected hPSC lines free of unwanted mutations at 
the targeted locus. Our results demonstrate the utility of 
SpCas9-Gem for achieving effective and precise genome 
modifications while minimizing the ''on-target'' effects of 
NHEJ in both somatic cells types, such as fibroblasts, and 
pluripotent cell types, such as embryonic stem cells and 
iPSCs. This is a significant advance in the downstream 
application of hPSCs for disease modeling and functional 
genomics, and prepares the field for gene-correction appli-
cations in regenerative medicine. The use of additional 
peptides or sequences that promote greater cell-cycle spec-
ificity of Cas9 may permit even further reductions in ''on-
target'' NHEJ while increasing desirable HR activity. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Oligonucleotide and gBlock Sequences </p>

<p>A list of oligonucleotide (ODN) sequences for PCR amplification 
and generation of sgRNA plasmids (Table S4) and complete se-
quences of the gBlocks (Integrated DNA Technologies) used in 
this study can be found in Supplemental Sequencing Data. </p>

<p>Vector Construction </p>

<p>To enable in vitro transcription of mRNA encoding SpCas9, an 
XbaI-NsiI fragment from plasmid hCas9 (Addgene plasmid 
#41815) containing the entire SpCas9 sequence was inserted into 
the NheI and SbfI sites of the pDNR-Dual vector (Clontech), to 
generate pDNR-SpCas9. The SpCas9-Gem variant was generated 
by PCR-amplifying sequence from hCas9 using ODNs 1 and 2 
and sequence from pTRE-CellCycle (Clontech) using ODNs 3 
and 4 followed by insertion into the EcoRI and AgeI restriction sites 
in pDNR-SpCas9. The pSpCas9-CdtI variant was generated by PCR-
amplifying sequence from hCas9 using ODNs 1 and 2 and 
sequence from pTRE-CellCycle (Clontech) using ODNs 3 and 5 fol-
lowed by insertion into the EcoRI and AgeI restriction sites in 
pDNR-SpCas9. For construction of the DNMT3B targeting vector, 
a gBlock encoding 5 
0 BglII and NdeI sites, nucleotides 150-724 of </p>

<p>the EGFP gene, an SV40 polyA signal, and 700 bp of sequence 
beginning at the DNMT3B start codon was cloned into the HincII 
site of the pSMARTHCKan plasmid vector (Lucigen). ODNs 6 and 
7 were used to PCR amplify (from a previously generated BAC 
clone carrying an EGFP reporter inserted at the DNMT3B 
start codon) a DNA fragment carrying an approximately 1.1-kb 
sequence upstream of the DNMT3B start codon and the first 
150 bp of EGFP, which was subsequently inserted into the BglII 
and NdeI sites of the plasmid described above. A plasmid designed 
for insertion and expression of sgRNA sequences was constructed 
by inserting a gBlock encoding a U6 promoter, two BbsI sites, 
and SpCas9-specific tracrRNA sequence into the HincII site of 
pSMARTHCKan. ODNs specific to each target locus were annealed 
and inserted into the BbsI sites of the pSMART-sgRNA vector. For 
repair of the patient-specific mutation, two gBlocks encoding a to-
tal of 1750 bp of the SCN2A gene was inserted into the AatII and 
EcoRI sites of the pDNR-Dual vector. A serine residue within the re-
gion recognized by our SCN2A-specific sgRNA was changed from 
TCA to AGT to minimize Cas9-induced cutting of the plasmid 
following its introduction into cells. A BFP targeting vector was 
generated by inserting a gBlock encoding the full-length BFP 
gene into the AatII and EcoRI sites of pDNR-Dual. The DNMT3B 
gene-targeting construct containing the EGFP and puromycin 
resistance genes was generated as previously described (Howden  et al., 2015). The plasmids used for in vitro transcription of native 
SpCas9 (plasmid 80425), SpCas9-Gem (plasmid 80424), and 
SpCas9-Cdt1 (plasmid 80426) along with the plasmid used for 
sgRNA expression (plasmid 80427) are all available from Addgene 
upon request. </p>

<p>In Vitro Transcription </p>

<p>Capped and polyadenylated in vitro transcribed mRNA encoding 
SpCas9, SpCas9-Gem, and SpCas9-Cdt1 was generated using the 
mMESSAGE mMACHINE T7 ULTRA transcription kit (Thermo 
Fisher) according to the manufacturer's recommendations. 
Plasmid template was linearized with PmeI prior to transcription. 
LiCl was used to precipitate mRNA before resuspension. A trun-
cated version of the EBNA1 protein was transcribed using the 
mMESSAGE mMACHINE SP6 transcription kit, as previously 
described (Howden et al., 2006). </p>

<p>Transfection </p>

<p>All transfections were performed using the Neon Transfection Sys-
tem (Thermo Fisher). For simultaneous reprogramming and gene 
editing of human fibroblasts, cells were harvested with TrypLE 
(Thermo Fisher) 2 days after passaging and resuspended in Buffer 
R at a final concentration of 1 3 10 
7 cells/mL. One hundred micro-</p>

<p>liters of the cell suspension was added to a tube containing plas-
mids necessary for both reprogramming and gene targeting as 
well as mRNA encoding either SpCas9, SpCas9-Gem, or SpCas9-
Cdt1. In vitro transcribed mRNA encoding a truncated version of 
the EBNA1 protein was also included to enhance nuclear uptake 
of the reprogramming plasmids (Chen et al., 2011; Howden  et al., 2006). See Table S5 for DNA/mRNA concentrations used in 
each transfection. Electroporation was performed in 100-mL tips 
using the following conditions: 1,400 V, 20 ms, two pulses. 
Following electroporation, cells were plated on a single 10-cm </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 7 j 508-517 j September 13, 2016 515 </p>

<p>Matrigel-coated (Corning) plate and maintained in fibroblast me-
dium until 4 days post transfection, then switched to E7 medium 
(E8 medium without transforming growth factor b) supplemented 
with 100 mM sodium butyrate and changed every other day as 
described previously (Chen et al., 2011). Sodium butyrate was 
removed from the medium after the appearance of the first iPSC 
colonies at around day 10. iPSC and H9 transfections were per-
formed in 10-mL and 100-mL tips, respectively, according to the 
manufacturer's recommendation using the following conditions: 
1,100 V, 30 ms, one pulse. Following transfection, cells were trans-
ferred to Matrigel-coated plates containing E8 medium supple-
mented with 5 mM Y-27632 (Tocris), which was omitted in subse-
quent media changes. </p>

<p>Cell Culture </p>

<p>Fibroblast lines were derived from donors with informed parental 
consent and approval from the local research ethics committee. Fi-
broblasts were cultured in DMEM (Thermo Fisher) supplemented 
with 15% fetal bovine serum (HyClone) at 37 
C, 5% CO 2 , and </p>

<p>5% O 2 . All hPSC lines were maintained and expanded in E8 me-
dium with daily media changes and passaged every 3-4 days 
with EDTA in 13 PBS as previously described (Chen et al., 2011). </p>

<p>PCR, RT-PCR, and Sanger Sequencing </p>

<p>Total genomic DNA was extracted using the DNeasy Blood and Tis-
sue kit (Qiagen). PCR was performed using GoTaq Green PCR Mas-
termix (Promega). Sequence encompassing the DNMT3B start 
codon and surrounding region PCR was amplified using ODNs 8 
and 9. Exon 14 of SCN2A and surrounding sequence was amplified 
using ODNs 15 and 16. Prior to sequencing, PCR amplicons 
were treated with rAPid Alkaline Phosphatase (Roche Life Science) 
and Endonuclease I (NEB) for 30 min at 37 
C followed by heat </p>

<p>inactivation at 80 
C for 15 min. Sequencing reactions were per-</p>

<p>formed using BigDye Terminator v3.1 (Thermo Fisher). Reactions 
were purified and sequenced by the Australian Genome Research 
Facility. </p>

<p>Flow Cytometry </p>

<p>Cells were analyzed for EGFP and BFP expression by flow cytome-
try using a LSRFortessa Call Analyzer (BD Biosciences). Data acqui-
sition and analysis were performed using FACSDiva (Becton Dick-
inson) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">FlowLogic</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Inivai</rs>). Gating was performed on 
live cells based on forward and side scatter analysis. </p>

<p>Cell Sorting </p>

<p>Prior to sorting, cells were harvested with TrypLE and resuspended 
in 2 mL of E8 medium containing Hoechst 33,342 (10 mg/mL) and 
incubated at 37 
C for 30 min. Cells were sorted according to their </p>

<p>DNA content using a FACSAria Fusion Cell Sorter (BD Biosciences). </p>

<p>Western Blot </p>

<p>Western blots were performed by standard Tris-glycine SDS-PAGE 
followed by transfer to polyvinylidene fluoride membranes. 
Following blocking with 10% skim milk in TBS-T (20 mM Tris-Cl 
[pH 8.0], 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% Tween 20), membranes were probed 
with anti-CRISPR/Cas9 (Abcam, ab191468) at 1 mg/mL and anti-</p>

<p>b-actin (Cell Signaling Technology, #4970) at 1:5,000 and visual-
ized by chemiluminescence. </p>

<p>Intracellular Staining </p>

<p>Prior to harvest, cells were incubated in medium containing Hoechst 
33342 (10 mg/mL) at 37 
C for 30 min. Cells were harvested, </p>

<p>fixed with 2% paraformaldehyde, and permeabilized with 0.1% 
Triton X-100. Cells were stained with anti-CRISPR/Cas9 (AbCam, 
ab191468) for 1 hr followed by staining with a goat immunoglobulin 
G anti-mouse secondary antibody directly conjugated to allophyco-
cyanin. Cells were analyzed by flow cytometry as described above. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION </p>

<p>Supplemental Information includes Supplemental Sequencing 
Data, three figures, and five tables and can be found with this 
article online at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.stemcr.2016.07.001. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>S.E.H. conceived the experiments and wrote the paper; B.M and J.V 
performed western blot analysis; A.G. conceptualized EGFP-to-BFP 
conversion experiments; S.P. facilitated SCN2A gene-correction ex-
periments; A.G.E., M.H.L., and E.G.S. provided supervision and as-
sisted in manuscript preparation. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>S.E.H. is supported by a National Health and Medical Research 
Council (NHMRC) Overseas Biomedical Fellowship. A.G.E. and 
E.G.S. are Senior Research Fellows and M.H.L. Senior Principal 
Research Fellow of the NHMRC. Murdoch Children's Research 
Institute is supported by the Victorian Government's Operational 
Infrastructure Support Program. </p>

<p>Received: March 17, 2016 
Revised: July 1, 2016 
Accepted: July 4, 2016 
Published: August 4, 2016 </p>







</text></tei>