<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5181807" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>We investigated the relationship between augmentation index (AI) and smoking habits in community-dwelling Japanese. 
This cross-sectional study enrolled 1926 subjects (769 males and 1157 females) aged 40 to 95 years who underwent a health 
check-up in a Japanese cohort of the Seven Countries Study, in Tanushimaru, a typical farming town in Kyushu Island in 2009. The 
subjects' medical history, alcohol intake, smoking habit, and current medications for hypertension, dyslipidemia, and diabetes were 
ascertained by questionnaire. Radial arterial pressure wave analysis was used to obtain AI. We analyzed the data stratified by gender. 
Age-adjusted means of AI in males showed a clear dose-response relationship in 4 categories of smoking habits (P = 0.010). 
There was no significant relationship between AI and smoking habits in females (P = 0.127). The significant dose-response 
relationship (P = 0.036) in males between AI and 4 categories of smoking habits still remained even after adjustment for age, body 
mass index, systolic blood pressure, estimated glomerular filtration rate, glucose, hypertensive medication, and alcohol intake. 
The present study demonstrated that AI values were significantly associated with smoking habits in a dose-dependent manner in 
Japanese males. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: AI = augmentation index, BMI = body mass index, BP = blood pressure, BUN = blood urea nitrogen, CAD = 
coronary artery disease, DL = dyslipidemic, DM = diabetes mellitus, eGFR = estimated glomerular filtration rate, FPG = fasting 
plasma glucose, HbA 1c = glycosylated hemoglobin A 1c , HDL-c = high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, HT = hypertensive, LDL-c = 
low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, PP = pulse pressure, PWV = pulse wave velocity. </p>

<p>Tanushimaru Study is a cohort of the Seven Countries Study, [1] 
which has begun in 1958. Tanushimaru is a rural farming 
community located in southwestern Japan. Although the Seven 
Countries Study ended in 1989, we continued the epidemiologic 
study in the same district. As previously reported, the 
demographic backgrounds of the subjects in this area are similar 
to those of the Japanese general population. [2] During the past 6 
decades, lifestyle and eating patterns have been dramatically </p>

<p>changes, associated with socioeconomic development, [3] which 
may affect atherosclerosis development. [4,5] 
In atherosclerosis progression, inflammation, and immune 
responses are involved in all layers of the arterial wall, [6] which 
can cause abnormal vasospastic responses. [7,8] In such situation, 
arterial stiffness has been a good marker to detect the early stages 
of atherosclerosis, which is also able to predict coronary artery 
disease (CAD) events to a larger extent than brachial pulse 
pressure (PP), not only because it directly influences left 
ventricular afterload and coronary perfusion, but also because 
it may partially parallel the extent of coronary atherosclerosis. [9] 
Arterial stiffness can be noninvasively assessed by measurement 
of pulse wave velocity (PWV), a simple and reproducible 
method. [10] Different aspects of large artery stiffness at rest in 
relation to ischemic threshold have been assessed using arterial 
compliance, distensibility index, and augmentation index (AI). [11] 
Cigarette smoking is one of the most important causes of 
cardiovascular diseases acting via oxidative stress, [12] in which it 
has been demonstrated that smoking increases arterial stiffness, 
independent of blood pressure (BP). [13,14] Interestingly, smoking 
cessation more than a decade has been reported to recover 
arterial stiffness parameters to nonsignificant levels, [13] because 
smoking cessation reduces the levels of inflammatory markers 
such as C-reactive protein and fibrinogen. [15] However, no study 
has focused on the effects of dose-dependency of current 
smoking, including smoking cessation, on arterial stiffness using 
AI in a general population. Therefore, this study aimed to 
examine whether radial AI is associated with smoking habits in a 
Japanese general population in Tanushimaru Study. </p>

<p>Editor: Giovanni Tarantino. </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>a Division of Cardio-Vascular Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Kurume 
University School of Medicine, Kurume, Japan, b Department of Community 
Medicine, Kurume University School of Medicine, Kurume, Japan. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Correspondence: Hisashi Adachi, Department of Community Medicine, Kurume 
University School of Medicine, 67 Asahi-machi, Kurume 830-0011, Japan 
(e-mail: hadac@med.kurume-u.ac.jp). </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC), where it is 
permissible to download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided 
it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially without permission 
from the journal. </p>

<p>Medicine (2016) 95:51(e5368) </p>

<p>Received: 20 July 2016 / Received in final form: 17 October 2016 / Accepted: 
17 October 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000005368 </p>

<p>Observational Study </p>

<p>Medicine ® </p>

<p>OPEN </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2. Subjects and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Study population </p>

<p>A total of 1943 subjects (774 males and 1169 females; aged 
40-95 years) were enrolled in this study in Tanushimaru, a 
typical farming town, where we have conducted a periodic 
epidemiological survey in 2009, and performed cross-sectional 
analysis. The respondents accounted for 48.2% of the men and 
62.0% of the women in Tanushimaru who were older than 40 
years of age (total target population: 3463). </p>

<p>2.2. Data collection </p>

<p>The subjects' medical history, use of alcohol, and smoking were 
ascertained by a questionnaire. Alcohol intake was classified as 
current habitual use or not. We also obtained the data of 
medications for hypertension, dyslipidemia, and diabetes, and 
history of CAD. Daily cigarette consumption in males was 
expressed 4 categories such as nonsmoker (n = 225), former 
smoker (n = 346), current smoking of 1 to 19 cigarettes per day 
(light smoker, n = 89), and 20 or more (heavy smoker, n = 109). 
Daily cigarette consumption in females was expressed 4 
categories such as nonsmoker (n = 1104), former smoker (n = 
19), current smoking of 1 to 19 cigarettes per day (light smoker, 
n = 24), and 20 or more (heavy smoker, n = 10). The nonsmokers 
were defined as no past or current history of smoking, the former 
smokers as smoking cessation before the examination, and the 
current smokers as smoking at least 1 cigarette a day. Height and 
weight were measured, and body mass index (BMI) was 
calculated as weight (kilograms) divided by the square of height 
(square meters) as an index of obesity. BP was measured in the 
supine position twice at 3-minute intervals using an upright 
standard sphygmomanometer. Vigorous physical activity and 
smoking were avoided for at least 30 minutes before BP 
measurement. The second BP with the fifth-phase diastolic 
pressure was used for analysis. 
Blood was drawn from the antecubital vein for determinations 
of lipids profiles (total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein 
cholesterol [HDL-c], low-density lipoprotein cholesterol [LDL-c] 
and triglycerides), uric acid and glycosylated hemoglobin A 1c 
[HbA 1c (Japan Diabetes Society)]. Fasting blood samples were 
centrifuged within 1 hour after collection. Estimated glomerular 
filtration rate (eGFR) was calculated according to the following 
estimation formula that has been recommended by the Japan 
Society of Nephrology: eGFR (mL/min/1.73 2 ) = (194 Â Scr -1.094-
Â age -0.287 ) Â (0.739 for females). [16] 
Other chemistries, such as lipid profiles (enzymatic assay 
method), HbA 1c (ion-exchange high-performance liquid chro-
matography), creatinine (enzymatic assay method), uric acid (a 
standard analytical technique), and fasting plasma glucose (FPG) 
were measured at a commercially available laboratory (Kyodo 
Igaku Laboratory, Fukuoka, Japan). 
The measurements of BP and radial AI were conducted after 
the subjects had rested for 5 minutes in a sitting position, in an air-
conditioned room (18-24°C) earmarked exclusively for this 
purpose. The BP was determined in the right upper arm using an 
oscillometric method (HEM-900AI; Omron Healthcare Co. Ltd, 
Kyoto, Japan). 
This study was approved by the Japan Medical Association of 
Ukiha (Tanushimaru) branch, by a mayor, and by the welfare 
section of the Tanushimaru town office. The Ukiha and 
Tanushimaru Branches of the Japan Medical Association, by 
the local citizens' committee of Tanushimaru, and by the </p>

<p>Research Ethics Committee of the Kurume University School 
of Medicine (Process numbers 9019/2009) approved the study 
in conformity with the principles embodied in the declaration 
of Helsinki. All participants were informed about research 
procedures and risks before signing an informed consent. </p>

<p>2.3. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Because of skewed distributions, the natural logarithmic (ln) 
transformations were performed for triglycerides. Log-trans-
formed values were reconverted to antilogarithm forms in tables. 
Medications for hypertension, dyslipidemia, and diabetes were 
coded as dummy variables. Alcohol intake, smoking habits, and 
history of CAD were also coded as dummy variables. The mean 
parameters and frequencies stratified by smoking habits were 
compared using the Mantel-Haenszel x 2 test. Demographic and 
clinical characteristics of study subjects stratified by gender 
(Table 1) were demonstrated. Demographic and clinical 
characteristics of the study subjects in both genders stratified 
by smoking habits adjustment for age were also demonstrated in 
Tables 2 and 3. Multivariate analysis for AI adjusted for age was 
performed by a linear regression analysis (Tables 4 and 5). 
Multiple stepwise regression analysis was performed for 
independent associated factors of AI (Tables 6 and 7). Adjusted 
means of AI levels stratified by the 4 groups of smoking status in 
both genders were compared using multiple linear regression 
analysis (Fig. 1A and B). </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Demographic and clinical characteristics of study subjects. </p>

<p>Parameters </p>

<p>Men 
(n = 769) </p>

<p>Women 
(n = 1157) </p>

<p>Total 
(n = 1926) </p>

<p>Age, y 
66.3 ± 10.9 
65.5 ± 11.5 
65.8 ± 11.3 
BMI, kg/m 2 
23.7 ± 3.0 
23.2 ± 3.5 
23.4 ± 3.3 
Systolic BP, mm Hg 
135.5 ± 19.3 
132.2 ± 19.3 
133.5 ± 19.4 
Diastolic BP, mm Hg 
83.6 ± 11.5 
80.4 ± 10.9 
81.6 ± 11.3 
Total cholesterol, mg/dL 
198.8 ± 33.0 
215.2 ± 34.9 
208.7 ± 35.1 
HDL-cholesterol, mg/dL 
56.2 ± 13.6 
63.3 ± 15.5 
60.5 ± 15.2 
Triglycerides, mg/dL </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>114.4 (33-849) 
98.5 (12-707) 
104.6 (12-849) 
LDL-cholesterol, mg/dL 
119.7 ± 30.5 
131.9 ± 31.7 
127.1 ± 31.8 
BUN, mg/dL 
17.0 ± 5.4 
16.0 ± 4.3 
16.4 ± 4.8 
Creatinine, mg/dL 
0.86 ± 0.26 
0.64 ± 0.13 
0.73 ± 0.22 
eGFR, mL/min/1.73 m 2 
72.5 ± 16.5 
73.9 ± 16.1 
73.4 ± 16.3 
Uric acid, mg/dL 
6.0 ± 1.4 
4.6 ± 1.1 
5.2 ± 1.4 
FPG, mg/dL 
101.2 ± 26.1 
97.2 ± 26.2 
98.8 ± 26.3 
Hemoglobin A 1c , % 
5.6 ± 0.7 
5.5 ± 0.6 
5.5 ± 0.7 
Augmentation index 
82.1 ± 11.0 
88.4 ± 10.9 
85.9 ± 11.4 
Smoking habits, % 
198 (25.7) 
34 (2.9) 
230 (11.9) 
No smoker, % 
225 (29.3) 
1104 (95.4) 
1329 (69.0) 
Former smoker, % 
346 (45.0) 
19 (1.6) 
365 (18.9) 
1-19 cigarettes/day 
89 (11.6) 
24 (2.1) 
113 (5.9) 
≥20 cigarette/day 
109 (14.1) 
10 (0.9) 
119 (6.2) 
Alcohol intake, % 
560 (73.2) 
300 (25.8) 
860 (44.7) 
HT medication, % 
344 (45.0) 
465 (40.0) 
809 (42.0) 
DL medication, % 
114 (14.9) 
108 (9.3) 
222 (11.5) 
DM medication, % 
250 (32.7) 
491 (42.3) 
741 (38.5) 
History of CAD, % 
155 (20.3) 
131 (11.3) 
286 (14.9) </p>

<p>Data are means ± standard deviation or percentage, unless otherwise indicated. 
BMI = body mass index, BP = blood pressure, BUN = blood urea nitrogen, CAD = coronary artery 
disease, DL = dyslipidemic, DM = diabetes mellitus, eGFR = estimated glomerular filtration rate, 
FPG = fasting plasma glucose, HDL = high density lipoprotein, HT = hypertensive, LDL = low density 
lipoprotein. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Log-transformed values were used for the calculation and reconverted to anti-logarithm forms. </p>

<p>Tsuru et al. Medicine (2016) 95:51 
Medicine </p>



<p>Statistical significance was defined as P &lt; 0.05. All statistical 
analyses were performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SAS, Inc.</rs>., Cary, 
NC). [17] </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>Demographic and clinical characteristics of study subjects 
stratified by gender are presented in Table 1. Mean values of 
AI were 82.1% in males and 88.4% in females, and mean BMI 
values were 23.7 kg/m 2 in males and 23.2 kg/m 2 in females, 
indicating most of subjects were nonobese. In Table 2, age-
adjusted means of AI in males showed a clear dose-response 
relationship with four categories of smoking habits (P = 0.010). 
In Table 3, there was no significant relationship between AI and 
smoking habits in females. Table 4 shows multivariate analyses 
adjusted for age with AI as a dependent variable in males. BMI 
(P = 0.032; inversely), systolic (P &lt; 0.001) and diastolic (P &lt; 
0.001) BPs, creatinine (P = 0.010; inversely), eGFR (P = 0.002), 
FPG (P = 0.001; inversely), smoking habits (P &lt; 0.001), alcohol 
intake (P = 0.004; inversely), and hypertensive (HT) medication 
(P = 0.031) were significantly associated with AI levels. Table 5 
shows multivariate analyses adjusted for age with AI as a 
dependent variable in females. Systolic (P &lt; 0.001) and diastolic 
(P &lt; 0.001) BPs, HDL-cholesterol (P = 0.048), FPG (P = 0.023; 
inversely), smoking habits (P = 0.035). For the significant factors 
detected by multivariate analysis in Tables 4 and 5, we performed 
multiple stepwise regression analysis (Tables 6 and 7). AI levels in 
males were significantly and independently associated with age 
(P &lt; 0.001), systolic BP (P &lt; 0.001), FPG (inversely; P &lt; 0.001), 
smoking habits (P &lt; 0.001), eGFR (P = 0.008), and BMI 
(inversely; P = 0.019). AI levels in females were significantly 
and independently associated with age (P &lt; 0.001), systolic 
BP (P &lt; 0.001), FPG (inversely; P = 0.011), and smoking habits 
(P = 0.027). Eventually, the significant dose-response relation-
ship (P = 0.036) in males between AI and 4 categories of smoking </p>

<p>(%) 
AI 
p=0.036 for trend </p>

<p>84 </p>

<p>85 </p>

<p>83 </p>

<p>84 </p>

<p>82 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>81 </p>

<p>79 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>No smoker 
Former smoker 1 19 cigarees/day ≥20 cigarees/day 
No smoker 
Former smoker 1-19 cigarees/day ≥20 cigarees/day </p>

<p>Age, BMI, systolic BP, eGFR, FPG, hypertensive medicaon and alcohol intake </p>

<p>9 
8 
= 
n 
5 
2 
2 
= 
n 
n=109 
n=346 </p>

<p>adjusted means of AI levels by cigaree smoking habits in males </p>

<p>(%) 
AI 
p=0.086 for trend </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>91 </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>87 </p>

<p>88 </p>

<p>85 </p>

<p>86 </p>

<p>No smoker 
Former smoker 1 19 cigarees/day ≥20 cigarees/day 
No smoker 
Former smoker 1-19 cigarees/day ≥20 cigarees/day </p>

<p>Age, systolic BP and, FPG adjusted means of AI levels by cigaree smoking habits </p>

<p>4 
2 
= 
n 
4 
0 
1 
, 
1 
= 
n 
n=10 
n=19 </p>

<p>In females </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 1. AI stratified by the 4 groups of smoking status, adjusted for age, 
BMI, systolic BP, eGFR, FPG, hypertensive medication, and alcohol intake in 
males (A) and adjusted for age, systolic BP, and FPG in females (B). AI = 
augmentation index, BMI = body mass index, eGFR = estimated glomerular 
filtration rate, FPG = fasting plasma glucose. </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Demographic and clinical characteristics of study subjects in males stratified by smoking habits adjustment for age. </p>

<p>Parameters 
No smoker 
Former smoker 
1-19 cigarettes/d 
≥20 cigarettes/d 
P for trend </p>

<p>Number 
225 
346 
89 
109 
BMI, kg/m 2 
24.0 ± 2.9 
24.0 ± 2.9 
22.6 ± 2.9 
23.4 ± 3.0 
&lt;0.001 
Systolic BP, mm Hg 
135.1 ± 19.1 
135.6 ± 19.2 
134.8 ± 19.1 
136.3 ± 19.6 
0.934 
Diastolic BP, mm Hg 
82.6 ± 11.3 
83.9 ± 11.3 
84.4 ± 11.3 
84.2 ± 11.5 
0.452 
Total cholesterol, mg/dL 
198.6 ± 32.4 
199.4 ± 31.5 
197.7 ± 32.4 
197.4 ± 33.1 
0.943 
HDL-cholesterol, mg/dL 
56.2 ± 13.7 
57.1 ± 13.6 
58.8 ± 13.7 
51.5 ± 13.9 
&lt;0.001 
Triglycerides, mg/dL (range) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>105.6 (34-480) 
115.5 (33-849) 
112.0 (40-833) 
134.6 (52-648) 
0.002 
LDL-cholesterol, mg/dL 
120.2 ± 30.2 
119.1 ± 30.1 
117.8 ± 30.2 
120.3 ± 30.8 
0.915 
BUN, mg/dL 
17.2 ± 5.3 
17.7 ± 5.3 
15.6 ± 5.3 
16.1 ± 5.4 
0.002 
Creatinine, mg/dL 
0.89 ± 0.32 
0.89 ± 0.31 
0.82 ± 0.32 
0.80 ± 0.32 
0.028 
eGFR, mL/min/1.73 m 2 
71.7 ± 15.8 
70.4 ± 15.8 
76.3 ± 15.8 
77.4 ± 16.1 
&lt;0.001 
Uric acid, mg/dL 
5.8 ± 1.4 
6.2 ± 1.5 
5.7 ± 1.4 
5.9 ± 1.5 
0.015 
FPG, mg/dL 
100.2 ± 26.1 
100.8 ± 26.0 
97.1 ± 26.1 
107.5 ± 26.6 
0.033 
Hemoglobin A 1c , % 
5.5 ± 0.8 
5.6 ± 0.8 
5.4 ± 0.8 
5.7 ± 0.7 
0.182 
Augmentation index 
80.9 ± 10.8 
81.5 ± 10.7 
83.9 ± 10.7 
84.6 ± 10.9 
0.010 
Alcohol intake, % 
154 (68.4) 
258 (74.6) 
75 (84.3) 
77 (70.6) 
0.044 
HT medication, % 
96 (42.7) 
142 (41.0) 
26 (29.2) 
16 (14.8) 
&lt;0.001 
DL medication, % 
29 (12.9) 
56 (16.2) 
7 (7.8) 
12 (11.0) 
0.125 
DM medication, % 
28 (12.4) 
35 (10.1) 
4 (4.5) 
9 (8.3) 
0.180 
History of CAD, % 
59 (26.2) 
66 (19.0) 
19 (21.3) 
14 (12.8) 
0.035 </p>

<p>Bold values indicate statistical significance of P &lt; 0.05. 
Data are age-adjusted means ± standard deviation or percentage, unless otherwise indicated. 
The mean parameters and frequencies stratified by smoking habits were compared using analysis of variance and the Mantel-Haenszel x 2 test, respectively. 
BMI = body mass index, BP = blood pressure, BUN = blood urea nitrogen, CAD = coronary artery disease, DL = dyslipidemic, DM = diabetes mellitus, eGFR = estimated glomerular filtration rate, FPG = fasting 
plasma glucose, HDL = high density lipoprotein, HT = hypertensive, LDL = low density lipoprotein. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Log-transformed values were used for the calculation and reconverted to antilogarithm forms. </p>

<p>Tsuru et al. Medicine (2016) 95:51 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>habits still remained even after adjustment for age, BMI, systolic 
BP, eGFR, FPG, HT medication, and alcohol intake (Fig. 1A). 
However, the significant dose-response relationship in females 
between AI and 4 categories of smoking habits was not observed 
(Fig. 1B). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Our study demonstrated that coronary risk factors, including 
smoking habits were independently associated with AI levels, in 
which smoking habits was dose-dependently associated with AI 
in Japanese males population. </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Demographic and clinical characteristics of study subjects in females stratified by smoking habits adjustment for age. </p>

<p>Parameters 
No smoker 
Former smoker 
1-19 cigarettes/d 
≥20 cigarettes/d 
P for trend </p>

<p>Number 
1104 
19 
24 
10 
BMI, kg/m 2 
23.2 ± 3.6 
23.5 ± 3.5 
22.8 ± 3.6 
23.2 ± 3.6 
0.626 
Systolic BP, mm Hg 
132.3 ± 18.6 
127.3 ± 18.6 
128.9 ± 18.7 
132.8 ± 18.8 
0.563 
Diastolic BP, mm Hg 
80.4 ± 11.3 
78.8 ± 11.3 
77.7 ± 11.3 
82.4 ± 11.5 
0.547 
Total cholesterol, mg/dL 
215.4 ± 34.9 
206.8 ± 34.9 
212.8 ± 35.2 
215.0 ± 35.0 
0.743 
HDL-cholesterol, mg/dL 
63.3 ± 15.3 
62.9 ± 15.3 
67.4 ± 15.4 
60.7 ± 15.4 
0.575 
Triglycerides, mg/dL (range) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>98.6 (12-707) 
104.4 (49-604) 
85.5 (40-256) 
148.4 (64-400) 
0.030 
LDL-cholesterol, mg/dL 
132.2 ± 31.6 
122.4 ± 31.6 
129.8 ± 31.9 
128.0 ± 31.7 
0.557 
BUN, mg/dL 
16.0 ± 4.1 
17.7 ± 4.2 
15.6 ± 4.2 
16.1 ± 4.2 
0.998 
Creatinine, mg/dL 
0.64 ± 0.30 
0.70 ± 0.29 
0.64 ± 0.29 
0.71 ± 0.29 
0.738 
eGFR, mL/min/1.73 m 2 
74.0 ± 14.9 
67.9 ± 15.0 
75.1 ± 15.1 
69.0 ± 15.0 
0.231 
Uric acid, mg/dL 
4.6 ± 1.1 
4.6 ± 1.1 
4.6 ± 1.1 
5.7 ± 1.1 
0.022 
FPG, mg/dL 
97.1 ± 25.1 
93.3 ± 25.0 
96.6 ± 25.3 
97.9 ± 25.2 
0.931 
Hemoglobin A 1c , % 
5.5 ± 0.6 
5.4 ± 0.6 
5.6 ± 0.6 
5.5 ± 0.6 
0.830 
Augmentation index 
88.2 ± 10.8 
90.8 ± 10.8 
92.9 ± 10.9 
90.4 ± 10.8 
0.127 
Alcohol intake, % 
269 (24.4) 
9 (47.3) 
15 (62.5) 
6 (60.0) 
&lt;0.001 
HT medication, % 
368 (33.3) 
4 (21.0) 
3 (12.5) 
4 (40.0) 
0.127 
DL medication, % 
269 (24.4) 
5 (26.3) 
3 (12.5) 
3 (30.0) 
0.554 
DM medication, % 
69 (6.3) 
1 (5.3) 
2 (8.3) 
1 (10.0) 
0.938 
History of CAD, % 
126 (11.4) 
2 (10.5) 
2 (8.3) 
1 (10.0) 
0.966 </p>

<p>Bold values indicate statistical significance of P &lt; 0.05. 
Data are age-adjusted means ± standard deviation or percentage, unless otherwise indicated. 
The mean parameters and frequencies stratified by smoking habits were compared using analysis of variance and the Mantel-Haenszel x 2 test, respectively. 
BMI = body mass index, BP = blood pressure, BUN = blood urea nitrogen, CAD = coronary artery disease, DL = dyslipidemic, DM = diabetes mellitus, eGFR = estimated glomerular filtration rate, FPG = fasting 
plasma glucose, HDL = high density lipoprotein, HT = hypertensive, LDL = low density lipoprotein. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Log-transformed values were used for the calculation and reconverted to anti-logarithm forms. </p>

<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>Association between AI levels and correlates adjusted for age in 
males. </p>

<p>Characteristics 
b 
SE 
P </p>

<p>BMI 
À0.278 
0.130 
0.032 
Systolic BP 
0.108 
0.020 
&lt;0.001 
Diastolic BP 
0.182 
0.034 
&lt;0.001 
Total cholesterol 
À0.004 
0.012 
0.768 
HDL-cholesterol 
0.028 
0.028 
0.329 
Triglycerides </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.170 
0.728 
0.815 
LDL-cholesterol 
À0.012 
0.013 
0.350 
BUN 
À0.102 
0.074 
0.168 
Creatinine 
À4.796 
1.489 
0.010 
eGFR 
0.076 
0.025 
0.002 
Uric acid 
À0.207 
0.275 
0.451 
FPG 
À0.048 
0.015 
0.001 
Hemoglobin A 1c 
À0.366 
0.514 
0.478 
Smoking habits (no = 0, yes = 1) 
3.020 
0.913 
0.001 
Alcohol intake 
À2.540 
0.885 
0.004 
HT medication 
1.658 
0.811 
0.031 
DL medication 
À0.987 
0.818 
0.228 
DM medication 
À0.877 
0.981 
0.372 
History of CAD 
À0.792 
0.975 
0.417 </p>

<p>Bold values indicate statistical significance of P &lt; 0.05. 
AI = augmentation index, BMI = body mass index, BP = blood pressure, BUN = blood urea nitrogen, 
CAD = coronary artery disease, DL = dyslipidemic, DM = diabetes mellitus, eGFR = estimated 
glomerular filtration rate, FPG = fasting plasma glucose, HDL = high density lipoprotein, HT = 
hypertensive, LDL = low density lipoprotein, SE = standard error. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Log-transformed values were used for the analysis. </p>

<p>Table 5 </p>

<p>Association between AI levels and correlates adjusted for age in 
females. </p>

<p>Characteristics 
b 
SE 
P </p>

<p>BMI 
À0.149 
0.090 
0.098 
Systolic BP 
0.079 
0.017 
&lt;0.001 
Diastolic BP 
0.141 
0.029 
&lt;0.001 
Total cholesterol 
0.012 
0.009 
0.194 
HDL-cholesterol 
0.041 
0.021 
0.048 
Triglycerides </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.265 
0.638 
0.677 
LDL-cholesterol 
0.005 
0.010 
0.589 
BUN 
À0.102 
0.078 
0.189 
Creatinine 
À3.764 
2.393 
0.116 
eGFR 
0.021 
0.021 
0.334 
Uric acid 
0.155 
0.285 
0.587 
FPG 
À0.028 
0.012 
0.023 
Hemoglobin A 1c 
À0.959 
0.519 
0.065 
Smoking habits (no = 0, yes = 1) 
4.076 
1.936 
0.035 
Alcohol intake 
0.622 
0.753 
0.409 
HT medication 
À0.142 
0.752 
0.851 
DL medication 
0.032 
0.636 
0.960 
DM medication 
À1.259 
0.931 
0.176 
History of CAD 
À1.058 
1.021 
0.300 </p>

<p>Bold values indicate statistical significance of P &lt; 0.05. 
AI = augmentation index, BMI = body mass index, BP = blood pressure, BUN = blood urea nitrogen, 
CAD = coronary artery disease, DL = dyslipidemic, DM = diabetes mellitus, eGFR = estimated 
glomerular filtration rate, FPG = fasting plasma glucose, HDL = high density lipoprotein, HT = 
hypertensive, LDL = low density lipoprotein, SE = standard error. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Log-transformed values were used for the analysis. </p>

<p>Tsuru et al. Medicine (2016) 95:51 
Medicine </p>



<p>4.1. AI levels and obesity </p>

<p>As consistent with other previous studies, [18-20] the present study 
demonstrated the positive association of AI and coronary risk 
factors, including systolic and diastolic BPs and smoking habits, 
and the negative association of AI and BMI and FPG in 
multivariate analysis in males (Table 4). Obesity is associated 
with several disorders, such as hypertension, dyslipidemia, 
diabetes mellitus, and sleep apnea syndrome. [21,22] In spite of a 
positive correlation between obesity and increased cardiovascu-
lar morbidity, better clinical outcomes in overweight and obese 
patients have been observed, which is called "obesity para-
dox." [23] 
The correlation between AI levels and BMI has been inconsis-
tent. Some were positive, and some were negative. [18-20,24,25] 
Although the previous studies have been done in western countries 
with high BMI levels (25-27.0 kg/m 2 ), [18,19] we included many 
healthy subjects with normal BMI levels (23.4 kg/m 2 ), in wide 
ranges of age from 40 to 95 years old in the present study, which 
indicated the significant inverse association between AI and BMI. 
Otsuka et al [25] have shown the significant inverse association of 
radial AI with BMI using a multivariate analysis. However, the 
mechanisms and pathophysiology relating AI and BMI are poorly 
understood. </p>

<p>4.2. AI levels and smoking habits </p>

<p>Recently, smoking in men has been more common in Asia than in 
the United Kingdom and United State of America, which is 
opposite in women. [26] Smoking rates in men were 25.8% and 
those in women were 2.8% in the present study. In this 
background, our data indicated that AI levels were significantly 
associated with smoking habits in a dose-dependent manner. 
Correlations between AI levels and smoking status were found in 
Japanese and European investigations, [14,27] which are consistent 
with our study. Although the mechanisms are not still clear, 
endothelial dysfunction and oxidative stress may play important 
roles in the relationship between AI and cigarette smoking. [28,29] 
Further, the present study indicated a clear dose-response 
relationship between AI and smoking status in males, in which AI 
might be increased as a marker of smoking-specific oxidative 
stress. [29] Although AI levels in former smokers (81.3%) were 
slightly elevated than those in nonsmokers (81.2%) in this study, 
former smokers showed an almost normal range of AI levels. By 
contrast, AI levels between light and heavy smokers seemed to be 
comparable, suggesting that smoking cessation, but not cutting 
down, may be favorable to the reduction of oxidative stress, as 
previously reported. [13,29] 
As for medications, there is no significant relationship between 
AI and medications for dyslipidemia and diabetes (Table 4). 
Because of the strong association of AI with medication for 
hypertension in males, we analyzed the data after adjustment for 
the factor in addition to the confounding factors (Fig. 1A). 
However, the significance still remained. 
The significant dose-response relationship in females between 
AI and 4 categories of smoking habits was not observed. These 
results may be caused by a small number of smoking habits in 
former and current smokers in females. </p>

<p>4.3. Study limitations </p>

<p>There are several limitations in our study. First, the study design 
was a cross-sectional. Thus, nothing conclusive for the associa-</p>

<p>tion of AI and smoking habits can be stated. Prospective studies 
are needed to investigate the role of AI in smokers, especially in 
the aspects of mortality or cardiovascular events. Second, from 
the multiple correlation coefficients, the significant 6 factors (as 
shown in Table 6) explained only 5.0% of the variation of AI. 
Third, we obtained the number of cigarettes by questionnaires, 
which might not be quantitatively accurate. Moreover, we do not 
have the detailed data regarding smoking duration. Forth, 
because the survey conducted in 2009, the data are little old. 
Finally, although medications for hypertension, dyslipidemia, 
and diabetes were not correlated with AI levels in our analyses, 
we were not able to exclude the contributions of some therapeutic 
agents. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>In conclusion, the present study demonstrated that AI levels 
were significantly associated with smoking habits in males 
Japanese. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We are grateful to members of the Japan Medical Association of 
Ukiha, the elected officials and residents of Tanushimaru, and the 
team of physicians for their help in carrying out the health 
examinations. </p>



<p>Table 6 </p>

<p>Multiple stepwise regression analysis for correlates of AI levels in 
males. </p>

<p>Characteristics 
b 
SE 
P </p>

<p>Age 
0.265 
0.039 
&lt;0.001 
Systolic BP 
0.124 
0.020 
&lt;0.001 
FPG 
À0.059 
0.015 
&lt;0.001 
Smoking habits (no = 0, yes = 1) 
2.556 
0.899 
0.005 
eGFR 
0.065 
0.024 
0.008 
BMI 
À0.309 
0.131 
0.019 
R 2 = 0.050 </p>

<p>Bold values indicate statistical significance of P &lt; 0.05. 
AI = augmentation index, BMI = body mass index, BP = blood pressure, eGFR = estimated glomerular 
filtration rate, FPG = fasting plasma glucose, SE = standard error. </p>

<p>Table 7 </p>

<p>Multiple stepwise regression analysis for correlates of AI levels in 
females. </p>

<p>Characteristics 
b 
SE 
P </p>

<p>Systolic BP 
0.098 
0.017 
&lt;0.001 
Age 
0.117 
0.029 
&lt;0.001 
FPG 
À0.032 
0.013 
0.011 
Smoking habits (no = 0, yes = 1) 
4.248 
1.918 
0.027 
R 2 = 0.134 </p>

<p>Bold values indicate statistical significance of P &lt; 0.05. 
AI = augmentation index, BP = blood pressure, FPG = fasting plasma glucose, SE = standard error. </p>

<p>Tsuru et al. Medicine (2016) 95:51 
www.md-journal.com </p>







</text></tei>