<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5012598" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Division of gastrointestinal 
surgery, Department of general surgery, 
The affiliated huai'an hospital of 
Xuzhou Medical college, 
6 Division of 
gastrointestinal surgery, Department of 
general surgery, The second People's 
hospital of huai'an, huai'an, Jiangsu, 
People's republic of china </p>

<p>*These authors contributed equally 
to this work </p>

<p>Purpose: To further observe and verify the effect of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) 
on the response to antiviral therapy in patients with chronic hepatitis B (CHB) and investigate 
the relationship between the virologic response and insulin resistance. 
Patients and methods: A retrospective study was adopted and 61 NAFLD patients with 
HBeAg-positive CHB were included as the observation group (group A), and 64 patients with 
simple CHB were included as the control group (group B). 
Results: After 12 weeks of treatment with entecavir, the total virologic response rate in group A 
was statistically significantly lower than that in group B (P0.05). During weeks 24-96, the 
difference was not statistically significant (P0.05). In weeks 48 and 96, there was no significant 
difference in the HBeAg seroconversion rates between the two groups (P0.05). In weeks 12 
and 24, there was also no significant difference in the alanine transaminase (ALT) normaliza-
tion rate between the two groups (P0.05). Then, in weeks 48 and 96, the ALT normalization 
rate of group A was obviously lower than that of group B (P0.05). Group A patients were 
divided into group A1 (M) and group A2 (M) according to the median value (M=2.79) of the 
baseline homeostatic model assessment method insulin resistance levels. In weeks 48 and 96, the 
ALT normalization rate of group A1 was significantly higher than that of group A2 (P0.05). 
The correlation coefficient (r) of the baseline homeostatic model assessment method insulin 
resistance level and the severity of fatty liver in group A was 0.426 (P=0.001). 
Conclusion: NAFLD cannot affect the long-term total virologic response rate and HBeAg 
seroconversion rate in CHB patients treated with entecavir but can reduce the long-term bio-
chemical response rate, which has a positive correlation with the severity of fatty liver and the 
insulin resistance index. 
After years of effective prevention and control, the incidence of patients with 
HBsAg has been significantly reduced; however, chronic hepatitis B (CHB) is 
still the primary chronic liver disease that threatens people's health in the People's 
Republic of China. 
1,2 With the improvement in living standards, the morbidity of 
fatty liver disease has gradually increased, and it has become the second most com-
mon chronic liver disease surpassed only by hepatitis, especially for nonalcoholic 
fatty liver disease (NAFLD) due to an improper diet and lifestyle. 
3 Definitions of 
NAFLD have been proposed using biochemical criteria and hepatic imaging, such as </p>

<p>correspondence: Xiao-Yu Zhang 
Division of gastrointestinal surgery, 
Department of General Surgery, The Affiliated 
huai'an hospital of Xuzhou Medical college, 
62 south huaihai road, huai'an 223002, 
Jiangsu, People's republic of china 
email zhangxiaoyu_ey@163.com </p>

<p>Wei-Jie Dai 
Department of gastroenterology, huai'an First 
People's hospital, nanjing Medical University, 
6 West Beijing road, huaiyin District, huai'an 
223300, Jiangsu, People's republic of china 
email daiweijie_yy@163.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Drug Design, Development and Therapy 
30 August 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2740 </p>

<p>Zhu et al </p>

<p>ultrasonography (US), computed tomography, and magnetic 
resonance imaging. 
4-10 Among these definitions, the US 
definition has been used most frequently in Chinese research 
studies, 
4-6,11,12 and this approach has been endorsed by the 
Asia-Pacific regional guidelines. 
7-10 NAFLD is commonly 
associated with type II diabetes mellitus and conditions asso-
ciated with metabolic syndrome. CHB is frequently associ-
ated with hepatic steatosis. 
13-15 Long-term studies of obese 
patients with the spectrum of NAFLD have shown that the 
progression of liver disease is predominantly observed in 
patients with biopsy-proven nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. 
As a result, the number of patients suffering from CHB 
with NAFLD has increased, and the complexity of liver 
disease has expanded, which introduces new challenges to 
the clinical diagnosis and treatment. NAFLD appears to be 
associated with insulin resistance and represents the hepatic 
manifestation of metabolic syndrome. Hepatic steatosis is 
significantly associated with entecavir treatment failure, 
and the metabolic factors seem to be independent of hepatic 
steatosis in CHB patients, therefore requiring a specific anti-
viral strategy for CHB patients with NAFLD. 
16 Not surpris-
ingly, patients with NAFLD are at a high risk of developing 
metabolic complications, which may be much higher than 
the risk of developing liver cirrhosis. 
3 However, a recent 
study 
17 in Turkey found that virologic replication decreases 
in CHB patients in the presence of NAFLD, and NAFLD 
had no impact on the virologic response to entecavir along 
with tenofovir treatment. Therefore, in the present study, we 
analyzed the effect of NAFLD on the response to antiviral 
therapy of CHB through a retrospective clinical analysis and 
explored the relationship between the differences in response 
to therapy and insulin resistance index. </p>

<p>Patients and methods 
Patient selection </p>

<p>Between June 2008 and June 2013, 125 HBeAg-positive 
patients with CHB received entecavir as an initial treatment at 
The Fourth People's Hospital of Huai'an, Jiangsu province. Of 
them, 61 patients (48.8%) emerged with NAFLD. This retro-
spective study was performed with the approval of the ethics 
committee of The Fourth People's Hospital of Huai'an. The 
ethics committee of The Fourth People's Hospital of Huai'an 
did not require patient consent be obtained for this study, as 
this was a retrospective study, and all data was anonymous. 
The inclusion criteria were as follows: 1) age between 
18 years and 60 years; 2) a standard diagnosis of CHB and 
antiviral treatment indications according to the CHB preven-
tion guidelines (2015), 
18 including i) patients with a history 
of CHB or those who are HBsAg positive for 6 months, </p>

<p>without normal antiviral therapy; ii) patients who are HBeAg 
positive; iii) alanine transaminase (ALT) two or more times 
of the upper limit of normal; iv) hepatitis B virus (HBV) 
DNA 10 
5 copies/mL; and v) the exclusion of other factors 
that lead to increases in ALT, such as another infection with 
hepatotropic viruses, alcohol, liver toxic drugs, autoimmune 
liver disease, and hepatolenticular degeneration; and 3) for 
patients with both CHB and fatty liver disease, the diagnosis 
of fatty liver must be in accordance with the diagnosis of 
nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (revised in 2010), 
9,10 which 
must meet two or more of the three abdominal ultrasound 
findings in the diagnostic criteria, including i) the echo of the 
near-field liver is enhanced and stronger than the kidney; ii) 
the echo of the far-field liver is gradually attenuated; and (iii) 
the intrahepatic duct structure display is not clear. 
A diagnosis of fatty liver by US is defined by the pres-
ence of at least two of the following three abnormal findings: 
diffusely increased echogenicity "bright" liver with liver 
echogenicity greater than the kidney or spleen, vascular 
blurring, and deep attenuation of the ultrasound signal. 
5 In 
addition, the dividing standards of fatty liver based on US </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>are as follows: in the mild fatty liver, the liver and hepatorenal 
echogenicity is increased and the diaphragm is shown clearly; 
in the moderate fatty liver, the echo shows an enhancement 
in the anterior region of the liver and the hepatorenal contrast 
but a weakening in the posterior region, and the diaphragm 
is shown less clearly; in the serious fatty liver, the echo is 
increased in the anterior region of the liver and weakened in 
the posterior region, and the diaphragm and structure of the 
intrahepatic bile duct are not shown clearly. All patients pro-
vided verbal informed consent to the antiviral treatment. 
In this retrospective study, we assigned 61 patients with 
CHB and NAFLD into group A and 64 patients with only 
CHB into group B. We observed the effects of NAFLD 
in CHB patients treated with entecavir on the virology, 
serology, and biochemical responses. Hepatitis B virus 
serum markers (HBsAG, anti-HBs, HBeAg, anti-HBe, and 
anti-HBc) were tested by enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
assay. The fluorescent quantitative polymerase chain reac-
tion test was used to test the serum HBV-DNA level. ALT, 
fasting blood glucose (FBG), concentrations of triglycer-
ide, total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, 
and low-density lipoprotein cholesterol in serum were 
measured using an automatic serum biochemical assay 
device. Using the radioimmunity method to determine the 
fasting insulin level, we then estimated insulin sensitivity 
by homeostasis model assessment method insulin resis-
tance (HOMA-IR = fasting serum insulin × FBG/22.5). 
Standard methods were used to measure the height, waist </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2741 </p>

<p>effects of insulin resistance index on virologic response to entecavir </p>

<p>circumference, and body mass. Body mass index = body mass 
(kg)/height (m). 
2 All patients' liver ultrasound results were 
evaluated by an ultrasound doctor, and unified diagnostic 
reports were issued. The evaluation criteria were as follows: 
biochemical response to the serum ALT returned to normal; 
complete virologic response referred to the serum DNA-
HBV load of 500 copies/mL; and HBeAg seroconversion 
referred to HBeAg negative and anti-HBe positive. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>The <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">21.0</rs> statistical software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, 
Armonk, NY, USA) was used for the statistical analysis. The 
measurement data were shown as mean ± standard deviation, 
the mean value of the two samples was compared by t-test, 
and the rate was compared by χ 
2 test. Spearman correlation 
analysis was used to compare the correlation between the 
severity of fatty liver and the HOMA-IR index. All statistical 
tests were two sided and evaluated at the 0.05 alpha level. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The two groups were well-matched in terms of age, sex, 
ALT levels, HBV-DNA levels, genotyping, and low-density 
lipoprotein cholesterol levels (P0.05). The patients in group 
A showed a higher level of body mass index, waist circumfer-
ence, fasting serum insulin, FBG, HOMA-IR, triglyceride, 
total cholesterol, and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol 
compared with group B (P0.05), and all these variables </p>

<p>were statistically significantly different. The propensity 
scores generated from the variables before antiviral therapy 
are listed in Table 1. 
In both group A and group B, the HBV-DNA untestable 
rate (HBV-DNA level 500 copies/mL) increased gradually 
after treatment with entecavir. However, there was a differ-
ence in the HBV-DNA untestable rate at different follow-up 
time points. After 12 weeks of entecavir therapy, the total 
virologic response rate in group A was lower than that in 
group B (group A 32.8% vs group B 51.6%, P=0.034). 
However, after 24, 48, and 96 weeks, the differences were 
not statistically significant (group A 52.5%, 62.3%, 82.0% vs 
group B 64.1%, 75.0%, 85.9%; P=0.188, P=0.125, P=0.545, 
respectively; Table 2). 
For both group A and group B, the HBeAg seroconver-
sion rate increased gradually after entecavir treatment. The 
HBeAg seroconversion rate was equivalent for both groups at 
48 and 96 weeks (group A 21.3%, 29.5% vs group B 23.4%, 
32.8%; P=0.776, P=0.690, respectively; Table 3). 
After entecavir treatment, the ALT normalization rate 
increased gradually (Table 4). An equivalent percentage of 
patients' serum ALT levels returned to normal in each cohort 
at 12 and 24 weeks (group A 50.8%, 55.7% vs group B 59.4%, 
65.5%; P=0.336, P=0.258, respectively). However, at 48 and 
96 weeks, the ALT normalization rates were significantly 
lower in group A than in group B (group A 65.6%, 82.0% vs 
group B 81.3%, 93.8%; P=0.047, P=0.043, respectively). </p>

<p>Table 1 comparison of the data of the chB patients with and without nonalcoholic fatty liver disease </p>

<p>Group A (n=61) 
Group B (n=64) 
t 
P-value </p>

<p>age (years), mean ± sD 
39.26±10.39 
39.61±10.87 
0.18 
0.05 
sex 
Male (n) 
42 
41 
0.32 
0.05 </p>

<p>Female (n) 
19 
23 </p>

<p>BMi (kg/m 
2 ), mean ± sD 
26.29±3.99 
22.50±2.85 
6.11 
0.05 </p>

<p>Wc (cm), mean ± sD 
89.88±11.25 
79.84±9.99 
5.28 
0.05 </p>

<p>alT (U/l), mean ± sD 
179.87±78.50 
187.95±79.88 
0.57 
0.05 </p>

<p>hBV-Dna (lg copies/ml), mean ± sD 
6.24±0.78 
6.20±0.64 
0.31 
0.05 
genotyping 
hBV genotype B (%) 
38 
42 
0.15 
0.05 </p>

<p>hBV genotype c (%) 
23 
22 </p>

<p>hOMa-ir, mean ± sD 
3.67±3.89 
2.07±1.98 
3.6 
0.05 </p>

<p>Fins (mU/l), mean ± sD 
15.46±10.93 
9.03±7.36 
3.84 
0.05 </p>

<p>FBg (mmol/l), mean ± sD 
5.11±0.85 
4.89±0.80 
1.52 
0.05 </p>

<p>Tg (mmol/l), mean ± sD 
1.80±0.95 
1.33±0.64 
3.29 
0.05 </p>

<p>Tc (mmol/l), mean ± sD 
3.78±1.07 
3.72±0.97 
0.31 
0.05 </p>

<p>hDl-c (mmol/l), mean ± sD 
0.86±0.34 
1.07±0.35 
3.32 
0.05 </p>

<p>lDl-c (mmol/l), mean ± sD 
2.31±0.72 
2.16±0.68 
1.15 
0.05 </p>

<p>Notes: group a: naFlD patients with hBeag-positive chB; group B: patients with simple chB. 
Abbreviations: chB, chronic hepatitis B; BMi, body mass index; Wc, waist circumference; alT, alanine transaminase; hBV, hepatitis B virus; hOMa-ir, homeostatic 
model assessment method insulin resistance; Fins, fasting serum insulin; FBg, fasting blood glucose; Tg, triglyceride; Tc, total cholesterol; hDl-c, high-density lipoprotein 
cholesterol; lDl-c, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; naFlD, nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2742 </p>

<p>Zhu et al </p>

<p>PEGylated interferon treatment. Jin et al 
16 investigated the 
effect of hepatic steatosis, a common hepatocyte change in 
NAFLD, on antiviral therapy in patients with CHB. They 
found that hepatic steatosis is significantly associated with 
entecavir treatment failure and that metabolic factors are 
independent of hepatic steatosis in CHB patients, which 
calls for a specified antiviral strategy in CHB patients 
with NAFLD. 
The purpose of this study was to observe and verify 
the effects of NAFLD on the antiviral therapy response in 
patients with CHB and investigate the relationship between 
the response differences and the insulin resistance index. 
In our study, the HBV-DNA clearance rate was lower 
in patients with NAFLD than that of the CHB group at 
12 weeks, but it was equivalent at 24, 48, and 96 weeks. 
The results indicated that NAFLD may affect the rate of 
early viral response in CHB, but it would not affect the 
long-term treatment virologic response rate. However, this 
result was not consistent with that of Jin et al. 
16 Considering 
the HBeAg seroconversion rate, we found that there were 
no significant differences between the two groups at 48 and 
96 weeks, which suggested that NAFLD was not affecting 
patients' HBeAg seroconversion rate with CHB. Unfortu-
nately, the aforementioned finding was also different from 
that of Jin et al. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Table 2 comparison of the hBV-Dna untestable rate between 
the study groups at different follow-up time points </p>

<p>Group A 
(n=61) </p>

<p>Group B 
(n=64) </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>12 weeks 
20 (32.8%) 
33 (51.6%) 
4.508 
0.034 
24 weeks 
32 (52.5%) 
41 (64.1%) 
1.731 
0.188 
48 weeks 
38 (62.3%) 
48 (75.0%) 
2.349 
0.125 
96 weeks 
50 (82.0%) 
55 (85.9%) 
0.366 
0.545 </p>

<p>Notes: group a: naFlD patients with hBeag-positive chB; group B: patients 
with simple chB. 
Abbreviations: chB, chronic hepatitis B; hBV, hepatitis B virus; naFlD, 
nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. </p>

<p>Table 3 comparison of the hBeag seroconversion rate between 
the study groups at follow-up time points </p>

<p>Group A 
(n=61) </p>

<p>Group B 
(n=64) </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>48 weeks 
13 (21.3%) 
15 (29.5%) 
0.081 
0.776 
96 weeks 
18 (23.4%) 
21 (32.8%) 
0.159 
0.69 </p>

<p>Notes: group a: naFlD patients with hBeag-positive chB; group B: patients 
with simple chB. 
Abbreviations: chB, chronic hepatitis B; naFlD, nonalcoholic fatty liver 
disease. </p>

<p>Table 4 comparison of the alT normalization rate between the 
study groups at different follow-up time points </p>

<p>Group A 
(n=61) </p>

<p>Group B 
(n=64) </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>12 weeks 
31 (50.8%) 
38 (59.4%) 
0.924 
0.336 
24 weeks 
34 (55.7%) 
42 (65.6%) 
1.281 
0.258 
48 weeks 
40 (65.6%) 
52 (81.3%) 
2.95 
0.047 
96 weeks 
50 (82.0%) 
60 (93.8%) 
4.106 
0.043 </p>

<p>Notes: group a: naFlD patients with hBeag-positive chB; group B: patients 
with simple chB. 
Abbreviations: alT, alanine transaminase; chB, chronic hepatitis B; naFlD, 
nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. </p>

<p>Table 5 comparison of the alT normalization rate between 
group a patients with different baseline levels of hOMa-ir at 
follow-up time points </p>

<p>Group 
Patients 
(n) </p>

<p>ALT normalization 
rate, n (%) </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>48 weeks 
96 weeks </p>

<p>a1 
31 
24 (77.4%) 
29 (93.5%) 
3.918 
0.048 
a2 
30 
16 (53.3%) 
21 (70.0%) 
5.72 
0.017 </p>

<p>Notes: group a: naFlD patients with hBeag-positive chB; group a1: hOMa-ir 
 median (2.79); group a2: hOMa-ir  median (2.79). 
Abbreviations: alT, alanine transaminase; chB, chronic hepatitis B; hOMa-ir, 
homeostatic model assessment method insulin resistance; naFlD, nonalcoholic fatty 
liver disease. </p>

<p>According to the baseline level of the HOMA-IR median 
(M=2.79), the 61 patients in group A were divided into 
two groups (group A1, IR M, 31 patients and group A2, 
IR M, 30 patients). Table 5 shows that the A1 patients' ALT 
normalization rates were higher than those of A2 patients 
at 48 and 96 weeks (group A1 77.4%, 93.5% vs group A2 
53.3%, 70.0%; P=0.048, P=0.017, respectively). 
The 61 patients in group A were divided into three groups 
according to the severity of the fatty liver determined by 
ultrasonic results. Of them, 30 patients were categorized as 
mild, 22 patients were categorized as moderate, and 9 patients 
were categorized as severe. The severity of the pathological 
changes due to the fatty liver was positively correlated with 
HOMA-IR (r=0.426, P=0.001; Table 6). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The key to treating CHB is antiviral therapy, and there are 
many guidelines for treatment programs. However, there is 
no clear antiviral treatment program for CHB patients who 
also have NAFLD, and it is unknown whether the antiviral 
effect is affected by the fatty infiltration of the liver. There-
fore, there is no consensus, and it has gradually become a 
hot issue of public concern. 
Ates et al 
20 found that the occurrence of hepatic ste-
atosis is significantly higher in CHB patients, and this 
association leads to a trend of decreased, but statistically 
insignificant, sustained virologic response rates to 48-week </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2743 </p>

<p>effects of insulin resistance index on virologic response to entecavir </p>

<p>The ALT normalization rate indicated that there were 
significant differences between the two groups after treat-
ment with entecavir for 48 and 96 weeks but showed an 
equivalent percentage at 12 and 24 weeks. The results we 
observed suggested that NAFLD did not affect the early 
biochemical response rate in CHB patients, which might be 
due to the early use of drugs to protect the liver and reduce 
enzymes. However, it might affect the long-term biochemical 
response rate, which is consistent with the results of related 
studies. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>According to the demographic information and baseline 
of the two groups, it was demonstrated that the occurrence 
of NAFLD was not related to viral factors and ALT levels, 
while the disorder of the metabolism and insulin resistance 
might play an important role. Further studies found that the 
level of insulin resistance was positively correlated with the 
severity of the fatty liver in group A (r=0.426, P=0.001). 
The subgroup analysis of group A indicated that the baseline 
levels of HOMA-IR and the biochemical responses were 
negatively correlated, which was more apparent when treat-
ment period was longer. 
Admittedly, there are many limitations to this study. 
First, the diagnosis may be biased without a liver biopsy at 
the baseline diagnosis. Furthermore, the sample of observed 
patients is small. Finally, there are differences in the conclu-
sion when compared with related research. Future research 
should increase the number of observed patients and conduct 
liver biopsies at baseline to provide a reference for clinical 
diagnosis and treatment. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The results of this study indicated that NAFLD may decrease 
the total virologic response rate in patients with CHB over 
a short period of time, but it does not affect the long-term 
total virologic response rate and HBeAg seroconversion 
rate. NAFLD may not have a significant effect in the short-
term on the biochemical response rate in CHB patients, but 
it can decrease the biochemical response rate in long-term 
treatment, and the decrease in the biochemical response rate </p>

<p>is related to the severity of NAFLD, especially the insulin 
resistance index. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This study was supported by the Key Project of Research 
and Development of Huai'an (HAS2015009). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Table 6 correlation analysis between the severity of fatty liver 
and hOMa-ir </p>

<p>Severity 
Patients (n) 
HOMA-IR, 
mean ± SD </p>

<p>Mild 
30 
2.57±1.39 
Moderate 
22 
3.54±2.11 </p>

<p>serious 
9 
7.67±4.61 </p>

<p>Note: spearman correlation analysis, r=0.426, P=0.001 (positive correlation). 
Abbreviation: hOMa-ir, homeostatic model assessment method insulin resistance. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/drug-design-development-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal that spans the spectrum of drug design 
and development through to clinical applications. Clinical outcomes, 
patient safety, and programs for the development and effective, safe, 
and sustained use of medicines are the features of the journal, which </p>

<p>has also been accepted for indexing on PubMed Central. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2744 </p>



</text></tei>