<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5056957" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>BACKGROUND/OBJECTIVES: Obesity prevention during adolescence is a health priority. The 'Physical Activity 4 Everyone' (PA4E1) 
study tested a multi-component physical activity intervention in 10 secondary schools from socio-economically disadvantaged 
communities. This paper aimed to report the secondary outcomes of the study; to determine whether the intervention impacted on 
adiposity outcomes (weight, body mass index (BMI), BMI z-score), and whether any effect was moderated by sex, baseline BMI and 
baseline physical activity level, at 12 and 24 months. 
SUBJECTS/METHODS: A cluster randomised controlled trial was conducted in New South Wales, Australia. The school-based 
intervention included seven physical activity strategies targeting the following: curriculum (strategies to maximise physical 
activity in physical education, student physical activity plans, an enhanced school sport programme); school environment 
(physical activity during school breaks, modification of school policy); and parents and the community (parent engagement, 
links with community physical activity providers). Students' weight (kg), BMI and BMI z-score, were collected at baseline 
(Grade 7), 12 and 24 months. Linear Mixed Models were used to assess between-group mean difference from baseline to 
12 and 24 months. Exploratory sub-analyses were undertaken according to three moderators of energy balance. 
RESULTS: A total of 1150 students (mean age = 12 years) provided outcome data at baseline, 1051 (91%) at 12 months and 985 
(86%) at 24 months. At 12 months, there were group-by-time effects for weight (mean difference = -0.90 kg (95% confidence 
interval (CI) = -1.50, − 0.30), P o 0.01) and BMI (−0.28 kg m 
− 2 (−0.50, − 0.06), P = 0.01) in favour of the intervention group, but not 
for BMI z-score (−0.05 (−0.11; 0.01), P = 0.13). These findings were consistent for weight (−0.62 kg (−1.21, 0.03), P = 0.01) and BMI 
(−0.28 kg m 
− 2 (−0.49, − 0.06), P = 0.01) at 24 months, with group-by-time effects also found for BMI z-score (−0.08 (−0.14; − 0.02), 
P = 0.02) favouring the intervention group. 
CONCLUSION: The PA4E1 school-based intervention achieved moderate reductions in adiposity among adolescents from 
socio-economically disadvantaged communities. Multi-component interventions that increase adolescents' engagement in 
moderate-to-vigorous physical activity (MVPA) may assist in preventing unhealthy weight gain. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Internationally, among adolescent populations (10-19 years), the 
prevalence of overweight and obesity is estimated to be between 
20-30%, 
2 and is increasing. 
3 During puberty, adolescents experience 
changes in body composition and physical fitness, and decreased 
insulin sensitivity. 
1 Changes in eating behaviours, physical activity, 
sedentary behaviours and psychological wellbeing may also occur 
during this critical period of growth and development. 
1 These 
behavioural and physiological changes increase the risk of 
overweight and obesity during adolescence. 
1 Global self-reported 
data from 105 countries estimate that just 20% of adolescents 
participate in ⩾ 60 min of moderate-to-vigorous physical activity </p>

<p>(MVPA) each day. 
4 Longitudinal studies have also shown a decline in 
physical activity during adolescence of~7% of MVPA per year. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Research across 32 countries in Europe, Israel and North America 
indicates a positive association between physical inactivity and socio-
economic disadvantage in adolescents. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>The school environment is a recommended setting for the 
promotion of physical activity among adolescents; 
7 however, 
school-based physical activity interventions have resulted in only 
a small increase in objectively measured MVPA (~4 min per day) of 
children, and limited reductions in the adiposity of adolescents. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>A systematic review and meta-analysis of 18 studies (including 
18 141 students) that aimed to determine the effect of school-
based physical activity interventions (46 months duration) on </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Hunter New England Population Health, The University of Newcastle, Wallsend, New South Wales, Australia; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>School of Medicine and Public Health, University of Newcastle, 
Callaghan, New South Wales, Australia; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Hunter Medical Research Institute, Lambton, New South Wales, Australia; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Priority Research Centre in Physical Activity and Nutrition, 
School of Education, University of Newcastle, Callaghan, New South Wales, Australia; </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Early Start Research Institute, Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Wollongong, 
Wollongong, New South Wales, Australia and </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Illawarra Health and Medical Research Institute, University of Wollongong, Wollongong, New South Wales, Australia. 
Correspondence: Mrs R Sutherland, Hunter New England Population Health, The University of Newcastle, Locked Bag 10, Wallsend 2287 New South Wales, Australia. 
E-mail: Rachel.Sutherland@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au 
Received 20 January 2016; revised 18 April 2016; accepted 2 May 2016; accepted article preview online 10 June 2016; advance online publication, 19 July 2016 </p>

<p>International Journal of Obesity (2016) 40, 1486-1493 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ijo </p>

<p>body mass index (BMI) in children and adolescents found that 
neither BMI (mean difference = − 0.05 kg m </p>

<p>− 2 </p>

<p>, 95% CI (confidence 
interval): − 0.19; 0.10) nor any other body composition measures 
improved. 
9 The review primarily included elementary-aged 
students in Grades 3-6, and 15 of the 18 studies included 
a nutrition co-intervention. The lack of an overall effect on BMI 
was explained by insufficient intervention dose, either due to 
the amount of physical activity or low intervention compliance 
by the students. 
9 In a more recent meta-analysis of 43 studies 
(involving 36 579 children) that aimed to evaluate the impact of 
nutrition and physical activity school-based interventions on BMI 
in children and adolescents ( o18 years old), studies that assessed 
physical activity-only interventions reduced BMI by − 0.13 kg m </p>

<p>− 2 </p>

<p>(−0.22; − 0.04). 
10 Intervention duration ranged from 1 month to 6 
years. 
10 Neither of the reviews reported the physical activity 
intervention findings separately for adolescents, 
9,10 precluding the 
drawing of conclusions regarding the effect of physical activity 
interventions on adiposity in adolescent populations. 
To increase the likelihood of an effect, school-based interven-
tions that are multi-component and socio-ecologically framed are 
recommended. 
11,12 Systematic reviews of school-based physical 
activity interventions have also recommended that interventions 
address educational, curricular and environmental changes in 
the school. 
13,14 The 'Physical Activity 4 Everyone' (PA4E1) 
cluster randomised controlled trial (RCT) was designed based on 
these recommendations and aimed to reduce the decline 
in physical activity typically observed during adolescence. 
15 The 
multi-component intervention resulted in a significant differential 
change in the primary outcome (daily minutes MVPA) from baseline 
to 24 months of seven minutes/day (Po0.01). 
16 The secondary 
aims of PA4E1 reported in this paper, were to determine whether the 
intervention impacted on adiposity outcomes (weight, BMI and 
BMI z-score), and whether any effect on such measures was 
moderated by (i) sex (male, female), (ii) baseline BMI (underweight/ 
healthy weight; overweight/obese) and (iii) baseline physical activity 
level (active/inactive), at 12 and 24 months. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Study design and setting </p>

<p>A cluster RCT was conducted in secondary schools in socio-economically 
disadvantaged communities in New South Wales (NSW), Australia. 
Communities were considered socio-economically disadvantaged if they 
had a socio-economic status score of five or less (lower 50% of NSW) based 
on the postal code. Outcome assessments were undertaken at baseline, 12 
and 24 months. The study was approved by the University of Newcastle 
Human Research Ethics Committee (H-201-0210), the Hunter New England 
Ethics Committee (11/03/16/4.05) and the Department of Education and 
Catholic Schools Diocese. The trial adhered to the Consolidated Standards 
of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) guidelines 
17 and was registered with the 
Australian New Zealand Clinical Trials Registry (ACTRN 12612000382875). 
Detailed methods of the PA4E1 study have been reported elsewhere. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Participants and recruitment </p>

<p>Secondary schools. Randomly selected secondary schools within the study 
region were invited to participate between October and December 2011. 
Schools were eligible to participate in the study if they were (i) Government 
or Catholic schools, (ii) had a socio-economic status score of five or less 
(lower 50% of NSW) based on the postal code, 
18 (iii) had at least 120 Grade-7 
students and (iv) were not participating in any other physical activity 
or health intervention study. School Principals were provided with a study 
information package and asked to provide written informed consent. 
The consenting schools were randomly allocated to intervention or control 
groups following the collection of baseline data, using a computer generated 
block randomisation procedure (1:1 ratio) by an independent statistician. </p>

<p>Students. A cohort of first-year high-school students (Grade 7, aged 12-13 
years) at the consenting secondary schools were invited to participate. 
Parents were provided with an information package and asked to 
provide written informed consent for their child. Two weeks following </p>

<p>the distribution of the information package, the non-responding parents 
were telephoned and asked to provide verbal consent. Children also 
provided assent for participating in the study. </p>

<p>'Physical Activity 4 Everyone' intervention </p>

<p>The design of the PA4E1 intervention was guided by social cognitive 
theory 
19 and socio-ecological theory, 
20 and based on evidence of effective 
intervention features including multiple intervention components, delivery 
for a period of at least 12 months, 
13,14,21 and the inclusion of strategies 
to enhance implementation of intervention components. 
13,21-24 The 
intervention strategies have been outlined in detail elsewhere. 
15,16 Briefly, 
the intervention components targeted the school curriculum, school 
environment, and broader community and parental support 
7,21,25-27 in 
accordance with the WHO's Health Promoting Schools framework. 
7 The 
intervention was delivered over seven to eight school terms (19-24 months), 
and included the following seven physical activity intervention strategies: </p>

<p>School curriculum 
1. 'Teaching strategies to maximise student physical activity in health and 
physical education (PE) lessons'. PE teachers received two professional 
learning workshops (conducted at 6-month intervals) that focused on 
(i) increasing motivation and MVPA in PE lessons to meet the target of 
50% of PE lesson time in MVPA recommended by the US Centers for 
Disease Control and Prevention, 
28 (ii) an implementation guide for 
delivering the 10-week enhanced school sport programme (that is, 
Program X) and (iii) recommended procedures for fitness testing and 
'personal best' days. A final booster session provided a summary of all 
concepts and strategies included in the PA4E1 intervention. 
2. 'Development and monitoring of student physical activity plans within 
PE lessons'. The student physical activity plans focused on (i) short-and 
long-term physical activity, (ii) actions and timelines, (iii) fitness 
assessments, (iv) recording actions and goal achievements, and 
(v) rewards for goal attainment (for example, balls, wrist bands and 
drink bottles). </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>3. 'Implementation of an enhanced school sports programme'. All students 
participated in a 10-week enhanced school sport programme during 
school sport. The programme was based on Program X, which was 
originally designed for less-active students. </p>

<p>25,30-32 </p>

<p>School environment 
4. 'Development and modification of school policies'. School policies were 
established or modified with the aim of enhancing students' physical 
activity. 
33,34 For example; incorporating pedometer-based lessons 
with PE, offering the enhanced school sport programme as a standard 
school sport option, routinely providing physical activity information 
to parents. 
5. 'Physical activity programmes during school breaks'. Schools were 
provided with physical activity equipment (for example, balls, skipping 
equipment) and encouraged to offer supervised physical activity on at 
least 2 days per week during recess and lunch breaks. </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>Partnership and services 
6. 'Promotion of community physical activity providers (community 
links)'. 
33,36 Schools were supported to host a physical activity expo that 
promoted local physical activity providers to students in Grade 8. 
Community physical activity providers were also promoted in school 
newsletters. 
7. 'Parent engagement'. Information was regularly sent to the parents via 
existing school newsletters, the school website and PA4E1 newsletters 
on physical activity recommendations, school-based physical activity 
strategies, promotion of community physical activity providers and 
strategies to support their child's physical activity. </p>

<p>31,37 </p>

<p>Four of the seven intervention strategies were implemented during the 
first 12 months (strategies 1, 2, 5 and 7 above). The remaining strategies 
were implemented over the next 12 months, with delivery of the initial 
strategies being maintained. The intervention strategies, particularly those 
under the curriculum domain, included a range of behaviour-change 
techniques with students 
15,38 such as the provision of information </p>

<p>Effects of a school physical activity intervention 
JL Hollis et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity (2016) 1486 -1493 </p>

<p>about the behaviour and the consequences, general encouragement, 
prompting specific goal setting and a review of behavioural goals, 
prompting self-monitoring, prompting practice, modelling and demon-
strating the behaviour, and the provision of feedback on performance. </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>The intervention further used six strategies to support the implementa-
tion of the seven physical activity intervention strategies listed above. 
The intervention implementation strategies included (i) an in-school 
physical activity consultant 1 day per week (change agent position), </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>(ii) establishing leadership and support, (iii) teacher training, </p>

<p>39,40 </p>

<p>(iv) resources, (v) teacher prompts 
41 and (vi) intervention implementation 
performance feedback to schools. </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>Control schools </p>

<p>Schools allocated to the control group participated in the measurement 
components of the study. Controls schools were requested to follow 
their usual PE and sport programmes during the study period and were 
offered all intervention materials, equipment packs and the findings at the 
conclusion of the study. </p>

<p>Measures </p>

<p>Study outcome assessments were conducted at baseline and on the same 
cohort of students after 12 and 24 months post baseline. Data were collected 
at the schools by trained research assistants using standardised protocols. </p>

<p>Student characteristics. Students completed an online survey to collect data 
regarding their socio-demographic characteristics including age, sex, Abori-
ginal and Torres Strait Islander status, language spoken at home and 
residential postal code. Baseline accelerometer data were collected to derive 
minutes of MVPA per day. Students wore an accelerometer (Actigraph GT3X+ 
and GT3X models, Pensacola, FL, USA </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>) for 7 days during waking hours. 
Physical activity data were included in the physical activity analyses if the 
accelerometer was worn for ⩾ 600 min on ⩾ 3 days per week. 
44-46 The 
Evenson cutpoints were used to categorise the intensity of physical activity. </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>Outcome measures: indicators of adiposity. At each measurement point, 
trained research assistants used the International Society for Advanced 
Kinathropometry (ISAK) procedures to assess height and weight. 
48 Participants 
were required to complete the assessments in light clothing and wearing 
no shoes. Weight was measured to the nearest 0.1 kg on a portable digital 
scale (Model no. UC-321PC, A&amp;D Company Ltd, Tokyo, Japan). Height 
was measured to the nearest 0.1 cm using a portable stadiometer (Model no. 
PE087, Mentone Educational Centre, Springvale, VIC, Australia). Two record-
ings of height (cm) and weight (kg) measures were taken to calculate baseline 
BMI (weight (kg)/height (m) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). BMI z-scores were calculated using the WHO 
2007 growth reference ranges for 5-19 years of age. </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were analysed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC, USA). 
Summary statistics were used to describe student characteristics and 
accelerometer wear time. Participants were categorised as 'active' at baseline 
if they participated in ⩾ 60 min of MVPA per day for a least 3 days and 
'inactive' if they participated in o60 min of MVPA per day. Weight status 
(underweight/healthy weight; overweight/obese) was categorised according 
to International Obesity Task Force cutpoints. 
50 Participants with a baseline 
BMI ⩾ 60 kg m 
− 2 and weight ⩾ 150 kg were excluded from the analysis. 
The characteristics of those that provided follow-up data were compared 
with those that did not, using t-tests for continuous variables and χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-tests for 
categorical variables. 
The study was powered on the primary trial outcome (daily minutes of 
MVPA), based on ten schools providing 120 students per school (assuming 
50% of the Grade consented and provided valid accelerometer data). </p>

<p>51,52 </p>

<p>If 65% of the cohort provided usable data at 24 months, 
53 and after 
adjustment for a design effect of 1.38, the effective sample size was 
estimated to be 141 students per group. Previous studies were used to 
estimate the standard deviation of mean daily minutes of MVPA per group 
(17.1) 
54 and intra-class correlation coefficient (0.01). 
55 With 80% power and 
an α-level of 0.05, the study was able to detect a difference in daily mean 
minutes of MVPA between intervention and control students of ± 5.73 min 
at 24 months. On the basis of this, the detectable difference for weight 
with a standard deviation of 12.1 kg was 4 kg. 
Analyses followed intention-to-treat principles. Significance levels 
were set at Po 0.05. Linear mixed models (LMM) were used to examine </p>

<p>the outcome measures of weight, BMI and BMI z-score. A three-level 
hierarchical model was used to capture correlations in the data with 
random intercepts for repeat measures (level 1), on individuals (level 2) 
and clustering within schools (level 3). The LMM analyses aimed to 
determine if there was a significant difference in mean change from 
baseline to 12 months and baseline to 24 months between intervention 
and control groups for each outcome measure, both assessed using an 
interaction term between treatment group (intervention vs. control) and 
time (baseline vs. 12 months and baseline vs. 24 months). Two sensitivity 
analyses were conducted, first using only those that provided complete 
adiposity outcomes at all three time points (complete cases), and 
second using multiple imputation to fill in the missing data. The multiple 
imputation model used the method of chained regression equations, 
including variables that were prognostic of missing data and additional 
demographic and outcome data to create five imputed data sets. The 
results from fitting the LMM were pooled over the five data sets using 
Rubin's method. </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>Sub-analyses. Exploratory sub-analyses (defined a priori) were undertaken 
to determine whether the intervention impacted on the outcome 
measures for students according to three moderators of energy balance 
(i) sex (male; female), (ii) baseline BMI (underweight/healthy weight; 
overweight/obese) and (iii) baseline physical activity level (active; inactive). 
The moderator interaction terms were included in individual LMM analyses 
for each outcome, and the P-value for the three-way interaction term 
(group × time × moderator) was used to assess the level of evidence 
against the null hypothesis of no effect modification. Treatment effects are 
presented within each subgroup regardless of this P-value. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Sample 
Of the 22 eligible schools, 13 were approached to participate 
in the study. Ten schools consented to participate (77%) and 
parental consent was obtained for 1233 of the 1468 Grade-7 
students in the 10 schools (84%). A total of 1150 students 
provided adiposity outcome data at baseline, 1051 (91%) at 
mid-point (12 months) and 985 (86%) at 24 months. Demographic 
characteristics of the sample at baseline, 12 and 24 months 
are outlined in Table 1. At baseline, the mean age of participants 
was 12 years, 51% were female, 17% were overweight and 5% 
were obese, and 64% did not meet the physical activity 
recommendation of ⩾ 60 min of MVPA per day. Participants who 
were lost to follow-up were more likely to be older in age (P = 0.03) 
and did not speak English as a primary language (P = 0.02) compared 
with those who provided outcome data at all time points. 
At 24 months, all 5 intervention schools had implemented 6 
of the 7 physical activity strategies. The exception was strategy 5 
(school policy); 4 of the 5 schools had developed a school policy. 
All intervention implementation strategies were delivered as 
planned. The majority of intervention group PE teachers (n = 35) 
reported using pedometers to increase activity levels in 
PE (88.9%), and 58.8% reported including student physical activity 
plans each term. All schools were represented by at least one 
PE teacher (range 1-5) at each professional learning workshop. 
More information on intervention delivery can be found in the 
24-month physical activity outcome paper. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Indicators of adiposity 
The results for the 12-and 24-month adiposity outcomes are 
presented in Table 2. At 12 months, there were group-by-time 
effects for weight (mean difference (95% CI) = − 0.90 kg 
(−1.50; − 0.30), P o0.01) and BMI (−0.28 kg m 
− 2 (−0.50; − 0.06), 
P = 0.01) in favour of the intervention group, but not for BMI 
z-score (−0.05 (−0.11; 0.01), P = 0.13). These findings were 
consistent for weight (−0.62 kg (−1.21; − 0.03), P = 0.01) and 
BMI (−0.28 kg m 
− 2 (−0.49; − 0.06), P = 0.01) at 24 months, with 
group-by-time effects also found for BMI z-score (−0.08 
(−0.14; − 0.02), P = 0.02) favouring the intervention group. </p>

<p>Effects of a school physical activity intervention 
JL Hollis et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity (2016) 1486 -1493 </p>

<p>Intervention effects were significant for all adiposity outcomes at 
12 and 24 months in both the complete cases and multiple 
imputation analyses (Supplementary Appendix 1 and 2). </p>

<p>Subgroup analyses 
The results of the subgroup analyses are presented in Supplementary 
Appendix 3. </p>

<p>Sex. There was weak evidence of a differential treatment on 
effect on weight in males compared with females (three-way 
interaction P = 0.22). Among males there was a statistically 
significant treatment effect at 24 months in favour of the 
intervention group (−1.26 kg (−2.11; − 0.41), P = 0.01). There were 
no significant effects on weight, BMI and BMI z-score at either 
12 or 24 months for females. </p>

<p>Weight status at baseline. We found very little evidence 
of differential treatment effects depending on baseline weight 
for weight (P = 0.50), BMI (P = 0.57) or BMI z-score (P = 0.64). 
Nevertheless, we did observe the following results. 
Among underweight and normal weight participants combined, 
there were significant effects for weight (−0.71 kg (−1.28; − 0.14), 
P = 0.04), BMI (−0.33 kg m 
− 2 (−0.55; − 0.10), P = 0.01) and BMI 
z-score (−0.08 (−0.15; − 0.01), P = 0.01) in favour of the intervention 
group at 12-month follow-up. Similar findings for weight (−0.71 kg 
(−1.28; − 0.14), P = 0.04), BMI (−0.33 kg m 
− 2 (−0.55; − 0.10), 
P = 0.01) and BMI z-score (−0.08 (−0.15; − 0.01), P = 0.01) in </p>

<p>underweight/normal weight participants were found at 24 months 
in favour of the intervention group. 
Among overweight and obese students, no significant effects 
were found at 12 or 24 months for weight (12 months = − 1.29 kg 
(−3.12; 0.53), P = 0.16; 24 months = − 1.16 kg (−2.98; 0.67), 
P = 0.30), BMI (12 months = − 0.39 kg m 
− 2 (−1.01; 0.22), P = 0.21; 
24 months = − 0.18 kg m 
− 2 (−0.80; 0.44), P = 0.45) and BMI z-score 
(12 months = − 0.07 (−0.21; 0.07), P = 0.31; 24 months = − 0.00 
(−0.14; 0.14), P = 0.54). </p>

<p>Physical activity level at baseline. We found no evidence of 
differential treatment effects depending on activity status at 
baseline for weight (P = 0.94), BMI (P = 0.95) or BMI z-score 
(P = 0.31).There was no significant effect on weight, BMI or BMI 
z-score for either active or inactive students at 12 or 24 months. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
This study reports the 12-and 24-month effects of PA4E1 on 
the secondary outcomes of weight, BMI and BMI z-score. The 
intervention had a favourable impact on adiposity outcomes, 
having a moderate effect on weight and BMI at 12 months, and 
weight, BMI and BMI z-score at 24 months. A difference in BMI of 
− 0.28 kg m 
− 2 over 24 months between intervention and control 
groups is twice the effect found in a meta-analysis of 11 school-
based physical activity intervention studies (−0.13 kg m 
− 2 ). </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>However, of the 11 physical activity interventions, only 2 were 
conducted in secondary schools and only 1 of these during school </p>

<p>Table 1. Sample characteristics at baseline, 12 and 24 months for students who provided adiposity outcome measures </p>

<p>Variable 
Subgroup 
Baseline 
Mid-point (12 months) 
Follow-up (24 months) </p>

<p>Control 
(n = 505) </p>

<p>Intervention 
(n = 645) </p>

<p>Control 
(n = 459) </p>

<p>Intervention 
(n = 592) </p>

<p>Control 
(n = 425) </p>

<p>Intervention 
(n = 560) </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Male 
244 (49%) 
299 (48%) 
219 (48%) 
268 (46%) 
219 (52%) 
266 (48%) 
Female 
254 (51%) 
329 (52%) 
233 (52%) 
311 (54%) 
204 (48%) 
287 (52%) 
ATSI </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>No 
456 (91%) 
581 (92%) 
415 (91%) 
540 (92%) 
390 (92%) 
520 (93%) 
Yes 
44 (8.8%) 
53 (8.4%) 
39 (8.6%) 
45 (7.7%) 
35 (8.2%) 
40 (7.1%) 
Language </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>English 
474 (97%) 
593 (99%) 
425 (97%) 
539 (98%) 
392 (97%) 
506 (98%) 
Other 
15 (3.1%) 
8 (1.3%) 
11 (2.5%) 
9 (1.6%) 
11 (2.7%) 
8 (1.6%) 
SEIFA </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Low 
295 (61%) 
349 (59%) 
260 (60%) 
308 (57%) 
236 (59%) 
285 (56%) 
High 
190 (39%) 
246 (41%) 
172 (40%) 
235 (43%) 
163 (41%) 
222 (44%) 
Rurality 
Metropolitan 
236 (47%) 
340 (53%) 
220 (48%) 
324 (55%) 
207 (49%) 
304 (54%) 
Rural 
269 (53%) 
305 (47%) 
239 (52%) 
268 (45%) 
218 (51%) 
256 (46%) 
BMI category 
e Underweight 
30 (6.3%) 
41 (7.3%) 
19 (5.8%) 
29 (6.9%) 
7 (2.0%) 
12 (2.5%) 
Normal weight 
321 (67%) 
397 (71%) 
214 (65%) 
291 (69%) 
214 (62%) 
320 (66%) 
Overweight 
100 (21%) 
97 (17%) 
72 (22%) 
75 (18%) 
95 (28%) 
111 (23%) 
Obese 
29 (6.0%) 
27 (4.8%) 
25 (7.6%) 
24 (5.7%) 
27 (7.9%) 
45 (9.2%) 
MVPA </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>Inactive ( o60 min per day) 
324 (67%) 
414 (67%) 
277 (72%) 
340 (68%) 
226 (72%) 
261 (66%) 
Active (⩾60 min per day) 
162 (33%) 
207 (33%) 
108 (28%) 
158 (32%) 
90 (28%) 
137 (34%) 
Age </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>median (min., max.) 
12 (11,13) 
12 (11,13) 
13 (12,14) 
13 (12,14) 
14 (12,15) 
14 (12,15) 
Height </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>Mean (s.d.) 
156.81 (7.92) 
157.13 (7.47) 
162.56 (8.20) 
162.39 (8.73) 
167.28 (9.40) 
167.02 (7.88) 
Weight </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>Mean (s.d.) 
50.01 (12.05) 
49.43 (11.05) 
55.96 (12.60) 
55.22 (12.51) 
61.50 (13.23) 
60.52 (12.72) 
BMI </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>Mean (s.d.) 
20.19 (3.81) 
19.90 (3.59) 
21.04 (3.76) 
20.77 (3.96) 
21.90 (4.33) 
21.64 (4.06) 
BMI z-score </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>Mean (s.d.) 
0.58 (1.16) 
0.54 (1.11) 
0.61 (1.13) 
0.55 (1.11) 
0.72 (1.09) 
0.65 (1.12) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ATSI, Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander; BMI, body mass index; MVPA, moderate-to-vigorous physical activity; SEIFA, Socio-Economic 
Indexes for Australia. 
a Baseline (control = 7, intervention = 17), mid-point (control = 7, control = 13), follow-up (control = 2, intervention = 7). 
b Baseline 
(control = 5, intervention = 11), mid-point (control = 5, control = 7), follow-up (control = 0, intervention = 0). 
c Baseline (control = 16, intervention = 44), 
mid-point (control = 23, control = 44), follow-up (control = 22, intervention = 46). 
d Baseline (control = 20, intervention = 50), mid-point (control = 27, 
control = 49), follow-up (control = 26, intervention = 53). 
e Baseline (control = 25, intervention = 83), mid-point (control = 129, control = 173), follow-up 
(control = 82, intervention = 72). 
f Baseline (control = 19, intervention = 24), mid-point (control = 74, control = 94), follow-up (control = 109, intervention = 
162). Participants (n). 
g Baseline (control = 491, intervention = 593), mid-point (control = 409, control = 516), follow-up (control = 407, intervention = 534). 
h Baseline (control = 491, intervention = 590), mid-point (control = 442, control = 573), follow-up (control = 415, intervention = 549). 
i Baseline 
(control = 491, intervention = 587), mid-point (control = 440, control = 562), follow-up (control = 410, intervention = 547). 
j Baseline (control = 491, 
intervention = 584), mid-point (control = 440, control = 562), follow-up (control = 409, intervention = 547). 
k Baseline (control = 484, intervention = 571), 
mid-point (control = 406, control = 502), follow-up (control = 343, intervention = 488). </p>

<p>Effects of a school physical activity intervention 
JL Hollis et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity (2016) 1486 -1493 </p>

<p>time. 
10 In the latter study, the effectiveness of a 12-week 
school exercise training programme was tested in 24 obese, 
adolescent males, and found a significant intervention effect 
of − 0.59 kg m 
− 2 (95% CI = − 1.4; 0.23). 
57 The small sample in a 
high-risk, single-sex obese subgroup and the short intervention 
duration makes it difficult to equate to PA4E1. In an earlier 
meta-analysis of 18 studies, the intervention effect on BMI was 
much lower at − 0.05 kg m 
− 2 (−0.19; 0.10). 
9 However, only two of 
the 18 studies exclusively investigated the effect of a physical 
activity intervention in middle-or secondary-school students. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>The exploratory subgroup analyses found a significant effect at 
24 months, favouring the intervention group on (i) weight 
among male adolescents, and (ii) weight, BMI and BMI z-score 
among underweight/healthy weight adolescents. There were 
no treatment effects on any of the adiposity measures for the 
other subgroups examined including females, overweight/obese 
students or active/inactive students. Although the moderator 
analyses indicate that the PA4E1 intervention was effective in 
limiting weight and BMI increases in the underweight/healthy 
weight subgroup, there was no evidence that the intervention had 
an adverse effect on underweight students as the proportion of 
underweight students decreased during the study, from 7.3% at 
baseline to 2.5% at 24 months. Weight, BMI and BMI z-score 
increased in both intervention and control underweight/healthy 
weight students, but increased to a lesser extent among students 
in the intervention group. 
In PA4E1, 76% of students were not overweight or obese 
at baseline meaning a lower propensity to reduce adiposity 
measures. For this reason the authors of the HEALTHY study </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>have suggested that although population-based primary preven-
tion interventions should continue to target all children, the study 
aim and primary outcomes should be evaluated in the highest-risk 
subgroup (overweight/obese adolescents) instead of the entire 
cohort. Although there were no significant intervention effects in 
the PA4E1 overweight/obese subgroup, the adiposity results for 
the intervention group are trending in the hypothesised direction 
and the effect was larger than that found in the main analysis and 
among healthy weight/underweight students. A lack of significant 
findings in overweight and obese students is likely to be a sample 
size issue, as the disproportionate number of adolescents in each 
weight status group may have contributed to the sub-analyses 
being underpowered. 
At 24 months, the mean difference in BMI change between 
groups was − 0.28 kg m 
− 2 , with the intervention group's students 
increasing BMI by 1.59 kg m 
− 2 and control by 1.87 kg m 
− 2 over 2 
years. This BMI trajectory is higher (intervention =~0.80 kg m </p>

<p>− 2 </p>

<p>per year; control =~0.94 kg m 
− 2 per year) than that found in 
a longitudinal study in Britain that aimed to examine the 
developmental trajectory of obesity throughout adolescence in 
relation to sex, ethnicity and socio-economic status in a cohort of 
5836 adolescents. 
59 Over 5 years from Grade 7 to Grade 11, BMI 
increased by 0.73 kg m 
− 2 per year. 
59 The rate of BMI increase 
did not differ by sex; however, socio-economically disadvantaged 
and black female adolescents had higher rates of overweight 
and obesity. 
59 The higher BMI trajectory in participants of the 
PA4E1 study may also explain why PA4E1 was effective in limiting 
the adiposity increases in underweight/healthy weight adoles-
cents, but had a limited, non-significant effect on overweight and 
obese adolescents. 
The majority of school-based physical activity interventions 
targeting adolescents from socio-economically disadvantaged 
communities have not reported the effect on adiposity outcomes, 
and few have found an intervention effect. 
60,61 However, the 
results of PA4E1 are similar to findings from the 'Intervention 
Centred on Adolescent Physical Activity and Sedentary Behaviour' 
(ICAPS) study, which found intervention effects on BMI z-score. </p>

<p>62 </p>

<p>Similar to PA4E1, ICAPS was a socio-ecologically framed, 
multi-component intervention, implemented over a longer 4-year </p>

<p>Table 2. Changes in adiposity outcomes from baseline to 12-and 24-month follow-up </p>

<p>Outcome </p>

<p>Intervention </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Intervention-Control </p>

<p>Difference in change between groups </p>

<p>Baseline (n = 645) 
mean (95% CI) </p>

<p>12 m (n = 592) 
mean (95% CI) </p>

<p>24 m (n = 560) 
mean (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value 
(baseline to 
follow-up) 
Baseline (n = 505) 
mean (95% CI) </p>

<p>12 m (n = 459) 
mean (95% CI) </p>

<p>24 m (n = 425) 
mean (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value 
(baseline to 
follow-up) </p>

<p>Baseline </p>

<p>to 12 m </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Baseline </p>

<p>to 24 m 
P-value Group × time </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Weight (kg) 
50.08 (48.83, 51.34) 55.91 (54.65, 57.17) 61.08 (59.83, 62.34) 
o0.0001 50.04 (48.69, 51.38) 56.48 (55.13, 57.83) 61.94 (60.59, 63.30) </p>

<p>o0.001 
− 0.90 (−1.50, </p>

<p>− 0.30) 
0.0034 − 0.62 (−1.21, </p>

<p>− 0.03) </p>

<p>0.0396 </p>

<p>0.0106 </p>

<p>BMI (kg m </p>

<p>− 2 </p>

<p>) 20.27 (19.76, 20.78) 21.07 (20.56, 21.59) 21.86 (21.34, 22.37) </p>

<p>o0.0001 20.19 (19.65, 20.72) 21.27 (20.73, 21.81) 22.06 (21.52, 22.60) </p>

<p>o0.001 
− 0.28 (−0.50, </p>

<p>− 0.06) 
0.0126 − 0.28 (−0.49, </p>

<p>− 0.06) </p>

<p>0.0116 </p>

<p>0.0145 </p>

<p>BMI z-score </p>

<p>0.62 (0.47, 0.77) </p>

<p>0.61 (0.46, 0.75) </p>

<p>0.69 (0.54, 0.84) </p>

<p>0.0002 
0.59 (0.43, 0.74) </p>

<p>0.66 (0.50, 0.81) </p>

<p>0.71 (0.55, 0.86) 
o0.0001 − 0.05 (−0.11, 0.01) </p>

<p>0.1307 − 0.08 (−0.14, </p>

<p>− 0.02) </p>

<p>0.0062 </p>

<p>0.0226 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; CI, confidence interval. Bold values are statistically significant. </p>

<p>Effects of a school physical activity intervention 
JL Hollis et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity (2016) 1486 -1493 </p>

<p>period. 
62 The intervention involved changing attitudes towards 
physical activity (that is, educational component), promoting 
social support from teachers and parents (that is, regular 
meetings), and providing environmental and institutional conditions 
to promote physical activity (for example, break-time and 
after-school physical activity, sporting events and cycle to school 
days). 
62 The impact of ICAPS on adiposity (BMI z-score = − 0.11; 
P = 0.02) was comparable to PA4E1 (BMI z-score = − 0.08; Po0.01), 
and were maintained for 2 years 6 months after the intervention had 
finished, indicating that the results could be sustained. Similar 
proportions of overweight and obese adolescents were reported in 
ICAPS (23%) and PA4E1 (22%), and neither of the studies found 
significant adiposity effects on adolescents who were initially 
overweight or obese. The findings provide evidence for long-term 
multi-component interventions that target determinants at all 
socio-ecological levels (that is, intra-personal, inter-personal, organi-
sation, community and policy). 
PA4E1 is one of few school-based physical activity interventions 
to reduce the risk of overweight and obesity in adolescents living 
in socio-economically disadvantaged areas. 
9,63,64 A recent 
systematic review of childhood-obesity-prevention programmes 
incorporating diet and physical activity strategies, found that 
the strength of evidence was high for physical activity-only 
interventions in schools with home involvement, and for combined 
diet-physical activity interventions delivered with both home 
and community components. The PA4E1 findings indicate that 
school-based physical activity-only interventions (with home and 
community components) show promise, particularly adolescent 
populations. The impact of the intervention on adiposity outcomes 
could also be enhanced by incorporating a dietary school-based 
component with home and community involvement. 
Although the adiposity results are unlikely to be clinically 
significant at an individual level, the reduced adiposity trajectory 
may produce health benefits at a population level and over an 
individual's lifetime. A 1% reduction in the prevalence of overweight 
and obesity in 16-17-year-old adolescents today has been projected 
to reduce the number of obese adults by 52 821 in the future, 
decrease total lifetime medical costs by $586.3 million dollars 
and increase the quality-adjusted life years by 47 138 years. </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>The positive effect of PA4E1 on adiposity may have occurred due to 
the increase in objectively measured MVPA of 7 more minutes 
of MVPA per day than the control students at 24 months. 
16 The 
PA4E1 intervention was a multi-component and socio-ecologically 
framed school-based intervention, key elements of which have 
been recommended to increase physical activity and reduce 
the prevalence of obesity during adolescence. 
11,12 The intervention 
addressed educational, curricular and environmental changes in the 
school, supported by evidence from recent systematic reviews of 
school-based interventions. 
13,14 A 'change agent', who was a trained 
PE teacher, visited each of the intervention schools 1 day per week 
for the duration of the intervention to support the school and PE 
teachers in implementing the strategies (the change agent did not 
deliver any classes). The use of strategies within a sustainable 
framework of PA4E1 makes it a potentially scalable interven-
tion. The intervention could be disseminated more broadly in 
secondary schools by education departments, and therefore, 
warrants dissemination evaluation. 
This PA4E1 study had several strengths including the RCT 
design, the long intervention duration and a large sample size. 
The study included a suite of intervention implementation 
strategies based on the theoretical frameworks and evidence 
from past school-based physical activity reviews. Analyses were 
repeated using complete cases only and multiple imputation 
which reported similar results to the main analysis with regard to 
weight, BMI and BMI z-score, suggesting that the findings are 
robust. A number of limitations of the study need to be 
acknowledged. Although BMI is an acceptable measure of change 
in adiposity, direct measures, such as dual-energy radiography </p>

<p>absorptiometry, give a more accurate measure of adiposity. </p>

<p>66 </p>

<p>Although the study was implemented over a 24-month period, the 
study did not assess whether the adiposity differences were 
sustained in the longer term once the 'change agent' ceased 
visiting the intervention schools. The students were recruited 
from moderate-to-large sized, socio-economically disadvantaged 
schools from one area in Australia, which may reduce the 
generalisability of the findings. The study did not collect maturation 
data from students. The study is likely to be underpowered for 
the subgroup analyses so these findings should be interpreted with 
caution, as the lack of a treatment effect may have been due to type 
II error (failing to detect an effect that is present). Assessment of the 
cost and cost effectiveness of the PA4E1 intervention will be 
reported in a separate paper. 
There is a need for innovative physical activity interventions 
to target adolescents most at risk of overweight and obesity. 
The results from the PA4E1 intervention provide evidence for 
a multi-component physical activity intervention implemented 
in secondary schools to have a moderate effect on adiposity 
outcomes at the population level among adolescents from socio-
economically disadvantaged communities. Multi-component inter-
ventions that increase adolescents' engagement in MVPA may assist 
in preventing overweight and obesity. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank the PA4E1 staff who worked as project officers, research assistants and data 
collectors on the project. We are also indebted to the schools and students 
participating in the study. This study is funded through the NSW Ministry of Health, 
Heath Promotion Demonstration grant scheme. In kind, support for the study is also 
provided by the Hunter New England Local Health District. The project also received 
infrastructure support from the Hunter Medical Research Institute (HMRI).The study 
has been approved by the Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee 
(Ref No. 11/03/16/4.05), University of Newcastle (Ref No. H-2011-0210), NSW 
Department of Education and Communities (SERAP 2011111), Maitland Newcastle 
Catholic School Diocese and Broken Bay Catholic School Diocese. Anthony Okely is 
supported by a National Heart Foundation Career Development Fellowship. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>JW, PJM, DRL, LC, LW and KG obtained funding for the research. All authors 
contributed to developing the intervention and data collection protocols and 
materials. JLH drafted the manuscript, and all authors reviewed, edited and 
approved the final version of the paper. All authors accept full responsibility for, 
and have read and approved, the final manuscript. </p>



<p>Effects of a school physical activity intervention 
JL Hollis et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity (2016) 1486 -1493 </p>



<p>Effects of a school physical activity intervention 
JL Hollis et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity (2016) 1486 -1493 </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or 
other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons 
license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under 
the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license 
holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>© The Author(s) 2016 </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on International Journal of Obesity website (http://www.nature.com/ijo) </p>

<p>Effects of a school physical activity intervention 
JL Hollis et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity (2016) 1486 -1493 </p>

</text></tei>