<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5062751" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>We examine differences between college students and non-students 
with respect to orientation toward e-cigarettes. Participants were U.S. 
adults 18-24 (465 students, 409 non-students). Data collection 
employed an online survey by GfK Custom Research. Smoking, vaping, 
and use of alternate tobacco were assessed, as were variables from the 
Theory of Reasoned Action and Diffusion of Innovations. This study 
showed that smoking status largely explains use and orientation 
toward electronic cigarettes among both students and non-students, 
with differences attributable to higher smoking rates among non-stu-
dents. Results also showed that among student smokers there was a 
greater level of information exposure concerning electronic cigarettes, 
and more prevalence in the use of alternate tobacco. Hookah use in 
that group was significantly greater than for non-student smokers. 
Together these findings suggest that students may be more vulnerable 
to electronic cigarette use due to higher related information exposure 
and the integration of vaping into hookah culture. </p>

<p>A growing body of research is available examining e-cigarettes with 
recent studies focusing on college students. Sutfin and colleagues sur-
veyed college students from eight universities in North Carolina and 
report that while only 5% of the students had ever used an e-cigarette 
(in 2009), 12% of those individuals had never been smokers. 1 This is 
concerning as it is evidence for the potential of nicotine initiation in 
youth. In a smaller single-campus study, Trumbo and Harper focused 
on behavioural intention to try e-cigarettes and attitudes toward their 
use in public spaces. 2 They found that 71% of the students had heard 
of e-cigarettes and 13% had tried them. They also found that students 
were strongly more accepting of public vaping compared to smoking, 
suggesting that differences in social norms associated with e-cigarette 
use might support wider use. And Pokhrel and colleagues surveyed col-</p>

<p>lege students in Hawaii to examine the effect of outcome expectancies 
on use of e-cigarettes. 3 They present evidence that e-cigarette users 
are motivated by greater positive expectancies while non-users are 
motivated by greater negative expectancies. 
The purpose of this study was to examine differences between 
young adults attending and not attending college with respect to their 
attitudes toward e-cigarettes, use of e-cigarettes, and associated tobac-
co use behaviour. Such comparisons have been made on a range of 
topics such as alcohol, hookah, or drugs. 4-6 We found no studies exam-
ining this difference for e-cigarettes. 
It is important to examine differences in these two broad demo-
graphics because in the U.S. the pathway through young adulthood is 
very strongly determined by whether there is a continuation to higher 
education or not. While there is strong variance within each group, 
nonetheless the typical socioeconomic environments for the two 
groups differ strongly. Additionally, educational attainment is linked to 
better long-term health outcomes. Finally, an attendant aspect of such 
a comparison within the present context is to identify the unique 
effect of student status versus smoking status since smoking status 
has a particularly strong association with orientation and use of other 
tobacco products, including electronic cigarettes. Therefore, the analy-
sis, detailed below, is designed to test for any student versus non-stu-
dent differences that cannot be accounted for by smoking status. </p>

<p>Design and methods </p>

<p>Ethics and approval </p>

<p>The research presented in this article met the ethical guidelines, 
including adherence to the legal requirements, of the United States 
and received approval from the Colorado State University Institutional 
Review Board. </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>This study focuses on the population in the U.S. aged 18-24, 48% of 
whom are enrolled in a college or professional school (education 
beyond 12th grade). 7 Data collection was executed by GfK Custom 
Research through their online KnowledgePanel ® survey services. A 
number of published studies have shown their sampling approach to 
be superior to random digit dialing (RDD) phone and other internet-
based methods. 8 Students who attend a two-or four-year college or 
university either part-or full-time comprised approximately half of the 
sample; non-students made up the other half of the sample. Approval 
by the campus Institutional Review Board was obtained (exempt), and 
the survey was presented to 2032 KnowledgePanel participants 
between March 21 and April 2, 2013. Individuals who did not answer 
the first question, which verified student status, were terminated from </p>

<p>Significance for public health </p>

<p>This is the first study that we are aware of that looks specifically at the dif-
ferences between college students' and non-students' behaviours and atti-
tudes toward electronic cigarettes. A critical concern for young adults is 
whether adoption of electronic cigarettes will eventually lead to adoption of 
tobacco use. In this study we find that differences between student and non-
student groups can be largely accounted for by smoking status. However, stu-
dents may be more vulnerable to electronic cigarette use due to higher relat-
ed-information exposure and the integration of vaping into hookah culture. </p>

<p>Journal of Public Health Research 2016; volume 5:595 </p>

<p>Brief Report </p>

<p>[page 88] </p>

<p>[Journal of Public Health Research 2016; 5:595] </p>

<p>the survey. While free to leave the survey without penalty, respondents 
were required to complete all items in order to progress through the 
questionnaire such that missing data were not created. Respondents 
equalled 874 (465 students, 409 non-students, 43% completion rate). 
GfK provides a weighting scheme to adjust the sample to the popula-
tion. </p>

<p>Questionnaire </p>

<p>Determination of variables to include in the study was based on a 
larger project (in progress) modelling e-cigarette use within the 
Theory of Reasoned Action and Diffusion of Innovations. 
Questionnaire items are available from the first author. Means and 
standard deviations are reported in Table 1. 
Smoking and vaping status were each assessed using well-validated 
ongoing measures from the Behavioural Risk Factor Surveillance 
System. 9 The measure indicates (1 through 4) never, former, occasion-
al, and daily use. Alternate tobacco use for five activities (hookah, pipe, 
cigar, snuff, chewing tobacco) was measured using an identical 
approach (1 through 4, never to daily, a=0.70). 
Acceptability of smoking or vaping in public was measured following 
the Tobacco Use Supplement of the U.S. Census Current Population 
Survey. 10 This provides an estimate of social norms against tobacco 
smoking in public places. We asked respondents to state if 
smoking/vaping should be allowed in all areas, in some areas, or not at 
all in ten locations. Summing across the items yielded a 10-30 scale 
(smoking a=0.91, vaping a=0.98). 
Behavioural intention, attitude, and perceived social norms were 
measured using best practice recommendations provided by Ajzen. 11  Intention was a single likelihood item (How likely do you think it is 
that you would use an e-cigarette in the not-to-distant future, say in the 
next six months? from absolutely not to absolutely yes). Attitude includ-
ed three items (a=0.82) (e.g., strongly agree to strongly disagree, The 
use of e-cigarettes should be legal for adults). Norms consisted of three 
pairs of items for closest friends, most people I know, and closest family 
members. This was computed as the sum of the product of the three-
paired statements (a =0.84) (e.g., strongly agree to strongly disagree It 
would be acceptable to my very closest friends if I used e-cigarettes with 
When it comes to things like using an e-cigarette, it is important to me 
to follow the wishes of my very closest friends). 
Measures for the perceived innovation characteristics of e-cigarettes 
were based on the measurement study by Moore and the work of 
Rogers. 12,13 Two items were used for each of the five elements of an 
innovation (1-5 agree/disagree) for e-cigarettes' relative advantage, 
compatibility (e.g., I believe using e-cigarettes would fit in well with the 
lifestyle of most smokers), complexity, trialability, and observability 
(e.g., It would be easy to tell whether a person was using an e-cigarette 
versus smoking tobacco). The final measure was the sum of the 10 indi-
cators (a=0.93). 
An assessment of information exposure was also included. 
Participants were asked Where have you heard or seen information 
about e-cigarettes? and were provided a yes/no checklist including 
newspapers, magazines, television, the Web, and point of purchase (on 
store shelves). This formed an additive measure of the five items from 
0 for no exposure to 5 for greatest exposure (a=0.41). </p>

<p>Statistical methods </p>

<p>All measures were coded so as to be consistent such that higher val-
ues indicate more positive orientations toward e-cigarettes and the 
likelihood of their use. Descriptive analyses used appropriate measures 
of central tendency and dispersion. Cronbach's alpha was used to 
assess scale reliability. Tests for differences and associations were 
done so as to separate the effect of student status and smoking status 
due to their conflation. Factorial ANOVA was used to compare differ-
ences in means across student status and smoking status, with effect </p>

<p>sizes calculated (h 2 ). Partial correlations (r and eta) controlling for 
smoking status were used to assess associations within student status 
and to compare associations across student status. Across-group com-
parisons of associations were tested using Fischer's r-to-z transforma-
tion. Data were weighted for comparison of student and non-student 
groups. All analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13</rs>. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Table 1 reports descriptive statistics and tests of differences between 
students and non-students, without regard to smoking status. The 
groups were equivalent in terms of sex, but non-students were some-
what older. There were no significant differences on the race/ethnicity </p>

<p>Brief Report </p>

<p>Figure 1. Significant interactions. </p>

<p>measures. While the percentages of former and occasional smoking 
were equivalent, a significantly greater proportion of students were 
never smokers, while a significantly greater proportion of non-students 
were daily smokers. On electronic cigarette use, a greater proportion of 
students were never vapers and a grater proportion of non-students 
were occasional vapers. There was not a significant difference at 
P&lt;0.05 in the percentage of dual users (among the 144 current smok-
ers, which might support a relaxed alpha in which case the rate is high-
er among non-students). Non-students were also significantly more </p>

<p>approving of public smoking, had a greater intention to use electronic 
cigarettes, and reported greater information exposure on electronic 
cigarettes. There were no significant differences on the remaining 
items (public vaping, attitude, norms, and innovation). 
Table 2 reports the simultaneous effects of smoking status (ever ver-
sus never) and student status on the eight variables of interest, with 
allowance for interaction terms. Significant differences were found for 
each variable conditioned on smoking, with uniformly small-to-medi-
um effect sizes. Student status showed no main effects. Two significant </p>

<p>[Journal of Public Health Research 2016; 5:595] 
[page 89] </p>

<p>Brief Report </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of measures for student and non-student groups. </p>

<p>Variable 
Group 
P/M (SD) 
test 
P </p>

<p>Sex (female) 
Student 
52.5% 
χ 2 (1)=2.9 
0.09 
Non-student 
46.7% 
Age (years) 
Student 
20.59 (1.85) 
t(872)=5.8 
&lt;0.001 
Non-student 
21.36 (2.05) 
White non-Hispanic 
Student 
63.0% 
χ 2 (1)=3.1 
0.08 
Non-student 
57.4% 
Black non-Hispanic 
Student 
11.8% 
χ 2 (1)=1.3 
0.25 
Non-student 
14.5% 
Other non-Hispanic 
Student 
8.4% 
χ 2 (1)=1.3 
0.25 
Non-student 
6.4% 
Hispanic 
Student 
16.8% 
χ 2 (1)=3.5 
0.06 
Non-student 
21.8% 
Never smoker 
Student 
84.3% 
χ 2 (1)=32.5 
&lt;0.001 
Non-student 
70.7% 
Former smoker 
Student 
4.3% 
χ 2 (1)=3.2 
0.07 
Non-student 
7.1% 
Occasional smoker 
Student 
7.1% 
χ 2 (1)=0.2 
0.66 
Non-student 
6.4% 
Daily smoker 
Student 
4.3% 
χ 2 (1)=33.3 
&lt;0.001 
Non-student 
15.9% 
Never vaper 
Student 
89.1% 
χ 2 (1)=4.6 
0.03 
Non-student 
84.1% 
Former vaper 
Student 
9.0% 
χ 2 (1)=0.7 
0.39 
Non-student 
10.7% 
Occasional vaper 
Student 
1.7% 
χ 2 (1)=4.6 
0.03 
Non-student 
4.1% 
Daily vaper 
Student 
0.2% 
χ 2 (1)=2.2 
0.14 
Non-student 
1.0% 
Dual use in current smokers 
Student 
9.4% 
χ 2 (1)=3.2 
0.08 
Non-student 
20.9% 
Alt. tobacco scale 
Student 
5.92 (1.52) 
t(872)=1.7 
0.09 
Non-student 
6.12 (1.88) 
Public smoking 
Student 
14.08 (3.86) 
t(872)=4.3 
&lt;0.01 
Non-student 
15.28 (4.31) 
Public vaping 
Student 
18.86 (7.08) 
t(872)=1.8 
0.08 
Non-student 
19.74 (7.48) 
Behavioral intention 
Student 
1.64 (1.24) 
t(872)=2.8 
&lt;0.01 
Non-student 
1.90 (1.52) 
Attitude 
Student 
9.84 (2.83) 
t(872)=1.0 
0.31 
Non-student 
10.03 (2.89) 
Norms 
Student 
22.10 (18.72) 
t(872)=1.3 
0.21 
Non-student 
24.47 (19.14) 
Innovation 
Student 
32.21 (8.05) 
t(872)=0.4 
0.69 
Non-student 
33.44 (8.68) 
Information 
Student 
0.82 (0.98) 
t((872)=2.4 
&lt;0.05 
Non-student 
0.99 (1.09) </p>



<p>[Journal of Public Health Research 2016; 5:595] </p>

<p>interaction effects were found, however, as reported in Table 2 and 
illustrated in Figure 1. A cross-over interaction was found for informa-
tion exposure in which student ever smokers scored higher than non-
student ever smokers and student never smokers scored lower than 
non-student never smokers (meaning, students who smoked had more 
exposure to information about e-cigarettes, but students who didn't 
smoke actually had less exposure to information about e-cigarettes 
than non-students). Also, student ever smokers scored higher on alter-
nate tobacco use than did non-student ever smokers, while the never 
smokers were equivalent across student groups. A closer look revealed 
that hookah use was dominant. Among ever smokers, the hookah use 
score was significantly higher among students (1.97 versus 1.61, 
t(191)=3.1 P&lt;0.01), with 58.3% of the non-students having never tried 
hookah, compared to 27.4% of students (χ 2 (3)=23.5 P&lt;0.001). Further 
examination also shows a higher rate of vape/hookah dual use. Among 
the student ever smokers who vape some days or every day, 50% use 
hookah some days or every day. The rate among non-students is half 
that, 26.3% (χ 2 (4)=17.6 P&lt;0.01). 
Table 3 reports partial correlations among the eight variables of 
interest, controlling for smoking status. Separate correlations were run 
for students and non-students. The Fischer r-to-z transformation was 
used to test for differences between coefficients. No significant differ-
ences were found, thus the correlations can be interpreted as equiva-
lent. Different sample sizes account for some of the borderline con-
trasts between the groups (approximately r=0.10 required for signifi-
cance). Despite no contrasts between student and non-students, the 
correlation analysis does reveal some interesting results. The variables 
can be considered as five attitudinal and two behavioural measures 
(with intention in the latter with alternate tobacco use). Each of the 
attitude measures presents a significant association with both of the 
behavioural measures, with the exception of information with inten-
tion. Of note, attitude, norms, innovation, and information have medi-
um-to-strong associations with the two key variables of interest: behav-
ioural intention to use an electronic cigarette and acceptability of pub-
lic vaping. </p>

<p>Discussion and Conclusions </p>

<p>Foremost, this study showed that smoking status explains use and </p>

<p>orientation toward electronic cigarettes among both students and non-
students. Differences that might be observed based on student status 
are accounted for by the much higher smoking rate among non-stu-
dents compared to students. The more subtle differences found in two 
significant interactions offer some additional insight, however. 
The first involved use of alternate tobacco products. While the target 
outcome of this study was electronic cigarettes, the use of alternate 
tobacco products was assessed as a predictor. This variable is also of 
interest as contrasted by smoking and student status. The interaction </p>

<p>Brief Report </p>

<p>Table 2. ANOVA by student and smoking status. </p>

<p>Dependent 
Factors 
P 
h 2 </p>

<p>Public smoking 
Smoke 
&lt;0.01 
0.11 
Student 
n.s. 
Interaction 
n.s. 
Public vaping 
Smoke 
&lt;0.01 
0.14 
Student 
n.s. 
Interaction 
n.s. 
Intention 
Smoke 
&lt;0.01 
0.25 
Student 
n.s. 
Interaction 
n.s. 
Attitude 
Smoke 
&lt;0.01 
0.06 
Student 
n.s. 
Interaction 
n.s. 
Norms 
Smoke 
&lt;0.01 
0.10 
Student 
n.s. 
Interaction 
n.s. 
Innovation 
Smoke 
&lt;0.01 
0.06 
Student 
n.s. 
Interaction 
n.s. 
Information 
Smoke 
&lt;0.01 
0.02 
Student 
n.s. 
Interaction 
&lt;0.05 
0.01 
Alt. tobacco 
Smoke 
&lt;0.01 
0.16 
Student 
n.s. 
Interaction 
&lt;0.05 
0.01 </p>

<p>n.s., not significant. </p>

<p>Table 3. Partial correlations (controlling for smoking) for students (N=465) and non-students (N=409). </p>

<p>Public vaping 
Alt. tobacco 
Intention 
Attitude 
Norms 
Innovation Information </p>

<p>Public smoking, students 
0.50** 
0.21** 
0.10* 
0.30** 
0.19** 
0.28** 
0.06 
Public smoking, non-students 
0.46** 
0.10 
0.10* 
0.19** 
0.24** 
0.23** 
0.17** 
Public vaping, students 
0.15** 
0.08 
0.55** 
0.29** 
0.49** 
0.13** 
Public vaping, non-students 
0.08 
0.12* 
0.51** 
0.32** 
0.52** 
0.25** 
Alt. tobacco, students 
0.19** 
0.19** 
0.13** 
0.13** 
0.14** 
Alt. tobacco, non-students 
0.30** 
0.06 
0.05 
0.08 
0.12* 
Intention, students 
0.13** 
0.13** 
0.05 
0.07 
Intention, non-students 
0.12* 
0.17** 
0.15** 
0.03 
Attitude, students 
0.52** 
0.86** 
0.18** 
Attitude, non-students 
0.60** 
0.90** 
0.20** 
Norms, students 
0.56** 
0.09 
Norms, non-students 
0.62** 
0.13** 
Innovation, students 
0.19** 
Innovation, non-students 
0.22** </p>

<p>*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01. No pairs significantly different at P&lt;0.05 using Fischer r-to-z transformation (two-tailed test). </p>

<p>shows that by a significant margin student ever smokers are more avid 
users of alternate tobacco products. The role of hookah use and 
hookah/vape dual use was also examined in this analysis. It is well 
established that hookah use has become a growing part of college life. 
The results of this study provide further evidence of this, and also pro-
vide a glimpse of the dual use of electronic cigarettes with hookah, an 
indicator that electronic cigarettes are becoming a part of the nicotine 
ecology on college campuses. 
The second interaction also offers some insight. Student ever smok-
ers report a significantly greater exposure to information on electronic 
cigarettes. The study did not assess the nature of information, which 
might be in various forms including news reports or advertising. The 
study also did not assess passive information exposure versus active 
information seeking. Nonetheless these results point toward the prolif-
eration of electronic cigarette stores near college campuses and sug-
gest the likelihood of electronic cigarette marketing directed at the col-
lege demographic. Many studies have shown that a significant propor-
tion of youth tobacco initiation can be linked to advertising exposure, 14  and that Internet-based marketing (the primary method for e-ciga-
rettes) may be particularly effective in the initiation of electronic ciga-
rette use in young adults, especially those in college. 15 Clearly further 
work is needed on the effect of e-cigarette advertising. 
Limitations of this study include self-report items for measurement, 
the narrow age-range of participants, and the cross-sectional design. A 
more critical limitation resides in the measurement of smoking and 
vaping status. The response category former fails to allow for the 
assessment of the extent a respondent had formerly smoked or vaped. 
These respondents may have tried either only once, or may have exper-
imented for a period and quit. 
The results of this study point toward avenues for future investiga-
tion and potential policy guidance. Investigation of orientation toward 
and use of electronic cigarettes in the young adult population should 
attend especially to the next cohort of individuals, which as noted 
above are known to be experimenting with electronic cigarettes at a 
significantly increasing rate. How these individuals will orient toward 
the range of tobacco products as they move away from home and into 
independent life on or off of a college campus merits monitoring. Policy 
efforts to make college campuses entirely tobacco free should certainly 
continue and expressly include electronic cigarettes, as should smok-
ing prohibited zones elsewhere in communities. In terms of current 
regulatory policy discussions, this study along with a growing number 
of others advocate for the extension of tobacco advertising regulations 
to electronic cigarettes. 
In conclusion, this is the first study that we are aware of that looks 
specifically at the differences between college students' and non-stu-
dents' behaviours and attitudes toward electronic cigarettes. A critical 
concern with respect to young adults is whether adoption of electronic 
cigarettes might lead to adoption of tobacco use, especially since the 
positive expectancies are similar for both products. In this study we 
found smoking status to be the main driver for electronic cigarette use, 
which should offer some positive encouragement for those engaged 
with promoting healthy behaviours on college campuses − college life 
does not appear to place young adults at greater risk for electronic cig-
arette use. However, the results also offer a cautionary note as the stu-
dent population was shown to be more engaged with electronic ciga-
rette messages and the use of electronic cigarettes is becoming nor-
malized within the broader nicotine social ecology on campuses. These 
factors may point toward vulnerabilities for the expansion of vaping on 
campuses. </p>



<p>Brief Report </p>

<p>Correspondence: Craig W. Trumbo, Department of Journalism and Media 
Communication, 1785 Campus Mail, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, 
CO 80526, USA. 
Tel.: +1.970.491.2077. 
E-mail: ctrumbo@mac.com 
Key words: Electronic cigarettes; students; non-students; public use; rea-
soned action. 
Contributions: CT participated in the design of the study. CT and RH con-
ducted data collection and performed the statistical analysis. All authors 
drafted and approved the final manuscript. 
Conflict of interest: the authors declare no potential conflict of interest. 
Funding: this research was supported by a Grant from the National Institute 
on Drug Abuse (1R03DA033578-01) to Dr Trumbo. 
Received for publication: 6 July 2015. 
Accepted for publication: 12 January 2016. 
©Copyright C.W. Trumbo and R. Harper, 2016 
Licensee PAGEPress, Italy 
Journal of Public Health Research 2016;5:595 
doi:10.4081/jphr.2016.595 
This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 
4.0 License (CC BY-NC 4.0). </p>

</text></tei>