<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5476584" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: The emergence of colistin-resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa in cystic fibrosis (CF) 
patients, particularly after long-term inhalation treatments, has been recently reported. Nanoen-
capsulation may enable preparations to overcome the limitations of conventional pharmaceutical 
forms. We have determined the time-dependent viability of P. aeruginosa biofilms treated with 
both free and nanoencapsulated colistin. We also examined the relationship between the optimal 
anti-biofilm activity of nanostructured lipid carrier (NLC)-colistin and the structural organiza-
tion of the biofilm itself. The results showed the more rapid killing of P. aeruginosa bacterial 
biofilms by NLC-colistin than by free colistin. However, the two formulations did not differ in 
terms of the final percentages of living and dead cells, which were higher in the inner than in 
the outer layers of the treated biofilms. The effective anti-biofilm activity of NLC-colistin and 
its faster killing effect recommend further studies of its use over free colistin in the treatment 
of P. aeruginosa infections in CF patients. 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa is a gram-negative opportunistic pathogen that frequently 
infects the lungs of cystic fibrosis (CF) patients in the form of chronic biofilm 
infections. 
1 The antimicrobial resistance of bacteria assuming a biofilm mode of growth 
poses challenges not only to host immune clearance mechanisms but also to health 
care settings, in the form of an increased risk of hospital-acquired infections. 
2 The 
high level of antibiotic resistance that characterizes biofilms can be attributed to their 
structurally heterogeneous microenvironments, some of which contain metabolically 
inactive cell population, 
3,4 as well as to the differential expression of multiple gene 
networks and extracellular matrix by the resident bacterial species. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Over the last decade, increasing attention has been paid to antimicrobial peptides 
(AMPs) as therapeutic agents, because resistance to them is thus far rare. Moreover, 
these peptides are able to modulate the innate immune response. 
5-7 The AMP colistin 
is a cyclic cationic decapeptide that attacks negatively charged bacterial membranes, 
thereby disrupting both the outer and inner membranes of gram-negative species. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Although the use of colistin as an antimicrobial is restricted by its high nephrotoxic-
ity, the increasing emergence of multiresistant pathogens has renewed interest in its 
therapeutic potential. 
8 In fact, nowadays, colistin is administered to CF patients and 
to other patients with chronic respiratory diseases for the treatment of lung infections </p>

<p>correspondence: Miguel Viñas 
Laboratory of Molecular Microbiology, 
University of Barcelona, Feixa Llarga 
s/n, 08907 L'Hospitalet de Llobregat, 
Barcelona, Spain 
Tel +34 93 402 4265 
email mvinyas@ub.edu </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nanomedicine 
12 June 2017 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4410 </p>

<p>sans-serramitjana et al </p>

<p>caused by P. aeruginosa. 
9 However, colistin resistance, 
mediated by the post-translational modification of lipopoly-
saccharide, has emerged, perhaps driven by the increasing 
clinical use of this drug. 
10,11 Although resistance rates are 
still low in many countries, the recent identification of a 
plasmid-borne colistin resistance gene (mcr-1) in human, 
animal, and environmental isolates of Enterobacteriaceae 
may soon lead to rapid increases in resistance on a global 
scale. 
12,13 An awareness of this threat has catalyzed the search 
for less toxic antimicrobials as well as the development of 
synthetically modified forms enabling dose reductions, longer 
administration intervals, and reduced systemic toxicity. An 
alternative is new delivery strategies, such as the use of solid 
lipid nanoparticles and nanostructured lipid carriers (NLCs) 
to deliver colistin in CF patients with P. aeruginosa respira-
tory infections. The nebulization of antimicrobials carried in 
lipid nanoparticles improves drug bioavailability and allows 
a reduced dosing frequency. 
14 In principle, the administration 
of encapsulated drugs could overcome preexisting resistance 
mechanisms, including the decreased uptake and increased 
efflux of the drug, as well as biofilm formation. 
15 In a previ-
ous study, we demonstrated the higher anti-biofilm activity 
of NLC-colistin than of free colistin in both susceptible and 
resistant P. aeruginosa strains isolated from the sputum 
samples of CF patients. 
16 As biofilms play a key role in the 
natural history of P. aeruginosa respiratory infections in CF, 
the use of NLC-colistin may offer new approaches to their 
treatment. However, the mechanism underlying the improved 
efficiency of NLC-colistin in biofilm removal is unknown. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Pamp et al 
17 showed that free colistin acts preferentially on 
bacteria with low metabolic rates; this is the case for bacte-
ria in the deepest layers of a biofilm, as metabolic activity 
decreases with increasing distance from the biofilm surface. 
Whether the same differential response occurs with NLC-
colistin has not been determined. Thus, this study explored 
the efficacy of NLC-colistin versus the free drug with respect 
to biofilm viability over time and across the different layers 
of the biofilm. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Preparation of lipid nanoparticles </p>

<p>NLCs were prepared using the hot melt homogenization 
technique. 
18 The lipid core consisted of Precirol 
® ATO 5 
(Gattefossé, Madrid, Spain) and Miglyol 812 (Sasol, Hamburg, 
Germany), which were mixed with colistin sulfate (Zhejiang 
Shenghua Biok Biology Co., Ltd., China). The tempera-
ture of the mixture was gradually increased to the melting 
temperature of the solid lipids. The surfactant solution was 
1.3% (w/v) Polysorbate 80 (Panreac Química, Castellar del </p>

<p>Vallès, Barcelona, Spain) and 0.6% (w/v) Poloxamer 188 
(BASF, Ludwigshafen, Rhineland-Palatinate, Germany). 
The mixture was emulsified by sonication for 15 s at 
20 W. The nanoparticles were recrystallized by an over-
night incubation at 4°C to stimulate particle formation. 
They were then washed three times by centrifugation at 
2,500 rpm in Amicon centrifugal filtration units (100,000 
MWCO). All prepared nanoparticles were freeze-dried with 
trehalose (15%). </p>

<p>Bacterial strain, culture conditions, and 
biofilm formation </p>

<p>P. aeruginosa strain PA01 in 20 mL of Mueller-Hinton II 
broth cation adjusted (Becton Dickinson Diagnostic Sys-
tems, Inc., Sparks, MD, USA) was grown overnight at 37°C 
with continuous shaking at 250 rpm. The culture was then 
adjusted to a concentration of 1-5×10 
8 cfu/mL, and 200 µL 
was used to inoculate µ-Slide 8 glass bottom wells (Ibidi, 
cat. num. 80827, Munich, Germany). Each well was previ-
ously coated with a 0.01% (w/v) poly-lysine hydrobromide 
(Sigma-Aldrich, Dorset, UK) solution to enhance bacterial 
cell adhesion and to prevent biofilm removal during the 
experiments. The slides were incubated at 37°C for 24 h to 
allow biofilm formation. </p>

<p>Confocal laser scanning microscopy 
imaging </p>

<p>Biofilms on the eight-well glass were washed once with 
Ringer ¼ to remove unfixed bacteria and then treated 
with free and NLC-colistin at a colistin concentration of 
128 µg/mL, based on previously published results. 
16 They 
were then incubated at 37°C for 20, 30, 40, 60, 80, and 
100 min after which they were rinsed once with Ringer ¼. 
To stain the biofilms, a mixture of SYTO 9 and propidium 
iodide prepared at a dilution ratio of 1:2 (1.5 µL of SYTO 
9 and 3 µL of propidium iodide in 1 mL of Ringer ¼) was 
applied to the entire biofilm. After 30 min of incubation in 
the dark at 37°C, the stained biofilms were washed once with 
Ringer ¼ to remove nonspecific staining. Fluorescence was 
observed using a Leica TCS-SL filter-free spectral confocal 
laser-scanning microscope (Leica Microsystems, Mannheim, 
Germany) equipped with a 488-nm argon laser, 543-nm and 
633-nm He/Ne lasers (Scientific and Technological Centers, 
University of Barcelona, Bellvitge Campus, L'Hospitalet de 
LLobregat, Spain), and a 63× magnification oil immersion 
objective (1.4 numerical aperture). The image resolution 
was 1,024×1,024 pixels. All experiments were performed 
in duplicate. Confocal laser scanning microscopy (CLSM) 
images were analyzed using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software (National </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4411 </p>

<p>Spatiotemporal survival of NLC-colistin-treated biofilm of P. aeruginosa </p>

<p>Institutes of health, Bethesda, MD, USA). The percentages 
of alive and dead bacterial cells were calculated from the 
total cell number. </p>

<p>Results and discussion 
Time-dependent killing of strain PaO1 
biofilms by free and NLC-colistin </p>

<p>Enumeration of the viable and dead bacteria for every treat-
ment showed an increase in bacterial death over time in the 
strain PAO1 biofilms (Figure 1). In the control (untreated) 
biofilms, most of the cells were viable, with live/dead ratios 
of 78.2% (green) and 21.8% (red), respectively. This result 
was in agreement with a previous report. 
19 The baseline 
viability was taken into account in the interpretation of 
the experimental data. A nonlethal effect was observed in 
biofilms exposed for 20 min to free colistin, with the pro-
portions of living and dead bacteria almost identical to that 
of the control (~80% and 20%, respectively). The killing 
efficiency reached a maximum of 80% after 60 min of treat-
ment with the free formulation. By contrast, after 20 min 
of exposure to NLC-colistin, ~75% of the individual cells 
were dead (red fluorescence) and after 60 min of treatment 
almost 100%, thus demonstrating the rapid killing effect of 
the encapsulated drug. 
The results shown in Figure 1 are in good agreement 
with the CLSM images of the untreated and treated biofilms 
(Figure 2). The latter mostly stained green (Figure 2), indi-
cating a high level of bacterial viability. After 20 and 40 min 
of exposure to NLC-colistin (Figure 2), the red population 
increased over time such that very few green-staining cells 
were observed, consistent with the significant damage of bac-
teria residing in the treated biofilm. After a 60-min incubation </p>

<p>with NLC-colistin, all bacterial cells stained red. In the biofilms 
treated with free colistin (Figure 2), the percentages of the red 
and green populations of bacteria after 20 min were almost 
identical to those of the control. After 40 and 60 min (Figure 2), 
the red population in the free colistin treatment was always 
smaller than that in the NLC-colistin treatment, evidence of 
the faster killing of bacterial biofilms by the latter. This may 
reflect the ability of the lipid nanoparticles to easily penetrate 
the biofilm matrix, with the nanoparticulated drug then reach-
ing the bacteria faster and more easily than free colistin. </p>

<p>21,22 </p>

<p>Islan et al 
22 reported similar results using levofloxacin-loaded 
lipid nanoparticles. In that study, rapid killing of P. aeruginosa 
biofilms by NLC-levofloxacin was achieved after 60 min of 
exposure. </p>

<p>Figure 1 graphical representation of living and dead bacteria treated or not treated 
with the different colistin formulations. 
Note: Error bars represent the standard deviation of the mean (time: 0, 20, 40, 
and 60 min). 
Abbreviations: F-C, free colistin; NLC-C, colistin nanoparticulated in nanostruc-
tured lipid carrier. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Confocal laser scanning microscopy images of Pseudomonas aeruginosa 
strain PAO1 biofilms. 
Notes: Control: untreated biofilm. Drug exposure time: 20, 40, and 60 min. Green: 
viable bacteria; red: dead bacteria. 
Abbreviations: free-col, free colistin; NLC-col, colistin nanoparticulated in 
nanostructured lipid carrier. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4412 </p>

<p>sans-serramitjana et al </p>

<p>Differentiation of distinct bacterial 
subpopulations in the strain PAO1 biofilm </p>

<p>Biofilms are a complex, multicellular structure that favors the 
generation of physiologically distinct subpopulations of bac-
teria that together form a community able to adapt to rapidly 
changing environmental conditions. 
23 To explore whether 
free and nanoencapsulated colistin differentially act on the 
subpopulations residing within the biofilm, the viability of 
bacteria in the different layers of the biofilm was determined. 
As seen in Table 1, the bacterial density was much higher in 
the inner layers of the biofilm, consistent with the previously 
reported high density of cells located close to the substratum 
in P. aeruginosa biofilms. 
24 The biofilms were investigated 
in greater detail by dividing them in half, which revealed that 
71% of the total number of cells occupied the inner layers 
(Table 1). This was essentially the case in all three types of 
biofilms (control, free colistin, and NLC-colistin) despite the 
demonstrated heterogeneity among biofilms with respect to 
their thickness and the strength of their surface attachment. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Nonetheless, our results can be explained by the initiation of 
cell detachment in the upper layers of the biofilm 
26 as well as 
the accumulation of high densities of smaller cells in deeper 
parts of the biofilm in response to external stress conditions. 
Also, it is likely that the washing step with buffer altered the 
external parts of the biofilm while leaving its deeper parts 
relatively undisturbed. Although weakly attached bacteria 
will be discarded by carefully washing the biofilms after 
24 h of incubation, simultaneous disruption of the superficial 
layers of the biofilm is difficult to avoid. 
The two colistin formulations did not differ in their 
effects on the various biofilm subpopulations, as the per-
centages of living and dead cells were higher in the inner 
than in the outer layers of biofilms treated with free colistin 
or NLC-colistin (Table 1). Our results demonstrate that 
both formulations are able to penetrate the deeper layers 
of the biofilm and thus access a dormant and anaerobically </p>

<p>growing subpopulation. 
27,28 A reduction of the free colistin 
concentration, the delayed penetration of the free drug into 
the deeper portions of the multilayered biofilm, and the lack 
of specificity of NLC-colistin in killing metabolically active 
bacteria versus starved cells may account for our results, as 
proposed in similar studies. 
17,29 Further experiments will be 
aimed at improving the experimental conditions to optimize 
the performance of NLC-colistin. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In our previous works, 
16,18 we demonstrated the identical antimi-
crobial activity of free colistin and NLC-colistin. Here we have 
shown that NLC-colistin was clearly more effective than its free 
form in eradicating biofilms of P. aeruginosa, the most relevant 
pathogen in CF patients. Thus, the use of lipid nanoparticles may 
be an interesting strategy to prevent the growth and develop-
ment of microbial biofilms in the clinical setting. NLC-colistin 
was much faster than free colistin in killing P. aeruginosa, 
based on the ability of the encapsulated drug to reach both the 
superficial and the deep regions of the biofilm. Further experi-
ments are needed to identify the precise mechanism underlying 
the efficient removal of biofilms by NLC-colistin. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Wendy Ran for copy editing the English version of 
the manuscript. This work was carried out under the Compre-
hensive Research on Effective Therapies for the Treatment 
of Cystic Fibrosis and Associated Diseases (IPT-2011-
1402-900000) funded by the Spanish Ministry of Economy 
and Competitiveness. The authors gratefully acknowledge 
the support of the Scientific and Technological Centers 
(University of Barcelona, Bellvitge Campus, L'Hospitalet de 
LLobregat, Spain) and particularly the technical assistance of 
Dr Benjamin Torrejón in the CLSM study. MV is a member 
of the ENABLE (European Gram Negative Antibacterial 
Engine) European consortium (IMI-ND4BB). </p>

<p>Table 1 Percentage of the bacterial population living in the various layers and percentages of live and dead bacteria of the Pseudomonas 
aeruginosa strain PAO1 biofilm after 20, 40, and 60 min of treatment with F-C and NLC-C </p>

<p>Treatment 
Biofilm 
layer </p>

<p>Percentage of the bacterial population (%) </p>

<p>t=0 min 
t=20 min 
t=40 min 
t=60 min </p>

<p>Total 
Live 
Dead 
Total 
Live 
Dead 
Total 
Live 
Dead 
Total 
Live 
Dead </p>

<p>c+ 
Outer 
28.5 
22.5 
6.1 
Inner 
71.5 
55.8 
15.7 
F-c 
Outer 
32.4 
29.0 
3.4 
35.2 
20.9 
14.3 
37.9 
6.6 
31.3 
Inner 
60.3 
50.3 
9.9 
64.8 
30.1 
34.8 
62.1 
7.6 
54.5 
Nlc-c 
Outer 
20.8 
5.5 
15.3 
17.4 
0.9 
16.5 
19.6 
0.2 
19.5 
Inner 
79.2 
19.7 
59.6 
82.6 
3.9 
78.7 
80.4 
0.9 
79.5 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: c+, untreated biofilm; F-C, free colistin; NLC-C, colistin nanoparticulated in nanostructured lipid carrier. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-nanomedicine-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of Nanomedicine is an international, peer-
reviewed journal focusing on the application of nanotechnology 
in diagnostics, therapeutics, and drug delivery systems throughout 
the biomedical field. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, 
MedLine, CAS, SciSearch®, Current Contents®/Clinical Medicine, </p>

<p>Journal Citation Reports/Science Edition, EMBase, Scopus and the 
Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4413 </p>

<p>Spatiotemporal survival of NLC-colistin-treated biofilm of P. aeruginosa </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>