<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5084670" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>(BOLT). In this study, clinically meaningful responses were 
observed in patients with advanced BCC from Europe, Austra-
lia and the USA with acceptable safety profile and manageable 
toxicities. </p>

<p>(8)   Here, we report results from our study evaluating the safety, 
tolerability, efficacy, pharmacokinetics, and pharmacodynamics 
of sonidegib in Asian patients in Japan, Hong Kong, and Tai-
wan with advanced solid tumors that had progressed despite 
standard therapy, or for whom no standard therapy exists. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Study design. This was an open-label, single-arm, multicen-
ter, two-group, parallel, dose-escalation, phase I study under-
taken in Asian patients; patient group 1 was from Japan and 
patient group 2 from Hong Kong and Taiwan. The primary 
objective of the study was to determine the MTD and the RD 
in groups 1 and 2 individually, as per the health authority's 
request. Additional objectives included safety, pharmacokinet-
ics, pharmacodynamics, and antitumor activity. All patients 
entered a 7-day pharmacokinetic run-in period to characterize 
the pharmacokinetic profile of sonidegib after a single dose. 
Patients received a single oral dose of sonidegib daily in a 28-
day cycle. At least three patients (per patient group) were 
enrolled into a dose cohort (400, 800, and 1250 mg q.d. as a 
provisional), and the occurrence of dose-limiting toxicity 
(DLT) was evaluated during the first administration in the 
pharmacokinetic run-in period to end of the first cycle. The 
MTDs were evaluated for DLT using an adaptive Bayesian 
logistic regression model using escalation with overdose con-
trol to guide the dose escalation process. </p>

<p>(9,10)   A DLT was defined as a significant adverse event (AE) or 
abnormal laboratory parameter adjudged to be Common Ter-
minology Criteria for Adverse Events (version 3.0) grade 3 or 
4 in severity and considered unrelated to disease progression, 
intercurrent illness, or concomitant medications. The MTD 
was defined as the highest probability of dose of sonidegib 
predicted to have 16-33% of the DLT rate and &lt;25% probabil-
ity of a DLT rate of ≥33% during cycle 1 (first 28 days). How-
ever, the AEs corresponding to DLTs were observed even 
after cycle 1 and were taken into consideration as part of the 
clinical review to decide the next dose level and determine 
MTD and/or RD. 
Patient population. Adult patients with histologically or cyto-
logically confirmed advanced solid tumors, including recurrent 
MB, whose disease progressed despite standard therapy or for 
whom no standard therapy was available, were eligible. 
Patients with recurrent MB who were taking corticosteroids 
should be on a non-increasing dose of steroids for at least 
14 days prior to starting the study drug. Other key inclusion 
criteria were measurable or evaluable disease defined by 
Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors version 1.0 </p>

<p>(11)   and performance status ≤2. In addition, all patients must have 
had adequate bone marrow (absolute neutrophil count 
[1.5 9 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L], hemoglobin [9 g/dL], and platelets [100 9 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/ 
L]), liver (serum total bilirubin [1.5 9 upper limit of normal 
(ULN)], aspartate aminotransferase, and alanine aminotrans-
ferase [2.5 9 ULN or 5.0 9 ULN if liver metastases are pre-
sent]), and kidney function (serum creatinine [1.5 9 ULN] or 
24-h creatinine clearance [50 mL/min]). Patients were 
excluded if they had a history of a brain tumor or brain metas-
tases (except relapsed MB), clinically significant cardiac dis-
ease, or gastrointestinal dysfunction that might impair 
sonidegib absorption. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women or </p>

<p>women of childbearing potential were excluded. Treatment 
with strong inhibitors or inducers of cytochrome P450 (CYP) 
3A4/5 or drugs metabolized by CYP2B6 or CYP2C9, which 
have a narrow therapeutic index, was prohibited during the 
study. All patients provided written informed consent before 
enrolment. The study followed the ethical principles of the 
Declaration of Helsinki and the International Conference on 
Harmonization Guideline for Good Clinical Practice, and was 
approved by the institutional review board. 
Safety evaluations. Safety was assessed according to the 
Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 
3.0. 
(12) Assessments included regular laboratory evaluations, 
physical examinations, vital signs, weight, and periodic elec-
trocardiogram recordings. In order to be considered a DLT by 
protocol, the toxicity must have occurred during pharmacoki-
netic run-in and the first 28-day cycle of sonidegib treatment. 
Pharmacokinetics. For the pharmacokinetic run-in period, 
serial blood samples were collected starting on day 1 (ending 
on day 7) at predose and 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 24, 48, 72, 96, and 
168 h post-dose. Serial blood samples were also collected on 
day 15 of cycle 1 at predose and 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, and 24 h 
post-dose. Furthermore, blood samples at predose were col-
lected on days 8 and 22 of cycle 1; days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of 
cycle 2; and day 1 of all subsequent cycles. Sonidegib concen-
trations in plasma were measured using a validated liquid 
chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry method 
(7) with the 
lower limit of quantification of 25.4 pg/mL. Pharmacokinetic 
parameters were estimated for each patient using a non-com-
partmental method with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Phoenix WinNonlin</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Pharsight</rs>, Moun-
tain View, CA, USA) using a linear trapezoidal method for 
area under the concentration-time curve (AUC) calculation. 
Biomarker and antitumor evaluations. Normal skin samples 
were collected from all patients before sonidegib treatment, at 
the end of cycle 1, and within 14 days after the last treatment. 
Ribonucleic acid was extracted from tissue samples and ana-
lyzed by RT-PCR 
(6,13) to estimate GLI1 expression and Hh 
pathway activation status. 
Tumor response was evaluated by investigators' judgment 
on the results of computed tomography or MRI according to 
the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors version 1.0. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Patient demographics and clinical characteristics. Overall, 45 
patients were enrolled in this study; group 1 had 21 patients 
and group 2 had 24 patients. For patients in group 1, the most 
common primary site of cancer was rectum (three patients, 
14%); 12 patients were treated with sonidegib 400 mg q.d. and 
nine patients were treated with 600 mg q.d. Patients received 
the 400 mg dose and 600 mg sonidegib for a median (range) 
of 88 (66-97) and 86 (69-91) days, respectively. 
For patients in group 2, the most common primary site of 
cancer was colon (seven patients, 29%); 12 patients were trea-
ted with sonidegib 400 mg q.d. (median [range] days = 76 
[57-97]), eight patients were treated with 600 mg q.d. (median 
[range] days = 89 [35-93]), and four patients were treated 
with 800 mg q.d. (median [range] days = 74 [71-85]). How-
ever, two patients at 400 mg, two patients at 600 mg, and one 
patient at 800 mg were excluded from the dose-determining 
set because of early termination relating to withdrawal of con-
sent, disease progression, and serious AEs not related to soni-
degib. 
The most common histological type of tumor was adenocar-
cinoma, and the most common metastasis site was lung in both </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | October 2016 | vol. 107 | no. 10 | 1478 </p>

<p>Original Article 
Phase I study of sonidegib in Asian patients 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas </p>

<p>groups. Two MB patients were enrolled. The majority of 
patients had performance status of 0 or 1. Patient characteris-
tics are listed in Table 1. 
Safety findings. In group 1, a single DLT of creatine kinase 
(CK) elevation was observed at both 400 and 600 mg in cycle 
1. However, one additional patient at the 400 mg dose and 
four additional patients at the 600 mg dose experienced grade 
3 or 4 CK elevation after cycle 1 that was associated with 
muscle-related symptoms (Table 2); therefore, these events 
were considered as DLTs in deciding MTD. Hence, dose-esca-
lation in group 1 was stopped and RD was established at 
400 mg q.d. based on clinical judgment. In group 2, a single 
DLT was observed at the dose level of sonidegib 800 mg in 
cycle 1. The event was related to CK elevation. Similar to 
group 1, two patients receiving 400 mg, one patient receiving 
600 mg, and one additional patient receiving 800 mg experi-
enced grade 3 or 4 CK elevation after cycle 1 (Table 2). The 
MTD of sonidegib for group 2 was established at 600 mg q.d. 
using a Bayesian logistic regression model taking all grade 3 
or 4 blood CK elevation incidents during the study period into 
account. However, one patient at 600 mg experienced grade 2 
myalgia, muscle weakness, dysgeusia, and vomiting 4 days 
after discontinuation of 42-day sonidegib treatment. Based on 
the safety findings observed at 600 mg in group 1 and no </p>

<p>significant pharmacokinetic difference between 400 and 
600 mg in group 2 (Table 3), the RD was established at 
400 mg q.d. in group 2 as well. 
Overall, grade 3 or 4 CK elevations were observed 
between days 22 and 63 after sonidegib treatment. The maxi-
mum CK level of 40 400 IU/L was observed with myoglobin 
level of 5320 ng/mL in a patient receiving 600 mg. A grade 
3 CK elevation was observed even 7-14 days after the last 
treatment in two patients at 600 mg. Three patients at the 
400-mg dose interrupted sonidegib when grade 3 CK eleva-
tion was observed. On recovery of CK levels to normal, 
these patients were restarted with a 200 mg dose and CK re-
elevation was not observed. Eleven of 12 patients with grade 
3 or 4 CK elevation experienced muscle-related symptoms 
such as muscle spasms, muscle weakness, and myalgia, but 
these symptoms were also observed without high grade CK 
elevation. 
In both groups, most patients (86% [n = 18] in group 1 and 
75% [n = 18] in group 2) experienced at least one AE, which 
was suspected to be related to sonidegib. The most common 
drug-related AE in both groups was increase in CK levels 
(33% in group 1 vs 50% in group 2). Other drug-related AEs 
in group 1 and group 2 were myalgia (29% and 33%, respec-
tively), fatigue (19% and 33%, respectively), and abnormal 
hepatic function (24% and 29%, respectively). All drug-related 
AEs were reported more frequently at the highest doses of 
sonidegib compared to other lower doses except dysgeusia in 
group 2 (Tables 4,5). 
Overall, there were four patients with SAEs that led to drug 
discontinuation in each group. Out of these four patients in 
group 1, two experienced rhabdomyolysis (one of these 
patients had grade 2 hepatic function abnormality as well), and 
the other two had increase in CK. In group 2, three patients 
had increase in CK and one patient had vomiting, which led to 
the drug discontinuation. Almost all patients who experienced 
grade 3 or 4 CK elevation also showed high blood myoglobin 
value, but no patients experienced renal impairment or renal 
failure. Most cases worsened even after the interruption of 
sonidegib and took a month to recover. Other than these AEs, 
there were no clinically significant treatment-emergent AEs. 
No clinically significant changes in electrocardiogram parame-
ters were noted during the course of treatment, and no deaths 
were reported. 
Pharmacokinetics. The plasma concentration-time profiles 
and the pharmacokinetic parameters of sonidegib are shown in 
Figure 1 and Table 3, respectively, for groups 1 and 2. The 
maximal plasma concentration (C max ) was observed at approxi-
mately 2-4 h (T max ) after a single dose in the pharmacokinetic 
run-in period and repeated dosing in cycle 1 day 15. Exposure 
(C max and AUC) increased as the dose escalated in both 
groups. However, an under-proportional dose-exposure rela-
tionship was observed in group 2 with three dose levels. The </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline demographics and characteristics of patients with 
advanced solid tumors who participated in a phase I study of 
sonidegib </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics 
Group 1 (n = 21) 
Japanese </p>

<p>Group 2 (n = 24) 
Chinese/Taiwanese </p>

<p>Age, median years (range) 
62 (20-71) 
53 (31-69) 
Male sex, n (%) 
8 (38) 
13 (54) 
Weight, median kg (range) 
56 (42-77) 
54 (32-83) 
Body surface area, 
median m 
2 (range) † </p>

<p>1.6 (1.3-1.9) 
1.6 (1.2-2.1) </p>

<p>Primary site of cancer, n (%) 
Colon 
1 (5) 
7 (29) 
Rectum 
3 (14) 
4 (17) 
Pancreas 
1 (5) 
2 (8) 
Ovary 
2 (10) 
0 (0) 
Soft tissue 
2 (10) 
0 (0) 
Lung 
0 (0) 
2 (8) 
Thyroid 
0 (0) 
2 (8) 
WHO performance status, n (%) 
0 
7 (33) 
14 (58) 
1 
14 (67) 
8 (33) 
2 
0 (0) 
2 (8) </p>

<p> †Body surface area BSA (m 
2 ) = 234.94*(height [cm] </p>

<p>0.422 </p>

<p>)*(weight 
[kg] </p>

<p>0.515 </p>

<p>)/10 000 (Gehan and George) 
(14) . </p>

<p>Table 2. Frequency of grade 3 or 4 creatine kinase elevation during all study period in group 1 (Japanese) and group 2 (Chinese/Taiwanese) </p>

<p>Sonidegib 400 mg qd 
Sonidegib 600 mg qd 
Sonidegib 800 mg qd 
All patients </p>

<p>Group 1 (Japanese) 
N = 12 
N = 9 
N = 21 </p>

<p>Grade 3 /4 Creatine kinase elevation: n (%) 
2 (17) † 
5 (56) † 
7 (33) </p>

<p>Group 2 (Chinese/Taiwanese) 
N = 12 
N = 8 
N = 4 
N = 24 </p>

<p>Grade 3 /4 Creatine kinase elevation: n (%) 
2 (17) 
1 (13) 
2 (50) 
5 (21) </p>

<p>qd, Once daily </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>One patient at each dose had reported rhabdomyolysis, as presented in Table 4 </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | October 2016 | vol. 107 | no. 10 | 1479 
© 2016 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Original Article 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas 
Minami et al. </p>

<p>plasma concentration was detected even at 168 h after a single 
dose of sonidegib in both groups at every dose. It shows that 
the 7-day pharmacokinetics run-in phase was not enough to 
allow for accurate estimation of the half-life. 
After repeated dosing in group 1, exposure accumulation in 
cycle 1 day 15 was 4.9-and 4.6-fold at 400 and 600 mg, respec-
tively, as the AUC ratio. Accumulation in trough levels at 400 
and 600 mg doses was 12.4-and 14.3-fold in cycle 2 day 1, and 
19.6-and 19.9-fold in cycle 2 day 22, compared with 24-h post-
dose concentrations in the pharmacokinetic run-in period. In 
group 2, AUC accumulation at 400, 600, and 800 mg in cycle 
1 day 15 was approximately 4.3-, 4.2-, and 6.0-fold, respec-
tively. Although trough concentrations beyond cycle 2 day 1 
were only available at 400 and 600 mg, trough accumulation at 
the respective dose was 13.9-and 12.3-fold in cycle 2 day 1 and 
16.3-and 13.8-fold in cycle 2 day 22. Steady state was consid-
ered not achieved within cycle 1 in both groups. 
A large interindividual variability was observed (for exam-
ple, the percentage of coefficient of variation in AUC is 50% 
or more when n ≥ 3) in this study, and there was no obvious 
difference or trend in exposure (C max and AUC) of sonidegib 
between the two groups. 
In cycle 1 day 15, nine of 12 patients with grade 3 or 4 CK 
elevations showed a higher individual AUC compared to the 
geometric mean observed for their respective groups. Further-
more, two of nine patients who experienced grade 3 CK eleva-
tions after the last treatment showed smaller AUC compared 
to the other patients with or without CK elevation. The </p>

<p>relationship between exposure and CK elevation for this study 
was not fully clarified. 
Target inhibition and antitumor activity. Normal skin samples 
for paired analysis (both before sonidegib treatment and at the 
end of cycle 1) were available from 22 patients. Based on the 
RT-PCR results, it was observed that sonidegib treatment 
decreased GLI1 expression in normal skin samples of all 
except one patient. Four patients at 400 mg showed 32-88% 
inhibition in GLI1, and nine patients at 600 mg showed 
73-96% inhibition in group 1. Six patients at 400 mg showed 
6.8-95% inhibition in GLI1, and two patients at 600 mg 
showed 53-83% inhibition in group 2. Higher GLI1 inhibition 
was observed at 600 mg compared to that of 400 mg in group 
1. However, dose-dependency in group 2 was not observed 
due to the small number of samples and large individual 
variability. 
In group 1, stable disease (SD) was achieved in five patients 
(24%; 4 at the 400 mg and 1 at the 600 mg) including 1 MB 
patient, and progressive disease was reported in 15 patients 
(71%). Best overall response in group 2 was SD in 10 patients 
(42%; six at 400 mg, three at 600 mg, and one at 800 mg), 
and progressive disease was reported in nine patients (38%). 
Five patients at 400 mg (from either patient group) maintained 
their SD status for more than 100 days. Cancer types in these 
patients were soft tissue sarcoma, rectum carcinoid, lung sar-
coma, colon adenocarcinoma, and maxilla ameloblastoma. Nei-
ther complete response nor partial response was observed in 
either group 1 or group 2. </p>

<p>Table 3. Summary of pharmacokinetic parameters of sonidegib by patient group </p>

<p>Period 
Pharmacokinetic 
parameter </p>

<p>Group 1 
Group 2 </p>

<p>Sonidegib 
400 mg q.d. 
n = 12 
Geometric 
mean (% CV) 
range </p>

<p>Sonidegib 
600 mg q.d. 
n = 9 
Geometric 
mean (% CV) 
range </p>

<p>Sonidegib 
400 mg q.d. 
n = 12 
Geometric 
mean (% CV) 
range </p>

<p>Sonidegib 
600 mg q.d. 
n = 8 
Geometric 
mean (% CV) 
range </p>

<p>Sonidegib 
800 mg q.d. 
n = 4 
Geometric 
mean (% CV) 
range </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetic run-in 
C max , ng/mL 
n = 12 
227 (91) 
84-984 </p>

<p>n = 9 
400 (42) 
83-2620 </p>

<p>n = 12 
348 (77) 
87-840 </p>

<p>n = 8 
377 (86) 
92-1060 </p>

<p>n = 4 
420 (134) 
147-1010 
T max , h † 
n = 12 
3 
1-8 </p>

<p>n = 9 
2 
2-8 </p>

<p>n = 12 
3 
1-6 </p>

<p>n = 8 
3 
2-8 </p>

<p>n = 4 
2 
2-4 
AUC last , h*ng/mL 
n = 12 
5070 (85) 
1418-12 035 </p>

<p>n = 9 
7905 (104) 
2651-26 949 </p>

<p>n = 12 
7395 (86) 
1701-19 299 </p>

<p>n = 8 
8741 (70) 
2588-17 432 </p>

<p>n = 4 
9735 (164) 
2137-23 850 
AUC 0-24 , h*ng/mL 
n = 12 
2006 (90) 
535-4936 </p>

<p>n = 9 
3333 (123) 
820-12 218 </p>

<p>n = 12 
2889 (74) 
723-6262 </p>

<p>n = 8 
3423 (74) 
1180-7877 </p>

<p>n = 4 
3654 (156) 
843-9314 
Cycle 1, day 15 
C max , ng/mL 
n = 12 
645 (83) 
217-1890 </p>

<p>n = 8 
1007 (59) 
404-2300 </p>

<p>n = 9 
777 (48) 
429-1550 </p>

<p>n = 5 
778 (50) 
511-1690 </p>

<p>n = 2 
1230 (23) 
1050-1440 
T max , h † 
n = 12 
2 
1-8 </p>

<p>n = 8 
2 
2-8 </p>

<p>n = 9 
2 
0-8 </p>

<p>n = 5 
4 
1-24 </p>

<p>n = 2 
2 (0) 
2-2 
AUC last , h*ng/mL ‡ 
n = 12 
9903 (88) 
3029-24 086 </p>

<p>n = 8 
15 380 (66) 
6379-36 308 </p>

<p>n = 9 
12 324 (65) 
5782-30 159 </p>

<p>n = 5 
14 399 (51) 
9537-29 551 </p>

<p>n = 2 
21 873 (30) 
17 811-26 860 </p>

<p> †Values are median (range).  ‡The last pharmacokinetic sampling point in the pharmacokinetic run-in period and on cycle 1 day 15 was set as 
168 h and 24 h, respectively, in the protocol. Therefore, AUC last (the AUC from time zero to the last measurable concentration sampling time), on 
day 15 approximately corresponds to AUC 0-24 (the AUC from time zero to 24 h) on day 15. Patients with advanced solid tumors were from Japan 
(group 1) or from Hong Kong and Taiwan (group 2). C max , maximum concentration; q.d., once daily; T max , time of maximum concentration. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | October 2016 | vol. 107 | no. 10 | 1480 </p>

<p>Original Article 
Phase I study of sonidegib in Asian patients 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study was a phase I clinical study of sonidegib to 
determine MTD and RD in patients with advanced solid 
tumors, carried out in two groups of Asian patients. As there 
was one DLT at both 400 and 600 mg in the Japanese group 
and late-onset grade 3 or 4 increase in CK levels, which were 
clinically dose limiting in additional patients, the dose could 
not be escalated further. Taking into account of all these 
events, an RD of 400 mg q.d. was established for the Japanese 
patient group. In the Chinese/Taiwanese patients, 400 mg was 
also considered safe to use in future studies. 
Common AEs reported in this study were consistent with the 
AEs reported in previous studies with SMO inhibitors. 
(7) Drug-
related myalgia could be explained based on the mechanism of 
action of sonidegib. 
(15) As reported previously, sonidegib can 
induce muscle contraction and muscle fiber twitching in pri-
mary human muscle cells. Hence, elevation in CK level could </p>

<p>be attributed to skeletal muscle toxicity. 
(7,15) Interestingly, 
increased concentrations of CK were also reported in a patient 
treated with vismodegib. Muscle spasms are reported in 
approximately 70% of patients treated with vismodegib. 
(16) It 
is known that both vismodegib and sonidegib are canonical Hh 
signaling inhibitors. However, vismodegib also activates a 
non-canonical SMO/Ca 
2+ /AMP-activated protein kinase-
dependent signaling cascade leading to a Warburg-like cata-
bolic reprograming, which sonidegib does not, and as a result 
SMO-dependent Ca 
2+ induction does not induce metabolic 
rewiring. 
(15,17) Other commonly reported AEs with sonidegib, 
including dysgeusia (70%), weight loss (46%), alopecia (63%), 
and asthenia (36%), could be due to sonidegib's intervention 
in Hh signaling. </p>

<p>(15,18,19)   Two Japanese patients suffered from rhabdomyolysis in our 
study. No case of rhabdomyolysis identified by investigators 
was confirmed by the independent safety review committee, </p>

<p>Table 4. Most common drug-related adverse events (occurring in &gt;10% of patients, all grade 3 or 4 and muscle-related) in group 1 (Japanese) 
patients with advanced solid tumors treated with sonidegib </p>

<p>Total adverse events, n (%) </p>

<p>400 mg q.d. (n = 12) 
600 mg q.d. (n = 9) 
All patients (n = 21) </p>

<p>All grades 
Grade 3 
Grade 4 
All grades 
Grade 3 
Grade 4 
All grades 
Grade 3 
Grade 4 </p>

<p>Blood creatine kinase increased 
2 (17) 
1 (8) 
0 (0) 
5 (56) 
2 (22) 
2 (22) 
7 (33) 
3 (14) 
2 (10) 
Hepatic function abnormal 
2 (17) 
1 (8) 
0 (0) 
3 (33) 
1 (11) 
1 (11) 
5 (24) 
2 (10) 
1 (5) 
Rhabdomyolysis 
1 (8) 
0 (0) 
1 (8) 
1 (11) 
1 (11) 
0 (0) 
2 (10) 
1 (5) 
1 (5) 
Decreased level of consciousness 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (11) 
0 (0) 
1 (11) 
1 (5) 
0 (0) 
1 (5) 
Hyperglycemia 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (11) 
1 (11) 
0 (0) 
1 (5) 
1 (5) 
0 (0) 
Lymphopenia 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (11) 
1 (11) 
0 (0) 
1 (5) 
1 (5) 
0 (0) 
Muscle weakness 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (11) 
1 (11) 
0 (0) 
1 (5) 
1 (5) 
0 (0) 
Myoglobin blood increased 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (11) 
1 (11) 
0 (0) 
1 (5) 
1 (5) 
0 (0) 
Myalgia 
2 (17) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
4 (44) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
6 (28) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Alopecia 
2 (17) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (22) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
4 (19) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Fatigue 
2 (17) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (22) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
4 (19) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Dysgeusia 
1 (8) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (22) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 (14) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Nausea 
1 (8) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (22) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 (14) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Muscle spasms 
1 (8) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (11) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (10) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>q.d., once daily. </p>

<p>Table 5. Most common drug-related adverse events (occurring in &gt;10% of patients, all grade 3 or 4 and muscle-related) in group 2 (Chinese/ 
Taiwanese) patients with advanced solid tumors treated with sonidegib </p>

<p>Total adverse 
events, n (%) </p>

<p>400 mg q.d. (n = 12) 
600 mg q.d. (n = 8) 
800 mg q.d. (n = 4) 
All patients (n = 24) </p>

<p>All 
grades 
Grade 3 Grade 4 
All 
grades 
Grade 3 Grade 4 
All 
grades 
Grade 3 Grade 4 
All 
grades 
Grade 3 Grade 4 </p>

<p>Blood creatine kinase 
increased </p>

<p>6 (50) 
1 (8) 
1 (8) 
3 (38) 
0 (0) 
1 (13) 
3 (75) 
0 (0) 
2 (50) 
12 (50) 
1 (4) 
4 (17) </p>

<p>Fatigue 
4 (33) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (13) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 (75) 
2 (50) 
0 (0) 
8 (33) 
2 (8) 
0 (0) 
Myalgia 
2 (17) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 (38) 
1 (13) 
0 (0) 
3 (75) 
1 (25) 
0 (0) 
8 (33) 
2 (8) 
0 (0) 
Hepatic function abnormal 2 (17) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (25) 
1 (13) 
0 (0) 
3 (75) 
2 (50) 
0 (0) 
7 (29) 
3 (13) 
0 (0) 
Decreased appetite 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 (38) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (50) 
1 (25) 
0 (0) 
5 (21) 
1 (4) 
0 (0) 
Muscular weakness 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (13) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 (75) 
2 (50) 
0 (0) 
4 (17) 
2 (8) 
0 (0) 
Dysgeusia 
2 (17) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 (38) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (25) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
6 (25) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Nausea 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 (38) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (50) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
5 (21) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Vomiting 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (25) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (25) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 (13) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Diarrhea 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (13) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (25) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (8) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Dizziness 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (13) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (25) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (8) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Pyrexia 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (13) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (25) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (8) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>q.d., once daily. </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | October 2016 | vol. 107 | no. 10 | 1481 
© 2016 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Original Article 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas 
Minami et al. </p>

<p>who defined rhabdomyolysis as CK concentrations more than 
10 times higher than baseline plus a 1.5-fold increase in crea-
tinine concentration in serum from baseline. Rhabdomyolysis 
was also reported previously in three patients in the 
CLDE225X2101 study and six cases in the BOLT study. </p>

<p>(7,8) </p>

<p>Grade 3 or 4 aspartate aminotransferase elevation and/or grade 
3 alanine aminotransferase elevations coincided with grade 4 
CK elevation in some patients, which could be attributed to 
skeletal muscle toxicity in the absence of any gross abnormal-
ity in liver function. 
Increases in CK levels were reversible after drug discontinu-
ation. However, in most cases, CK continued to worsen after 
interruption of drug and required 1 month for recovery, which 
could be partly explained by the long half-life (t 1/2 ,~28 days) 
of this drug, as reported in non-Asian patients. The t 1/2 was 
not calculated in this study due to the limited sampling period 
of 7 days to have the precise estimates. Exposure accumulation 
was observed and steady state was not achieved within cycle 
1, as expected from the long t 1/2 . Taken together, both accu-
mulation and long t 1/2 could contribute to the dose-limiting 
CK elevation observed in cycle 2 and thereafter. Therefore, 
toxicities observed in cycle 2 were considered when dose esca-
lation and recommended dose were decided. 
No difference in the pharmacokinetic profile of sonidegib 
between Japanese and Chinese/Taiwanese patients was seen. 
Exposure increased in an under-proportional manner with 
increasing doses as observed in Europe and the USA patients 
(CLDE225X2101). The exposure in this study tended to be 
higher than that in patients from Europe and the USA. The 
AUC last values in cycle 1 day 15 at 400 mg, the major investi-
gated dose in this study, were 9903 h*ng/mL, 12 324 h*ng/ 
mL, and 8806 h*ng/mL in group 1, group 2, and non-Asian </p>

<p>patients, respectively. However, data at 400 mg for Euro-
pean/US patients was very limited. It is of note that ethnic-
ity and body size were not statistically significant covariates 
for oral clearance in the population pharmacokinetic analysis 
(data not shown). Therefore, the difference in tolerability 
between Asians and non-Asians may not be completely 
explained by sonidegib exposure. It is possible that the dif-
ferences in drug sensitivity among ethnicities have the same 
principle as the sensitivity for statin-induced rhabdomyolysis 
in Asian patients. 
(20) The possible mechanism of sonidegib-
induced CK elevation may be related to autophagy in mus-
cle tissue, as sonidegib can increase the level of micro-
tubule-associated protein 1 light chain 3. 
(21) Hence, it is 
plausible that some racial difference in molecular mechanism 
may exist. 
The recommended dose in this study was 400 mg, which 
was lower than the MTD 800 mg for European and the USA 
patients. However, safety results in the BOLT study with a 
larger sample size confirmed that the safety profile at 200 mg 
was clinically preferable to 800 mg. 
(8) No substantial ethnic 
difference in the pharmacokinetics and safety data was sug-
gested by this study. Recently, US FDA and European 
Medicines Agency have approved sonidegib 200 mg q.d. for 
the treatment of adult patients with locally advanced BCC 
that has recurred following surgery or radiation therapy, or 
those who are not candidates for surgery or radiation 
therapy. </p>

<p>(7,8) </p>

<p>Inhibition of GLI1 was confirmed in biopsies of normal skin. 
However, due to the small number of evaluable samples, large 
variability among patients, and no fresh tumor biopsy, it could 
not be determined whether GLI1 inhibition in normal skin 
could be used as a surrogate marker for antitumor effects in </p>

<p>(a) 
Group 1 </p>

<p>Group 1 </p>

<p>Group 2 </p>

<p>Group 2 </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>(d) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Plasma concentration-time profiles of sonidegib in two groups of patients with advanced solid tumor. Mean plasma concentrations of 
sonidegib in the pharmacokinetic run-in period (a) and at cycle 1 day 15 (b) in patients from Japan (group 1). Mean plasma concentrations of 
sonidegib in the pharmacokinetic run-in period (c) and at cycle 1 day 15 (d) in patients from Hong Kong and Taiwan (group 2). q.d., Once daily. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Cancer Sci | October 2016 | vol. 107 | no. 10 | 1482 </p>

<p>Original Article 
Phase I study of sonidegib in Asian patients 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas </p>

<p>these populations. No tumor responses were observed during 
this study because no target patients, such as patients with 
BCC, were enrolled. Regarding MB patients in this study, no 
activation of Hh pathway genes, which were considered to be 
related to efficacy, were observed retrospectively. </p>

<p>(6)   This is the first study to establish the safety of sonidegib in 
East Asian patient groups. In summary, sonidegib showed a 
similar safety profile in East Asian patients as that of non-
Asian patients. No new AEs were reported. The RD of sonide-
gib in East Asian patients (400 mg) was lower than the MTD 
in European/the USA patients (800 mg daily or 250 mg twice 
daily), suggesting a difference in tolerability between the two 
populations. If any signal of ethnic difference is observed, an 
ethnic sensitivity study or race-specific study is warranted to 
provide safety data. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The study was supported by Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation. We 
thank the investigators of the study. We thank Ambrin Fatima of 
Novartis Healthcare Pvt. Ltd. for providing medical editorial and writ-
ing support with this manuscript. </p>

<p>Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>H.M. received research funding from Novartis Pharma. Y.A. received 
speaker fees from Novartis Pharma and is currently conducting 
research sponsored by Novartis. B.B.Y.M. received consultancy fee 
and a research grant from Novartis AG. Y.F. Received research grants 
from Astra Zeneca, Elli Lilly, GlaxoSmithKline, Chugai, Eisai, and 
Merck Serono. K.F., K.I., T.T., and A.M. are employees of Novartis 
Pharma. The other authors have no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Cancer Sci | October 2016 | vol. 107 | no. 10 | 1483 
© 2016 The Authors. Cancer Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd 
on behalf of Japanese Cancer Association. </p>

<p>Original Article 
www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cas 
Minami et al. </p>

</text></tei>