<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5144905" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: We aimed to assess the effects of comorbidities on COPD costs and to investigate </p>

<p>the relationship between comorbidities and clinical variables. 
Patients and methods: All patients hospitalized with a diagnosis of COPD exacerbation </p>

<p>between January 1, 2014, and December 31, 2014, at all state hospitals of Aydın province, 
a city located in the western part of Turkey, were included in this study. The costs examined in 
the study pertained to medications, laboratory tests, hospital stays, and other treatment-related 
factors, such as consumption of materials, doctor visits, and consultation fees. 
Results: A total of 3,095 patients with 5,237 exacerbations (mean age, 71.9±10.5 years; </p>

<p>2,434 males and 661 females) were evaluated. For 880 of the patients (28.9%), or 3,852 of the 
exacerbations (73.1%), at least one comorbid disease was recorded. The mean cost of each exac-
erbation was $808.5±1,586, including $325.1±879.9 (40.7%) for hospital stays, $223.1±1,300.9 
(27.6%) for medications, $46.3±49.6 (0.9%) for laboratory expenditures, and $214±1,068 
(26.5%) for other treatment-related factors, such as consumption of materials, doctor visits, 
and consultation fees. The cost of each exacerbation was $1,014.9 in patients with at least one 
comorbidity, whereas it was $233.6 in patients without comorbidity (P,0.001). Age .65 years, 
female gender, hospitalization in an intensive care unit, invasive or noninvasive mechanical 
ventilation, and a long duration of hospitalization were all found to be significant factors in 
increasing total costs during the exacerbations requiring hospitalization (P,0.05 for all). 
Conclusion: Comorbidities have an important role in the total costs of acute exacerbations of </p>

<p>COPD. Strategies for the prevention, diagnosis, and effective management of comorbidities 
would decrease the overall financial burden associated with acute exacerbations of COPD. 
COPD, a common public health problem worldwide, is characterized by irreversible 
progressive airway obstruction and systemic inflammation as a result of exposure to 
smoking, noxious gases, and particles. 1 
According to the World Health Organization (WHO), COPD is the fourth most 
common cause of death and is estimated to be third by the year 2020. 2,3 In addition to 
its high mortality and morbidity rates, COPD is a very expensive disease and consti-
tutes a significant liability to a nation's health care costs. For example, the annual cost 
of treatment for a patient with COPD is $9,981 in the USA and $3,224 in the UK. 4 
Because of continued exposure to COPD risk factors and an aging population, the 
global burden of COPD is expected to increase further in the coming years. 
The main cost load of COPD consists of acute exacerbations, a finding that has 
been highlighted in studies conducted in Turkey. 5-7 On average, patients with COPD 
experience one to three exacerbations per year. These exacerbations comprise the </p>

<p>Correspondence: Yusuf aydemir 
Department of Chest Diseases, sakarya 
University Faculty of Medicine, hastane 
Caddesi, 54100 sakarya, Turkey 
Tel +0090 505 636 94 94 
email dryaydemir@yahoo.com </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of COPD 
2 December 2016 </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3024 </p>

<p>Deniz et al </p>

<p>main reason for emergency department treatment and 
hospitalization. Acute exacerbations adversely affect the 
prognosis of the disease and accelerate the process of severe 
respiratory failure. Also, exacerbations become more fre-
quent and more severe as the disease progresses. 8,9 In turn, 
severe COPD exacerbations requiring mechanical ventilation 
and intensive care trigger higher costs. 
Another important component of COPD-related costs is 
the disease's comorbidities. Multisystem involvement with 
significant extrapulmonary manifestations is associated with 
COPD, and patients frequently suffer from comorbidities 
such as cardiovascular disease, osteoporosis, depression, 
malnutrition, metabolic syndrome, diabetes, and lung cancer. 1 
These comorbidities have a major impact on the patient's 
quality of life and survival. Previous reports have shown 
that .60% of COPD patient deaths are caused by comorbidi-
ties rather than by COPD itself. 10,11 
Although the high costs associated with COPD and the 
disease's comorbidity rates are well known, 12,13 studies on the 
effects of comorbidities on the disease's costs are both limited 
and controversial. 14-17 However, the management of comor-
bidities and their prevention might provide some benefit in 
reducing the global cost load. Accordingly, in this study, we 
aimed to assess the effects of comorbidities on COPD costs 
and to investigate the relationship between comorbidities and 
clinical variables such as age, gender, and the requirement 
of intensive care or mechanical ventilation. </p>

<p>Patients and methods 
study design and population </p>

<p>This retrospective descriptive case-series study included all 
patients older than 40 years who were hospitalized with a 
diagnosis of COPD exacerbation between January 1, 2014, 
and December 31, 2014, at all state hospitals of Aydın prov-
ince, a city located on the Aegean Seacoast in the western 
part of Turkey and having a population of one million. In this 
study, COPD exacerbation was defined as an acute change in 
baseline dyspnea as well as cough and/or sputum production. 1 
Patients who were admitted to a hospital more than once 
were excluded. The study was approved by the Institutional 
Ethics Committee of Adnan Menderes University Faculty of 
Medicine (no 2015/617). The informed consent requirement 
was waived by the Institutional Ethics Committee due to the 
study's retrospective design. </p>

<p>study procedures and data collection </p>

<p>The data on demographics, diagnoses, comorbid diseases, 
treatment procedures, total costs and a breakdown of cost </p>

<p>per exacerbation, hospitalization duration, length of intensive 
care unit stay, and spirometric measures were obtained from 
the hospitals' databases. 
The costs examined in the study pertained to medications, 
laboratory tests, hospital stays, and other treatment-related 
factors such as consumption of materials, doctor visits, and 
consultation fees. Costs recorded as Turkish lira (TL) in the 
hospital data were converted into US dollars based on 2014 
average currency (1$ was equal to 2.24 TL in 2014 and to 
3.06 TL in 2016). </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>The study data were summarized by the descriptive statistics 
(mean, standard deviation, minimum, median, maximum, 
frequency, and percentage). The difference between two 
independent groups showing a nonnormal distribution was 
investigated using Mann-Whitney U test. The relation 
between categorical variables was tested either by the chi-
square test or by the Fisher's exact test. A linear regression 
analysis was performed to estimate the relation between the 
cost and duration of a hospitalization. The level of statisti-
cal significance was determined as 0.05. Analyses were 
performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">MedCalc</rs> statistical software program 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 12.7.7</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">MedCalc Software bvba</rs>, Ostend, Belgium; 
http://www.medcalc.org; 2013). </p>

<p>Results 
study patients </p>

<p>A total of 3,095 patients with 5,237 exacerbations (mean 
age, 71.9±10.5 years; 2,434 males and 661 females) were 
evaluated. The patients' mean forced expiratory volume per 
1 second (FEV 1 ) was 32%±4.8%. </p>

<p>Cost of COPD exacerbations </p>

<p>The mean cost of each exacerbation was $808.5±1,586 
including $325.1±879.9 (40.7%) for hospital stays, 
$223.1±1,300.9 (27.6%) for medications, $46.3±49.6 (0.9%) 
for laboratory expenditures, and $214±1,068 (26.5%) for 
other treatment-related factors, such as consumption of 
materials, doctor visits, and consultation fees. The portion 
of antibiotic expenditures included in the medication costs 
was $44.4±94.4 on average (Table 1). 
Eight hundred forty-one of the exacerbations required hos-
pitalization in intensive care units. For 303 of these attacks, inva-
sive mechanical ventilation was applied, whereas noninvasive 
mechanical ventilation was applied in 406 cases, and 130 cases 
were followed up solely by monitoring. The cost related to 
the exacerbations requiring stays in intensive care units was </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3025 </p>

<p>Clinical factors affecting the cost of COPD exacerbations </p>

<p>$1,978±2,459. The mean duration of hospitalization for all 
exacerbations was 8.1±6.3 days, whereas it was 10.4±8.9 days 
for those of patients hospitalized in intensive care units. 
Age .65 years, female gender, hospitalization in an 
intensive care unit, invasive or noninvasive mechanical 
ventilation, and a long duration of hospitalization were all 
found to be significant factors in increasing total costs dur-
ing the exacerbations requiring hospitalization (P,0.05 for 
all) (Table 2). The duration of hospitalization was positively 
correlated with all costs, including laboratory (r=0.220, 
P,0.001), medication (r=0.681, P,0.001), hospital stay 
(r=0.712, P,0.001), and total (r=0.660, P,0.001) costs. </p>

<p>Cost of comorbidities </p>

<p>For 880 of the patients (28.9%), or 3,852 of the exacerba-
tions (73.1%), at least one comorbid disease was recorded. 
The comorbidities constituted hypertension in 780 patients </p>

<p>(25.2%), congestive heart failure in 645 patients (20.8%), 
coronary artery disease in 637 patients (20.6%), diabetes 
mellitus in 628 patients (20.3%), anemia in 501 patients 
(16.2%), gastroesophageal reflux in 348 patients (11.2%), 
anxiety/depression in 467 patients (15.1%), arrhythmia 
in 213 patients (6.9%), lung cancer in 58 patients (1.9%), 
pulmonary thromboembolism in 44 patients (1.4%), chronic 
renal failure in 25 patients (0.8%), cachexia in 91 patients 
(2.9%), obesity in 88 patients (2.8%), and osteoporosis in 
211 patients (6.8%) (Figure 1). 
Total cost was significantly higher in patients with exacer-
bations accompanied by any comorbidity than in those having 
no comorbidity. Considering comorbid diseases, total cost 
was found to be statistically and significantly much higher 
in cases with pneumonia, diabetes mellitus, cardiac failure, 
hypertension, coronary artery disease, anemia, lung cancer, 
arrhythmia, anxiety/depression, and osteoporosis (Table 3). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>COPD is a disease that affects patients' quality of life due to its 
progressive and continuously symptomatic nature. Almost all 
patients have reduced physical activity, and they experience 
two or more symptoms every day. For this reason, patients 
with COPD must continuously use a high volume of medica-
tions, which produces a significant cost load. Although the 
possibility of reducing the cost of chronic medication is low, 
exacerbations might be reduced or prevented. Exacerbations </p>

<p>Table 1 The breakdown of the costs for COPD exacerbations </p>

<p>Variable 
Cost in $ (mean ± 
standard deviation) </p>

<p>Breakdown 
of cost (%) </p>

<p>Cost of hospital stay 
325.1±879.9 
40.7 
Cost of medication 
223.1±1,300.9 
27.6 
Cost of laboratory 
46.3±49.6 
0.9 
Other costs (consumption 
materials, doctor visits, 
and consultation fee) </p>

<p>214±1,068 
26.5 </p>

<p>Total cost 
808.5±1,586 
100 </p>

<p>Table 2 The relationship between demographic/clinical variables and the cost </p>

<p>Variable 
n 
Cost of laboratory ($) 
Cost of medication ($) 
Cost of hospital stay ($) 
Total cost ($) </p>

<p>age (years) </p>

<p>,65 
1,193 
44.4±52.4 
200.4±637.5 
293.5±754.9 
738.9±1,368 </p>

<p>$65 
4,044 
46.8±48.8 
229.9±1,439.7 
334.5±913.8 
829.1±1,644.7 
P-value 
0.004 
0.076 
,0.001 
0.003 
gender 
Female 
841 
58±60.8 
175.7±460.7 
399.1±1,019.1 
922.5±1,597.5 
Male 
4,396 
44.1±46.9 
232.2±1,405.4 
311±850.5 
786.8±1,583 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
Intensive care stay 
absent 
4,396 
39.6±40.7 
205.2±1,149.6 
200.3±494.6 
584.9±1,236.8 
Present 
841 
84.1±71 
316.6±1,910.5 
976.2±1,749.1 
1,976.2±2,465.1 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
Intubation 
absent 
4,932 
43.1±45.5 
205±1,095.3 
232.9±477.5 
656.1±1,232.6 
Present 
305 
97.5±78 
516.6±3,099.8 
1,816.1±2,697 
3,273.3±3,495.8 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
noninvasive mechanical 
ventilation 
absent 
4,831 
43.7±47.6 
215.8±1,339.7 
290.3±888.6 
730.7±1,562 
Present 
406 
76.9±61.6 
310.3±689 
739.5±642.6 
1,735.7±1,581 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3026 </p>

<p>Deniz et al </p>

<p>Figure 1 The prevalence of comorbidities. 
Abbreviations: Ca, cancer; CAD, coronary artery disease; CHF, congestive heart failure; CRF, chronic renal failure; DM, diabetes mellitus; GER, gastroesophageal reflux; 
PTe, pulmonary thromboembolism. </p>































































<p>
Table 3 Diseases concomitant to COPD exacerbations and their effects on the cost </p>

<p>Kind of comorbidity 
n 
Cost of laboratory ($) 
Cost of medication ($) 
Cost of hospital stay ($) 
Total cost ($) </p>

<p>Pneumonia 
absent 
4,297 
44.6±46.8 
206.5±1,151.3 
291.1±667.1 
726±1,281.3 
Present 
940 
53.7±60.4 
229.2±1,835.4 
480.5±1,501.6 
1,185.9±2,519 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
Diabetes 
absent 
4,182 
42.5±46 
182.6±1,134.8 
245.3±524 
630.2±1,114.5 
Present 
1,055 
61.1±59.1 
383.8±1,808.8 
641.5±1,623 
1,515.5±2,635.3 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
heart failure 
absent 
4,252 
40.7±42.9 
188.2±1,366.4 
222±63.1 
583.3±9,425.6 
Present 
985 
70.6±66.7 
374.3±955.9 
770.1±1,660.4 
1,780.8±2,894.2 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
hypertension 
absent 
4,040 
38.7±38.75 
164.7±1,351.7 
194.3±423.9 
502.2±750 
Present 
1,197 
72±69.8 
420.3±1,091.7 
766.5±1,591 
1,841±2,780.5 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
Coronary artery disease 
absent 
4,225 
40.6±40.8 
165.8±1,081.8 
211.3±544.9 
553.1±984.3 
Present 
1,012 
70.1±71.1 
462.7±1,951.1 
800.3±1,578.6 
1,875.1±2,751.3 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
anemia 
absent 
4,510 
40.8±40.9 
179.9±1,302.9 
213.7±699.3 
595.4±1,133 
Present 
727 
80.4±77.5 
489.2±1,258.8 
904.9±1,469.6 
2,131.2±2,852.4 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
Reflux 
absent 
4,608 
46.6±50.7 
225±1,375.5 
315.8±898.6 
795.1±1,622.9 
Present 
629 
44.2±41.2 
209.7±483.4 
393.2±728.7 
906.4±1,281.8 
P-value 
0.982 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
lung cancer 
absent 
5,143 
46.1±49.7 
213.1±1,078.6 
325±884.2 
806.5±1,589.7 
Present 
94 
54.6±47 
771.9±5,539.3 
331.3±629.2 
919.6±1,387.4 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3027 </p>

<p>Clinical factors affecting the cost of COPD exacerbations </p>

<p>constitute 50%-75% of the economic load of COPD because 
of extra emergency department applications and increased 
hospitalizations. 18 Studies on the causality between treating 
exacerbations and slowing down the progression of COPD 
have indicated that successful management of the exacer-
bations is the main approach for reducing the costs, both 
directly and also indirectly, by slowing the progression of 
the disease. 1,16 In this study, the total cost of hospitalization 
due to COPD exacerbations was found to be $808. Previous 
studies have reported a wide range of cost per hospitalization 
(between $612 and $9,545). 5-7,19-24 
In this study, while the cost of hospital stays composes the 
main portion of total costs (40.7%), other costs such as those 
for medication, consumption of materials, consultations, 
and doctor visits, plus laboratory expenditures, constitute 
a significant percentage of total costs. In previous studies, 
the main cost is associated with hospital stays, followed by 
laboratory expenditures and medication costs. 19,20 Therefore, 
a major reduction in COPD-related costs could be achieved 
by reducing the expenditures of staying in hospital. </p>

<p>Comorbidities in COPD </p>

<p>The main reason for the hospitalization of COPD patients is 
the presence of comorbidities with or without exacerbation: 
these patients have a higher prevalence of comorbid diseases 
compared to the general population. 12,13 Although the mecha-
nisms by which COPD-related comorbidities develop are still 
unclear, it has been suggested that systemic inflammation 
contributes to the disease process. However, the causes of 
comorbidities are more likely to be multifactorial (eg, inac-
tivity, poor diet, hypoxia, and inflammation). 1 Comorbidity 
existence is a critical factor associated with high mortality in 
COPD. 12,13 Diabetes, heart failure, renal failure, cancer, and 
neuropsychiatric diseases are common with aging and often 
occur together; 25,26 if any of these diseases exists, the possibil-
ity that others exist is higher in these individuals compared to 
healthy adults. 27 In a previous study, more than three comor-
bid disorders were observed in 46% of COPD patients. 28 In 
our study, two comorbid diseases were recorded in 28.9% of 
patients, the most common being hypertension, followed by 
other cardiovascular diseases, such as coronary artery disease </p>

<p>Table 3 (Continued) </p>

<p>Kind of comorbidity 
n 
Cost of laboratory ($) 
Cost of medication ($) 
Cost of hospital stay ($) 
Total cost ($) </p>

<p>Pulmonary thromboemboli 
absent 
5,158 
46.3±49.7 
219.6±1,289.6 
323±862.1 
803.6±1,556.2 
Present 
79 
44.1±44.3 
450.1±1,910.6 
462.1±1,687.8 
1,110.8±3,639 
P-value 
0.011 
0.006 
0.126 
0.028 
arrhythmia 
absent 
4,903 
45.7±48.6 
215.7±1,327.1 
311.1±883.5 
774.8±1,574.8 
Present 
333 
55.4±62.7 
332.8±821.3 
531.9±802.9 
1,306.9±1,671.7 
P-value 
0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
Malnutrition 
absent 
5,072 
46.3±49.7 
224.1±1,321 
324.2±85.4 
807±1,602.7 
Present 
165 
47.8±46.3 
194±305 
354±546.3 
858±952.1 
P-value 
0.495 
0.155 
0.001 
0.003 
Obesity 
absent 
5,089 
46±49.33 
220.5±1,313 
324.4±888.3 
804.6±1,594.3 
Present 
148 
54.4±58.9 
314.5±788.9 
349.1±84.6 
954.4±1,272.5 
P-value 
0.150 
0.005 
0.042 
0.014 
anxiety/depression 
absent 
4,173 
42.3±46.3 
201±1,162.8 
289.8±925 
729.6±1,655.7 
Present 
1,063 
61.8±58.5 
310±1,740 
463.9±658.9 
1,118.7±1,230.8 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
Osteoporosis 
absent 
4,952 
45.5±48.7 
222.8±1,334.7 
310.5±818.9 
784.5±1,548.1 
Present 
285 
59.5±61.4 
227.9±396.1 
578.4±1,589.5 
1,226.5±2,102.6 
P-value 
,0.001 
0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
Total comorbidities 
absent 
1,383 
27.5±22.94 
120±1,744.6 
79±101.2 
233.6±176.5 
Present 
3,852 
53±54.6 
260.1±1,097.1 
413.4±1,009.4 
1,014.9±1,801.9 
P-value 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 
,0.001 </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3028 </p>

<p>Deniz et al </p>

<p>and congestive heart failure, as well as diabetes mellitus. 
Similarly, in the literature, cerebrovascular disease, mainly 
hypertension, was reported to be the most common comor-
bidity in patients with COPD. 13,14,29 In a study by Miyazaki 
et al, 30 36% of patients with COPD had hypertension and 
32% had cardiovascular disease, while 25% had cancer, 17% 
had mental disorders, and 15% had diabetes mellitus. In this 
study, comorbid disease was observed in 808 patients; the 
most common comorbid disease was hypertension, followed 
by other cardiovascular diseases and diabetes, anemia, anxi-
ety/depression, and other disorders. </p>

<p>Cost of COPD exacerbations and 
comorbidities </p>

<p>In this study, the exacerbation-related costs for patients with 
at least one comorbidity totaled $2,273, whereas the costs for 
patients with COPD exacerbations but no comorbidity totaled 
$523. The presence of comorbidities significantly increased 
the total costs associated with COPD exacerbations. The costs 
of COPD exacerbation associated with pneumonia, diabetes 
mellitus, heart failure, hypertension, coronary artery disease, 
anemia, lung cancer, arrhythmia, and anxiety/depression 
were found to be significantly higher than those associated 
with COPD without comorbidities. Comorbidities most sig-
nificantly related to high costs were anemia, coronary artery 
disease, and hypertension, likely because they are the most 
common comorbid diseases. 
Previous studies have demonstrated a direct relation-
ship between the yearly costs of COPD and the number of 
comorbid diseases. 15,23,31 Perera et al 23 assessed the factors 
responsible for increasing costs for patients hospitalized due 
to exacerbation and reported a significant relation between 
increased costs and comorbidities, such as acute myocardial 
infarction, congestive heart failure, cerebrovascular disease, 
lung cancer, arrhythmia, pulmonary thromboembolism, 
and low body weight. COPD patients with comorbidi-
ties require hospitalization, which lead to increased costs. 
Moreover, ~50% of COPD patients use cardiovascular 
medications and, more frequently, analgesic, antibiotics, and 
psychotherapeutic drugs. 31 One study of COPD patients with 
comorbid diseases showed direct costs that were 4.7 times 
higher than those for COPD patients with no comorbidity. 14 
Similarly, our study found that the costs associated with 
comorbid diseases were 4.3 times higher. Pneumonia was 
found to be associated with both direct and indirect costs. 
Some studies have demonstrated that pneumonia increases 
total direct costs by 1.9-2.5 times for outpatients and by 
3.39-4.72 times for hospitalized patients. 15,32 In this study, </p>

<p>costs were 1.6 times higher in patients with pneumonia 
compared to those without pneumonia. 
Dalal et al 22 observed that yearly direct costs were 38% 
more in COPD patients with cardiovascular disease compared 
to patients with COPD only. Pasquale et al 16 investigated 
the yearly costs of COPD cases and noted that the existence 
of cardiovascular disease (1.69 times higher) and diabetes 
mellitus (1.46 times higher) was found to be associated 
with increased yearly costs for COPD patients. In our study, 
cardiovascular disease (3.4 times higher) and diabetes mel-
litus (2.4 times higher) were found to be related to increased 
costs. In a study performed by Halpern et al, 17 anemia 
increased costs for hospitalized patients by ~2.5 times. This 
ratio was 3.5 times in our study. In addition, in previous 
studies, hypertension, cor pulmonale, chronic renal failure, 
peptic ulcer, liver disease, and apnea were shown to increase 
the total cost of COPD. 6,7,33-35 </p>

<p>Other clinical factors affecting the cost 
of COPD </p>

<p>In this study, age .65 years, female gender, hospitalization 
in an intensive care unit, intubation, noninvasive mechanical 
ventilation, and a long duration of hospitalization were fac-
tors increasing costs for patients with COPD exacerbations 
who required hospitalization. The mean duration of hospi-
talization was 8.1 days in this study. In previous studies, the 
mean duration was 4.5-14.5 days. 5-7,19,22-24 A longer hospital 
duration is also associated with increased daily costs due 
to treatment-resistant, severe cases with many accompa-
nying comorbidities in addition to increased expenditures 
for hospital stays. The relationship between increased 
costs and a lengthy hospital stay has been demonstrated in 
many studies. 6,23,33 
In our study, the rate of exacerbations requiring hospi-
talization in intensive care units was 16% (n=841), and the 
mean hospitalization duration was 10.4 days. The mean cost 
of hospitalization in an intensive care unit was $1,977, which 
was 3.4 times higher compared to cases without intensive 
care unit hospitalization. Being followed by noninvasive 
mechanical ventilation or intubation was also found to be 
associated with increased costs. In cases who require hospi-
talization in intensive care units, the costs of laboratory tests 
and medications increase as hospitalization time is extended. 
Similar to our study, Dalal et al 22 reported that the duration of 
hospitalization was longer in terms of exacerbations requir-
ing hospitalization in intensive care units and the cost was 
nearly doubled for cases in which patients were hospitalized 
in intensive care units compared to those who did not require </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3029 </p>

<p>Clinical factors affecting the cost of COPD exacerbations </p>

<p>intensive care hospitalization. Stanford et al 36 found that 
costs were nearly six times higher, and Örnek et al 6 noted 
that costs were tripled for COPD patients hospitalized in 
intensive care units. </p>

<p>limitations </p>

<p>Although this study is valuable because it included a large 
number of patients and exacerbations, it had some limitations 
that need to be mentioned. First, the retrospective design may 
have led to data loss, which precludes a definitive conclu-
sion. Furthermore, our results reflect COPD-related costs in 
Turkey, which complicates the generalization of our data to 
other countries. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Comorbidities have an important role in the total costs of 
acute exacerbations of COPD. Strategies for the prevention, 
diagnosis, and effective management of comorbidities would 
decrease the overall financial burden associated with acute 
exacerbations of COPD. </p>

<p>Clinical implications </p>

<p>The costs of acute exacerbations of COPD are mainly 
associated with comorbidities. During routine follow-up, 
questioning the patient about, as well as managing the most 
common comorbidities, such as diabetes mellitus, hyperten-
sion, and arrhythmia might reduce the cost load. Furthermore, 
COPD patients have a sedentary lifestyle due to limitations 
of daily physical activities, which causes a tendency toward 
anxiety and depression. Thus, during routine visits, patients 
with advanced COPD should be evaluated with respect to 
their psychological mood and be provided with psychosocial 
support, pulmonary rehabilitation, and physical exercise 
programs. The implementation of these measures would 
decrease the cost load of COPD and increase the cost-
effectivity of managing the disease. Finally, the prevention 
of pneumonia through vaccination of COPD patients and 
avoiding the usage of unnecessary and high-dose inhaled 
steroids should also be considered in efforts to decrease the 
cost of COPD management. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>SD designed the study, collected the data, and prepared the 
article. AŞ and YA prepared the article, analyzed the data, and 
searched the literature. JÇE and MHÖ reviewed the article. 
All authors contributed toward data analysis, drafting and 
critically revising the paper and agree to be accountable for 
all aspects of the work. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>References </p>



<p>International Journal of COPD </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-chronic-obstructive-pulmonary-disease-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of COPD is an international, peer-reviewed 
journal of therapeutics and pharmacology focusing on concise rapid 
reporting of clinical studies and reviews in COPD. Special focus is given 
to the pathophysiological processes underlying the disease, intervention 
programs, patient focused education, and self management protocols. </p>

<p>This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine and CAS. The 
manuscript management system is completely online and includes a 
very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3030 </p>



</text></tei>