<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5066378" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background/Aims: Glypican-3 (GPC3) protein is highly expressed in hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) tissue. It has been 
suggested as a diagnostic biomarker, but its inconsistent performance means that it requires further assessment. We 
therefore investigated the diagnostic value of the plasma GPC3 level compared to the alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) level as a 
diagnostic biomarker of HCC. 
Methods: We enrolled 157 consecutive patients with newly diagnosed HCC and 156 patients with liver cirrhosis (LC) as 
the control group. GPC3 plasma levels were measured using two commercially available enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
assays (ELISAs, named as Assay 1 and 2), and AFP levels were measured using an enzyme-linked chemiluminescent 
immunoassay. The diagnostic accuracy was analyzed using the receiver operating characteristics (ROC) curve. 
Results: Plasma GPC3 levels in HCC patients were very low (0-3.09 ng/mL) in Assay 1, while only 3 of the 157 patients 
(1.9%) showed detectable GPC3 levels in Assay 2. The median GPC3 level was not significantly elevated in the HCC 
group (0.80 ng/mL) compared with the LC group (0.60 ng/mL). The area under the ROC curve (AUC) for GPC3 was 0.559 
in Assay 1. In contrast, the median AFP level was significantly higher in HCC (27.72 ng/mL) than in LC (4.74 ng/mL), 
with an AUC of 0.729. 
Conclusions: The plasma level of GPC3 is a poor diagnostic marker for HCC, being far inferior to AFP. The development of a 
consistent detection system for the blood level of GPC3 is warranted. (Clin Mol Hepatol 2016;22:359-365) 
Copyright © 2016 by The Korean Association for the Study of the Liver 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>360 </p>

<p>http://www.e-cmh.org </p>

<p>Clin Mol Hepatol 
Volume_22 Number_3 September 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2016.0033 </p>

<p>recommend AFP as a tumor marker for HCC with a cutoff value at 
200 ng/mL in addition to radiological examinations. 3 However, 
the current guidelines of the American Association for the Study 
of Liver Disease and the European Association for the Study of the 
Liver have excluded AFP based on its limited accuracy. 4 AFP has 
moderate sensitivity for HCC, but lacks specificity as it is elevated 
in benign hepatic condition including cirrhosis and hepatitis. 5 
Therefore, additional biomarkers that are HCC-specific and -sensi-
tive require investigation. 
The heparin sulfate proteoglycan glypican-3 (GPC3) is a mem-
ber of the glypican family and is bound to the membrane through 
a glycophosphatidylinositol (GPI) anchor. 6 It is highly expressed in 
HCC cells and promotes HCC proliferation through the canonical 
Wnt pathway, and therapeutic methods that target GPC3 are cur-
rently being investigated. 6-8 However, GPC3 elevation in the sera 
of HCC patients is less conclusive. Initial studies reported high 
sensitivity of GPC3 as a specific biomarker for HCC. 5,9 Nonethe-
less, subsequent studies have led to inconsistent results, question-
ing plasma GPC3's value as a diagnostic biomarker. 6 The aim of 
this study was to address this concern by assessing and compar-
ing the diagnostic accuracy of GPC3 and AFP plasma level in a 
South Korean HCC population. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>The study design was a cross sectional, retrospective, case-con-
trol study including 157 HCC patients and a control group of 156 
liver cirrhosis (LC) patients at the Seoul National University Bun-</p>

<p>dang Hospital (Seongnam, Republic of Korea) from August 2006 
through September 2013. This study was approved by the Seoul 
National University Bundang Hospital's Institutional Review Board 
(IRB, B-1307/210-006). Informed consent was confirmed by the 
IRB and received from all HCC patients. LC plasma samples were 
derived from repository samples, and thus informed consent was 
waived by the IRB. 
HCC was diagnosed by histological and imaging findings out-
lined by American Association for the Study of Liver Disease 
guidelines and staged by the Barcelona Clinic Liver Cancer (BCLC) 
system. Patients with double primary cancer in non-liver organs or 
those who underwent intent-to-cure treatment (resection, liver 
transplantation, radiofrequency ablation, transarterial chemoem-
bolization, or percutaneous ethanol injection) were excluded from 
this study. LC was diagnosed by histological examination or by 
one or more clinical findings of portal hypertension: 1) cirrhotic 
appearance of the liver with splenomegaly on imaging studies (ul-
trasonography, computed tomography or magnetic resonance im-
age), 2) thrombocytopenia (platelet &lt; 120,000/mm 3 ), 3) presence 
of esophagogastric varices on endoscopy, 4) presence of ascites, 
and 5) presence of portosystemic encephalopathy. LC patients for 
whom the presence of HCC was not evaluated within six months 
before enrollment were excluded. </p>

<p>Sample storage and measurement of AFP and GPC3 </p>

<p>Blood samples were collected from HCC patients before cura-
tive treatment and from LC patients at the time of clinic visit. Plas-
ma aliquots were stored at -70 o C until time of measurement. Plas-
ma AFP was measured using an automated enzyme-linked 
chemiluminescent immunoassay (ELICA). Plasma GPC3 levels </p>

<p>Table 1. Descriptions of Assay 1 and Assay 2 used to measure plasma GPC3 levels </p>

<p>Category 
Assay 1 
Assay 2 </p>

<p>Manufacturer 
USCN Life Science Inc. 
R&amp;D Systems, Inc. </p>

<p>Capture antibody 
Monoclonal mouse 
Monoclonal mouse </p>

<p>Detection antibody 
Polyclonal rabbit 
Polyclonal sheep </p>

<p>Plate 
Pre-coated with capture antibody 
Manual capture antibody coating </p>

<p>Incubation temperature 
37ºC 
Room temperature </p>

<p>Biotin binding protein 
Avidin 
Streptavidin </p>

<p>Wash 
Aspirate but no wash between adding 
sample and detecting antibody </p>

<p>Aspirate and wash between adding 
sample and detecting antibody </p>

<p>Detection range 
0.156 ng/mL -10 ng/mL 
0.312 ng/mL -20 ng/mL </p>

<p>Sample dilution factor 
1:1 
1:100 </p>

<p>ELISA, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. </p>



<p>Yejoo Jeon, et al. 
GPC3 by ELISA is inferior to AFP for HCC diagnosis </p>

<p>http://www.e-cmh.org 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2016.0033 </p>

<p>were assessed using two different commercially available enzyme-
linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kits named as Assay 1 and 2 
(Assay 1: USCN Life Science Inc., Wuhan, China and Assay 2: R&amp;D 
Systems, Inc., Minneapolis, MN, USA), which were compared in 
Table 1. Tests were performed in accordance to manufacturer's in-
structions and in duplicates by two experienced researchers (YSC 
and YJ). In Assay 2, a sample dilution of 1:1 did not yield results 
within the range studied. Sample dilutions (1:1, 1:10, 1:50, 1:100, 
1:500, and 1:1000) showed that 1:100 yielded consistent and 
peak GPC3 values. This dilution factor was therefore used for all </p>

<p>samples. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Pearson's χ 
2 (categorical variables), Student's independent t-test </p>

<p>(continuous parametric variables), and Mann-Whitney U test (con-
tinuous nonparametric variables) were used to compare HCC and 
LC groups. Significance was defined as P&lt;0.05. Receiver operat-
ing characteristic (ROC) curve and area under the curve (AUC) 
analyses were performed to compare diagnostic accuracies of </p>

<p>Table 2. Clinical characteristics of the study population </p>

<p>Total 
(N=313) </p>

<p>LC 
(N=156) </p>

<p>HCC 
(N=157) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age, year* 
58.8 (11.5) 
56.7 (10.8) 
60.8 (11.8) 
0.002 </p>

<p>Gender  † </p>

<p>Male 
217 (69.3) 
90 (57.7) 
127(80.9) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Female 
96 (30.7) 
66(42.3) 
30(19.1) </p>

<p>BMI, kg/m 2 * 
23.88 (4.12) 
23.92 (4.6) 
23.84 (3.6) 
0.860 </p>

<p>Etiology  † </p>

<p>Alcohol Consumption 
20 (6.4) 
3 (1.9) 
17 (10.8) </p>

<p>HBV 
222 (70.9) 
116(74.4) 
106 (67.5) </p>

<p>HCV 
54 (17.3) 
37 (23.7) 
17 (10.8) </p>

<p>Cryptogenic 
14 (4.5) 
0 (0.0) 
14 (8.9) </p>

<p>Others 
3 (0.9) 
0 (0.0) 
3 (1.9) </p>

<p>Child-Pugh class  † </p>

<p>A 
261(83.0) 
133(85.3) 
128 (81.5) 
0.516 </p>

<p>B 
45 (14.8) 
19 (12.2) 
26 (16.6) </p>

<p>C 
7 (2.3) 
4 (2.5) 
3 (1.9) </p>

<p>Underlying liver disease  † </p>

<p>Chronic hepatitis 
10 (3.2) 
0 (0.0) 
10 (6.4) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Liver cirrhosis 
293 (93.6) 
156 (100.0) 
137 (87.3) </p>

<p>Tumor characteristics  † </p>

<p>BCLC stage </p>

<p>0 
-
-
21 (13.4) </p>

<p>A 
-
-
56 (35.7) </p>

<p>B 
-
-
11(7.0) </p>

<p>C 
-
-
62(39.5) </p>

<p>D 
-
-
7 (4.5) </p>

<p>Diffuse type 
-
-
18(11.5) </p>

<p>With major PVI 
-
-
32 (20.4) </p>

<p>LC, liver cirrhosis; HCC, hepatocellular carcinoma; BMI, body mass index; HBV, hepatitis B virus; HCV, hepatitis C virus; BCLC, barcelona clinic liver cancer; PVI, 
portal vein invasion. 
*Mean (Standard Deviation). </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Number (Percentage). </p>



<p>http://www.e-cmh.org </p>

<p>Clin Mol Hepatol 
Volume_22 Number_3 September 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2016.0033 </p>

<p>GPC3 and AFP. The maximum sum of sensitivity and specificity on 
the ROC curve determined the GPC3 cut-off level. All statistical 
analyses were performed via <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> Statistics <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chi-
cago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Characteristics of HCC patients and control group of 
cirrhosis patients </p>

<p>The clinical characteristics of the study population (157 HCC 
and 156 LC) were summarized in Table 2. The HCC group had a 
higher proportion of males and was older than the LC control 
group. In both groups, hepatitis B virus (HBV) was the most com-
mon etiology (67.5% in HCC and 74.4% in LC). Among the HCC 
patients, 6.4% and 87.3% had underlying liver diseases of chronic 
hepatitis and liver cirrhosis, respectively. There were no significant 
differences in Child-Pugh class between the two groups. BCLC 
staging was 0 in 13.4%, A in 35.7%, B in 7.0%, C in 39.5% and 
D in 4.5% of the HCC patients. Major portal vein invasion was 
observed in 20.4% of the HCC patients. </p>

<p>Plasma levels of GPC3 and AFP in HCC and LC 
patients </p>

<p>The median and mean levels of GPC3 and AFP were summa-
rized in Table 3. 
In Assay 1, the median GPC3 value for HCC patients was 0.80 
ng/mL (range, 0.00 ng/mL to 3.09 ng/mL) for HCC patients, and 
for LC patients was 0.60 ng/mL (range, 0.07 ng/mL to 7.40 ng/ 
mL). These differences were not significant (P=0.255). 
In Assay 2, all but 3 HCC samples were "Out of Range". None 
of the LC samples reached concentrations within the range of the 
assay. Because of the lack of HCC patients with detectable GPC3 
levels, AUC analysis was not performed based on this data. Clini-
cal characteristics and GPC3 concentrations based on Assay 1 
and 2 of these samples were listed in Table 4. 
Median plasma AFP level was 27.72 ng/mL (range, 0.72 ng/mL 
to 42,000.0 ng/mL) in HCC patients and 4.74 ng/mL in LC patients 
(range, 1.08 ng/mL to 145.08 ng/mL), which showed significantly 
elevated levels in HCC patients compared to LC patients 
(P&lt;0.001). 
In addition, when comparing LC GPC3 and AFP median values 
to just that of early HCC patients (BCLC 0~B, n=88), again only 
AFP was significantly elevated in the latter (GPC3 0.65 ng/mL 
P=0.916, AFP=11.94 ng/mL P&lt;0.001; data not shown). </p>

<p>Table 3. Plasma GPC3 and AFP levels in HCC and LC patients </p>

<p>Total (N=313) 
LC (N=156) 
HCC (N=157) 
P-value </p>

<p>AFP level 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Median 
7.44 
4.74 
27.72 </p>

<p>Range 
0.72-42000 
1.08-145.08 
0.72-42000.00 </p>

<p>Mean 
1960.79 
9.90 
3899.26 </p>

<p>SD 
8026.26 
17.72 
11011.53 </p>

<p>GPC3 in Assay 1 
0.255 </p>

<p>Median 
0.65 
0.60 
0.80 </p>

<p>Range 
0-7.40 
0.07-7.40 
0-3.09 </p>

<p>Mean 
0.89 
0.86 
0.92 </p>

<p>SD 
0.78 
0.86 
0.69 </p>

<p>GPC3 in Assay 2 * </p>

<p>Median 
14.79 
All Results 
14.79 </p>

<p>Range 
10.59-83.16 
Out of 
10.59-83.16 </p>

<p>Mean 
36.18 
Range 
36.18 </p>

<p>SD 
40.74 
40.74 </p>

<p>All values are in ng/mL. 
GPC3, Glypican-3; AFP, Alpha-fetoprotein; HCC, Hepatocellular carcinoma; LC, Liver cirrhosis; SD, Standard deviation. 
*Only three HCC samples had detectable GPC3 values. </p>



<p>Yejoo Jeon, et al. 
GPC3 by ELISA is inferior to AFP for HCC diagnosis </p>

<p>http://www.e-cmh.org 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2016.0033 </p>

<p>Diagnostic Accuracy of GPC3 and AFP </p>

<p>Using the ROC curves (Fig. 1), AUCs were calculated to assess 
the diagnostic accuracy of plasma AFP and GPC3 for HCC. Based 
on maximum sum of sensitivity and specificity, a GPC3 cut-off of 
0.61 ng/mL was determined. At this cut-off, GPC3 had a sensitivi-</p>

<p>ty of 60% and a specificity of 52%. At a cut-off of 20 ng/mL, AFP 
had a sensitivity of a 55% and specificity 91%. The AUC was 
0.559 and 0.729 for GPC3 and AFP respectively, indicating AFP 
as a stronger diagnostic tool. Combining the two markers only 
provided a marginal change; GPC3 and AFP (at cut-offs of 0.61 
ng/mL and 20 ng/mL respectively) had an AUC of 0.744, sensitivi-
ty of 55%, and specificity of 91%. Furthermore, when comparing 
the LC group to the early HCC subgroup, at the same cut-offs, 
AFP (AUC=0.665) was a superior diagnostic biomarker compared 
to GPC3 (AUC= 0.527). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We set out to determine whether GPC3 could be useful as a di-
agnostic biomarker for HCC in comparison to the traditional AFP 
in an HBV endemic, South Korean background. While AFP levels 
were significantly elevated in HCC patients compared to LC pa-
tients, plasma GPC3 levels were either very low or undetectable. 
Our study reported comparable sensitivity, but much lower speci-
ficity and AUC values for GPC3 (52% and 0.559) compared to 
other studies (84% and 0.762). 10 The ROC determined cut-off val-
ue for GPC3 of 0.61 ng/mL was lower than most reported values, 
though it has been reported to range from 3.9 pg/mL to 300 ng/ 
mL. 10 Meanwhile, AFP sensitivity, specificity, and AUC were com-
parable to reported results. 10 Overall, the plasma level of GPC3 
was a poor diagnostic biomarker for HCC compared to AFP. 
Though we used 2 commercially available GPC3 assays, GPC3 
values detected by the two assays showed discrepancies. Assay 1 
resulted in lower GPC3 values in HCC patients than those report-
ed by previous studies, although some studies have reported simi-
larly low values. 11-14 In Assay 2, only 1.9% of the HCC patients had 
detectable values in this study. The technical differences between 
the two assays included sample dilution factor and washing 
method. These differences may have contributed to discrepancies 
between the two assays. </p>

<p>Since first reported to be present in the plasma of 53% HCC </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparison of clinical characteristics for three patients with detectable plasma GPC3 levels in both ELISA assays </p>

<p>Patient 
Age 
Etiology 
Cirrhosis 
BCLC 
stage 
Tumor number 
Max tumor 
size (cm) </p>

<p>GPC3 (ng/mL) </p>

<p>Assay 1 
Assay 2 </p>

<p>A 
66 
HBV 
Yes 
A 
1 
3.0 
0.18 
83.16 </p>

<p>B 
62 
HBV 
Yes 
A 
2 
1.7 
1.11 
14.79 </p>

<p>C 
51 
HBV 
Yes 
C 
1 
4.6 
0.78 
10.59 </p>

<p>ELISA, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; BCLC, barcelona clinic liver cancer; GPC3, glypican-3; HBV, hepatitis B virus. </p>

<p>Marker Cut-off 
(ng/mL) </p>

<p>Sn 
(%) </p>

<p>Sp 
(%) </p>

<p>PPV 
(%) </p>

<p>NPV 
(%) </p>

<p>AUG 
(CI 95%) </p>

<p>GPC3 
0.61 
60 
52 
56 
56 
0.559 
(0.495-0.623) </p>

<p>AFP 
20 
55 
91 
86 
67 
0.729 
(0.672-0.786) </p>

<p>GPC3+ 
AFP </p>

<p>0.61+ 
20 </p>

<p>55 
91 
86 
67 
0.744 
(0.689-0.799) </p>

<p>1-Specificity </p>

<p>GPC3+ AFP 
GPC3 
AFP 
Reference line </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 
0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1.0 </p>

<p>Figure 1. ROC curves of plasma GPC3 and AFP levels for HCC diagnosis. 
ROC curve of GPC3 (cut off level of 0.61 ng/mL), AFP (cut off level of 20 
ng/mL), combined GPC3 and AFP, and reference for hepatocellular carci-
noma diagnosis displayed with data summary. ROC, receiver operating 
characteristic; GPC3, glypican-3; AFP, alpha-fetoprotein; Sn, sensitivity; Sp, 
specificity; PPV, positive predictive value; NPV, negative predictive value; 
AUC, area under the curve; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>364 </p>

<p>http://www.e-cmh.org </p>

<p>Clin Mol Hepatol 
Volume_22 Number_3 September 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2016.0033 </p>

<p>patients but undetectable in healthy liver controls, GPC3 has 
been studied as a biomarker for HCC to replace or complement 
AFP. 5 However, subsequent studies have yielded inconsistent 
results as summarized in Table 5, showing inter-and intra-ELI-
SA variances. Differences in capture and detection antibodies 
could explain inter-method differences. 5,9,11-20 While Capurro et 
al. developed antibodies targeting the COOH-terminus for their 
ELISA, Hippo et al. used antibodies targeting the NH2-termi-
nus. 5,9 Though Capurro et al. and Hippo et al. reported similar-
ly elevated rates of GPC3 in HCC patients (53% and 51%, re-
spectively), their scales were completely different (0-2924 ng/ 
mL vs 0-~60 ng/mL). 5,9 
The nature of plasma GPC3 may impact ELISA utility. Plasma 
GPC3 can be produced when an extracellular lipase (Notum) 
cleaves the GPI anchor of membrane bound GPC3 or when se-
creted, possibly by endogenous Notum or GPI-phospholipase 
D, by the cell. 21 Various species of GPC3 may also be found, as 
Hippo et al. was able to detect a 50-kDa fragment produced 
by a cleavage site in the COOH-terminal in addition to the 
commonly detected glycanated GPC3. 22 Furthermore, plasma 
GPC3 competitively binds with several growth factors, which 
could interfere with antibody binding. 23 Given these possibili-
ties, it is clear that a uniform understanding of plasma GPC3 
has not been reached. There may be ways to circumvent these 
proposed obstacles. Comparison of cell lysate and supernatant </p>

<p>could help differentiate membrane bound and secreted GPC3; 
an antibody that targets the NH2 terminal may detect both the 
50kDa and glycanated forms of GPC3; and a dilution of the 
plasma could help prevent interference of antibody binding. 22 
Nonetheless, for plasma GPC3 to be a universal biomarker, the 
biochemistry behind plasma GPC3 concerning its origin as well 
as structure(s) must be elucidated. 
Finally, heterogeneity in HCC composition, ethnicity, etiology, 
and clinical manifestation may lead to variability. 8,24 Moreover, 
meta-studies point out methodological issues such as differ-
ences in inclusion and exclusion criteria or use of reference 
standard tests. 6,10 
The limitations of this study were that it was a single center, 
cross-sectional design without external validation samples, no 
assessment of concurrent GPC3 tissue expression, and usage 
of plasma samples. It also included only 2 commercially avail-
able ELISA. 
In conclusion, plasma GPC3 level measured by currently 
available 2 ELISA kits clearly failed to be a useful diagnostic 
biomarker for HCC compared to AFP. Persistent inconsistency 
in GPC3 values questions its utility. Future studies regarding 
the development of more reliable detection systems perhaps 
including blood GPC3 levels are warranted. </p>

<p>Table 5. Summary of reported studies measuring blood GPC3 levels in HCC patients using ELISA </p>

<p>Author (year) 
Country 
HCC cases GPC3 mean GPC3 median 
GPC3 range 
ELISA kit </p>

<p>Beale et al. (2008) 13 
UK 
50 
161.41 ng/mL 56.57 ng/mL 
BioMosaics limited 
(Burlington, VT, USA) </p>

<p>Yasuda et al. (2010) 11 
Japan 
200 
924.8 pg/mL </p>

<p>Lee et al. (2014) 15 
South Korea 
120 
75.8 ng/mL 
21.7-482.5 ng/mL Cusabio (Wuhan, China) </p>

<p>Wang et al (2013) 14 
China 
84 
4.55 ng/mL </p>

<p>Badr et al. (2014) 16 
Egypt 
30 
551.47 µg/mL 
USCN Life Science Inc. 
(Wuhan, China) </p>

<p>El Gawad et al. (2014) 17 
Egypt 
40 
7.7 ng/mL </p>

<p>El-Shenawy et al. (2012) 18 
Egypt 
85 
1,646.3 ng/mL </p>

<p>Ozkan et al. (2011) 12 
Turkey 
75 
3.9 pg/mL 
EIAab Science Co. 
(Wuhan China) </p>

<p>Capurro et al. (2003) 5 
Canada 
34 
0-2924 ng/mL 
Non-Commercial </p>

<p>Chen et al. (2013) 19 
China 
155 
99.94 ng/mL 15.11 ng/mL 0-2400.00 ng/mL </p>

<p>Hippo et al. (2004) 9 
Japan 
69 
4.84 ng/mL </p>

<p>Tangkijvanich et al. (2010) *20 
Thailand 
100 
46.3 ng/mL 
0-7826.6 ng/mL </p>

<p>*Reported to use same procedure as (5). 
GPC3, glypican-3; HCC, hepatocellular carcinoma; ELISA, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. </p>



<p>Yejoo Jeon, et al. 
GPC3 by ELISA is inferior to AFP for HCC diagnosis </p>

<p>http://www.e-cmh.org 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2016.0033 </p>

<p>Funding support </p>

<p>This study was supported by an intramural grant (No.02-2014-
024) from the Seoul National University Bundang Hospital. We 
are grateful to Hyein Mann of Seoul National University Bundang 
Hospital for her devotion to sample collection and storage. We 
are also grateful to Professor Emeritus J. Patrick Barron Ph.D. of 
Tokyo Medical University for his pro bono editing of this manu-
script. </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts to disclose. </p>



</text></tei>