<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5071723" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abbreviations: ADH4 alcohol dehydrogenase 4, CH cluster headache, SNP single nucleotide polymorphism </p>

<p>(Headache 2016;56:835-840) </p>

<p>ian studies, whereas rs1800759 located in the pro-
moter region of ADH4 could only be associated with 
CH in the smaller case-control study. 17 The 
rs1126671 SNP induces an amino acid change from 
isoleucine to valine in the corresponding protein. It 
is hypothesized that this amino acid change could 
produce altered enzyme functionality by possibly 
interfering with an adjoining phosphorylation site. 16 
For the ADH4 SNP rs1800759, it has been demon-
strated that promoter activity in hepatoma cells is 
drastically increased in the mutant allele and could 
therefore alter ADH4 p-subunit expression. 18 In 
expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) analysis 
using the Gtex Portal (http://www.gtexportal.org/ 
home/), both rs1126671 and rs1800759 have been 
found to have a significant correlation to the tran-
script levels of ADH4. In esophagus muscularis tis-
sue, the risk alleles (A for both SNPs) were 
associated with higher ADH4 expression levels, 
while in fibroblast cells the risk alleles were associ-
ated with lower ADH4 expression levels (data sour-
ces GTEx Analysis Release V6; dbGaP Accession 
phs000424.v6.p1). 
In other genetic association studies, opposing 
results have pointed to the presence of geographical 
and ethnical differences that underline the impor-
tance of validating findings in independent, homoge-
neous cohorts. Thus, we performed a replication 
study on the ADH4 SNPs rs1126671 and rs1800759 
in a large, Swedish case-control cohort in order to 
further investigate the possible contribution of 
ADH4 to CH. </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METHODS 
The study cohort consisted of 390 CH patients 
and 389 controls (Table 1). The study material was 
obtained after approval of the local ethics committee 
in Stockholm and informed consent of both patients 
and controls. CH patients were recruited from the 
neurology clinic at the Karolinska University Hospital, 
Stockholm, Sweden. The diagnosis of CH was based 
on the International Classification of Headache Disor-
ders (ICHD-III) criteria. 1 The majority of the controls 
(n 5 379) were anonymous healthy blood donors from 
the Stockholm area recruited when donating blood at 
the Karolinska University Hospital. This group </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: None. </p>

<p> 
May 2016 </p>

<p>represents a general healthy Swedish population, with 
no demographic information available except for gen-
der. Ten additional controls were neurologically 
healthy individuals recruited when visiting the neurol-
ogy clinic at the Karolinska University Hospital. Blood 
samples were collected from CH patients during 2000 
and 2014-2015 and from control individuals during 
2005 and 2015. DNA was extracted using standard 
protocols. The majority of patients (n 5 349) as well as 
10 neurologically healthy controls completed a ques-
tionnaire regarding clinical data, medication, and life-
style. Genotyping was performed by TaqManV R 
quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (7500 
fast system using standard cycling conditions, 
TaqMan V R genotyping master mix and Genotyping 
Assay C_11941799_30 for rs1126671 or C_8829281_20 
for rs1800759; Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA). </p>

<p>The data on the two ADH4 SNPs for all 779 individu-
als were exclusively collected for this replication study. 
Statistical Analyses.-Genotype association was 
evaluated with chi-square (v 2 ) test and allele associ-
ation was analyzed with Fisher's exact test using 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">v5.04</rs> (GraphPad Softwares Inc, 
La Jolla, CA, USA). Additionally, genotypic associ-
ation was tested for via logistic regression with sex 
as covariate using PLINK whole genome associa-
tion analysis toolset v1.07. 19 A possible difference 
in the proportions of subgroups of the patient 
cohort regarding alcohol as a trigger factor was 
tested for by using a two-tailed two-proportion Z-
test. All statistical tests were performed at signifi-
cance level 0.05. Haplotype analysis was performed 
in HaploView v.4.2. 20 For power analysis, the 
power and sample size software <rs type="software">PS</rs> v3.0 21 was used. 
With our sample size and a minor allele frequency 
of 0.33 (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/SNP/), 
we are able to detect true odds ratios (OR) for CH 
below 0.64 or above 1.51, respectively. The 
observed frequencies of controls were in agreement 
with the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium which was 
tested for using the web-based <rs type="software">Online Encyclopedia 
for Genetic Epidemiology studies software</rs>. 22 </p>

<p>RESULTS 
We analyzed the two ADH4 SNPs rs1126671 
and rs1800759 in a total of 390 CH patients and 389 
controls, and tested for association between each of 
the polymorphisms and CH. Comparing genotype as 
well as allele frequencies of CH patients with </p>

<p>Table 1.-Demographic and Clinical Characterization of CH 
Patients and Control Subjects </p>

<p>CH Cases 
Controls </p>

<p>Total number of subjects 
390 
389 
Men (%) 
270 (69.2) 
208 (53.5) 
Mean age 6 SD in years 
53.5 6 14.5 
NA 
Mean age of onset 6 SD in years 
31.2 6 13.5 
Patients with chronic CH (%) 
39 (10.0) 
Positive family history †-n (%) 
40/349 (11.5) 
Alcohol trigger: Yes-n (%) 
196/349 (56.2) </p>

<p>NA 5 not available; n 5 fraction of patients who filled out 
questionnaire; SD 5 standard deviation. 
 †At least one first-, second-, or third-degree relative with 
CH diagnosis. </p>

<p>Table 2.-Genotype and Allele Frequencies of Two ADH4 Polymorphisms in Control Subjects and CH Patients </p>

<p>SNP 
Genotype </p>

<p>Controls 
(%) </p>

<p>CH Cases 
(%) </p>

<p>v 2 
(df) 
P-Value Allele </p>

<p>Controls 
(%) </p>

<p>CH Cases 
(%) </p>

<p>OR 
(95% CI) 
P-Value </p>

<p>rs1126671 
GG 
173 (44.7) 176 (45.1) 0.418 
.811 
G 
520 (67.2) 531 (68.1) 
0.96 
.745 
GA 
174 (45.0) 179 (45.9) 
(2) 
A 
254 (32.8) 249 (31.9) (0.78-1.19) 
AA 
40 (10.3) 
35 (9.0) 
rs1800759 
CC 
123 (32.1) 128 (32.8) 0.047 
.977 
C 
442 (57.7) 453 (58.1) 
0.98 
.918 
CA 
196 (51.2) 197 (50.5) 
(2) 
A 
324 (42.3) 327 (41.9) (0.80-1.21) 
AA 
64 (16.7) 
65 (16.7) </p>

<p>ADH4 5 alcohol dehydrogenase 4; v 2 5 chi-square; df 5 degrees of freedom; OR 5 odds ratio; CI 5 confidence interval. Geno-
type association was evaluated with a v 2 test and allele association was analyzed with Fisher's exact test. </p>

<p>Headache </p>

<p>
controls for each SNP did not reveal a significant dif-
ference between the case and control group (Table 
2). Logistic regression with sex as a covariate was 
run in order to exclude any bias introduced by the 
skewed sex ratio in the patient group. We could not 
find a genotypic association with CH for either 
rs1126671 (P 5 .753) or rs1800759 (P 5 .985) when 
applying sex-corrected logistic regression. To take 
into account variability in subgroups of patients, we 
additionally performed a stratified analysis with 
respect to whether the patient regarded alcohol as a 
trigger factor or not (information retrieved from the 
questionnaire). When comparing controls with only 
patients that have reported alcohol to trigger an 
attack (n 5 196; 56.2% of patients who filled out the 
questionnaire), there were no significant differences 
in the genotypes of the two groups for either SNP 
(Table 3). Furthermore, we did the following obser-
vations from the patients who answered the ques-
tionnaire: 58.1% of the male (n 5 236) and 52.2% of 
the female (n 5 113) CH patients reported alcohol as 
a trigger factor. In addition, 55.7% of the episodic 
(n 5 309) and 60.5% of the chronic (n 5 38) CH 
patients experienced alcohol to elicit an attack. 
There were no significant differences in the propor-
tions of male and female, or episodic and chronic, 
patients who reported alcohol as a trigger factor 
(data available upon request). Finally, a haplotype 
analysis was carried out for the two ADH4 polymor-
phisms (Table 4); none of the haplotypes were asso-
ciated with CH. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
This is the largest study on ADH4 and CH 
reported so far. Genotypic and allelic analyses of 
the investigated ADH4 polymorphisms rs1126671 
and rs1800759 in CH patients suggest that there is 
no association between these genetic variants and 
CH in Sweden. The power of this study is much 
higher compared with previous studies where an 
association between ADH4 and CH has been 
found. 16,17 The two previously reported studies 
have been carried out on comparably small cohorts 
including only 110 and 54 CH patients, respectively. 
However, it is possible that population differences 
may lead to these varying results. Genotype and 
allele frequencies observed in controls from our 
study roughly correspond to the ones reported in </p>

<p>Table 3.-Genotype and Allele Frequencies of Two ADH4 Polymorphisms in Control Subjects and CH Patients That 
Reported Alcohol as an Attack Trigger </p>

<p>SNP 
Genotype </p>

<p>Controls 
(%) </p>

<p>CH alctrigger 
(%) </p>

<p>v 2 
(df) P-Value Allele </p>

<p>Controls 
(%) </p>

<p>CH alctrigger 
(%) </p>

<p>OR 
(95% CI) P-Value </p>

<p>rs1126671 
GG 
173 (44.7) 
85 (43.4) 
0.402 
.818 
G 
520 (67.2) 
263 (67.1) 
1.00 
1.000 
GA 
174 (45.0) 
93 (47.4) 
(2) 
A 
254 (32.8) 
129 (32.9) 
(0.78-1.09) 
AA 
40 (10.3) 
18 (9.2) 
rs1800759 
CC 
123 (32.1) 
60 (30.6) 
0.141 
.932 
C 
442 (57.7) 
223 (56.9) 
1.03 
.802 
CA 
196 (51.2) 
103 (52.6) 
(2) 
A 
324 (42.3) 
169 (43.1) 
(0.81-1.32) 
AA 
64 (16.7) 
33 (16.8) </p>

<p>ADH4 5 alcohol dehydrogenase 4; CH alctrigger 5 CH patients that report alcohol as a trigger factor; v 2 5 chi-square; df 5 
degrees of freedom; OR 5 odds ratio; CI, confidence interval. Genotype association was evaluated with a v 2 test and allele 
association was analyzed with Fisher's exact test. </p>

<p>Table 4.-Haplotype Analysis for Two ADH4 
Polymorphisms in Control Subjects and CH Patients </p>

<p>Haplotype </p>

<p>Controls 
(%) </p>

<p>CH Cases 
(%) </p>

<p>v 2 
(df 5 1) 
P-Value </p>

<p>G-C † 
435 (57.0) 
454 (57.9) 
0.117 
.732 
A-A 
244 (32.0) 
250 (31.5) 
0.042 
.838 
G-A 
79 (10.4) 
80 (10.3) 
0.005 
.943 
A-C 
4 (0.6) 
2 (0.3) 
0.635 
.426 </p>

<p>v 2 5 chi-square; df 5 degrees of freedom. 
 †Reference haplotype (G-C) corresponds to wild-type allele 
of each ADH4 single nucleotide polymorphism where 
rs1126671 is in position 1 and rs1800759 in position 2. </p>

<p> 
May 2016 </p>

<p>the two Italian studies. Yet, for rs1800759 the 
mutant allele seems to be less common in the Ital-
ian cohorts (31.0%-33.7%) compared with our 
Swedish cohort (42.3%). From our questionnaire 
data, 56.2% of the patients reported that alcohol 
may trigger an attack which corresponds to what 
other groups have reported (52%-63%). 7-9 When 
performing a statistical analysis for control individ-
uals and CH patients reporting alcohol as a trigger 
factor, there were no significant differences in the 
genotypes of the two groups for either SNP. A 
comparison between the haplotype analysis from 
one of the Italian studies 16 and our Swedish analy-
sis emphasizes the deviation in haplotype frequen-
cies among these two populations. For example, the 
diplotype A-C, corresponding to the mutated allele 
of rs1126671 and the wild-type allele of rs1800759, 
is very rare in our Swedish material (0.6%), 
whereas in the Italian cohort (27.9%) it is much 
more common. 
In conclusion, our data suggest that the SNPs 
rs1126671 and rs1800759 in the ADH4 gene are not 
genetic risk factors for CH in the Swedish popula-
tion. Although we did not find a significant associa-
tion with CH in our Swedish case-control material, 
we could not exclude ADH4 as a candidate gene 
for CH. More studies on additional ADH4 SNPs as 
well as novel candidate genes will be needed to 
answer the question why and how alcohol may pre-
cipitate attacks during a bout in more than half of 
the patients with CH. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments: We thank Fengqing Xiang for </p>

<p>excellent technical assistance and Ann-Christin Karls-</p>

<p>son for help with recruitment of patients. This work 
was supported by the Swedish Brain Foundation, </p>

<p>Swedish Research Foundation, A ˚ ke Wibergs Stiftelse, </p>

<p>Swedish Brain Power, Svenska Migr€ ans€ allskapet, and </p>

<p>Karolinska Institutet Research funds. </p>

<p>STATEMENT OF AUTHORSHIP </p>

<p>Category 1 
(a) Conception and Design 
Carmen Fourier, Caroline Ran, Andrea Car-
mine Belin </p>

<p>(b) Acquisition of Data 
Carmen Fourier, Anna Steinberg, Christina 
Sj€ ostrand, Elisabet Waldenlind 
(c) Analysis and Interpretation of Data 
Carmen Fourier, Caroline Ran, Andrea Car-
mine Belin </p>

<p>Category 2 
(a) Drafting the Manuscript 
Carmen Fourier, Andrea Carmine Belin 
(b) Revising It for Intellectual Content 
Carmen Fourier, Caroline Ran, Anna Stein-
berg, Christina Sj€ ostrand, Elisabet 
Waldenlind, Andrea Carmine Belin </p>

<p>Category 3 
(a) Final Approval of the Completed Manuscript 
Carmen Fourier, Caroline Ran, Anna Stein-
berg, Christina Sj€ ostrand, Elisabet Waldenlind, 
Andrea Carmine Belin </p>



<p>Headache </p>



<p>
 
May 2016 </p>

</text></tei>