<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5383462" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Purpose: Pupillary dilatation with three types of eye drops is used regularly in the clinic; how-
ever, a mixture of these drops in a single bottle may be more beneficial in reducing workloads 
and resources. This study compared the efficacy in pupillary dilatation between two protocols 
of dilating drop instillation. 
Methods: This prospective, randomized, comparative study included 30 eligible Thai patients. 
The patients randomly received preoperative pupillary dilatations by either the conventional 
protocol (1% tropicamide (T), 10% phenylephrine (P) and 0.1% diclofenac (D) in three separate 
bottles) or the fixed combination (TPD) protocol which had the three types of eye drops mixed 
in a single bottle in a ratio of 4:3:3. The chi-square test and independent t-test were used to 
analyze the data. 
Results: The conventional protocol group and TPD protocol group each had 15 patients. Sixty 
minutes after the initial instillation, all patients in the TPD protocol and 13 patients (86.7%) in 
conventional protocol achieved at least 6 mm in the shortest diameter. The mydriatic rate 
between protocols showed no difference. In patients who received the TPD protocol, the 
systemic effects on the mean arterial blood pressure and pulse rate decreased over time. 
Conclusion: The mixture of tropicamide, phenylephrine and diclofenac had a comparable effi-
cacy for a pupillary dilatation to the conventional dilating drops in separate bottles. The 
systemic complications on blood pressure and arterial pulse of the TPD mixture were less than 
the conventional protocol. 
Trial registration: TCTR20130325001. 
Eficacia de la mezcla de gotas oculares para la dilatación de la pupila: estudio 
aleatorizado y comparativo </p>

<p>Resumen 
Objetivo: La dilatación de la pupila con tres tipos de gotas oculares se utiliza normalmente en 
la práctica clínica; sin embargo, la mezcla de dichas gotas en un único envase puede resultar 
más beneficiosa a la hora de reducir las cargas de trabajo y los recursos. Este estudio comparó 
la eficacia entre dos protocolos de dilatación de pupilas. 
Métodos: Este estudio prospectivo, aleatorizado y comparativo incluyó a 30 pacientes tai-
landeses elegibles. A dichos pacientes se les dilató aleatoria y preoperatoriamente la pupila 
utilizando el protocolo convencional (1% tropicamida (T), 10% fenilefrina (P) y 0,1% diclofenaco 
(D) en tres envases separados), o el protocolo de combinación fija (TPD), que contenía los tres 
tipos de gotas oculares mezclados en un único envase, a un ratio de 4:3:3. Se utilizaron las 
pruebas de 
2 y la prueba independiente t para analizar los datos. 
Resultados: Tanto el grupo de protocolo convencional como el grupo TPD incluyeron a 15 
pacientes. A los sesenta minutos de la instilación inicial, todos los pacientes del protocolo TPD 
y 13 pacientes (86,7%) del protocolo convencional lograron un mínimo de 6 mm en el diámetro 
menor. La tasa midriática entre ambos protocolos no reflejó diferencia alguna. En los pacientes 
del protocolo TPD, los efectos sistémicos sobre la presión sanguínea media y el índice de pulso 
disminuyeron con el tiempo. 
Conclusión: La mezcla de tropicamida, fenilefrina y diclofenaco mostró una eficacia compa-
rable a la de las gotas para dilatación de pupilas suministradas en envases separados. Las 
complicaciones sistémicas sobre la presión sanguínea y la presión arterial de la mezcla de TPD 
fueron menores a las del protocolo convencional. 
Registro del ensayo: TCTR20130325001. 
Pupillary dilatation is necessary for a fundus examina-
tion and ophthalmic procedures. The mydriatic agents 
that are generally available in the eye clinic are tropi-
camide and phenylephrine. For an intraocular examination 
or operation, a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug is 
additionally required to prolong the mydriatic effect and 
lessen post-operative inflammation. 
1,2 The conventional for-
mula of pre-operative pupillary dilatation commonly used 
in the hospital is 1% tropicamide, 10% phenylephrine, and 
0.1% diclofenac in separate bottles. Each eye-drop bottle 
contains preservatives to inhibit microbial contamination. 
However, these preservatives have been linked to unwanted 
ocular surface side effects, such as stinging, redness and 
corneal punctate epithelial erosion. A combination of pre-
operative eye drops in one bottle may not only reduce the 
frequency of multiple eye drop administrations but may 
also reduce the ocular and systemic complications. 
3---5 There 
were some reports on the efficacy and safety of a combi-
nation of tropicamide and phenylephrine, 
4---6 but there is no 
report on a combination of tropicamide, phenylephrine and 
diclofenac. 
The objective of this study is to compare the mydriatic 
efficacy of a mixture of tropicamide, phenylephrine and 
diclofenac in a single eye-drop bottle to the conventional </p>

<p>practice of applying the eye drops from separate 
bottles. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria </p>

<p>This randomized prospective study was performed in accor-
dance with the declaration of Helsinki and was approved 
by the Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Medicine, Prince 
of Songkla University, Thailand (EC 56-153-02-1-2). We 
followed our institution protocols regarding patient data 
protection. Written informed consents were obtained from 
30 consecutive, eligible patients before the study began. 
The inclusion criteria were patients of 18 years old or older 
and scheduled for an operation at Songklanagarind Hospi-
tal, Prince of Songkla University, Thailand from April to July 
2013. The pre-operative fasting plasma glucose of all dia-
betic patients was less than 200 mg/dl. The resting systolic 
pressure was ≤160 mmHg and the resting diastolic pressure 
was ≤90 mmHg. </p>

<p>Exclusion criteria </p>

<p>Patients with a risk of angle-closure, uncontrolled blood 
pressure, pregnancy, iris or pupil abnormality, or a history </p>

<p>Efficacy of an eye drop mixture for pupillary dilatation </p>



<p>of allergic reactions to any of the investigating drugs were 
excluded from the study. </p>

<p>Sample size of patients </p>

<p>The sample size of 30 patients was calculated from 
the formula n &gt; 2 × (Z˛/ 2 × /d 1 ) 
2 , where Z˛= 1.96, 
(sigma) = 0.6, d 1 (delta) = 8.0---7.0 mm (mean = 8.0 mm, lower 
limit = 7.0 mm). The calculated number of recruited patients 
was at least 14 for each group with an anticipated 20% drop-
out allowance. </p>

<p>Dilating eye drops </p>

<p>The eye drops for the conventional protocol included three 
commercial preparations: 1% tropicamide (Mydriacyl 
® , 
Alcon-Couvreur, Puurs, Belgium), 10% phenylephrine 
(Phenylephrine HCL 
® , Silom Medical Co., Ltd, Thailand) 
and 0.1% diclofenac (Voltaren Ophtha Oftalmico 
® , Novartis 
PharmaAG, Basel, Switzerland) in separate bottles. The 
mixture of the fixed combination protocol was a combina-
tion of those commercial preparations in a ratio of 4:3:3 
that resulted in a final concentration of 0.4% tropicamide 
(T), 3% phenylephrine (P) and 0.03% diclofenac (D). This 
reduced concentration mixture (TPD) was labeled for 
the TPD protocol. A pharmacist (PA) of the hospital was 
responsible for the preparation of this TPD mixture. The 
mixture was prepared from commercially available eye 
drops instead of using the primary preservative-free phar-
maceutical products. This mixture was easily prepared in 
the office and dispensed to several units. The precipitation 
of tropicamide, which may occur when mixed with phenyle-
phrine, was less likely to occur at a concentration less than 
0.5%. 
6 The fixed combination of these three medications 
was chemically stable. </p>

<p>Study protocols </p>

<p>Eligible patients were randomized into two groups and 
received either a conventional or TPD formula for pupillary 
dilatation. Patients in the conventional protocol received 
eye drops every 5 min (Table 1). Patients in the TPD pro-
tocol received the TPD mixture every 15 min. Other eye 
drops, such as topical anesthetics, were not allowed before 
the study. The measurements of pupillary diameters, pulse 
and blood pressure were taken at baseline, 10 min, 25 min 
and 60 min after the first eye drop instillation of each pro-
tocol that was administered. The pupillary diameter was 
measured in both horizontal and vertical dimensions by an 
infrared pupillometer (Colvard 
® , OASIS Medical Inc., CA, 
USA) and was read by only one investigator (SS). The average 
of these two values was recorded for the analysis. The sitting 
arterial blood pressure and pulse were measured by an auto-
matic sphygmomanometer (Spirit 
® , Spirit Medical Co., Ltd., 
Taiwan, ROC). The target pupillary size was at least 6 mm in 
the shortest dimension within 60 min. With a pupillary size 
of at least 6 mm in diameter, the fundus examination along 
with most intraocular operations achieved a sufficient view 
of the lens, retina and vitreous. </p>

<p>Table 1 Protocols of eye drop administration. 
Formula </p>

<p>Measurement 
0 min </p>

<p>5 min 
10 min Measurement 
15 min 20 min 25 min Measurement </p>

<p>30 min 35 min 40 min 45 min 60 min </p>

<p>Conventional 
protocol </p>

<p>BP, 
P, pupil </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>BP, 
P, pupil </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>BP, 
P, pupil </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>BP, 
P, pupil </p>

<p>TPD 
protocol </p>

<p>TPD </p>

<p>---</p>

<p>---</p>

<p>TPD </p>

<p>---</p>

<p>---</p>

<p>TPD </p>

<p>---</p>

<p>---</p>

<p>TPD </p>

<p>BP, blood pressure; P, arterial pulse; pupil, pupil diameter; D, 0.1% diclofenac; T, 1% tropicamide; P, 10% phenylephrine; TPD, Mixture consisting of 0.4% tropicamide (T); 3% phenylephrine 
(P) 
and 0.03% diclofenac (D). </p>



<p>P. Bhurayanontachai et al. </p>

<p>Table 2 Baseline demographic data. </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Conventional (n = 15) 
TPD (n = 15) 
p value </p>

<p>Gender, n (%) 
Male 
7 (46.7) 
9 (60.0) 
0.714 
Female 
8 (53.3) 
6 (40.0) </p>

<p>Age (years, mean ± SD) 
61.53 ± 16.95 
64.27 ± 11.77 
0.612 
Underlying diseases, n (%) 
Absence 
6 (40.0) 
9 (60.0) 
0.465 
Presence 
9 (60.0) 
6 (40.0) </p>

<p>Studied eye, n (%) 
Right 
8 (53.3) 
8 (53.3) 
1.000 
Left 
7 (46.7) 
7 (46.7) </p>

<p>Lens status, n (%) 
Phakic 
14 (93.3) 
13 (86.7) 
0.595 
Pseudophakic 
0 (0) 
1 (6.7) 
Aphakic 
1 (6.7) 
1 (6.7) </p>

<p>Previous ocular operation, n (%) 
Never 
8 (53.3) 
6 (40.0) 
0.714 
Presence 
7 (46.7) 
9 (60.0) </p>

<p>The primary outcome was a difference of the mean 
pupillary diameters at 60 min between the two protocols. 
The secondary outcomes were changes in the mean arte-
rial blood pressure (MAP) and arterial pulse. A formula 
for the MAP calculation was [(2 × diastolic value) + systolic 
value]/3. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>A comparative analysis of continuous data was performed by 
an independent t-test. A comparative analysis of categorical 
data was performed by a Chi-square test. <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 16.0</rs> 
was used for these analyses. A p-value of 0.05 or less was 
considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Patient demographic data </p>

<p>Thirty patients (16 male, 14 female) were enrolled in the 
study and were randomized to receive the conventional or 
the TPD protocol. The patients' ages ranged from 23 to 83 
years. Underlying diseases such as diabetes mellitus (DM), 
hypertension (HT) and dyslipidemia were reported in 60% of 
patients in the conventional group and in 40% of patients 
in the TPD group. Three patients (20%) in each group had 
diabetes mellitus. Eight patients (53.3%) in the conventional 
group and 5 patients (33.3%) in the TPD group had hyperten-
sion. Two patients (13.3%) in each group had dyslipidemia. 
However, none of these underlying diseases were statis-
tically different between the groups (p = 0.465 for overall 
conditions, p = 1.00 for DM, p = 0.46 for HT, and p = 1.00 for 
dyslipidemia). Other baseline characteristics of the patients 
are shown in Table 2. There were no differences in the basic 
characteristics of the patients between the protocols. </p>

<p>Primary outcome </p>

<p>At baseline, the mean pupillary size of the patients in 
the TPD group was slightly larger than the conventional 
group. However, the average difference in the final pupil-
lary size from baseline in both groups was equal. The 
pupil diameter increased by 4.12 ± 1.06 mm in the TPD 
group and by 4.10 ± 0.80 mm in the conventional group 
(Table 3). The average rate of mydriasis in the TPD group 
was 0.0687 mm/min and 0.0683 mm/min in the conven-
tional group. There was no statistical difference of mydriatic 
rates between the two protocols (Fig. 1). All patients 
in the TPD group and 13 patients (86.7%) in the con-
ventional group achieved their target pupillary size at 
60 min. Changes in the pupil diameter from baseline were 
not significantly different between protocols (Table 3). 
These changes also showed no differences between nor-
mal patients and patients with underlying diseases at every 
time point in the subgroup analyses of both protocols 
(Table 4). </p>

<p>Secondary outcome </p>

<p>The changes in MAP of the patients at each time point 
after initiating the dilating drops were not significantly 
different between the protocols. However, the changes 
of arterial pulse from the baseline were strikingly differ-
ent between the two protocols. While the mean arterial 
pulse of the patients who received the conventional pro-
tocol increased over time, the mean arterial pulse of the 
patients who were administered the TPD protocol decreased 
over time (p &lt; 0.005). Although the change in the MAP from 
baseline was not significantly different between the proto-
cols, the values showed a tendency to decrease over time 
(Table 3). </p>

<p>Efficacy of an eye drop mixture for pupillary dilatation </p>



<p>Table 3 Pupillary diameter, pulse and mean arterial blood pressure changes over time. </p>

<p>Variable 
Conventional (n = 15) 
TPD (n = 15) 
p value </p>

<p>Pupil diameter (mm, mean ± SD) 
Baseline 
3.45 ± 0.89 
4.33 ± 0.82 
0.009 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>At 10 min 
4.95 ± 1.41 
6.02 ± 1.05 
0.026 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(+1.50 ± 0.95) 
(+1.68 ± 0.98) 
(0.607) 
At 25 min 
6.33 ± 1.44 
7.50 ± 0.93 
0.013 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(+2.88 ± 0.95) 
(+3.17 ± 0.97) 
(0.427) 
At 60 min 
7.55 ± 1.25 
8.45 ± 0.77 
0.025 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(+4.10 ± 0.80) 
(+4.12 ± 1.06) 
(0.961) </p>

<p>Pulse (per min, mean ± SD) 
Baseline 
65.87 ± 13.56 
66.60 ± 11.54 
0.876 
At 10 min 
67.07 ± 13.38 
63.80 ± 10.37 
0.461 
(+1.20 ± 3.49) 
(−2.80 ± 3.26) 
(0.003 
* ) 
At 25 min 
67.93 ± 13.46 
63.00 ± 10.64 
0.275 
(+2.07 ± 4.38) 
(−3.60 ± 4.10) 
(0.001 
* ) 
At 60 min 
67.87 ± 12.32 
61.67 ± 9.84 
0.139 
(+2.00 ± 7.19) 
(−4.93 ± 4.43) 
(0.004 
* ) </p>

<p>MAP (mmHg, mean ± SD) 
Baseline 
88.91 ± 8.26 
91.62 ± 8.00 
0.369 
At 10 min 
85.37 ± 13.63 
88.98 ± 8.21 
0.388 
(−3.54 ± 12.01) 
(−2.64 ± 5.91) 
(0.798) 
At 25 min 
89.60 ± 7.55 
90.24 ± 8.32 
0.826 
(+0.69 ± 5.15) 
(−1.38 ± 5.031) 
(0.288) 
At 60 min 
91.84 ± 8.23 
89.33 ± 10.86 
0.481 
(+2.93 ± 7.84) 
(−2.29 ± 10.68) 
(0.138) </p>

<p>MAP, mean arterial pressure. 
The mean changes from baseline are shown in italics and parentheses. 
* statistical significance. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our study included DM and HT patients: 60% in the conven-
tional group and 40% in the TPD group. Although Table 2 
demonstrates that patients with these underlying diseases </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>.00 
10.00 
25.00 
60.00 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>Conventional </p>

<p>TPD 
Pupil size (mm) Mean </p>

<p>± SE </p>

<p>Figure 1 Pupillary diameter at each time point. </p>

<p>were not statistically different, the underlying diseases did 
have a more or less effect on the pupil size at baseline 
(Table 3). The mean baseline pupil size of the patients in 
the conventional group was smaller than the TPD group 
with a significant difference. Therefore, concerning the 
rates of pupillary dilatation, it would be more useful to 
compare the effect of the eye drops between protocols 
than the sizes of the final pupillary diameter. At the 
end of the study, both protocols yielded an equal degree 
of pupillary dilatation and the rate of pupillary dilata-
tion was not different between the two groups. There 
was also no statistical difference in the pupillary sizes 
between the patients with DM or HT who received either 
the conventional or TPD protocol at every time point 
(Table 4). 
A mixture of reduced concentration of tropicamide and 
phenylephrine in patients with darkly pigmented irides was 
reported to be sufficiently effective for pupillary dilata-
tion in indirect ophthalmoscopy. 
4,5 This study also showed 
that the lower concentration of dilating drops in the TPD 
protocol neither compromised the average gain in pupil-
lary increment nor the mean mydriatic rate at the 60 min 
mark. Diclofenac can be added into the mixture of tropi-
camide and phenylephrine without disturbing the mydriatic 
effects. However, the prolonged efficacy of pupillary dilata-
tion during the intraoperative period may be required in a 
future study. The limitation of this study was the small num-
ber of subjects. Therefore, a subgroup analysis of mydriatic </p>



<p>P. Bhurayanontachai et al. </p>

<p>Table 4 Pupillary diameter changes compared between normal patients and patients with underlying diabetes mellitus or 
hypertension. </p>

<p>Variable 
Conventional 
p value 
TPD 
p value </p>

<p>Normal patients 
Patients with 
DM or HT </p>

<p>Normal patients 
Patients with 
DM or HT </p>

<p>Pupil diameter (mm, mean ± SD) 
Baseline 
3.42 ± 1.11 
3.53 ± 0.81 
0.827 
4.42 ± 1.03 
4.25 ± 0.43 
0.739 
At 10 min 
4.92 ± 1.63 
4.84 ± 1.39 
0.929 
6.08 ± 1.05 
6.10 ± 1.18 
0.979 
At 25 min 
5.88 ± 1.69 
6.59 ± 1.34 
0.390 
7.61 ± 0.93 
7.40 ± 1.10 
0.708 
At 60 min 
7.21 ± 1.76 
7.81 ± 0.85 
0.465 
8.58 ± 0.72 
8.30 ± 0.97 
0.544 </p>

<p>Pupil diameter difference from baseline (mm, mean ± SD) 
At 10 min ---baseline 
1.50 ± 0.63 
1.31 ± 1.08 
0.712 
1.67 ± 0.86 
1.85 ± 1.32 
0.756 
At 25 min ---baseline 
2.45 ± 0.68 
3.06 ± 1.06 
0.247 
3.19 ± 0.90 
3.15 ± 1.29 
0.941 
At 60 min ---baseline 
3.79 ± 0.68 
4.28 ± 0.89 
0.284 
4.17 ± 1.13 
4.05 ± 1.15 
0.857 </p>

<p>DM, diabetes mellitus; HT, hypertension. </p>

<p>response between patients with underlying diseases and nor-
mal patients could not be provided. 
In regards to the systemic effects on the MAP and pulse, 
phenylephrine has a sympathetic stimulation on the heart 
rate and, therefore, probably induces a raise of the arterial 
blood pressure and pulse. Each patient in the conventional 
protocol received 3 drops of 10% phenylephrine while each 
patient in the TPD protocol received 4 drops of 3% phenyle-
phrine. Therefore, the total amount of phenylephrine in the 
conventional group of patients was much higher than the 
patients in the TPD group. This may be the reason the TPD 
protocol had fewer patients with cardiovascular side effects 
than patients who received the conventional protocol. The 
tendency of the mean arterial pulse to decrease over time 
in the TPD group may occur from a full rest of the patient 
with less sympathetic stimulation from the eye drops. A sim-
ilar result was also reported in a previous study. 
5 Therefore, 
the TPD protocol may be more beneficial in patients with 
systemic hypertension or cardiovascular diseases. 
Patients in the conventional protocol received the eye 
drops 10 times while patients in the TPD protocol received 
the mixture only 4 times. As a result, if the TPD protocol 
can yield an equal dilating efficacy compared to the conven-
tional protocol while requiring less work, the TPD protocol 
is preferred in daily practice. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The TPD protocol with the fixed combination of tropicamide, 
phenylephrine and diclofenac is equally effective as the con-
ventional protocol for preoperative pupillary dilatation with 
reduced side effects in the patient's blood pressure. </p>

<p>Author's contribution </p>

<p>PB conceived of the study, participated in its design and 
coordination, and wrote the manuscript. SS carried out the </p>

<p>patient's randomization and data collection. PA carried out 
the mixture preparation and stability test. All authors read 
and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>We thank Ms. Parichat Damthongsuk for the statistical anal-
ysis. </p>



</text></tei>