<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5389568" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The oncogenic transcription factor MYC and its bind-
ing partner MAX regulate gene expression by bind-
ing to DNA at enhancer-box (E-box) elements 5 -
CACGTG-3 . In mammalian genomes, the central E-
box CpG has the potential to be methylated at the 
5-position of cytosine (5mC), or to undergo further 
oxidation to the 5-hydroxymethyl (5hmC), 5-formyl 
(5fC), or 5-carboxyl (5caC) forms. We find that MAX 
exhibits the greatest affinity for a 5caC or unmodified 
C-containing E-box, and much reduced affinities for 
the corresponding 5mC, 5hmC or 5fC forms. Crystal-
lization of MAX with a 5caC modified E-box oligonu-
cleotide revealed that MAX Arg36 recognizes 5caC 
using a 5caC-Arg-Guanine triad, with the next near-
est residue to the carboxylate group being Arg60. In 
an analysis of &gt;800 primary multiple myelomas, MAX 
alterations occurred at a frequency of ∼3%, more 
than half of which were single nucleotide substitu-
tions affecting a basic clamp-like interface important 
for DNA interaction. Among these, arginines 35, 36 
and 60 were the most frequently altered. In vitro bind-
ing studies showed that whereas mutation of Arg36 
(R36W) or Arg35 (R35H/L) completely abolished DNA 
binding, mutation of Arg60 (R60Q) significantly re-
duced DNA binding, but retained a preference for the 
5caC modified E-box. Interestingly, MAX alterations 
define a subset of myeloma patients with lower MYC 
expression and a better overall prognosis. Together 
these data indicate that MAX can act as a direct epi-
genetic sensor of E-box cytosine modification states 
and that local CpG modification and MAX variants </p>

<p>converge to modulate the MAX-MYC transcriptional 
network. </p>

<p>Postsynthetic modifications to DNA and histone proteins 
play a key role in defining the three dimensional organi-
zation of chromatin in the nucleus and DNA accessibility, 
shaping gene expression programs by enabling the expres-
sion of some genes while restricting that of others. Such 
epigenetic regulation controls cell fate decisions during de-
velopment and the maintenance of cellular identity in dif-
ferentiated cells, a program that is frequently altered in the 
progression to cancer. Among these, the methylation of cy-
tosine residues (5mC) in the sequence context CpG is per-
haps the best studied and affects gene regulation through 
both direct and indirect (secondary to changes in chromatin 
structure) effects on the binding of proteins to DNA. Most 
CpGs in the genome are methylated and in the context of in-
tact chromatin, the absence of 5mC demarks accessible re-
gions of the genome, including CpG island-containing gene 
promoters and active enhancers (1,2). While the methyla-
tion status of most CpG sites are largely invariant across cell 
types, the fraction that do vary (∼20%) overlap distal reg-
ulatory regions, and in particular enhancers and transcrip-
tion factor binding sites, suggesting that the gain or loss of 
5mC at such sites is a key defining feature of lineage-specific 
gene regulation (3,4). 
It is now evident that 5mC patterns can be fur-
ther shaped during development and even in post-
mitotic cells by the ten-eleven translocation (Tet) fam-
ily of Fe(II)-and ␣-ketoglutarate-dependent dioxygenases 
which convert 5mC to 5-hydroxymethylcytosine (5hmC), 5-
formylcytosine (5fC) and 5-carboxylcytosine (5caC) in suc-
cessive oxidation steps (5-8). One fate of oxidized 5mC 
residues--particularly 5fC and 5caC--involves excision by </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 404 727 8491; Fax: +1 404 727 3746; Email: xcheng@emory.edu 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Paula M. Vertino. Tel: +1 404 778 3119; Fax: +1 404 778 2512; Email: pvertin@emory.edu </p>

<p> † These authors contributed equally to this work as first authors. </p>

<p>C The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 5 2397 </p>

<p>thymine DNA glycosylase (TDG) followed by incorpora-
tion of an unmodified C, leading to a net DNA 'demethyla-
tion' (8). Accumulated evidence now support the view that 
5hmC exists as a relatively stable modification unaffected 
by TDG depletion, constituting a distinct epigenetic signal 
that primarily marks lowly expressed genes, gene bodies and 
intragenic regions (9,10) (reviewed in (11,12)). In contrast, 
5fC and 5caC are found at much lower levels at steady state 
(1-10% that of 5hmC), and preferentially accumulate at en-
hancers and other distal regulatory regions in the absence of 
TDG (13-18), implying that the dynamic turnover of 5mC 
may be particularly important in enhancer function. Recent 
work by our group and others showing that the binding of 
certain transcription factors to DNA is influenced by the 
presence of oxidized 5mC bases in vitro (19-23) and that 
5fC/5caC pose a barrier to transcriptional elongation in 
cells (24) raise the question of whether 5fC/5caC may have 
functions in gene regulation beyond that of intermediates in 
the DNA demethylation cycle. 
The oncogenic transcription factor MYC and its bind-
ing partner MAX are basic-helix-loop-helix (bHLH) tran-
scription factors that preferentially recognize a subset of 
enhancer-box (E-box) sequences containing a central CpG 
dinucleotide (5 -CACGTG-3 ) (25-28). MYC-MAX bind-
ing to E-box sequences is thought 'amplify' transcrip-
tion by promoting elongation at a wide number of genes 
(29,30). MAX also dimerizes with a number of other bHLH 
proteins, including Mad1-4 (Mxd), Mnt, Mga and oth-
ers (31,32). The MAX-Mad/Mnt/Mga heterodimers di-
rectly antagonize the function of MYC by instead recruiting 
corepressor complexes to mediate transcriptional repres-
sion from the same E-box sequences. Ultimately, it is the 
relative abundance of MYC and the other binding partners 
and their competition for MAX that mediates distinct bi-
ologic outputs (32,33). Dysregulation of the MYC-MAX 
transcriptional network is a common mechanism driving 
oncogenic progression in many human cancers. Most often 
this is achieved through translocations or amplification of 
the MYC locus, resulting in its overexpression. Alterations 
in MAX have also recently been reported (34-36), but the 
functional significance of these is not well understood. In 
this study, we sought to determine the influence of 5mC ox-
idation and the impact of cancer-associated MAX muta-
tions on the biochemical and structural features of MAX 
binding with its cognate E-box. 
Here, we provide evidence that MAX, and potentially 
other bHLH transcription factors, can 'sense' the oxidation 
status of 5mCpGs, and further that cancer-associated muta-
tions in MAX differentially affect binding to these features. 
In a large collection of over 800 primary multiple myelomas, 
we establish that somatic MAX mutations occur at a fre-
quency of ∼3% and are likely to represent loss of function 
alterations. Among myeloma patients, MAX mutations are 
associated with low expression of MYC and a better over-
all prognosis. Taken together the data suggest that 5mCpG 
oxidation may play a critical role in fine-tuning E-box recog-
nition by the MYC family of transcription factors, and ul-
timately transcriptional output. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Protein expression and purification </p>

<p>Human full length MAX (NP 002373.3) and the bHLH-
leucine zipper domain (residues 22-107) were cloned into 
hexahistidine-SUMO (small ubiquitin-like modifier) tagged 
vector (pXC1385 and pXC1407, respectively) and expressed 
in Escherichia coli BL21 (DE3) Codon-plus RIL. Cells 
were cultured in LB medium at 37 
• C until OD600 reached 
0.5 before induction by adding 0.4 mM isopropyl ␤-D-1-
thiogalactopyranoside for 16 h at 16 
• C. Cells were har-
vested and lysed in 20 mM sodium phosphate, pH 7.4, 150 
mM NaCl, 1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 50 mM imidazol 
and 0.3 mM phenylmethyl-sulphonyl fluoride by sonica-
tion. The lysate was clarified by centrifugation at 35 000 × 
g for 60 min at 4 
• C. The hexahistidine fusion protein was 
isolated on nickel-charged chelating column (GE Health-
care). The hexahistidine-SUMO tag was removed by di-
gestion with Ulp1 protease (purified in-house) for 16 h at 
4 
• C (37), resulting in the retention of two extraneous N-
terminal residues (His-Met). The protein was further pu-
rified by tandem HiTrap Q and SP column (i.e. passing 
through Q and eluted from SP column). The protein do-
main used for crystallization was then loaded on a HiLoad 
Superdex 200 (16/60) column (GE Healthcare) and concen-
trated to approximately 87 mg/ml in 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 
8.0, 500 mM NaCl and 1 mM DTT. </p>

<p>Site-directed mutagenesis </p>

<p>Point mutations were introduced into the wild-type 6xHis-
SUMO-tagged human full length MAX (pXC1385) using 
the QuickChange site-directed mutagenesis kit (Stratagene) 
to generate MAX H28R (pXC1506), R35H (pXC1580), 
R35L (pXC1581), R36W (pXC1500), R36K (pXC1507) 
and R60Q (pXC1533). All mutants were verified by se-
quencing. The mutant proteins were purified as described 
above for the wild type (WT) protein. With the exception 
of H28R which yielded a lower protein yield (0.3 mg/l), the 
remaining mutant proteins were all recovered a similar or 
higher protein yields as the WT protein (2 mg from 1 l cul-
ture for WT, 3.3 mg for R35H, 6.5 mg for R35L, 1.4 mg 
for R36W, 2.7 mg for R36K and 3.2 mg for R60Q). Size ex-
clusion chromatography and dynamic light scattering mea-
surements indicated a similar size and integrity for all (Sup-
plementary Figure S1). </p>

<p>Electrophoretic mobility shift assay </p>

<p>The gel shift assays were performed by incubating 5 nM 
6-carboxy-fluorescein (FAM) labeled double-stranded 
oligonucleotides 
[FAM-5 -TAGGCCAXGTGACCGG-
3 /5 -CCGGTCAYGTGGCCTA-3 where X or Y is C, 
5-methyl-C (M), 5-hydroxymethyl-C (H), 5-formyl-C (F) 
or 5-carboxyl-C (5caC)] with an increasing amount (up 
to 0.5 M) of full length MAX protein at room tempera-
ture (∼22 
• C) for 30 min under the conditions of 20 mM 
Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 150 mM NaCl, 5% (v/v) glycerol, 1 
mM DTT and 0.1 mg/ml bovine serum albumin (BSA). 
Protein/DNA complexes were loaded onto a 6% native 1× 
TBE polyacrylamide gel, and electrophoresed for 40 min at </p>

<p>2398 Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 5   80 V in 1× TBE buffer. Gels were scanned using Typhoon 
Trio+ imager (GE Healthcare). </p>

<p>Fluorescent polarization </p>

<p>Fluorescence polarization measurements were carried out 
at 25 
• C on a Synergy 4 Microplate Reader (BioTek) as de-
scribed (38). A 5 nM of FAM-labeled double strand DNA 
was incubated for 10 min with increasing amounts of pro-
teins (up to 1 M) in 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 150 mM 
NaCl, 1 mM DTT, 5% (v/v) glycerol and 0.1 mg/ml BSA. 
No change in fluorescence intensity was observed with 
the addition of protein. Curves were fit individually using 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">GraphPad PRISM</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">5.0d</rs> software. Binding constants (K D ) 
were calculated as [mP] = [maximum mP] x [C] / (K D +[C]) 
+ [baseline mP], where [mP] is milli-Polarization and [C] is 
protein concentration (39). Saturated [mP] was calculated 
as saturation = ([mP] − [baseline mP])/([maximum mP] − 
[baseline mP]). Curves were normalized as percentage of 
bound and reported is the mean ± SEM of the interpolated 
K D from two independent experiments performed in dupli-
cate. For those binding curves that did not reach saturation, 
the lower limit of the binding affinity was estimated (39). </p>

<p>Crystallography </p>

<p>For co-crystallization, 1 mM MAX purified protein was 
mixed with 0.5 mM double-stranded oligonucleotide with 
nine different DNAs (Supplementary Figure S2). The best 
diffracting crystal used for data collection was obtained 
from 5 -AGTAGCAXGTGCTACT-3 (where X = 5caC) 
(synthesized by New England Biolabs). Crystals appeared 
within 1-day under the conditions of 0.1 M sodium citrate-
citric acid at pH 5.5, 20% (w/v) polyethylene glycol 3000. 
Crystals were cryoprotected by soaking in mother liquor 
supplemented with 30% ethylene glycol. X-ray diffraction 
datasets were collected at the SER-CAT beamline (22ID-D)  at the Advanced Photon Source, Argonne National Lab-
oratory and processed using XDS (40). The structure was 
solved by molecular replacement by <rs type="software">PHENIX</rs> (41,42) us-
ing the Max-DNA complex structure (PDB 1AN2 (43)) as 
a search model. <rs type="software">PHENIX</rs> refinement scripts were used for 
refinement, and the statistics shown in Supplementary Ta-
ble S1 were calculated for the entire resolution range. </p>

<p>MAX mutations in multiple myeloma </p>

<p>The CoMMpass (Clinical outcomes in Multiple Myeloma 
to personal assessment) database interim analysis IA9 was 
interrogated for single nucleotide variants (SNVs) and 
structural variants in the MAX locus (https://research. 
themmrf.org). RNA-seq data and overall survival data 
were extracted for those patients harboring MAX vari-
ants and compared to those for whom MAX status could 
be definitively called but whom lacked MAX SNVs (wild-
type). Overall survival data between the two groups were 
compared using a Log-rank (Mantel-Cox) test and Haz-
ard Ratio determined using the Mantel-Haenszel test in 
<rs id="software-5" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">6.0</rs>. MYC expression levels were deter-
mined from RNAseq data that was processed with Cuf-
flinks by the CoMMpass consortium and expressed as </p>

<p>FPKM--fragments per kilobase of exon per million reads 
mapped. The distributions between the two groups were 
compared using the Mann-Whitney U test implemented in 
<rs id="software-6" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">6.0</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The bHLH DNA-binding domain together with leucine 
zipper dimerization domains (bHLH-LZ) of the Max-Max, 
Max-Myc and Max-Mad dimers in complex with E-box 
DNA have been structurally examined (43,44). However, in 
these in vitro studies it was necessary to use a chemical liga-
tion approach to achieve homogeneous Max-Myc or Max-
Mad heterodimers (44). Whereas the various Max partners 
exhibit marked differences in the leucine zipper regions, the 
mode of interaction of the bHLH domains with DNA is es-
sentially identical between the Max homodimer and the het-
erodimers (44). Therefore, for simplicity, we used the full-
length human MAX-MAX homodimer to biochemically 
characterize interactions with E-box DNA, and the bHLH-
LZ region (residues 22-107) for structural analysis (Supple-
mentary Figure S3A and B). </p>

<p>Binding of MAX to CpG-modified E-boxes </p>

<p>We first compared the binding of human full-length MAX 
protein to double-stranded oligonucleotides containing the 
E-box sequence in which the status of the central CpG was 
either unmodified, 5mC-modified, or oxidized to 5hmC, 
5fC or 5caC by electrophoretic mobility shift assay. As ex-
pected, MAX bound to the unmodified E-box and methy-
lation of the CpG greatly inhibited DNA binding, as ob-
served previously (28) (Figure 1A and B). 5hmC further de-
creased binding significantly (Figure 1C). Surprisingly, the 
5fC containing oligo showed a small amount of discrete 
complex, whereas 5caC restored binding to the level of un-
modified C (Figure 1D and E). Due to synthetic limitations, 
the 5caC modification is not compatible with a FAM la-
bel on the same oligonucleotide, thus the 5caC-containing 
double-stranded oligonucleotide was only hemi-modified, 
with the 5caC base on the bottom strand only. In all other 
cases we compared both the fully modified setting in which 
the modified base was on both strands (Figure 1A-D, top) 
as well as the hemi-modified setting (Figure 1A-E, bottom). 
From the intensities of shifted bands, we estimated the ap-
parent binding affinity to be between 16 and 32 nM for 
both completely unmodified C and hemi-modified 5caC-
containing oligonucleotides. We expect that a fully modified 
5caC oligo might have an even stronger binding affinity to 
the MAX homodimer. 
We repeated the binding assays using fluorescence polar-
ization to quantitatively measure the dissociation constants 
(K D ) between the MAX protein and the five E-box forms, 
comparing directly double-stranded oligonucleotides that 
were modified only on the bottom strand (Figure 1F). MAX 
bound the unmodified C and the 5caC-containing oligonu-
cleotides equally well with a K D of ∼30 nM. Methylation 
(5mC) and 5-hydroxymethylation (5hmC) significantly re-
duced binding by a factor of &gt;13, whereas 5-formycytosine 
(5fC) reduced affinity by a factor of 8. The affinity of MAX 
for the E-box is thus on the order 5caC ∼ C &gt; 5fC &gt; 5mC </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 5 2399 </p>

<p>X/Y=C/C </p>

<p>0.0001 0.001 
0.01 
0.1 
1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>MAX wild-type (μM) </p>

<p>% of saturation </p>

<p>FAM-5'-TGCCACGTGACC-3' 
3'-ACGGTGXACTGG-5' </p>

<p>X 
K D (nM) 
5caC 31±3 
C 
36±9 
5fC &gt;240 
5mC &gt;400 
5hmC &gt;400 </p>

<p>150 mM NaCl </p>

<p>F 
A </p>

<p>X/Y=C/C 
5mC/5mC 
5hmC/5hmC 
5fC/5fC 
C/5caC </p>

<p>16-32 nM 
16-32 nM </p>

<p>Free DNA </p>

<p>Max-DNA 
complex </p>

<p>FAM-5'-TAGGCCAXGTGACCGG-3' 
3'-ATCCGGTGYACTGGCC-5' </p>

<p>C/5mC 
C/5hmC 
C/5fC 
C/5caC </p>

<p>Free DNA </p>

<p>Max-DNA 
complex </p>

<p>B 
C 
D 
E </p>

<p>Figure 1. MAX binds 5caC DNA. (A-E) Electrophoretic mobility shift assay of full length MAX protein binding to oligonucleotides containing a single 
E-box where the central CpG are unmodified (C/C), fully modified (M/M, H/H, F/F), or hemi-modified (C/M, C/H, C/F or C/5caC). The protein 
concentrations used were a maximum of 0.5 M (the right most lane of each panel) followed by serial 2-fold dilutions (from right to left). (F) DNA binding 
was quantified by fluorescence polarization. Data represent the mean ± SEM of two independent determinations performed in duplicate. </p>

<p>∼ 5hmC. We also tested the effect of independent modi-
fication of the two DNA strands (i.e. strand-biased DNA 
modification) on binding affinity. As expected, MAX had a 
slightly better affinity for the hemi-modified C/5caC than 
it did for unmodified C/C, whereas addition of a single 
methyl group onto one strand (5mC/5caC or C/5mC) re-
duced binding, regardless of which it was opposite, and was 
nearly as detrimental as that observed with the fully methy-
lated (5mC/5mC) site (Supplementary Figure S4). </p>

<p>Structure of MAX bound with 5caC DNA </p>

<p>To understand how MAX binds 5caC DNA, we next co-
crystallized the MAX bHLH-LZ (residues 22-107) with a 
16-base pair palindromic sequence containing a fully mod-
ified 5caCpG within the E-box element (Supplementary 
Figure S3B). The MAX-DNA complex structure was de-
termined to a resolution of 2.39Å (Supplementary Ta-
ble S1). The structure is composed of two long helices, ␣1 
(residues 22-49) and ␣2 (residues 60-106) connected by a 
loop (residues 50-59) (Supplementary Figure S3C). The ba-
sic region of the N-terminal portion of helix ␣1 binds in the 
major groove of the DNA (Figure 2A-C), recognizing half 
of the palindromic E-box sequence (Figure 2D). His28 do-
nates one hydrogen bond (H-bond) to either Guanine O6 
or Guanine N7 of the outer C 3 :G 3 base pair (Figure 2E). 
Glu32 accepts a H-bond from the N4 amino group (NH 2 ) 
of the opposite cytosine (Figure 2E), while its side chain 
aliphatic carbons (C␤ and C␥ ) are in the vicinity of the 
Thymine methyl group of the inner A 2 :T 2 base pair (Fig-
ure 2F). The Thymine methyl group also forms a carbon-
oxygen (C-H. . . O type) hydrogen bond (45) with the side 
chain carbonyl oxygen of Asn29 (Figure 2F). 
The central 5caCpG dinucleotide is involved in interac-
tions with three charged residues, Arg36, Lys40 and Arg60 
(Figure 2G and H). The guanidino group of Arg36 inter-
acts with the central 5 -CpG-3 dinucleotide by donating 
two hydrogen atoms to the O6 and N7 atoms of the 3 
Guanine (G 1 ), as well as stacks with the carboxylate group 
of the 5 5caC (Figure 2D and I), forming a 5caC-Arg-
Guanine triad. The next closest residues to the carboxy-
late group are Arg60 (∼6Å) and Lys40 (∼7Å) (Figure 
2G and H)--too far to make direct contact (but poten-
tially involved via water-mediated interactions). This cre-
ates a clamp-like basic environment ideal for electrostatic at-
traction with the two negatively charged carboxylate groups </p>

<p>of central 5caC:G base pairs and the phosphate backbone 
(Figure 2A and J). The negatively charged Glu32 and the 
polar residue Asn29 are further away and separated by base 
pairs in between. </p>

<p>Arg36 adopts alternative conformations: C-specific and 
5caC-specific </p>

<p>We compared our structure with previously characterized 
structures of the Max-Max homodimer, and the Max-Myc 
and Max-Mad heterodimers in complex with unmodified 
E-box DNA (43,44). Regardless of the partner, the corre-
sponding His28-G 3 and Glu32/Asn29-T 2 interactions are 
conserved between Max, Myc and Mad (Figure 3A and B). 
Of the side chains involved in DNA base contact, Arg36 
of Max has the largest conformational difference compar-
ing 5caC and unmodified E-box DNA binding (Figure 
3C and D). In the structures of the Max-Myc and Max-
Mad bound with unmodified DNA, the guanidino group of 
Arg36 forms a singular H-bond with the Guanine N7 atom 
of central CpG (Figure 3C). The corresponding arginine in 
Myc (Arg366) likewise forms a single H-bond with Gua-
nine N7, whereas the corresponding residue in Mad (Arg68) 
points away from the N7 atom of the Guanine (Figure 3D). 
In this conformation, which we term 'C-specific', the guani-
dino group of Arg36 (and the corresponding Arg336 of Myc 
or Arg68 of Mad) is quite close to the C5 atom of the CpG 
Cytosine (3.3-3.7Å) (Figure 3E). Methylation or hydrox-
ylmethylation at the C5 atom is likely to cause steric ob-
struction with the Arg36 in this conformation (Figure 3f), 
perhaps explaining the diminished binding to E-box DNA 
containing these modifications. In contrast, the negatively 
charged carboxylate group of 5caC is accommodated by in-
ducing the positively charged Arg36 to adopt the rotated 
'5caC-specific' conformation (Figure 3G), via a series of 
the side chain torsion angle rotations. In this conforma-
tion, Arg36 makes two H-bond interactions with Guanine 
O6 and N7. The conformation of Max Arg60 on the other 
hand, also involved in the distant binding of 5caC (Figure 
2G), appears to be relatively constant regardless of whether 
Max is in the homodimer, or heterodimer with Myc or Mad, 
or whether the DNA is unmodified or 5-carboxylated (Fig-
ure 3H). The strong binding for 5caC/C (Figure 1) sug-
gests that if the two DNA strands were modified indepen-
dently, Arg36 from each monomer of the Max homodimer </p>



<p>Figure 2. Structure of MAX-5caC complex. (A) The surface charge of MAX homodimer at neutral pH is displayed as blue for positive, red for negative, and 
white for neutral. (B) The inner surface of the clamp-like DNA binding domain is predominantly basic. (C) Electron density 2F o -F c , contoured at 1σ above 
the mean, is shown for the entire 16-bp DNA with major and minor grooves indicated. (D) Each MAX monomer recognizes one half of the palindromic 
E-box sequence (x = 5caC). (E) Interactions with the outer C 3 :G 3 base pair. The numerical numbers indicate the inter-atom distance in angstrom. (F) 
Interactions with the inner A 2 :T 2 base pair. (G) The bidentate hydrogen bonds formed between Arg36 and the central G 1 --a pattern specific to Guanine. 
(H) Close-up view of the central C 1 :G 1 base pair, recognized by the pair of Arg36 residues. Additional neighboring residues near the carboxylate group of 
5caC are Lys40 and Lys60. Two 5caC:G base pairs interact with two side chains of Arg-36 residues. Lys-40 interacts with the phosphate group of 5caC. 
(I) Arg36 forms a 5caC-Arg-Gua triad with the central CpG dinucleotide. Simulated annealing omit electron densities, contoured at 3 and 5 above the 
mean, are shown for Arg36 (green mesh) and the carboxylate moiety of 5caC (red mesh), respectively. (J) Phosphate interactions with Arg33, Lys40 and 
Arg60. </p>

<p>(or by extension, each monomer of the Max-Myc or Max-
Mad heterodimers) could adopt strand-specific conforma-
tion: one for the 5caC-specific mode and the other for the 
C-specific mode. </p>

<p>Cancer-associated MAX mutations have altered DNA bind-
ing properties </p>

<p>While 
the 
oncogenic 
consequences 
of 
MYC 
overexpression/amplification are well documented, re-
cent work indicates that MAX is also a target of mutation 
in human cancers. Germline mutations in MAX confer 
a hereditary predisposition to pheochromocytoma and 
paragangliomas (34,35) and somatic mutations have been 
described in a number of other sporadic tumor types 
(cBioportal, http://www.cbioportal.org/) (36,46,47). We 
characterized three such cancer related MAX mutations: </p>

<p>R36W has been found in a myeloma, H28R found pri-
marily in endometrial cancers, and R60Q found in a 
wide variety of cancers including endometrial, glioma, 
acute myeloid leukemia, colorectal and stomach cancers. 
Among these, H28R and R60Q were recently identified as 
recurrent 'hotspot' mutations predicted to have functional 
consequences in cancer development (48). 
Consistent with the central role for Arg36-mediated hy-
drogen bonding to the central CpG base pair noted above, 
the change from a positively charged Arg36 to an aromatic 
tryptophan (R36W) resulted in complete loss of DNA bind-
ing (Figure 4A). In contrast, substitution of His28, which 
recognizes the outer guanine (G 3 ) (Figure 2E), with argi-
nine (H28R), resulted in significantly higher affinity for all 
five forms of E-box DNA (Figure 4B). This observation is 
in agreement with previous studies showing that both Arg </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 5 2401 </p>

<p>Max H28-Gua interaction: 
Max-Max-5caC (this study) (green) 
Max-Max-C (PDB 1AN2) (dark grey) 
Max-Myc (PDB 1NKP) (light pink) 
Max-Mad (PDB 1NLW) (light grey) </p>

<p>Max H28-Gua (this study) (cyan) </p>

<p>Myc H359-Gua (PDB 1NKP) (light pink) 
Mad H61-Gua (PDB 1NLW) (light grey) </p>

<p>(5caC-specific) 
Max-Max R36 </p>

<p>(Myc)-Max R36 </p>

<p>(Mad)-Max R36 
(C-specific) </p>

<p>Max R60 </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>Max H28 
Max H28 
Myc H359 
Mad H61 </p>

<p>(5caC-specific) 
Max-Max R36 </p>

<p>(Max)-Mad R68 
(C-specific) </p>

<p>( M 
a x ) -M </p>

<p>y c </p>

<p>R 
3 6 6 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>G3 
G3 
G1 </p>

<p>G1 </p>

<p>Max-Max R36 
(5caC-specific) </p>

<p>5caC </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>CH 3 </p>

<p>5mC </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>(A model) 
Max R36 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>(Myc)-Max R36 
(C-specific) </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>3.3 </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>Figure 3. Arg36 adopts alternative conformations: C-specific and 5caC-specific. (A) Comparison of Max His28-Gua interaction among Max-Max ho-
modimer, Max-Myc and Max-Mad heterodimers. (B) Comparison of Max His28 and its corresponding residue in Myc (His359) and Mad (His61). (C) 
Superimposition of Max Arg36-Gua interaction in Max-Max homodimer (in complex with 5caC DNA), Max-Myc (unmodified DNA) and Max-Mad 
(unmodified DNA) heterodimers. (D) Superimposition of Max Arg36 (5caC DNA) and its corresponding residue in Myc (Arg366) and Max (Arg68) in 
complex with unmodified DNA. (E) With unmodified DNA, Max Arg36 forms a van der Waals contact with the ring C5 atom of unmodified Cyt and a 
hydrogen bond with Gua of the central CpG dinculeotide, adopted from PDB 1NKP (44). (F) Modeling a methyl group (in yellow ball) onto unmodified 
CpG site potentially results in repulsion (indicated by a star) with the Arg36 of Max in the C-specific conformation. (G) The 5caC-Arg-Gua triad in the 
5caC-specific interactions observed by Max Arg36. (H) Max Arg60 conformation is conserved among Max-Max, Max-Myc and Max-Mad dimers. (I) A 
close-up view of 5caCpG dinucleotide connected by the sugar-backbone (p: phosphate group). </p>

<p>and His can be used in Guanine recognition (49) (e.g. see 
(50)). Indeed, H28R bound DNA so tightly that the esti-
mated K D values were below the probe concentration of as-
say conditions regardless of CpG modification status (5 nM 
probe, 150 mM NaCl) (Figure 4B). We thus increased the 
NaCl concentration to 350 mM. Under these more strin-
gent conditions, H28R retained the same relative order of 
binding preference as wild-type MAX (5caC∼C &gt; 5fC &gt; 
5mC∼5hmC), with the K D values ranging from 11 to 110 
nM (Figure 4C). Moreover, H28R was able to bind two 
control sequences (C-1 and C-2) that retain one or both 
of the outer G 3 :C 3 base pairs, but lack the cognate E-box 
sequence--albeit with a reduced affinity relative to the E-
box containing sequence. Wild-type MAX showed no de-
tectable binding to the canonical E-box sequence or the con-
trol sequences under the same high salt condition (Figure 
4C). It appears that the retention of both of the outer G 3 :C 3 
base pairs renders the control-1 sequence a reasonable tar-
get for the H28R mutant, with an affinity only about 2-</p>

<p>fold lower than that of the hemi-methylated E-box sequence 
and 14-fold less than the unmodified sequence (Figure 4D). 
These data suggest that the H28R mutation may confer very 
tight, potentially indiscriminate DNA binding of MAX to 
degenerate E-box sequences. 
Substitution of the positively charged Arg60 with a po-
lar glutamine residue (R60Q) reduced DNA binding signif-
icantly, by a factor of ∼20. Nevertheless, even at the lower 
affinity, the mutant retained its preference for the 5caC 
modification over 5mC or the other oxidized forms (5hmC, 
5fC) (Figure 4E). The weakened DNA binding by the mu-
tant might provide an opportunity for other enzymes (such 
as the DNA glycosylase TDG (8)) to compete and excise 
5caC base, resulting in demethylation. </p>

<p>MAX mutations in Multiple Myeloma </p>

<p>Multiple myeloma (MM) is a malignancy of the long-lived 
antibody-producing plasma cells of the bone marrow. While </p>



<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>MAX WT 
(X=C) 
K D 36nM </p>

<p>R36W </p>

<p>150 mM NaCl </p>

<p>0.0001 0.001 
0.01 
0.1 
1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>MAX R36W [µM] </p>

<p>% of saturation </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0.0001 0.001 
0.01 
0.1 
1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>MAX H28R [µM] </p>

<p>% of saturation </p>

<p>X 
K D (nM) 
5caC 11±2 
C 
14±3 
5fC 
&gt;60 
5mC &gt;80 
5hmC &gt;110 
C-1 &gt;200 (control) </p>

<p>350 mM NaCl </p>

<p>( </p>

<p>E-box </p>

<p>MAX WT (E-box X=C) </p>

<p>0.0001 0.001 
0.01 
0.1 
1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>MAX H28R [μM] </p>

<p>% of saturation </p>

<p>MAX WT (X=C) K D 36nM </p>

<p>H28R </p>

<p>150 mM NaCl </p>

<p>K D &lt; 5 nM </p>

<p>E-box 
FAM-5'-TGCCACGTGACC-3' (6/6) 
3'-ACGGTGXACTGG-5' 
| | || 
Control-1 5'-GTCAGCGCATGG-3' 
(4/6) 
3'-CAGTCGCGTACC-5'-FAM 
| || 
Control-2 
5'-GAGGCGTGGC-3' (4/6) 
3'-CTCCGCACCGTT-5'-FAM 
| 
Control-3 5'-ATAAGATCAATA-3' 
(1/6) 
3'-TATTCTAGTTAT-5'-FAM </p>

<p>K D (nM) 
E-box &gt;80 (X=5mC) 
C-1 &gt;200 </p>

<p>C-2 &gt;1100 </p>

<p>C3 </p>

<p>350 mM NaCl </p>

<p>0.0001 0.001 
0.01 
0.1 
1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>MAX H28R [μM] </p>

<p>% of saturation </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>150 mM NaCl </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>0.001 
0.01 
0.1 
1 
10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>MAX R60Q [µM] </p>

<p>% of saturation </p>

<p>X 
K D (µM) 
5caC 0.7±0.1 
C 
1.2±0.4 
5mC 
5hmC &gt;5-7 
5fC </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 4. Cancer associated MAX mutants with altered DNA binding property. (A) R36W diminished DNA binding as measured by fluorescence po-
larization assays. Inset within the box: Sequences of the various modified E-box and control (C-1, C-2 and C-3) DNA substrates used. (B and C) H28R 
enhanced DNA binding with oligos containing varied forms of cytosine. The estimated dissociation constant K D values are uniformly low in 150 mM NaCl 
(panel B) but considerably increased in 350 mM NaCl (panel C). Note that the smaller the calculated K D value, the higher the binding affinity. (D) The 
enhanced DNA binding affinity of H28R might allow the mutant to bind near-cognate sequence. (E) The effect of the R60Q mutation on DNA binding. 
Despite significant reduction of affinity, 5caC DNA is still preferred over unmodified DNA by the R60Q mutant. Data represent the mean ± SEM of two 
independent determinations performed in duplicate. </p>

<p>myeloma cells maintain many of the features of their nor-
mal counterparts (e.g. antibody production, dependence on 
interactions with the bone marrow stroma for survival), 
they acquire proliferative capacity and the dysregulation of 
MYC is thought to play a central role in driving their clonal 
expansion (51). Rearrangements that juxtapose MYC to the 
immunoglobulin loci or other super-enhancers drive high 
levels of MYC expression in ∼20-50% of cases (52,53). 
In addition to dysregulated MYC, MAX mutations are 
also observed in myeloma. The R36W mutation described 
above was originally uncovered in a study of ∼200 multiple 
myelomas, three of whom harbored MAX mutations (1.5%, </p>

<p>cBioportal (54)). To determine the frequency and scope 
of MAX mutations, we queried the CoMMpass project 
(https://research.themmrf.org/), a prospective collection of 
purified tumor samples from over 1000 newly diagnosed 
myeloma patients, the majority of which have been charac-
terized by exome sequencing and have corresponding RNA-
seq and clinical outcomes data. Among the 805 patients for 
whom exome sequence was available, we identified 24 pri-
mary patient samples with 25 unique mutations affecting 
the MAX locus (16 missense, 5 nonsense, 2 splice site and 
2 deletion/rearrangements; Supplementary Table S2) sug-
gesting an overall frequency of ∼3%. The finding that many </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 5 2403 </p>

<p>Figure 5. MAX alterations in multiple myeloma. (A) Relative position of MAX variants detected in multiple myeloma and their relationship to the struc-
tural features of the MAX protein. Features of the DNA binding (bHLH) and dimerization domains (leucine zipper) are shown. Missense mutations are 
shown below. Purple stars show the position of nonsense mutations. Black/gray shaded residues are those conserved across the MAX bHLH family (see 
Supplementary Figure S3D). Those 'hotspot' mutations that were biochemically analyzed (H28R, R60Q) are marked in red. (B-D) Structural impacts of 
MAX variants in different regions of the MAX protein. (B) The detailed impact of missense mutations in the basic region--detailed interactions can be 
observed in panels of Figure 2E, F and G. (C) An I71 to F variant is likely to interfere with the dimer interaction via the leucine zipper. (D) The L94V, 
located on the outer surface of helix ␣2, has the potential to alter interactions with regions outside of structured region of the dimer or other proteins. 
(E) R36K reduced DNA binding significantly, whereas the R35H and R35L completely abolished binding under the same conditions. Data represent two 
independent determinations performed in duplicate. (F) Comparison of MYC expression in multiple myeloma samples from patients with wild type MAX 
(n = 625) or MAX alterations (n = 18). Shown are box plots of the MYC expression levels between samples in each class. Median is indicated by a line, 
box is the 1st and 3rd quartiles, whiskers are the most extreme data point that is 1.5 times the interquartile range. Significance (P &lt; 0.0001) was assessed 
by the Mann-Whitney U test. (G) Survival outcomes among Multiple Myeloma patients with wild-type MAX (n = 740) or MAX alterations (n = 24). 
Patients with MAX alterations exhibit a significantly better outcomes [Mantel-Cox log rank test, P = 0.041 (95% CI, 0.13-0.96)]. </p>

<p>tumors harbor nonsense mutations, start codon mutations, 
or deletion/rearrangements predicted to result in a loss of 
all or most of the MAX gene product (n = 10), as well as sev-
eral patients with more than one mutation (n = 5), strongly 
suggests that it is loss of function alterations in MAX that 
are important in myeloma. Indeed, of the remaining mis-
sense mutations, more than half affected amino acids 29-36 
(Figure 5A), and in particular conserved residues R35 (n = 
4) or R36 (n = 8). The finding that R36 can be mutated to 
a number of other residues (G, S, M, W or K), and R35 
to L or H, suggested that the loss of the positively charge 
side chain(s) in the basic clamp region is particularly im-
portant in these cases. These mutations are likely to directly 
interfere with the Arg side chain interaction with the cen-
tral guanine G 1 (Figure 2G) resulting in a complete loss of 
binding affinity, as shown for the R36W mutant above (Fig-</p>

<p>ure 4A). Although the R36K mutation retains the positive 
charge, we found it reduced the mutant MAX binding affin-
ity by &gt;30-fold (Figure 5E). Likewise, mutation at R35 to a 
hydrophobic residue (L) or a shorter side chain (H), which 
could affect interactions with the negatively charged DNA 
phosphate group and E32 side chain (Figure 2E), also re-
sulted in a total loss of binding (Figure 5E). An additional 
25% (n = 4) affected R60, which was again changed to a 
hydrophobic residue (W) or the smallest residue (G), which 
might introduce flexibility and affect protein stability. We 
predict that this might weaken overall DNA binding affinity 
by abolishing electrostatic interaction with the phosphate 
backbone (Figure 2J) as exemplified by the reduced bind-
ing affinity of the R60Q mutation (Figure 4E) described 
above. Two additional missense mutations were observed 
in the helical leucine zipper region (I71W and L94V) (Fig-</p>



<p>ure 5C and D), which might affect dimerization or other 
protein-protein interactions. 
The above data suggested that MAX inactiva-
tion plays an important role in the pathogenesis 
of at least some myelomas. As noted above, MYC 
translocation/overexpression is also common in multiple 
myeloma, and has been associated with a poorer outcome 
(52,53). We therefore next examined the relationship be-
tween MAX mutations and MYC expression and outcomes 
among MM patients. Interestingly, among the 643 patients 
for whom both mutation status and RNA-seq data were 
available, there was an inverse relationship between MYC 
expression and MAX status, in that tissue from patients 
harboring MAX alterations expressed significantly lower 
levels of MYC transcript than those with wild-type MAX 
(Figure 5F). Such patients are also trending towards a 
more favorable outcome; among the 764 patients for whom 
mutation status and outcomes data were available, the 24 
patients with MAX alterations had a significantly better 
prognosis, with a hazard ratio for overall survival of 0.35 
(Figure 5G), which may be a reflection of the tendency 
toward low MYC expression among this group of patients. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>DNA 5mC is a major epigenetic signal that acts to reg-
ulate chromatin structure and ultimately gene expression. 
The Tet-mediated 5mC oxidation products, 5hmC, 5fC and 
5caC are now recognized as an additional component of 
the 'methylome'. While accumulating evidence supports a 
role for 5hmC as a stable epigenetic mark, 5fC and 5caC 
are the preferred substrates among the five forms of cyto-
sine for excision by TDG and thus have been largely con-
sidered an intermediate in the demethylation cycle. Our re-
sults show that the DNA binding bHLH domain of MAX 
is responsive to all forms of modified CpG within its E-box 
recognition sequence, displaying the highest affinity for cog-
nate sequences containing a central 5caC and unmodified 
C, with reduced affinity for 5fC and much lower affinity for 
5mC and 5hmC. Taken at face value, this result could be 
interpreted to mean that the progressive Tet-mediated oxi-
dation of 5mC may be a way to titrate in transcriptional ac-
tivity in a graded and cyclical fashion, with the 5mC form of 
such sites being the 'off' position and Tet-mediated oxida-
tion steps a way of progressively increasing affinity for the 
binding site while moving towards 5caC (Figure 6). Given 
the similarities between the bHLH domains of MAX and 
its binding partners, and the structural conservation of the 
critical amino acids whether partnered with MYC or Mad 
(Mxd), it is likely that the ability to 'sense' the 5mC oxida-
tion state translates to most (if not all) MAX heterodimers 
and the extended MYC family of bHLH transcription fac-
tors. The balance between Tet-mediated generation of 5caC 
and TDG-mediated removal and replacement by unmod-
ified C could define an equilibrium state that ensures the 
maintenance of a favorable (5caC or C) platform for MAX 
binding and regulatory activity. Dynamic competition be-
tween MAX binding and the local action of de novo DNA 
methyltransferase(s) might then represent the switch back 
to the 'off' position. In this context, one hypothesis is that 
the reduced binding affinity to the C/5caC forms exhib-</p>

<p>ited by certain MAX variants (R36, R60) provides an in-
creased opportunity for TDG-mediated turnover and sub-
sequent methylation, whereas the H28 variant (H28R) with 
increased binding affinity may have the opposite effect. In 
all, these data raise the possibility that the role of DNA 
modification (methylation and/or oxidation) in regulating 
transcription factor activity may be more refined than a sim-
ple on-off switch. 
MAX and other transcription factors that can sense the 
oxidation status of 5mC and preferentially bind the Tet-
mediated oxidation products may play a role in continually 
recruiting Tet enzymes to their genomic targets to main-
tain their open, active status and/or to initiate a shift in 
cell state. Indeed, in the absence of Tet function, DNA 
methylation accumulates predominantly at enhancers and 
other DNase hypersensitive regions (55,56). To this end, 
Wilms tumor protein WT1, which displays a preference for 
C, 5mC or 5caC over the 5hmC or 5fC forms (21), physi-
cally interacts with Tet2 and may recruit Tet2 to its target 
genes and/or bind to the products of Tet2 enzymatic activ-
ity (57,58). Moreover, recent genome-wide mapping of full-
length Tet3 binding sites in mouse neural progenitor cells se-
lectively enriched for sequences containing an E-box motif 
(5 -TCACGTGA-3 ) that matches the recognition sequence 
of TFEB, another bHLH transcription factor (59) (Supple-
mentary Figure S3D). 
We provide evidence that for a subset of patients, so-
matic alterations in MAX play a role in the pathogenesis 
of multiple myeloma. An examination of the largest collec-
tion of multiple myeloma available to date showed MAX 
mutations to occur in ∼ 3% of cases, with missense mu-
tations affecting R35/R36, and/or nonsense mutations be-
ing the most frequent. These alterations are unlikely to be 
therapy-related but rather appear to occur early in disease 
progression as the majority of CoMMpass samples (and 
all of those detected with MAX mutations) are derived 
from newly diagnosed patients. The finding that many tu-
mors harbor nonsense mutations, start codon mutations, or 
deletion/rearrangements predicted to result in a loss of all 
or most of the MAX gene product (n = 10) and that several 
patients (n = 5) have more than one mutation strongly sug-
gests that it is the inactivation of MAX that contributes to 
myelomagenesis, similar to what has been observed in other 
settings (34-36). Our in vitro binding experiments showing 
that alteration at R36 (R36W/K), R35 (R35H/L) or R60 
(R60Q) (another one third of patients) significantly reduces 
or abolishes MAX DNA binding altogether is consistent 
with this suggestion. 
Interestingly, MAX mutations marked a subset of pa-
tients with low levels of MYC expression and a better prog-
nosis overall, as compared to those with wild-type MAX. 
One interpretation is that the consequences of MAX inac-
tivation are functionally redundant with that of MYC over-
expression in promoting myelomagenesis, but that the long-
term disease course of a MYC-promoted versus a MAX-
promoted myeloma ultimately differ. For example, when 
MAX is absent, MYC activity may go unrestrained. Analy-
sis of the genome-wide occupancy of MYC and MAX in a 
myeloma cell line in which MYC is translocated and over-
expressed (MM.1S (29)) indicates that whereas nearly all 
(97%) of MAX sites are co-occupied by MYC, only 3% </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 5 2405 </p>

<p>Figure 6. A hypothetical model of the cyclical impact of CpG modification on transcription factor binding. Schematic of chemical reactions of DNA 
cytosine methylation and 5mC oxidation. DNA methyltransferases convert a proportion of the cytosines (Cs) into 5mC in a S-adenosyl-L-methionine 
(AdoMet)-dependent reaction. The Tet dioxygenases then convert a fraction of 5mC to 5hmC, 5fC and 5caC in three consecutive Fe(II)-and ␣-ketoglutarate 
(␣KG)-dependent oxidation reactions without releasing any formaldehyde. The potential consequence of modifications is indicated by color: green for 
activities associated with an increased level of gene expression ('ON') and red for those tending to decrease the level of expression ('OFF'). </p>

<p>of MYC binding sites are co-occupied by MAX (Supple-
mentary Figure S5A and B). This is consistent with the re-
cent suggestions that once MYC's high affinity sites are sat-
urated, it can 'invade' other low affinity sites in areas of 
open chromatin, eventually including the majority of pro-
moters (29,60,61) potentially facilitated through binding to 
other factors (e.g. WDR5) (61,62). Loss of MAX may shift 
the balance towards these lower affinity, non-physiologic 
sites. It is interesting to note that whereas MYC-MAX co-
occupied sites are enriched in canonical E-box sequences, 
the MYC-only sites show reduced specificity for the central 
CpG (29) (Supplementary Figure S5C), which would poten-
tially remove any impact of CpG methylation status. Alter-
natively, loss of MAX function could promote myeloma-
genesis by alleviating MAX-mediated repression of select 
genes normally mediated by its interaction with other part-
ners. Ectopic expression of the repressive MAX partners 
directly antagonizes MYC-driven transformation in cell-
based assays, and deletion of certain partners (e.g. MNT) 
is sufficient to promote tumor formation in mouse models 
(63), and is observed in human leukemias (64,65). It is pos-
sible that both consequences contribute. 
Taken together, our data suggest that bHLH transcrip-
tion factors join a growing group of transcriptional regu-
lators that have adapted to respond to different cytosine 
modification states, potentially acting as direct epigenetic 
sensors to instruct downstream events. The TET enzymes 
are altered in human cancers, particularly hematologic ma-
lignancies, and are associated with altered genomic patterns 
of 5mC/5hmC (reviewed in (12,66)). Inactivating mutations 
in TET2 are observed in a wide variety of myeloid and lym-
phoid tumors, and although mutations in TET1/3 are rel-
atively rare, mice deficient in Tet1 or the combination of 
Tet1/Tet2 develop late-onset B-cell lymphomas that exhibit 
gene expression patterns consistent with human B-cell ma-
lignancies (67,68). Thus, the convergence of altered patterns 
of oxidized 5mC and acquired mutations in the factors that 
read them hint at a new level of epigenetic complexity in 
cancer progression. </p>

<p>ACCESSION NUMBER </p>

<p>The X-ray structure (coordinates and structure factor files) 
of MAX residues 22-107 with bound 5caC DNA has been 
submitted to PDB under accession number 5EYO. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank B. Baker of New England Biolabs for synthesiz-
ing the oligonucleotides. The Department of Biochemistry 
of Emory University School of Medicine supported the use 
of SER-CAT beamlines. We also thank Daniel Auclair and 
Joan Levy from the Multiple Myeloma Research Founda-
tion, the MMRF CoMMpass Network and Jonathan Keats 
(TGEN) for support and advice regarding the CoMMpass 
trial and associated data. 
Author Information: D.W. performed protein expression 
and purification, DNA binding assays and crystallization. 
H.H. performed X-ray data collection and structure deter-
mination. B.G.B. performed bioinformatics analysis; S.L., 
L.H.B. and P.M.V. participated in discussion and myeloma 
data analyses. X.Z., P.M.V. and X.C. organized and de-
signed the scope of the study. All were involved in analyzing 
data and in preparing the manuscript. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>National Institutes of Health (NIH) [GM049245-23 to X.C. 
and CA077337-15 to P.M.V.]; T.J. Martell Foundation [to 
L.H.B.]; Georgia Research Alliance Eminent Scholar [to 
X.C.]. The open access publication charge for this paper has 
been waived by Oxford University Press -NAR Editorial 
Board members are entitled to one free paper per year in 
recognition of their work on behalf of the journal. 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2017, Vol. 45, No. 5 2407 </p>



</text></tei>