<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5016904" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background and purpose -Body mass index (BMI) outside the 
normal range possibly affects the perioperative morbidity and 
mortality following total hip arthroplasty (THA) and total knee 
arthroplasty (TKA) in traditional care programs. We determined 
perioperative morbidity and mortality in such patients who were 
operated with the fast-track methodology and compared the 
levels with those in patients with normal BMI. 
Patients and methods -This was a prospective observational 
study involving 13,730 procedures (7,194 THA and 6,536 TKA 
operations) performed in a standardized fast-track setting. Com-
plete 90-day follow-up was achieved using national registries and 
review of medical records. Patients were grouped according to 
BMI as being underweight, of normal weight, overweight, obese, 
very obese, and morbidly obese. 
Results -Median length of stay (LOS) was 2 (IQR: 2-3) days 
in all BMI groups. 
30-day re-admission rates were around 6% for both THA 
(6.1%) and TKA (5.9%), without any statistically signifi cant dif-
ferences between BMI groups in univariate analysis (p &gt; 0.4), but 
there was a trend of a protective effect of overweight for both 
THA (p = 0.1) and TKA (p = 0.06). 
90-day re-admission rates increased to 8.6% for THA and 8.3% 
for TKA, which was similar among BMI groups, but there was 
a trend of lower rates in overweight and obese TKA patients (p 
= 0.08 and p = 0.06, respectively). When we adjusted for preop-
erative comorbidity, high BMI in THA patients (very obese and 
morbidly obese patients only) was associated with a LOS of &gt; 4 
days (p = 0.001), but not with re-admission. No such relationship 
existed for TKA. 
Interpretation -A fast-track setting resulted in similar length 
of hospital stay and re-admission rates regardless of BMI, except 
for very obese and morbidly obese THA patients. </p>

<p>■ </p>

<p>Body mass index (BMI) might possibly infl uence outcome 
after total hip arthroplasty (THA) and total knee arthroplasty 
(TKA). Underweight may be associated with malnutrition and 
comorbidities. In a large Danish study it was found (after hip 
replacement and knee replacement) be a risk factor for post-
operative ischemic stroke, acute myocardial infarction, and 
cardiovascular death-with higher mortality than in patients 
with normal BMI (Thornqvist et al. 2014). Also, underweight 
has been associated with re-admission after THA or TKA 
in general, and specifi cally for infection and hip dislocation 
(Alfonso et al. 2008, Zhang et al. 2012). 
Obesity of varying severity in TKA operations has been 
found to result in more complications and inferior objective 
and functional Knee Society scores (McElroy et al. 2013, Issa 
et al. 2013, Adhikary et al. 2015), but without any difference 
in length of hospital stay (LOS) (Issa et al. 2013). 
Also, in THA operations, obesity has resulted in smaller 
improvements in outcome scores and quality of life and more 
wound complications compared to normal weight, and higher 
BMI has also resulted in more re-admissions and reoperations 
(Haverkamp et al. 2011, Jameson et al. 2014, Liu et al. 2015). 
Prescribed weight loss may be diffi cult or impossible for 
patients to achieve and maintain, with or without arthroplasty 
(Ast et al. 2015), and even successful weight loss preopera-
tively-with or without bariatric surgery-may not reduce the 
possible complications associated with the subsequent arthro-
plasty operation (Inacio et al. 2014 a, b). Thus, the risk profi le 
appears to be increased with THA or TKA in overweight or 
obese patients, and even in previously obese patients. As some 
overweight/obese patients still need arthroplasty operations 
and because high BMI may only (to some extent) compromise 
the clinical outcome (Foster et al. 2015) or implant survival 
(Tai et al. 2014), it is important to assess the risks in different </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 466-472 </p>



<p>weight classes. As fast-track THA and TKA may offer the best 
available treatment, combining evidence-based clinical fea-
tures with organizational optimization and reduced morbidity 
and mortality (Husted 2012, Husted et al. 2014, Jørgensen et 
al. 2013, 2015), we determined perioperative morbidity and 
mortality levels in patients with BMIs outside the normal 
range who were operated with the fast-track methodology, and 
compared these levels to those in patients with normal BMI. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>This study was based on an ongoing study registry of preop-
erative patient characteristics run by the Lundbeck Foundation 
Center for Fast-track Hip and Knee Replacement Collabora-
tion (www.fthk.dk), and parts of the cohort have featured 
previously in other studies focusing on other aspects of post-
operative morbidity and risk factors (Jørgensen et al. 2013, 
2015). The current study cohort had surgery between January 
2010 and November 2013 in 8 large arthroplasty departments, 
each of which performed more than 400 primary arthroplas-
ties a year. 
The Lundbeck Foundation Center database (LCDB) pro-
spectively registers preoperative patient characteristics through 
a patient-reported questionnaire, with staff available for assis-
tance, and is registered at ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT01515670). 
The questionnaire is completed by all patients who are to have 
surgery at the participating departments. The only require-
ments for being one of the collaborating hospitals are having 
a documented median LOS of ≤ 3 days, including transfer to 
other departments, and discharge planned to the patient's own 
home. 
Data from the LCDB were subsequently merged with data 
from the Danish National Database of Reimbursed Prescrip-
tions for information on prescribed drugs before and after 
surgery, while information on LOS, 90-day re-admission, 
and mortality was acquired from the Danish National Patient 
Registry (DNPR). Reporting to the DNPR is mandatory and 
necessary in order to receive reimbursement from the govern-
ment, and it is independent of patient insurances, income, and 
geographic location, thus assuring complete follow-up. 
Optimized clinical features included using spinal anesthesia 
whenever possible, using small standard incisions (the medial 
parapatellar approach for TKA and the posterior approach for 
THA), using tranexamic acid, using local infi ltration analge-
sia (LIA) in TKA, not using drains, mobilization within a few 
hours after surgery, using multimodal opioid-sparing analge-
sia, having fi xed functional discharge criteria, and discharging 
directly to home (Husted 2012). 
As suggested by the World Health Organisation, patients 
can be classifi ed according to their BMI as being underweight 
(BMI &lt; 18.5), of normal weight (&gt; 18.5 and &lt; 25 ), overweight 
(&gt; 25 and &lt; 30 ), obese (&gt; 30 and &lt; 35 ), very obese (&gt; 35 and 
&lt; 40), and morbidly obese (&gt; 40). </p>

<p>Study objectives 
The main study objective was to determine the infl uence of dif-
ferent BMI groups on LOS of &gt; 4 days, re-admissions within 
30 and 90 days, and specifi ed complications resulting in either 
LOS of &gt; 4 days or re-admission. Secondarily, we evaluated 
the association between BMI groups and the same outcomes, 
but adjusting for differences in baseline characteristics using 
multiple logistic regression. 
Specifi ed complications of interest that resulted in re-admis-
sions were defi ned according to the existing literature (Husted 
et al. 2008, 2015, Jørgensen et al. 2013, 2014, 2015) and com-
prised: thromboembolic episodes (DVT, PE, arterial embo-
lism), myocardial infarction, acute coronary syndrome, angina 
pectoris, ischemic stroke/TCI, deep infection (requiring sur-
gery), wound/superfi cial infection (managed without surgery 
below the fascia), any intraoperative complications includ-
ing fracture and arterial lesions, any early prosthesis-related 
complications, and periprosthetic fractures with or without 
trauma-and for THA, also dislocation. Mortality within 90 
days was registered based on the nationwide civil registry. </p>

<p>Statistics 
All percentages are reported, including 95% confi dence inter-
vals (CIs). Continuous data are reported as median and inter-
quartile ranges (due to skewing of the data). Comparisons of 
categorical data were done using chi-squared test. Compari-
sons of re-admission rates were done on a per-procedure basis, 
regardless of whether patients had multiple re-admissions. 
However, evaluation of specifi c complications of interest 
included all cases with LOS of &gt; 4 days or re-admission. For 
multiple logistic regression analysis, we included variables 
previously found to infl uence outcome after fast-track THA 
and TKA (use of walking aids, preoperative anemia etc.) or 
related to increased BMI (hypertension, diabetes etc.). The 
model included 11 variables, with hospital of surgery added 
as a random effect. Analyses were done with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 20.</rs>. 
95% CI values for percentages were calculated at http://vas-
sarstats.net/. Any p-value of &lt; 0.05 was considered signifi cant. </p>

<p>Ethics 
No approval from the National Ethics Committee was nec-
essary, as this was a non-interventional observational study. 
Permission to store and review patient data was obtained from 
the Danish National Board of Health (entry no. 3-3013-56/1/ 
HKR) and the Danish Data Protection Agency (entry no. 
20047-58-0015). </p>

<p>Results 
The total cohort involved 13,775 procedures, 45 of which 
(0.3%) had data on BMI missing in the LCDB and were there-
fore excluded. Thus, the study analysis was done on 13,730 
procedures: 7,194 THAs and 6,536 TKAs. Most patients were </p>



<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 466-472 </p>

<p>overweight with a trend of knee patients being more obese 
than hip patients, and with only a small proportion of each 
being underweight (1.1% for THA and 0.4% for TKA) (Table 
1). 
Median LOS was 2 (IQR: 2-3) days in all BMI groups, with 
slightly higher mean values for outliers being underweight or 
morbidly obese for both THA and TKA (p = 0.5 and p = 0.1, 
respectively). The proportion of THA patients with a LOS of 
more than 4 days increased (from that in patients with normal 
weight; around 8%) with increasing BMI, although this was 
only statistically signifi cant for very obese patients (around 
13%; p = 0.03). In other overweight patients, a smaller frac-
tion had a LOS of ≤ 4 days (6%; p &lt; 0.02). The same trend was 
seen for TKA patients: in the group of patients with normal 
weight, 11% had a LOS of &gt; 4 days as opposed to only 8% in 
the overweight and obese group (p = 0.01). </p>

<p>The greatest proportion of patients with a LOS of &gt; 4 
days-for both THA (17%) and TKA (13%)-was found in 
the underweight group, but this was not statistically signifi -
cant (with small numbers; p &gt; 0.1). For both procedures, the 
median LOS for underweight patients with a LOS of &gt; 4 days 
was similar (p &gt; 0.5). 
30-day re-admission rates were 6.1% for THA and 5.9% 
for TKA, without any signifi cant differences between BMI 
groups in univariate analysis (p &gt; 0.4), but there was a trend of 
a protective effect of overweight for both THA (p = 0.1) and 
TKA (p = 0.06). 
90-day re-admission rates increased to 8.6% for the THA 
group and to 8.3% for the TKA group. This was similar 
between BMI groups, but there was a maintained trend of 
lower values for overweight and obese TKA patients (p = 0.08 
and p = 0.06, respectively). 
No increased risk of the specifi ed complications of interest 
(thromboembolic episodes, myocardial infarction, acute coro-
nary syndrome, angina pectoris, ischemic stroke/TCI, deep 
or superfi cial infection, periprosthetic fractures, and disloca-
tion) was found with increasing BMI. The distribution of BMI 
groups with all specifi ed reasons for a LOS of &gt; 4 days and 
re-admission can be seen in Table 2 (see Supplementary data). 
Table 3 shows the combined proportions of patients in each 
BMI group with a LOS of more than 4 days, with re-admis-
sion within 90 days, and with specifi c complications. 
After adjusting for differences in relevant preoperative char-
acteristics, higher BMI (very obese and morbidly obese only) 
was found to be associated with a LOS of &gt; 4 days, but not 
with re-admission for THA. In contrast, no associations with 
LOS of &gt; 4 days, re-admission within 90 days, or specifi c 
complications were found for TKA (Tables 4 and 5). 
Overall 90-day mortality was 0.2% following THA and 
0.1% following TKA, with the small numbers not allowing 
detailed statistical analysis between BMI groups. </p>

<p>Table 1. Distribution of grouped BMI on type of procedure </p>

<p>Joint of surgery/BMI 
Number of patients Fraction </p>

<p>Hip, median: 26.6, IQR: 24.0-29.7 
&lt;18.5 
77 
1.1 
18.5-24.9 
2,396 
33.3 
25.0-29.9 
3,008 
41.8 
30.0-34.9 
1,329 
18.5 
35.0-39.9 
299 
4.2 
&gt;39.9 
85 
1.2 
Total 
7194 
100 
Knee, median: 28.9, IQR: 25.8-32.6 
&lt;18.5 
29 
0.4 
18.5-24.9 
1,250 
19.1 
25.0-29.9 
2,524 
38.6 
30.0-34.9 
1,745 
26.7 
35.0-39.9 
699 
10.7 
&gt;39.9 
289 
4.4 
Total 
6,536 
100 </p>

<p>IQR: Interquartile range </p>

<p>Table 3. Fractions of patients with a LOS &gt; 4 days , 90 days readmissions and specifi c conditions according to BMI 
group. Values are n (%; 95% confi dence intervals) </p>

<p>Joint BMI 
LOS &gt; 4 days 
p-value 90-days readmissions p-value Specifi c complications p-value </p>

<p>THA 
&lt; 18.5 
10 (13.0; 7.2-22.3) 
0.1 
3 (3.4; 1.3-11) 
0.2 
2 (2.6; 0.7-9.0) 
0.6 
18.5-24.9 
189 (7.9; 6.9-9.0) 
-
209 (8.7; 7.7-9.9) 
-
113 (4.7; 3.9-5.6) 
-
25.0-29.9 
188 (6.3; 5.4-7.2) 
0.02 
237 (7.9; 7.0-8.9) 
0.3 
135 (4.5; 3.8-5.3) 
0.7 
30.0-34.9 
98 (7.4; 6.1-8.9) 
0.6 
125 (9.4; 8.0-11) 
0.5 
83 (6.3; 5.1-7.7) 
0.05 
35.0-39.9 
35 (11.7; 8.5-15.9) 
0.02 
35 (11.7; 8.5-16) 
0.09 
21 (7.0; 4.6-10.5) 
0.08 
≥ 40.0 
11 ( 12.9; 7.4-21.7) 
0.09 
9 (10.6; 5.7-19) 
0.6 
7 (8.2; 4.1-16.0) 
0.2 
TKA 
&lt; 18.5 
5 (17.2; 7.6-34.6) 
0.3 
4 (5.2; 2.0-13) 
0.5 
0 (0.0; 0.0-4.8) 
1 
18.5-24.9 
141 (11.3; 9.6-13.2) 
-
120 (9.6; 8.1-11) 
-
33 (2.6; 1.9-3.7) 
-
25.0-29.9 
213 (8.4; 7.4-9.6) 
0.005 
200 (7.9; 6.9-9.0) 
0.08 
47 (1.9; 1.4-2.5) 
0.2 
30.0-34.9 
145 (8.3; 7.1-9.7) 
0.006 
133 (7.6; 6.5-9.0) 
0.06 
29 (1.7; 1.2-2.4) 
0.06 
35.0-39.9 
70 (10.0; 8.0-12.5) 
0.4 
66 (9.4; 7.5-12) 
0.9 
16 (2.3; 1.4-3.7) 
0.6 
≥ 40.0 
35 ( 11.7; 8.6-15.9) 
0.7 
22 (7.4; 4.9-11) 
0.3 
11 (3.7; 2.1-6.5) 
0.3 </p>

<p>BMI: body mass index THA: total hip arthroplasty TKA: total knee arthroplasty. Comparisons are vs. BMI of 18.5-24.9 </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 466-472 </p>



<p>Table 4. Multiple logistic regression THA (n = 6,809) </p>

<p>LOS &gt; 4 days (n = 502) 
90-days readmission (n = 584) Specifi c complications (n = 336) 
Variable 
OR 
95%CI 
p-value 
OR 
95%CI 
p-value 
OR 
95%CI 
p-value </p>

<p>BMI 
&lt; 0.001 
0.1 
0.01 
&lt; 18.5 
1.19 0.55-2.59 
0.7 
0.4 
0.11-1.20 
0.1 
0.47 0.11-2.00 
0.3 
18.5-24.9 
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
25.0-29.9 
0.96 0.76-1.21 
0.7 
0.93 0.75-1.14 
0.5 
1.02 0.78-1.35 
0.9 
30.0-34.9 
1.28 0.97-1.21 
0.09 
1.17 0.91-1.50 
0.2 
1.55 1.13-2.11 
0.006 
35.0-39.9 
2.10 1.37-3.23 
0.001 
1.30 0.85-1.96 
0.2 
1.83 1.10-3.04 
0.02 
&gt; 39.9 
3.23 1.58-6.59 
0.001 
1.24 0.57-2.70 
0.6 
1.65 0.64-4.29 
0.3 
Age/year 
1.05 1.03-1.06 &lt; 0.001 
1.03 1.02-1.04 &lt; 0.001 
1.03 1.01-1.04 &lt; 0.001 
Male vs female 
0.90 0.72-1.11 
0.3 
1.10 0.91-1.33 
0.3 
0.97 0.77-1.24 
0.8 
Living 
&lt; 0.001 
0.8 
0.7 
With others 
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
Alone 
1.78 1.45-2.20 &lt; 0.001 
1.05 0.86-1.27 
0.6 
1.10 0.86-1.34 
0.5 
Institution 
1.86 0.87-4.00 
0.1 
1.18 0.53-2.62 
0.7 
1.31 0.50-3.45 
0.6 
Walking aid 
2.31 1.87-2.85 &lt; 0.001 
1.59 1.31-1.93 &lt; 0.001 
1.26 0.97-1.62 
0.08 
Pre-op. anemia 
1.98 1.58-2.48 &lt; 0.001 
1.44 1.15-1.80 
0.002 
1.48 1.12-1.20 
0.007 
Diabetes 
0.4 
0.4 
0.3 
No DM 
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
IDDM 
1.48 0.85-2.58 
0.1 
1.40 0.83-2.37 
0.2 
1.15 0.58-2.28 
0.7 
NIDDM 
1.07 0.75-1.53 
0.7 
0.99 0.72-1.38 
1 
0.70 0.44-1.12 
0.1 
Hypertension 
0.80 0.65-0.99 
0.04 
1.13 0.94-1.37 
0.2 
1.10 0.86-1.39 
0.5 
Anticoagulants 
1.20 0.81-1.78 
0.4 
1.33 0.93-1.90 
0.1 
0.57 0.33-0.80 
0.04 
Cardiac disease 
1.53 1.15-2.04 
0.003 
1.42 1.10-1.85 
0.008 
1.72 1.25-2.36 
0.001 
Pulmonary disease 
1.40 1.04-1.87 
0.03 
1.42 1.10-1.85 
0.008 
1.20 0.83-1.74 
0.3 
Psychiatric disorder 
1.82 1.44-2.31 &lt; 0.001 
1.54 1.22-1.93 &lt; 0.001 
1.31 0.97-1.77 
0.08 </p>

<p>THA: total hip arthroplasty, LOS: length of stay, OR: odds ratio, CI: confi dence interval, BMI: body mass index DM: 
diabetes mellitus, IDDM: insulin dependent diabetes mellitus, NIDDM: non-insulin dependent diabetes mellitus. </p>

<p>Table 5. Multiple logistic regression TKA (n = 6,123) </p>

<p>LOS &gt; 4 days (n = 559) 
90-days readmission (n = 499) Specifi c complications (n = 122) 
Variable 
OR 
95%CI 
p-value 
OR 
95%CI 
p-value 
OR 
95%CI 
p-value </p>

<p>BMI 
0.2 
0.1 
1 
&lt; 18.5 
1.96 0.66-5.85 
0.2 
1.94 0.64-5.89 
0.2 
0.67 0.06-6.99 
0.7 
18.5-24.9 
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
25.0-29.9 
0.78 0.60-0.99 
0.049 
0.84 0.66-1.09 
0.2 
0.93 0.65-1.32 
0.7 
30.0-34.9 
0.85 0.65-1.12 
0.3 
0.76 0.57-1.01 
0.06 
0.91 0.62-1.35 
0.6 
35.0-39.9 
1.08 0.76-1.53 
0.7 
0.93 0.66-1.33 
0.7 
1.02 0.62-1.67 
0.9 
&gt; 39.9 
1.04 0.64-1.69 
0.9 
0.57 0.33-0.99 
0.046 
1.19 0.62-2.26 
0.6 
Age/year 
1.04 1.02-1.05 &lt; 0.001 
1.01 1.00-1.02 
0.04 
1.01 0.99-1.02 
0.2 
Male vs female 
1.01 0.82-1.24 &lt; 0.001 
1.31 1.07-1.59 
0.008 
1.10 0.84-1.44 
0.5 
Living 
&lt; 0.001 
0.8 
0.7 
With others 
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
Alone 
1.60 1.31-2.00 &lt; 0.001 
1.05 0.85-1.28 
0.7 
0.98 0.74-1.30 
0.9 
Institution 
1.21 0.37-3.97 
0.7 
3.15 1.20-8.25 
0.02 
0.64 0.07-6.35 
0.7 
Walking aid 
2.43 1.98-2.98 &lt; 0.001 
1.66 1.34-2.06 &lt; 0.001 
1.27 0.93-1.73 
0.1 
Pre-op. anemia 
1.70 1.34-2.15 &lt; 0.001 
1.41 1.10-1.82 
0.007 
0.96 0.65-1.43 
0.8 
Diabetes 
0.4 
0.4 
0.3 
No DM 
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
1 
-
-
IDDM 
1.48 0.94-2.33 
0.09 
1.62 1.04-2.53 
0.03 
1.24 0.63-2.44 
0.5 
NIDDM 
1.23 0.91-1.65 
0.2 
1.23 0.92-1.66 
0.2 
0.98 0.63-1.53 
0.9 
Hypertension 
1.08 0.89-1.32 
0.4 
1.10 0.90-1.34 
0.4 
0.92 0.70-1.23 
0.6 
Anticoagulants 
1.60 1.10-2.35 
0.02 
1.25 0.84-1.86 
0.3 
0.97 0.52-1.79 
0.9 
Cardiac disease 
1.26 0.95-1.67 
0.1 
1.23 0.93-1.63 
0.2 
1.17 0.78-1.77 
0.4 
Pulmonary disease 
1.35 0.99-1.83 
0.05 
1.18 1.36-2.41 &lt; 0.001 
1.29 0.84-1.98 
0.2 
Psychiatric disorder 
2.11 1.70-2.62 &lt; 0.001 
1.47 1.16-1.85 
0.001 
1.26 0.91-1.75 
0.2 </p>

<p>For legends, see Table 4 </p>



<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 466-472 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Fast-track hip and knee arthroplasty reduces morbidity and 
mortality compared to longer and more conventional hospital 
stays (Malviya et al. 2011, Khan et al. 2014). It also results 
in favorable safety profi les regarding LOS, morbidity, and re-
admissions in particular high-risk patients (Husted et al. 2015, 
Jørgensen et al. 2013, 2015). 
The distribution of BMI in this large multicenter cohort of 
unselected patients operated with the fast-track methodology 
showed that one-third of hip arthroplasty patients and only 
one-fi fth of knee arthroplasty patients had a normal BMI 
with the latter being heavier. We found that the median LOS 
was 2 days in all BMI groups, but the proportion of patients 
who stayed more than 4 days was signifi cantly higher in the 
very obese THA patients-whereas being a little overweight 
appeared to be protective, as this group of patients generally 
had a shorter LOS. The same trend was seen in TKA patients, 
as the proportion of patients in the overweight and obese 
groups who stayed more than 4 days was less than in the nor-
mal-BMI group. A possible explanation for this fi nding would 
be higher muscle volume in the slightly to moderately over-
weight patients, facilitating earlier fulfi llment of the strictly 
functional discharge criteria (Husted 2012)-whereas the very 
obese patients might be limited in this by having too much 
body weight, as one study found postoperative improvements 
in quadriceps function following TKA to be slower in patients 
with higher BMIs (Pua et al. 2015) and a similar underlying 
mechanism could explain the same fi nding in THA. As strictly 
functional discharge criteria were used, and reduced muscle 
strength has been identifi ed as being 1 of 3 main reasons for 
delayed discharge (the other 2 being pain and dizziness), the 
slower regaining of quadriceps strength may result in delayed 
functional recovery and therefore in a longer time to discharge 
(Husted et al. 2011). 
Of the BMI groups, the underweight group of patients 
had the greatest (but statistically insignifi cant) proportion of 
patients who stayed longer than 4 days, although over 80% 
still managed a median LOS of 2 days. No large studies have 
involved this group before. In the literature there has only 
been 1 study, in 20 patients, on the outcome in underweight 
THA patients with the fi nding of an increased risk of disloca-
tion (Alfonso et al. 2008). We found no association between 
being underweight and having a LOS of &gt; 4 days, re-admis-
sion after &lt; 90 days, or mortality-for either fast-track THA 
or fast-track TKA-and no correlation with any particular 
complication, including dislocation. A registry study found 
U-shaped risk associations between BMI and perioperative 
cardiovascular events and mortality, which were highest in 
the underweight group, in THA and TKA, suggesting that this 
was a subpopulation at risk (Thornqvist et al. 2014). 
In the present fast-track study, multiple logistic regression 
analysis showed an association between BMI of THA patients 
and a LOS of more than 4 days, manifested by a higher odds </p>

<p>ratio (OR) for longer stays in the very obese (where OR was 
doubled) and in the morbidly obese (where OR was 3 times 
higher). This contrasts with the results of a smaller fast-track 
study, where BMI was not associated with LOS (den Hartog et 
al. 2015), but it is in accordance with fi ndings in other studies 
(Bradley et al. 2014, Inneh et al. 2015). 
In fast-track TKA, high BMI was not associated with longer 
LOS. This is in accordance with the results of most previously 
published studies on conventional stays (Issa et al. 2013), and 
shows that BMI does indeed not affect LOS-as the studies 
with longer stays may have concealed a "hidden" difference 
that was not apparent because all patients were staying longer. 
A nationwide study involving 1,777,068 primary TKAs found 
a slightly but statistically signifi cantly longer LOS in morbidly 
obese TKA patients (3.6 days) than in non-obese patients (3.5 
days) in non-fast-track settings (D'Apuzzo et al. 2015). 
In light of the previously published meta-analyses showing 
more complications and re-admissions in the obese patients, 
it is both interesting and reassuring that in this large, multi-
center cohort of unselected patients who were operated in the 
fast-track setting, we found that BMI did not affect 30-day 
re-admission rates, which were around 6% for both THA and 
TKA. Also, BMI did not affect 90-day re-admission rates, 
although there was near-statistical signifi cance in overweight 
and obese TKA patients, whereas the groups of very obese 
and morbidly obese patients did not have more re-admissions 
than the other BMI groups. This contrasts with most of the 
published studies, where more conventional pathways were 
followed without strict adherence to fast-track principles with 
optimization of both evidence-based clinical features and 
logistics (see Material and methods). A meta-analysis on the 
potential infl uence of a BMI of greater than 30 on outcome 
after TKA has found substantially higher complication rates in 
obese and morbidly obese patients than in non-obese patients 
(15% and 22% as compared to 9%) (McElroy et al. 2013). 
Also, a cohort study on the clinical outcome of TKA patients 
(comparing those with a BMI of between 30 and 40 with those 
with a BMI of less than 30) found higher complication rates 
in the former group (11% vs. 4%), but without any signifi -
cant difference in LOS (Issa et al. 2013). Also, in obese THA 
patients, smaller improvements in outcome scores and more 
wound complications have been found. In patients who were 
more obese, even reduced outcomes in function and quality 
of life, more wound complications, more re-admissions, and 
more reoperations were found (Jameson et al. 2014). A recent 
meta-analysis on the infl uence of obesity on the outcome of 
THA also found that obese patients have more complications 
in general and more dislocations and deep infections in par-
ticular-while having longer operations, similar LOS, and 
reduced functional outcome than non-obese patients (Liu et 
al. 2015). These fi ndings in patients who are operated in more 
conventional settings contrast with our fi ndings from a fast-
track setting, where no difference in specifi c complications 
was found between different BMI groups. </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 466-472 </p>



<p>Our study confi rmed the well-known risk factors for pro-
longed hospital stay, re-admission, and specifi c complications 
that have been reported by other authors (Husted et al. 2008, 
Jørgensen et al. 2013, 2014, 2015, den Hartog et al. 2015, 
Husted et al. 2015). Age, preoperative use of walking aids, 
anemia, diabetes, hypertension, use of anticoagulants, and 
cardiopulmonary and psychiatric disease may infl uence both 
LOS and re-admission rates; these considerations are outside 
the scope of the present study and have been evaluated and 
discussed in previous articles from our group (Husted et al. 
2008, 2015, Jørgensen et al. 2013, 2014, 2015). 
We found no association between BMI and 90-day re-admis-
sion in fast-track THA in general, and only an association in 
obese and very obese patients regarding particular complica-
tions, though not dislocation. This contrasts with the results of 
other studies where there was an increased risk of dislocation 
with increasing BMI (Liu et al. 2015). 
Specifi cally, we found no increased risk of DVT/PE, infec-
tion/wound problems, or periprosthetic fracture associated 
with increasing BMI. This is in contrast to most-but not 
all (D'Apuzzo et al. 2015)-other studies using more con-
ventional pathways, which have found associations between 
higher BMI and a higher incidence of venous thromboembolic 
episodes (Haverkamp et al. 2011, Zhang et al. 2015) and of 
infection/wound problems (McElroy et al. 2013, Jameson et 
al. 2014, D'Apuzzo et al. 2015, Liu et al. 2015). Although 
technical errors in the obese TKA patients (due to diffi cult 
exposure and procedure) could be expected to result in more 
periprosthetic fractures, we found no association between 
higher BMI and periprosthetic fracture, as did others also not 
(Haverkamp et al. 2011). Other studies have found increased 
mortality associated with higher BMI, especially in morbidly 
obese patients (Thornqvist et al. 2014, D'Apuzzo et al. 2015). 
We cannot confi rm this fi nding in fast-track surgery, but the 
numbers were small, complicating interpretation. 
For fast-track TKA patients, we found no association 
between BMI and a LOS of more than 4 days, re-admission 
within 90 days, or particular complications-although a curi-
ous protective effect of being morbidly obese was seen on 
re-admission. While we cannot explain the latter fi nding, it 
is reassuring to see that there is no safety signal for any BMI 
group in TKA patients undergoing fast-track surgery. This is 
not in line with other recently published studies, which have 
found increased morbidity with higher BMI (Issa et al. 2013, 
McElroy et al. 2013, Adhikary et al. 2015). 
Thus, most studies on patients who were operated in more 
conventional settings have shown higher morbidity in the 
obese, the very obese, and the morbidly obese than in non-
obese patients. Overall, it appears that the fast-track method-
ology may protect against the increased risk probably-due to 
a combination of improved perioperative care, pain treatment, 
and early mobilization. 
We acknowledge that the present study had some limita-
tions. First of all, no PROMs or objective data on function are </p>

<p>reported, as we concentrated solely on LOS and complications 
necessitating re-admission. However, in Demark the unique 
registries ensure complete follow-up, and the basis of achiev-
ing a good functional result is to avoid severe complications 
that result in re-admission. Secondly, the numbers were small 
regarding underweight patients (77 THA patients (1.1%) and 
29 TKA patients (0.4%)) and morbidly obese patients (85 
THA patients (1.2%) and 289 TKA patients (4.4%)), making 
the statistical conclusions less robust and increasing the width 
of the confi dence intervals. Nonetheless, we did have enough 
patients and events to justify adjustment for multiple variables 
previously found to infl uence outcome after fast-track THA 
and TKA. In conclusion, higher BMI (very obese patients 
and morbidly obese patients only) in THA is associated with 
a slightly higher risk of having a LOS of more than 4 days, 
but not with re-admissions, whereas no such relationship 
existed for TKA. The fast-track methodology therefore pro-
tects against the higher morbidity found with higher BMI in 
more conventional settings. Furthermore, BMI should not be 
a limiting factor for THA or TKA, and surgery in a fast-track 
setting is a safe way to reduce the risk of complications and 
re-admission, irrespective of BMI. </p>

<p>Supplementary data 
Table 2 is available at the Acta Orthopaedica website (www. 
actaorthop.org), identifi cation number 9979. </p>

<p>HH, CCJ, KG, and HK designed the study. CCJ gathered the data and HH, 
CCJ, KG, and HK analyzed it. HH wrote the initial draft and all the authors 
revised it. </p>

<p>This work was sponsored by a grant from the Lundbeck Foundation, which 
had no infl uence on any part of the study or on the content of the paper. </p>





<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2016; 87 (5): 466-472 </p>



</text></tei>