<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5407229" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background: In order to provide a better healthcare education to the society, health care students should have an 
acceptable electronic health (E-Health) literacy. 
Objective: The aim of this study was to assess the level of E-Health literacy of Medicine and Health Sciences 
university students in Mashhad, Iran. 
Methods: This cross-sectional study was performed on 192 students of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences 
using a validated Persian translate of the E-Health literacy scale (P-EHEALS) questionnaire in 2016. 
Demographic data including age, monthly income, level of education, preference of website for obtaining health 
related information and minutes of Internet use per day were obtained from the subjects. Independent-samples t-
test and analysis of variance (ANOVA) were used for comparison between groups, and Pearson correlation 
coefficient and linear regression were used to assess the correlation between study parameters and EHEALS 
score using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">21</rs>. 
Results: A total of 192 (67.2% female and 32.8% male) subjects with mean age of 24.71±5.30 years participated 
in the study. Mean P-EHEALS score of the subjects was 28.21±6.95. There was a significant difference in P-
EHEALS score between genders (p&lt;0.001), department (p=0.001), education level (p&lt;0.001) and health status 
(p=0.003) as well as monthly income (p=0.03), website preference categories (p=0.02). Male students were 
significantly more likely to gain higher P-EHEALS scores. 
Electronic physician </p>

<p>Page 3967 </p>

<p>individuals have the capacity to obtain, process, and understand basic health information and services needed to 
make appropriate health decisions" (4). With the increased usage of the Internet, electronic health literacy (e-Health) 
has become the center of attention for health care professionals (2). E-health literacy is defined as "the ability to 
seek, find, understand, and appraise health information from electronic sources, and apply the knowledge gained to 
addressing or solving a health problem" (5). </p>

<p>Unlike traditional health literacy, which is mainly based on basic literacy skills including the ability to speak and 
write language as well as to read and understand written passages, e-health literacy encompasses six core skills 
(traditional literacy, health literacy, information literacy, scientific literacy, media literacy and computer literacy). 
Therefore e-health literacy is under influence of a variety of factors including age, gender, level of education, 
availability and accessibility of Internet and income (6, 7). Although health literacy is an important issue for the 
public, health care providers should also learn to use the basic skills to develop and use the electronic sources in 
order to implement better standards of health services (8, 9). In the United States, there is a constant supervision on 
the content and quality of sources of health information (10). Besides this supervision, the American Medical 
Association has published guidelines for patients in order to educate them on how they should evaluate and use the 
Internet for their medical and health inquiries (10). Unlike the United States, such a system does not exist in Iran and 
therefore there is a high probability that the information spread in the social media be contaminated with myths and 
rumors instead of evidence based recommendations (11). It has been shown that misinformation may play a negative 
role in health beliefs and behavior of individuals (11, 12). Health care providers, as reliable sources of information, 
should be aware of the ways to evaluate the sources of information besides basic knowledge of Internet use and E-
Health literacy (13). This knowledge will help health care providers address issues and misinformation in the social 
media as well as workplace and therefore provide a better health education to their target groups (14). This 
education should start from basic university level (15). Previous studies found that the level of e-Health literacy of 
undergraduate health students was low and that they felt the need for improving their skills in e-Health literacy (16- 18). Studies have also shown that university students lack the skills in identifying valuable sources for their 
information and mainly use low level sources (14, 19). Besides, studies have also shown that university students 
gained the required skills in obtaining information by experience (14, 19). It was also shown that even in the North 
American and European countries, E-Health related education is only provided to students of medical fields, and 
mainly doctors and specialists and students of other medical related fields are ignored while, there is a lack for such 
education even in doctoral and specialist level in developing countries (15). Therefore, there is a global attempt to 
improve the E-Health literacy of students of medicine and medical related fields in order to tackle future global 
health education issues (15). Based on the previous researches, the Internet penetration rate was reported to be 55% 
in Iran and the usage of the Internet in Iran was reported to be 45% (20). In another study, 98% of Iranians between 
the ages of 20 and 30 years were using the Internet (21). This data suggests a high accessibility to the Internet for 
Iranian youth at post-secondary education level. Regarding the availability of the internet, students need to acquire 
other skills to benefit from the health information in the Internet. On the other hand, it was shown that Iranian 
Internet users trusted in the lifestyle modification information provided in unofficial sources including Facebook 
more than governmental sources (22). Similar to the studies in developed and developing countries, Iranian 
university students relied on low level websites for obtaining their information needs (23). Regarding the fact that 
Iranian medicine and healthcare providers deal with a population that trusts more in Internet sources that have higher 
probability of conducting misinformation, it is crucial for students who study in Medicine and Health Sciences to be 
aware of the proper use of Internet sources, and to evaluate their validity and credibility despite an effective 
supervision on the content of Internet sources of health information. Due to the scarcity of data regarding the basic 
E-Health literacy of Iranian Medicine and Health Science students, this study was conducted to assess the level of E-
Health literacy and its required skills and influencing factors on E-Health literacy among Mashhad Medicine and 
Health Sciences. </p>

<p>2. Material and Methods 
2.1. Study design 
This study was a pilot study for assessing the E-Health literacy of Medicine and Health Sciences university students 
in Mashhad, Iran in order to identify whether the E-Health literacy of Mashhad Medicine and Health Sciences 
students were adequate for their future career. This cross-sectional study was conducted in the Mashhad University 
of Medical Sciences. Students from all fields of education in this university were enrolled in the study. This study 
was approved by the Ethical Committee of the Mashhad University of Medical Sciences. The data collection was 
performed on September 3rd 2016 and ended on October 4th 2016. Based on the previously published data on E -
Health literacy of university students in developing countries and lack of curricular education programs in the field </p>

<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>



<p>of E-Health, it is hypothesized that the E-Health literacy of the Medicine and Health Sciences university students is 
low. Unfortunately, no cut-off for E-Health literacy scores have been provided and researchers used their own 
interpretation based on the current and previous observations. Sample size was calculated based on the formula 
presented by Viechtbauer et al. on sample size for pilot study (24). Using 0.95 as the confidence level and 0.02 as 
probability (based on the previously reported 2-8% range of nursing students who reported unconfident in related 
skills to E-Health literacy, the largest calculated sample size was 149 subjects. Considering 30% drop out, the final 
manuscript was 194 subjects (25). </p>

<p>2.2. Subjects 
The reason for selecting Medicine and Health Sciences university students was due to the fact that these students 
were going to deal with healthcare seekers who have access to the Internet and may not be aware of the 
identification of reliable sources, and ask their healthcare providers regarding beneficial sources for their further 
information requirements. Medicine and Health Sciences graduates should be able to identify, validate and 
recommend trustworthy sources to their clients in order to improve their health information level and prevent them 
from receiving rumors and fiction instead of academic material. All volunteered university students who were 
studying in a field related to Medicine or Health Sciences were eligible to participate in the study. Inclusion criteria 
were being registered as an Iranian citizen, holding a current student position in the university and willing to 
participate in the study. Exclusion criteria were physical disability which interfered with Internet and computer use 
including blindness, paralysis and dyslexia. Subjects were chosen randomly from the list of Students obtained from 
the university education affairs office. Subjects were approached by the researcher and were informed about the aim 
and overview of the research. Subjects who were willing to participate in the study signed a written informed 
consent form. </p>

<p>2.3. Instruments 
Study subjects were provided with a socio-demographic questionnaire regarding age, department, level of education, 
household income and their website preference regarding Internet material, whether they prefer to use popular 
websites that have health information from unknown sources (general websites) or to refer to registered and trusted 
sources for health information including university and governmental health related websites which specifically 
provide health care information with scientific and evidence based references (specific sources). Subjects were also 
required to fill the Persian translate of the e-Health Literacy Scale (P-EHEALS) questionnaire. Similar to the E-
Health questionnaire, P-EHEALS questionnaire consists of 8 items, where subjects are required to score each item 
based on a 5 point Likert-scale ranging from 1 indicating strongly disagree to 5 which indicates strongly agree. 
Therefore, the P-EHEALS score would range from 8 to 40. The higher P-EHEALS score indicates higher E-Health 
literacy. EHEALS is a questionnaire which is designed to assess eHealth literacy by measuring skills in finding, 
analyzing and implementing eHealth to health problems (5). An 8-item short form of this questionnaire was 
previously generated, and was found to be user friendly (5). This questionnaire, which is able to assess e-Health 
literacy, has been previously validated in different populations and countries (5, 26-30). The validity and reliability 
of the EHEALS questions were previously reported ranges of 0.92-0.93 and 0.63-0.93 respectively (5, 27, 29). In a 
study on a separate sample of Mashhad University students, the validity and reliability of the P-EHEALS 
questionnaire was assessed. The construct validity of the P-EHEALS questionnaire was assessed in an interview 
with 10 health education experts based on content validity ratio (CVR), and content validity index (CVI) and 
construct validity were assessed in as study on 164 university students. Exploratory factor analysis revealed two 
distinct categories in the questions (first 4 vs. second 4 questions). Confirmatory factor analysis revealed acceptable 
validity for P-EHEALS. The reliability of the P-EHEALS questionnaire was assessed using Cronbach's alpha 
(overall Cronbach's alpha was 0.89) </p>

<p>2.4. Statistical Analysis 
Data was analyzed using IBM© <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS©</rs> Statistics version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">21</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM© Corp</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA). Continuous 
variables were checked for normality using the Shapiro-Wilk test. Mean and standard deviation (SD) were used to 
describe the normally distributed variables while median and interquartile range (IQR) were used to describe non-
normally distributed variables. Categorical variables were described using frequency and percentage. Comparison of 
the P-EHEALS scores between genders and departments was performed using independent-samples t-test, while the 
one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to compare p-EHALS scores between monthly income categories. 
The Mann-Whitney U test was used for comparison of minutes of Internet use between groups. The Pearson 
correlation coefficient was used to assess the correlation of age with P-EHEALS score, while the Spearman 
correlation coefficient was used to assess the correlation between minutes of Internet use and P-EHEAS score. </p>

<p>Electronic physician </p>



<p>Linear regression with backward elimination method was performed to assess the relationship between P-EHEALS 
score with study parameters. Binary logistic regression analysis was performed with gender as dependent variable 
and other study variables as dependent variables, in order to identify the e-Health literacy related factors that might 
be affected by gender. Statistical analyses were considered significant at p&lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>3. Results 
A total of 192 (129, 67.2% female and 63, 32.8% male) university students participated in this study. Mean age of 
the subjects was 24.71±5.30 years. Sociodemographic characteristics of subjects are shown in Table 1. Median 
minutes of Internet use per day was reported as 120.00, IQR=180.0 minutes (minimum was 10.0 minutes and 
maximum was 900.0 minutes). The mean P-EHEALS score for the subjects was 28.21±6.95. The mean scores for 
each question of the P-EHEALS are shown in Table 2. There was no significant correlation between total P-
EHEALS score and age (Pearson correlation coefficient, r=0.02, p=0.83) and minutes of Internet use (Spearman 
correlation coefficient, r=0.07, p=0.35). There was a significant difference in terms of total P-EHEALS scores 
between genders (p&lt;0.001), levels of education (p&lt;0.001), departments (0.001) and referral websites (p=0.02) as 
well as monthly income (p=0.03) (Table 3). Linear regression analysis revealed a significant relationship between 
total P-EHEALS score and gender, β=0.27, t (182) =3.83, p&lt;0.001. Logistic regression analysis found that gender 
was significantly associated with total P-EHEALS score (p=0.001, OR=1.11, 95% CI for OR=1.04, 1.17) (Table 4). </p>

<p>Table 1. Sociodemographic characteristics of study subjects 
Variable 
n 
% 
Gender 
Male 
63 
32.0 
Female 
134 68.0 
Monthly income (USD) No income 
140 71.1 
&lt;US160.00 
20 
10.2 
160-USD330 
12 
6.1 
&gt;330.00 
25 
12.7 
Level of education 
Graduate 
99 
50.3 
Post graduate 
98 
49.3 
Department 
Health Sciences 
110 55.8 
Medicine 
87 
44.2 
Health status 
Healthy 
155 78.7 
Illness 
13 
6.6 
Healthy with illness in family 28 
14.2 
Preferred website 
General 
60 
31.3 
Specific 
130 67.7 </p>

<p>Table 2. Mean score for P-EHEALS questions 
Question 
Mean SD 
Q1: I know how to find helpful health resources on the Internet 
3.42 
1.10 
Q2: I know how to use the Internet to answer my health questions 
3.53 
1.10 
Q3: I know what health resources are available on the Internet 
3.04 
1.11 
Q4: I know where to find helpful health resources on the Internet 
3.17 
1.09 
Q5: I know how to use the health information I find on the Internet to help me 
3.40 
1.07 
Q6: I have the skills I need to evaluate the health resources I find on the Internet 
3.17 
1.06 
Q7: I can tell high quality from low quality health resources on the Internet 
3.00 
1.09 
Q8: I feel confident in using information from the Internet to make health decisions 3.20 
1.16 </p>

<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>



<p>Table 3. Comparison of the total P-EHEALS scores of study subjects between genders, levels of education and 
departments 
Variable 
Total P-EHEALS score t 
p-value 
Gender 
Female 
24.47±6.43 
-4.25 &lt;0.001 
Male 
28.92±7.42 
Monthly income (USD </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) 
No income 
25.38±6.90 
3.01 0.03 
&lt;160.00 
29.74±7.14 
60-USD330 
28.50±6.56 
&gt;330.00 
24.62±7.26 
Department 
Health Sciences 
24.43±6.54 
-3.40 0.001 
Medicine 
27.84±7.28 
Level of education 
Graduate 
24.03±6.57 
-3.93 &lt;0.001 
Post graduate 
27.90±7.05 
Referral website preference General 
24.30±6.66 
2.35 0.02 
Specific 
26.85±6.98 
Health status 
Healthy 
26.74±6.75 
6.07 0.003 
Illness 
21.25±8.07 
Healthy with illness in family 23.18±6.95 
1: USD=United States Dollar </p>

<p>Table 4. Relation between study parameters and gender 
Variable 
Wald 
p-value OR 95% CI for OR 
lower Upper 
Age (years) 
&lt;0.001 0.99 
1.00 0.91 
1.10 
Monthly income (USD </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) 
1.68 
0.64 
-
-
-
Department (Medicine) 
1.31 
0.25 
2.64 0.50 
13.90 
Health status 
5.50 
0.06 
-
-
-
Healthy with illness in family 
1.63 
0.20 
0.45 0.13 
1.53 
Website preference (Specific) 
0.40 
0.53 
1.29 0.58 
2.88 
Minutes of Internet use 
1.12 
0.29 
1.00 0.99 
1.00 
Total P-EHEALS score 
11.93 
0.001* 1.11 1.04 
1.17 
Level of education (Post graduate) 0.21 
0.65 
0.67 0.12 
3.74 
1: USD= United States Dollar </p>

<p>4. Discussion 
This study revealed that the mean P-EHEALS score of the subjects was 28.21 ± 6.95. In a study on 541 Jordanian 
nursing students, the mean EHEALS score was 28.96 (31). Although this score was higher than the reported 
EHEALS score of 24.89 in a previously published study on 88 university students in Hong Kong, China in 2009 
(32), the EHEALS score in the current study was lower than the reported EHEAS score of 28.4 from a more recent 
study on 6th grade school students in China in 2012 (29). This finding implies that e-Health literacy evolves with 
time, and considering the increasing rate of Internet usage, e-Health literacy should increase rapidly. In contrast, the 
mean EHEALS score in a sample of a 2,142 Japanese population was 23.4 (33). A reason for the difference in the 
level of e-Health literacy between Iranian university students and Chinese students might be due to the higher 
availability of trusted sources of health information in China. Besides the report by the Medical Library Association 
Consumer and Patient Health Information Section, many American and international websites that are dedicated to 
providing health and medical information have material in Chinese language, the Chinese government has also made 
a growing attempt to provide health related information on social media (34, 35). Similarly, the lack of an efficient 
online healthcare system in Japan was identified as a main cause of lower comprehensive health literacy in Japan 
compared to Europe (33). Although the Internet penetration rate in Iran is slightly higher than China (55% in Iran vs. 
52.3% in China), higher accessibility of the Internet in Iran may not have been a contributing factor to e-Health 
literacy but, on the other hand, the lack of the required number of validated and trusted online sources of information 
in Iran and the reliance of Iranian Internet users on untrusted sources might have attributed to the lower e-Health 
literacy in Iran compared to China (22, 34, 35). Furthermore, this study found that ability to identify useful websites 
and differentiating high quality from low quality sources, accounted for the lowest scores in P-EHEALS. This 
finding also indicates that university students have good access to the Internet and health related websites, but do not </p>

<p>Electronic physician </p>



<p>have the ability to identify which websites provide trustable information on health issues. This might come from the 
fact that unlike Europe or the Unites states, the ministry-supported websites that deal with health education are 
either scarce or less advertised so that they have become difficult to find even by Medicine and Health Sciences 
students. This study also found a sexual divide in e-Health literacy among Iranian Medical and Health Sciences 
university students indicating that male students were 27% more likely to have higher e-Health literacy scores 
compared to female students. Various reasons have been proposed for the digital divide in societies including 
ethnicity, poverty and lower level of education (36-38). It was previously shown that lower level of education 
results in reduced Internet usage, while inequalities in the provision of services, including Internet access to 
minorities and low income population, was the reason for their reduced Internet access and therefore low e-Health 
literacy (36-38). On the other hand, previous studies have found either no significant effect for gender on e-Health 
literacy (31), or a higher attitude and referral to medical websites for women (39, 40). Since no significant 
association was found between gender and other study parameters, the higher observed scoring in P-EHEALS in 
men might be due to cultural differences that allow boys and men to have an unlimited access to communication 
technology from a younger age compared to women. Further research is required to assess the effect of gender in e-
Health of university students. One of the strengths of this study was the use of a validated Persian translate of 
EHEALS questionnaire which provided the opportunity to compare the e-Health literacy of Iranian Medicine and 
Health Sciences university students with other countries. Furthermore, to the best of our knowledge, this study was 
the first study that assessed the e-Health literacy in university students in Iran. A weakness of this study might be the 
small sample size. Due to the design of the study, pilot study, the sample size was calculated and therefore, the 
results of this study may not be generalized to the total population of Mashhad Medicine and Health Sciences 
university students. Furthermore, the uneven distribution of duration of Internet usage in the study, prevented the use 
of more reliable statistical analysis. Therefore, it is recommended that further researchers assess e-Health literacy in 
a larger sample of the university students who study in Medicine or health Sciences. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions 
This study found that the level of e-Health literacy is low among the Medicine and Health Sciences university 
students in Iran and that the female students have a lower e-Health literacy level compared to their male 
counterparts. It is required for further researchers to assess the level of e-Health literacy in larger samples of 
university students in order to identify the extent of e-Health literacy in a nationwide assay and make proper 
decisions to improve the e-Health literacy of students who study in health-related fields. Furthermore, since the aim 
of this study was not to assess the gender and digital divide in university students, this result was not able to identify 
the exact reason for lower e-Health literacy in female students. It is recommended that further studies should focus 
on the contributing factors to e-Health literacy in university students. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments: 
Authors of this study wish to thank all the university authorities who complied with the research and provided 
support to the researcher as well as the students who participated in the study. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: 
There is no conflict of interest to be declared. </p>

<p>Authors' contributions: 
SD and NP designed and performed the study. SD drafted the manuscript. MT participated in the design of the 
study, HE performed the statistical analysis and interpretation of data. All authors read and approved the final 
manuscript. </p>



<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>





<p>Electronic physician </p>





</text></tei>