<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5390613" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: To quantitatively measure hepatic fibrosis on gadoxetic acid-enhanced magnetic resonance (MR) in chronic 
hepatitis B (CHB) patients and identify the correlations with aspartate aminotransferase-to-platelet ratio index (APRI) and 
fibrosis-4 index (FIB-4) values. 
Materials and Methods: This study on gadoxetic acid-enhanced 3T MR imaging included 81 patients with CHB infection. To 
quantitatively measure hepatic fibrosis, MR images were analyzed with an aim to identify inhomogeneous signal intensities 
calculated from a coefficient of variation (CV) map in the liver parenchyma. We also carried out a comparative analysis 
between APRI and FIB-4 based on metaregression results. The diagnostic performance of the CV map was evaluated using a 
receiver-operating characteristic (ROC) curve. 
Results: In the MR images, the mean CV values in control, groups I, II, and III based on APRI were 4.08 ± 0.92, 4.24 ± 0.80, 
5.64 ± 1.11, and 5.73 ± 1.28, respectively (p &lt; 0.001). In CHB patients grouped by FIB-4, the mean CV values of groups A, B, 
and C were 4.22 ± 0.95, 5.40 ± 1.19, and 5.71 ± 1.17, respectively (p &lt; 0.001). The mean CV values correlated well with APRI 
(r = 0.392, p &lt; 0.001) and FIB-4 (r = 0.294, p &lt; 0.001). In significant fibrosis group, ROC curve analysis yielded an area under 
the curve of 0.875 using APRI and 0.831 using FIB-4 in HB, respectively. 
Conclusion: Gadoxetic acid-enhanced MR imaging for calculating a CV map showed moderate correlation with APRI and 
FIB-4 values and could be employed to quantitatively measure hepatic fibrosis in patients with CHB. 
Chronic hepatitis B (CHB) has a high prevalence in Asia. 
If left untreated, it can lead to serious conditions such 
as hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), liver cirrhosis (LC), 
esophageal varices, or hepatic encephalopathy. In Korea, 
hepatitis B was the most common cause of the underlying 
liver diseases in HCC patients (1-4). The liver biopsy is a 
gold-standard modality for evaluating the hepatic fibrosis 
and its stage. However, repeated liver biopsy for fibrosis 
evaluation has several limitations, including sampling 
errors related to the sample size and complications such 
as pain and hemorrhage (5, 6). As such, there is a need </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.3348/kjr.2017.18.3.444 </p>

<p>pISSN 1229-6929 · eISSN 2005-8330 </p>

<p>Original Article | Gastrointestinal Imaging </p>



<p>Hepatic Fibrosis on MRI </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 18(3), May/Jun 2017 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>for a noninvasive evaluation of liver fibrosis. Noninvasive 
assessment methods of liver fibrosis can be divided into 
three categories: serological markers, fibrosis biomarkers, 
and imaging techniques. In many previous studies, multiple 
serological marker-based indices have been proposed, 
including aspartate aminotransferase (AST)-to-platelet ratio 
index (APRI), fibrosis-4 (FIB-4) score, age-platelet count 
index, and AST/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ratio, and 
these have exhibited good correlations with the pathology 
of liver fibrosis (7-9). These indices are inexpensive and 
simple, as they incorporate routine laboratory results that 
are readily available in most of the hospital laboratories. 
Of the above-mentioned indices, APRI and FIB-4 provide an 
accurate assessment of liver fibrosis in CHB patients and are 
used as reference modalities for liver fibrosis (10). Recently, 
from a meta-analysis study, Xiao et al. (11) reported that 
APRI and FIB-4 possess moderate diagnostic accuracy for 
predicting fibrosis in patients with CHB viral infection. 
Among the serological markers, the two indices still could 
be considered as options for predicting fibrosis from CHB 
infection in regions with limited healthcare resources. 
Gadolinium ethoxybenzyl diethylenetriaminepentaacetic 
acid or gadoxetic acid (Gd-EOB-DTPA) is an extracellular, 
hepatocyte-specific magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) 
contrast agent used to evaluate focal hepatic lesions such 
as HCC, cholangiocarcinoma, and hemangioma, as well as 
for liver perfusion, extracellular diffusion, and bile excretion 
analysis (11-14). This contrast agent is absorbed by 
organic anion transporting polypeptides (OATPB1/B3) and 
metabolized in hepatocytes during the hepatobiliary (HB) 
phase, which occurs approximately 15-20 minutes after 
injection (15-17). In LC, the expression level and activity 
of OATPB1/B3 are decreased, and the liver signal intensity 
in the HB phase is weaker in the cirrhotic portion relative </p>

<p>to the normal liver parenchyma, yielding decreased signal 
intensity and inhomogeneous enhancement during the HB 
phase. In previous studies, the histogram in HB phase was 
well correlated with liver fibrosis grade and this notion was 
supported by the fact that heterogeneity in HB phase may 
be correlated with liver fibrosis grade (16-19). 
We hypothesized that we could suspect the degree of liver 
fibrosis by calculating liver enhancement heterogeneity 
in the HB phase, and accordingly, developed new <rs id="software-0" type="software">MATLAB</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">R2012a</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">MathWorks</rs>, Natick, MA, USA)-based software to 
identify inhomogeneous signal intensities calculated from 
a coefficient of variation (CV) map to objectively quantify 
liver parenchymal heterogeneity. 
In this paper, we aimed to evaluate the heterogeneity of 
liver parenchyma on Gd-EOB-DTPA-enhanced MR images, 
using CV value processed by our <rs type="software">MATLAB-based software</rs>, 
and to demonstrate a correlation between the calculated 
heterogeneity and the calculated serologic markers including 
APRI and FIB-4, which have been known to have diagnostic 
accuracy for predicting hepatic fibrosis in CHB patients. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study Population 
The local Institutional Review Board (IRB) approved 
this retrospective study and waived the requirement for 
written informed consent. A computer search identified a 
total of 138 patients with serologically confirmed CHB who 
underwent Gd-EOB-DTPA-enhanced MRI from December 1, 
2013 to April 1, 2015 at our hospital. The exclusion criteria 
were inpatients that underwent Gd-EOB-DTPA-enhanced 
MRI (n = 32), patients who underwent a right lobectomy 
(n = 10), patient having scans with poor image quality (n 
= 6), and patients who did not undergo a laboratory study </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and Biochemical Characteristics of Patients Grouped by APRI Values </p>

<p>Control (n = 36) 
Group I (n = 17) 
Group II (n = 46) 
Group III (n = 18) 
Age (years) 
All patients 
56.8 (14-80) 
56.8 (38-74) 
57.8 (42-74) 
59.2 (50-85) 
Men 
56.5 (14-75) 
56.4 (38-74) 
57.5 (42-74) 
58.1 (50-85) 
Women 
57.3 (37-80) 
57.5 (41-72) 
59.1 (46-69) 
63.0 (51-70) 
Sex* 
Male 
22 (61) 
11 (65) 
37 (80) 
14 (78) 
Female 
14 (39) 
6 (35) 
9 (20) 
4 (22) 
AST level (IU/L) 
28.4 (15-54) 
23.7 (15-34) 
40.6 (21-68) 
66.9 (34-220) 
Platelet count (10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L) 
254 (102-529) 
198.6 (133-331) 
137.9 (73-231) 
83.1 (42-357) </p>

<p>Unless otherwise indicated, data are presented in means, with range denoted in parentheses. *Data indicate numbers of patients, with 
percentages in parentheses. APRI = aspartate aminotransferase to platelet ratio index, AST = aspartate aminotransferase </p>



<p>Lee et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 18(3), May/Jun 2017 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>within 7 days from the MR study date (n = 9). Finally, 81 
patients were included in the study (Tables 1, 2). Patients 
were divided into 3 subgroups according to their APRI: 
≤ 0.5, non-significant fibrosis group (group I, n = 17); 
0.5-1.4, significant fibrosis group (group II, n = 46); and 
≥ 1.4, advanced fibrosis group (group III, n = 18) (9, 10). 
In addition, the patients were divided into control group 
and three groups based on FIB-4 threshold &lt; 1.45 (group 
A, n = 29), 1.45-3.25 (group B, n = 42), and &gt; 3.25 (group 
C, n = 10). Xiao et al. (11) cited this cut-off value in their 
study. None of the patients with CHB had a viral hepatitis C 
coinfection, biliary cirrhosis, Wilson disease, or autoimmune 
hepatitis. In addition, 36 patients without chronic liver 
disease who underwent Gd-EOB-DTPA-enhanced MRI during 
the study period were enrolled as the control group; colon 
cancer with liver metastasis (n = 11), biopsy for solitary 
hepatic tumor, which was confirmed benign tumor (n = 19). 
All serologic data were obtained through laboratory 
studies conducted within 7 days from the Gd-EOB-DTPA-
enhanced MRI study date. APRI and FIB-4 were calculated 
using the following formula: </p>

<p>AST 
APRI = 
ULN* 
x 100 
platelet count [x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L] </p>

<p>FIB-4 = 
(age [yr] x AST [U/L]) 
(platelet count [10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L] x ALT [U/L]) </p>

<p>*The upper limit of normal (ULN) AST was 35 in this 
study. </p>

<p>MRI 
Magnetic resonance imaging was performed on a 3T </p>

<p>scanner (Achieva; Philips Healthcare, Best, the Netherlands) 
with a 32-channel receiver body matrix coil. In all subjects, 
imaging was performed under fasting condition. All MR 
images were obtained in the axial plane, and T2-weighted 
images (WI) were additionally acquired in the coronal plane. 
The Gd-EOB-DTPA-enhanced MRI was performed before 
and after the administration of Gd-EOB-DTPA (Primovist; 
Bayer Healthcare, Berlin, Germany) and comprised of T1WI, 
acquired with a 3-dimensional T1 high-resolution isotropic 
volume excitation pulse sequence. Gd-EOB-DTPA (0.1 mL/ 
kg body weight) was injected intravenously as a rapid bolus 
at a rate of 1.5 mL/s via a power injector (Sonic Shot 50; 
Nemoto Kyorindo Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) while the patient 
was in the bore of the magnet. This was followed by a 15-
mL flush with normal saline (1.5 mL/s). Arterial-phase 
imaging started after a modified scan delay with visual 
confirmation of contrast agent arrival in the abdominal 
aorta using a fluoroscopic triggering injection method. 
Subsequent contrast-enhanced-MRI was initiated at 50 
seconds, 3 minutes, and 20 minutes (or HB phase) after the 
start of the bolus injection (13, 20). </p>

<p>Imaging Analysis and Measurement of Hepatic Fibrosis 
To measure hepatic fibrosis quantitatively, we developed 
a <rs id="software-4" type="software">MATLAB</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">R2012a</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">MathWorks</rs>, Natick, MA, USA)-based 
software to calculate a CV map, as suggested by Li et al. 
(21). The following procedure was used to calculate the CV 
map: bias correction of intensity inhomogeneity, followed 
by calculation of the CV map by dividing the CV value by 
each pixel value in the circular region of interest (ROI; 
diameter = 40 pixels) and, finally, calculating the mean 
value on the CV map (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Table 2. Demographic and Biochemical Characteristics of Patients Grouped by FIB-4 Values </p>

<p>Control (n = 36) 
Group A (n = 29) 
Group B (n = 42) 
Group C (n = 10) 
Age (years) 
All patients 
56.8 (14-80) 
61.7 (47-85) 
56.6 (42-74) 
52.0 (38-63) 
Men 
56.5 (14-75) 
60.7 (47-85) 
56.6 (42-74) 
49.3 (38-62) 
Women 
57.3 (37-80) 
64.3 (51-70) 
56.9 (46-72) 
56.0 (41-63) 
Sex* 
Male 
22 (61) 
22 (76) 
34 (81) 
6 (60) 
Female 
14 (39) 
7 (24) 
8 (19) 
4 (40) 
AST level (IU/L) 
28.4 (17-33) 
23.8 (15-34) 
36.6 (21-65) 
58.6 (30-220) 
Platelet count (10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L) 
254 (102-529) 
207.1 (152-289) 
151.0 (76-331) 
96.6 (42-257) </p>

<p>Unless otherwise indicated, data are presented in means, with range denoted in parentheses. *Data indicate numbers of patients, with 
percentages in parentheses. AST = aspartate aminotransferase, FIB-4 = fibrosis-4 </p>



<p>Hepatic Fibrosis on MRI </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 18(3), May/Jun 2017 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>CV = 
Standard deviation x 100 
Mean </p>

<p>CV Map = 
CV 
x 100 
Pixel value </p>

<p>Gd-EOB-DTPA-enhanced axial images obtained during the 
HB phase MR image were obtained in Digital Imaging and 
Communications in Medicine format and stored on console 
containing the <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs>-based program. For quantitative 
measurements of liver parenchymal heterogeneity, two 
abdominal radiologists (with 24 years of experience and 
with 4 years of experience in abdominal imaging), blinded 
to clinical information and pathological fibrosis grades, 
performed the procedure by positioning separate circular 
ROIs (diameter = 40 pixels) on the selected MR images, 
which was bias-corrected. In all subjects, ROIs were placed 
on the anterior segment of the right hepatic lobe with no 
overlap over large vessels and focal lesions such as cysts or 
tumors (Fig. 2). Each radiologist measured ROIs 3 times in 
the selected MR images and calculated the mean. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
The relationships between the CV values on HB-
phase images and APRI and FIB-4 were evaluated 
using nonparametric Spearman correlation coefficients. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Workflow for calculation of coefficients of variation (CV) in control subject (A) and in patient with chronic hepatitis 
B (B) in hepatobiliary phase of Gd-EOB-DTPA-enhanced MRI. To measure hepatic fibrosis quantitatively, <rs type="software">MATLAB-based software</rs> was </p>

<p>used to calculate CV map. After acquisition of MR images, bias correction and segmentation of liver parenchyma were performed, and then 
mean value of CV map on region of interest at anterior segment of right lobe of liver was calculated. Gd-EOB-DTPA = gadolinium ethoxybenzyl 
diethylenetriaminepentaacetic acid or gadoxetic acid, MRI = magnetic resonance imaging </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Acquisition 
Bias correction 
Segmentation 
CV mapping </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Images show representative CV maps on control and 
patients with chronic hepatitis B of group I, II, and III on HB 
phases of Gd-EOB-DTPA-enhanced MRI. CV values are 3.54, 3.58, </p>

<p>5.58, and 6.7 in HB phase, respectively. CV = coefficients of variation, 
Gd-EOB-DTPA = gadolinium ethoxybenzyl diethylenetriaminepentaacetic 
acid or gadoxetic acid, HB = hepatobiliary, MRI = magnetic resonance 
imaging </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Group II </p>

<p>5.58 </p>

<p>3.54 </p>

<p>CV </p>

<p>CV </p>

<p>Group I </p>

<p>Group III </p>

<p>6.7 </p>

<p>3.58 </p>



<p>Lee et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 18(3), May/Jun 2017 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>Comparisons of CV values between the control group and 
CHB groups I, II, or III and between the control group and 
CHB groups A, B, or C were performed using the Kruskal-
Wallis test and intergroup comparisons were performed 
using the Mann-Whitney test. The diagnostic performance 
of CV with respect to significant liver fibrosis was evaluated 
using a receiver-operating characteristic (ROC) curve and 
calculated two times; the first one was for the APRI version 
(&gt; 0.5) and the second one was for the FIB-4 version (&gt; 
1.45). The ROC curve is a plot of the sensitivity versus 
(100-specificity) values at all possible cut-off values. 
Optimal cut-off values were selected using a common 
optimization step that maximized the Youden index for 
predicting significant fibrosis; sensitivity and specificity 
were calculated from the same data without further 
adjustments. The inter-observer agreement was performed 
based on the intraclass correlation coefficient. The Kruskal-
Wallis test, Mann-Whitney test, Spearman correlation </p>

<p>coefficients, and intraclass correlation coefficient were 
conducted using <rs id="software-10" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-10" type="version-number">version 18.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, 
USA) and ROC, sensitivity, and specificity were analyzed 
with MedCalc version 15.6 (MedCalc, Mariakerke, Belgium). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The mean CV and APRI values for the control and CHB 
groups are listed in Table 3. In the HB phase of enhanced 
T1WI, the mean CV values of control and patients in groups 
I, II, and III by APRI were 4.08 ± 0.92, 4.24 ± 0.80, 5.64 
± 1.11, and 5.73 ± 1.28, respectively (p &lt; 0.001) and 
the mean CV values of control and patients in groups A, 
B, and C by FIB-4 were 4.08 ± 0.92, 4.22 ± 0.95, 5.40 ± 
1.19, and 5.71 ± 1.17, respectively (p &lt; 0.001). The CV 
values in groups II and III were significantly higher than 
the values in the control group and group I (p &lt; 0.001). 
The comparative analysis of CV values among the control 
group and CHB groups revealed higher mean CV values in 
CHB group III/C, followed by those in CHB group II/B, CHB 
group I/A, and the control group, and these differences 
were significant (p &lt; 0.001) (Table 3). Pairwise comparisons 
of CHB groups I/A and II/B with respect to HB phase MR 
images revealed very significant results (p &lt; 0.001). 
An analysis of the relationship between the CV with the 
APRI and FIB-4 among patients with CHB revealed moderate 
correlations; r value for APRI and FIB-4 was 0.392 and 0.294, 
respectively (Fig. 3). ROC curves for the CVs in CHB patients </p>

<p>Table 3. Mean Values of Coefficients of Variation (CV) in Liver 
Parenchyma in Hepatobiliary Phase Images among Control and 
Chronic Hepatitis B Groups by Using APRI and FIB-4 </p>

<p>APRI 
CV Value 
FIB-4 
CV Value 
Control group 
4.08 ± 0.92 
Control group 
4.08 ± 0.92 
Group I 
4.24 ± 0.80 
Group A 
4.22 ± 0.95 
Group II 
5.64 ± 1.11 
Group B 
5.40 ± 1.19 
Group III 
5.73 ± 1.28 
Group C 
5.71 ± 1.17 </p>

<p>Data are shown as means ± standard deviations. APRI = aspartate 
aminotransferase-to-platelet ratio index, FIB-4 = fibrosis-4 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Correlation of CV with APRI and FIB-4. </p>

<p>A. Shows correlation between aspartate aminotransferase-to-platelet ratio and coefficient of variation (CV) (r = 0.392, p &lt; 0.001). B. Shows 
correlation between FIB-4 and CV values (r = 0.294, p &lt; 0.001) in HB phases of Gd-EOB-DTPA-enhanced MRI. FIB-4 = fibrosis-4, Gd-EOB-DTPA = 
gadolinium ethoxybenzyl diethylenetriaminepentaacetic acid or gadoxetic acid, HB = hepatobiliary, MRI = magnetic resonance imaging </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>4.00 </p>

<p>3.00 </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>APRI </p>

<p>3.00 
4.00 
5.00 
6.00 
7.00 
8.00 
9.00 
CV </p>

<p>r = 0.392 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>20.00 </p>

<p>15.00 </p>

<p>10.00 </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>FIB-4 </p>

<p>3.00 
4.00 
5.00 
6.00 
7.00 
8.00 
9.00 
CV </p>

<p>r = 0.294 </p>

<p>B </p>



<p>Hepatic Fibrosis on MRI </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 18(3), May/Jun 2017 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>with or without significant fibrosis are described in Figure 
4 and Table 4. The area under the curve (AUC) was 0.875 
in APRI version with an optimal cut-off value of 4.19 for 
predicting significant fibrosis in the HB phase. The sensitivity 
and specificity at the optimal cut-off values of the HB phase 
were 82.8 and 88.2%, respectively. Secondly, the AUC was 
0.831 in FIB-4 version with an optimal cut-off value of 4.56. 
The sensitivity and specificity at the optimal cut-off values 
were, 80.0 and 81.8%, respectively on the HB phase. The 
intraclass correlation coefficient between the two radiologists 
was 0.947 (95% CI, 0.918-0.966) in HB phase image. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Gd-EOB-DTPA is a liver-specific contrast agent. Gd-EOB-
DTPA transport from the sinusoids to hepatocytes is mostly 
mediated by OATPB1/B3, and its excretion into the bile 
duct is mediated by the multidrug resistance protein 2 
(MRP2) (21-26). Progressive liver fibrosis has been reported 
to reduce OATPB1/B3 activity and features the activation 
of collagen-producing hepatic stellate cells, collagen 
deposition in the subendothelial space of Disse, and all of 
which may promote the development of a fibrotic barrier in 
the liver parenchyma and reduced Gd-EOB-DTPA uptake (27-
29). It was also supported by another literature. In a study 
by Tsuda and Matsui (29), higher levels of MRP2 activity 
were observed in cirrhotic rats, indicating that advanced 
liver fibrosis may lead to earlier Gd-EOB-DTPA excretion. 
Therefore, the absence of even distribution of Gd-EOB-DTPA 
in all liver parenchymal compartments and hepatocytes has 
been observed after administration of the contrast agent to 
CHB patients, thus leading to inhomogeneous enhancement 
of the liver parenchyma. 
Our results revealed a significant difference in mean 
CV values between CHB groups I/A and II/B. This 
finding indicates that heterogeneous liver parenchymal 
enhancement is helpful in determining the presence of 
significant fibrosis in patients with CHB. We found the 
diagnostic accuracy of CV value, which is comparable to 
APRI and FIB-4 for predicting CHB-related fibrosis. The 
results showed that CV had ROC values of 0.875 in APRI 
version and 0.831 in FIB-4 version. The results suggested 
that the CV value had modest accuracy for detecting 
significant fibrosis. The AUC results from another previous 
study on quantification of liver fibrosis in CHB by imaging 
modality were similar to our results. For example, in a meta-
analysis of the fibroscan in CHB, the AUC for the diagnosis 
of significant fibrosis (F2) was 0.859 (30). In a study by Shi 
et al. (31), MR elastography demonstrated good diagnostic 
performance for ≥ F2 (AUC values was 0.986) and the value 
was higher than our results. 
The CV measurements of liver fibrosis are associated 
with many advantages. First, this type of liver fibrosis 
assessment is very simple and does not require new imaging 
equipment. Recently, MR elastography, ultrasonographic 
elastography, and fibroscan were developed for liver fibrosis 
evaluation. However, all of these techniques require new 
imaging equipment, thus placing a restriction on access (32, 
33). Second, CV mapping does not require any additional </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Receiver operating characteristic curves of coefficient 
of variation used for diagnosis in patient with significant 
fibrosis (aspartate aminotransferase-to-platelet ratio &gt; 0.5 
and FIB-4 score &gt; 1.45). AUC was 0.875 in APRI version with </p>

<p>optimal cut-off values of 4.1866 (red line). AUC was 0.831 in FIB-
4 version with optimal cut-off values of 4.5642 (blue line). APRI = 
aspartate aminotransferase to platelet ratio index, AUC = area under 
the curve, FIB-4 = fibrosis-4 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 </p>

<p>100-specificity </p>

<p>Nonsignificant fibrosis (APRI &lt; 0.5) vs. 
significant fibrosis (APRI &gt; 0.5) </p>

<p>Nonsignificant fibrosis (FIB-4 &lt; 1.45) vs. 
significant fibrosis (FIB-4 &gt; 1.45) </p>

<p>Table 4. Cut-Off and Diagnostic Performance Values of 
Coefficient of Variation (CV) in Patients with Chronic Hepatitis 
B and Significant Fibrosis by Using APRI and FIB-4 </p>

<p>APRI 
FIB-4 
Cut-off value of CV 
&gt; 4.19 
&gt; 4.56 
Sensitivity (%) 
82.8 
80.0 
Specificity (%) 
88.2 
81.8 
AUC 
0.875 
0.831 
p 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>APRI = aspartate aminotransferase-to-platelet ratio index, AUC = 
area under the curve, FIB-4 = fibrosis-4 </p>



<p>Lee et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 18(3), May/Jun 2017 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>MR scanning. This technique is mediated by software and 
objectively quantifies liver parenchymal heterogeneity. 
Third, heterogeneity measurements require only Gd-EOB-
DTPA-enhanced MRI, which includes information about 
the liver function and simultaneously facilitates HCC 
screening. Fourth, measurement using CV mapping is 
highly reproducible, which is revealed by a high inter-
observer agreement of 0.947 between the most experienced 
radiologist and one with less experience. Any radiologist 
or clinician can use the CV value on HB phase MR image by 
following simple instructions using this software. 
Nowadays, Gd-EOB-DTPA enhanced MRI has become 
popular and has revealed high diagnostic accuracy for HCC 
surveillance. Based on our results, it is hypothesized that 
the CV values would impart an additional value for Gd-
EOB-DTPA-enhanced MR in predicting advanced hepatic 
fibrosis or cirrhosis, and a radiologist or clinician could pay 
attention to the patients with high CV values. Further study 
is needed for analyzing the correlation between CV values 
and pathologic fibrosis grades. 
When this study was designed, only outpatients were 
enrolled as laboratory data are influenced by the patient's 
general condition. Moreover, many patients with CHB 
and advanced LC had comorbid HCC, ascites, or portal 
hypertension and were treated with various drugs, including 
chemotherapeutic agents. These drugs are metabolized in 
the liver and cause liver toxicity. Accordingly, we wanted to 
exclude other potential influences on AST or platelet levels 
and therefore included only outpatients in our study. 
This study has several limitations. First, LC and normal 
liver parenchyma were not histologically confirmed in 
our patient population, as the patients were followed 
up using noninvasive evaluations such as blood tests or 
imaging modalities, and only a few patients with CHB 
who had special indications underwent liver biopsy at 
our hospital. As a result, we depended on clinical data to 
obtain a reference degree of liver fibrosis and evaluated 
the heterogeneity of liver enhancement effects based on 
APRI and FIB-4, rather than on the histological grading of 
fibrosis. Second, we positioned the ROI at the right anterior 
or posterior segment of the liver (segments 5/6 and 7/8) 
because this area does not contain major vessels and is 
far from the heart, thus reducing the incidence of cardiac 
motion artifacts. However, the CV of the ROI area is not 
representative of the whole liver, and thus some selection 
bias might have occurred. Third, this was a retrospective 
study and the APRI and FIB-4 values were used for a </p>

<p>reference liver fibrosis assessment; accordingly, we included 
laboratory data obtained within 7 days from the Gd-EOB-
DTPA-enhanced MRI study date to minimize the influence 
of factors other than liver fibrosis on the AST and platelet 
levels. However, this effort could not remove all bias. 
In conclusion, this study was the first study to evaluate 
liver fibrosis by calculating CV values in liver parenchyma. 
CV values were well correlated with APRI and FIB-4 index. 
Among patients with CHB, the CV values differed significantly 
between those with non-significant and significant liver 
fibrosis. As such, a CV map on gadoxetic acid-enhanced MRI 
could render the possibility of quantitatively measuring 
hepatic fibrosis in patients with CHB. </p>





<p>Hepatic Fibrosis on MRI </p>



</text></tei>