<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5329788" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T19:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Cytokine-induced killer (CIK) cells were isolated 
and proliferation from human peripheral blood and cul-
tured in appropriate growth medium. The biological char-
acteristics of CIK cells were further determined by the 
characterization of surface markers by flow cytometry. 
CIK cells inhibited the proliferation of human lung ade-
nocarcinoma NCL-H157 cells. Vascular endothelial growth 
factor (VEGF) expression was down-regulated in CIK cells 
co-cultured with NCL-H157 cells by western blotting anal-
ysis. Furthermore, in comparison with cells untreated by 
CIK, the NCL-H157 had a lower proliferation capacity. We 
proposed that the pharmacological mechanisms of NCL-
H157 promoted by CIK can be estimated possibly with 
different biological significance that can be ascribed to 
down-regulated VEGF expression in vitro. The results 
suggest that the VEGF pathway guides developmental 
inhibiting of NCL-H157, and we speculate that the function 
of VEGF pathways is to guide NCL-H157 to inhibition by 
abundant CIK. </p>

<p>Human lung cancer is one of the most common malig-
nant diseases and a leading cause of death annually 
in much of the developed world especially in China [1]. 
Adenocarcinoma, the most common form of lung cancer, 
is one of main human malignant tumors, and its occur-
rence and development are highly correlated with inacti-
vation of tumor suppressor genes. Many genes play a role 
in negatively regulating lung tumor growth and apopto-
sis [2-3]. Beyond that, there is little that can be definitively 
said. The standard test to confirm multipotency is differ-
entiation of the cells into osteoblasts, adipocytes, and 
chondrocytes, as well as myocytes and neurons. A type 
of immunological cell, cytokine-induced killer (CIK) cells 
are a heterogeneous cell population that was first discov-
ered in the 1990s and can be generated from lymphocytes 
co-cultured with an anti-CD3 antibody and many other 
cytokines in vitro [4-5]. Numerous studies have demon-
strated that CIK cells exhibit active and potent antitumor 
cytotoxicity against multifarious tumor cells in vitro and in 
vivo [6]. CIK cells alter the cytokine secretion profiles of 
dendritic cells, T cells, and natural killer cells to induce 
a more anti-inflammatory or tolerant phenotype. This 
phenomenon has been documented in specific cells and 
tissues in living animals and their counterparts growing 
in cell culture [7]. 
It is well known that CIK cells used in biological 
systems are required to be anti-tumor. More and more sci-
entists are devoting themselves to the field of growth and 
differentiation of NCL-H157. In vitro, CIK cells have greater 
expansion capability and a faster growth rate. However, 
the conquest of NCL-H157 by CIK is still a great challenge 
to medical science. In this study, we evaluated the inhi-
bition of NCL-H157, which was significant with prolonged 
cellular doubling time and the possible molecular regula-
tion mechanism of the proliferation of NCL-H157 by CIK. </p>



<p>Dengrui Li et al </p>

<p>2 Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1 CIK cells isolated and expanded? </p>

<p>CIK cells were isolated and cultured according to standard 
protocol. Peripheral blood (50 mL) was drawn from the 
patients with heparin as an anticoagulant. Mononuclear 
cells were isolated by Ficoll-Conray (GE Healthcare, 
Fairfield, CT, USA) density gradient centrifugation, and 
then the remaining cells were washed twice with phos-
phate buffer saline (PBS). The viability and concentra-
tion of mononuclear cells were determined with trypan 
blue and a hemacytometer. Approximately 2.0×10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>/mL 
suspension and mononuclear cells were cultured in six-
well culture dishes with medium containing RPMI 1640 
plus 1.0×10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>U/L human interferon gamma (IFN-γ), 10% 
heat inactivated fetal bovine serum, 25 mM HEPES and 
2 mM L-glutamine and incubated overnight at 37 °C in 
5% carbon dioxide. After 24 hours, 50 μg/L monoclonal 
antibody (MAb) against CD3 and rhIL-2 (1×10 
6 U/L) were 
added. Fresh complete medium with rhIL-2 (1×10 
6 U/L) was 
changed every 2 to 3 days, and the cells were harvested on 
day 7, 14 and 21. All CIK cell cultures were tested for contam-
ination (bacteria, fungi, and mycoplasma) throughout the 
study to assure culture quality and transfusion safety. The 
morphological changes were observed under an inverted 
phase contrast microscope at 200× magnification. </p>

<p>2.2 CIK cell surface maker detected by flow 
cytometer measurement </p>

<p>In order to assay the percentages of cell surface antigen, 
FITC-and APC-stained cells were analyzed. After washing 
with ice-cold PBS two times, CIK cells were re-suspended 
in 200 mL binding buffer (10 mM HEPES/NaOH, pH 7.4, 
150 mM NaCl, 5 mM KCl, 1 mM MgCl 2 , 1.8 mM CaCl 2 ) and 
co-incubated with 10 mL FITC-annexin V (25 g/mL) and 5 L 
propidium iodide (PI, 50 g/mL) in the absence of light for 
15 minutes at room temperature. To confirm the cellular 
identity of cultured cells, CIK cells were subjected to flu-
orescence-activated cell sorting using CD3FITC, CD56APC 
positive markers. Finally, fluorescent intensities of stained 
cells were analyzed with a FACScalibur Flow cytometer 
(Becton Dickinson Corp., USA). </p>

<p>2.3 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-5-(3-car-
boxymethoxyphenyl)-2-(4-sulfophenyl)-2H-
tetrazolium (MTS) assay </p>

<p>A 200 μL suspension of NCL-H157 cells per well was seeded 
in a 96-well plate at a density of 5×10 
4 cell/mL. NCL-H157 
cells were grown for 12 hours after seeding, and then 
treated with CIK. After a 24-hour incubation, the medium 
was removed, and the cells were treated with CIK cells for 
72 hours. Effector-to-target cell ratios (E/T ratio) ranged 
from 10:1, 20:1 and 30:1. NCL-H157 cells were re-suspended 
in a fresh culture medium after being centrifuged at 1000 
rpm for 10 minutes; 20 μL MTS (5 mg/mL) was added to 
each well, and incubation was allowed to continue for an 
additional 4 hours. Finally, all media were removed by 
the centrifugation; 150 μL DMSO was added to each well 
and shaken for 10 minutes. The absorbance was read at 
a wavelength of 550 nm with a Benchmark Microplate 
Reader (Bio-Rad Corp. USA). </p>

<p>2.4 Western blotting analysis to detect 
vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) in 
NCL-H157 treated by CIK cells </p>

<p>Western blotting analysis was performed to evaluate the 
influence of DMOG on the expression of VEGF in NCL-H157 
cells. The cells were cultured in regular medium with the 
addition of different concentrations of CIK (concentra-
tion of effector-to-target cell ratios (E/T ratio) ranged from 
10:1, 20:1 and 30:1). The total protein was harvested from 
the cultured cells according to standard protocols. Then 
the protein concentration was measured with a bicin-
choninic acid (BCA) protein assay kit (Thermo Scientific, 
Waltham, MA, USA). The cell lysates were separated on 
SDS-PAGE with 12% gels and transferred to nitrocellulose 
membranes. The membranes were then incubated with 
primary antibodies of β-actin (1:1000, Santa Cruz, USA), 
VEGF (1:500, Santa Cruz, USA). Then the membranes were 
incubated with gentle agitation for 2 hours at 37°C with 
horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody 
diluted in 5% skim milk powder at 1:7500. After washing 
three times in Tris-Buffered Saline-Tween-20 (Beyotime, 
China) (10 minutes each wash), the membranes were </p>

<p>developed by an enhanced chemiluminescence (ECL) </p>

<p>western blotting detection system. Immunoreactive pro-
teins were then detected by ChemiDoc MP System #170-
8280 (Bio-Rad, USA). Images were captured and analyzed 
by <rs id="software-0" type="software">Quantity One</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Bio-Rad</rs>, USA). </p>

<p>The possible molecular regulation mechanism of CIK cells </p>



<p>2.5 Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>All of the in vitro experiments were performed in triplicate, 
and data were presented as the mean ± standard deviation 
(SD) of three independent experiments. Wherever appro-
priate, the data were subjected to statistical analysis by a 
one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) test followed by the 
Student-Newman-Keuls test for comparison of all pairs of 
means. A value of P&lt;0.05 was considered to be statistically 
significant. <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">11.5</rs> for Windows software was used for 
the statistical analysis. P-values &lt;0.05 were considered 
significant. </p>

<p>Ethics Statement: The study was approved by the insi-
titutional review board (CWO) of Hebei Chest Hospital 
Ethics Committee, Shijiazhuang, The People's Republic of 
China. All people provided written informed consent. </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>3.1 Isolation and expansion of CIK cells with 
cytokine induced methods </p>

<p>Cultured CIK cells began to grow within 3 days and entered 
the proliferation stage within 5 days. Following 7 days of 
culture, the proliferation rate of CIK cells significantly 
grew faster and faster. After 21 days, cultured cells reached 
a density of (149.42±4.59)×10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>. Cells were harvested and 
examined under an inverted microscope, which revealed 
that the cells grew as colonies in suspension (Figure 1). 
Cell volume was markedly increased over time, and the 
survival rate of cultured cells was &gt;95%. </p>

<p>3.2 Immune phenotype of CIK cells </p>

<p>Intensive and strict studies on the immune phenotype of 
CIK cells have been conducted. The CIK cells were ana-
lyzed by flow cytometric analysis and gated for granular-
ity, size and surface markers. The gated cells were ana-
lyzed for the expression of cell membrane protein markers 
and found to be positive for the expression of a hetero-
geneous cell population, comprising CD3+CD56+, which 
are generally considered markers of CIK cells (Figure 2). 
CD3+CD56+ T cells expression of CIK cells was 39.2± 1.1%. </p>

<p>3.3 CIK inhibited the proliferation of 
NCL-H157 cells </p>

<p>The effects of CIK on the viability of NCL-H157 cells were 
evaluated by MTS assay (Figure 3). The results showed 
that exposure to CIK for 48 hours resulted in a dose-de-
pendent increase in CIK, with a statistically significant 
difference between different groups. Compared to the 
untreated control in DMEM/F12 cultured medium, the MTS 
assay showed CIK was more active against or with NCL-
H157 cells in an ascending order. Figure 2 shows the effect 
of CIK on the inhibition of NCL-H157. As shown in Figure 
2, when NCL-H157 was incubated with CIK, dose-depen-
dent decreases of NCL-H157 viability from 21.4%, 54.0% 
and 71.3% were observed after increasing the CIK concen-
tration of effector-to-target cell ratios (E/T ratio) ranging 
from 10:1, 20:1 and 30:1, respectively, compared with NCL-
H157 in the control group. The concentration-dependent 
decreases of cell viability were observed as shown in 
Figure 2. </p>

<p>Figure 1: Representative image of CIK cell morphology at days 0, 7, 
14 and 21 of culture (magnification, ×100). </p>

<p>Figure 2: Flow cytometry was used to detect the surface antigen of 
CIK. CIK can be characterized by a panel of surface markers, which is 
positive for markers CD3 and CD56. </p>



<p>Dengrui Li et al </p>

<p>Also, the time-dependent decreases of cell viabil-
ity were observed as in Figure 2. The cell viability was 
decreased from 66.8% to 79.8% to 86.9% after the incu-
bation time 24 hours, 48 hours and 72 hours, respectively. </p>

<p>3.4 Molecular expression changes in CIK 
co-cultured with hUCNCL-H157 </p>

<p>To evaluate the influence of CIK on the expression of 
VEGF in NCL-H157, the protein levels of VEGF in NCL-H157 
treated with different concentrations of CIK were detected 
by western blotting. The results showed the level of VEGF 
protein was enhanced in response to CIK treatment in a 
dose-dependent manner. VEGF is a molecule associated 
with the proliferation of NCL-H157 and the important pro-
teins associated with it. In order to discover the molecu-
lar mechanism underlying the proliferation effect of CIK 
on NCL-H157 in vitro, we investigated the expressions of 
the proteins in NCL-H157 by western blotting (Figure 4 
A). The results showed that CIK co-cultured with NCL-
H157 by transwell chamber for 48 hours resulted in the </p>

<p>significant down-regulation of VEGF as compared to con-
trols. We found increased VEGF levels in culture media of 
NCL-H157 cells. Irradiated NCL-H157 showed an inverse 
pattern, that is, decrease of VEGF. </p>

<p>4 Conclusions </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this is the first study of inhibition of 
NCL-H157 treated by CIK. In the event our study is viewed 
as merely phenomenological, we stress that our exper-
iments were carefully designed to facilitate the inhi-
bition of NCL-H157 cells and to record these effects, as 
well. Instead of focusing on NCL-H157 activity, we were 
more interested in following the inhibition of NCL-H157 
that involves cell signal pathways and the breakout func-
tion of biological material-CIK cell. We found that the 
CD3+CD56+ subset of CIK cells was variably naturally 
active. The CD3+CD56+ subset could be polarized toward 
either Th1 or Th2 phenotype that, in turn, shapes its 
anti-tumor activity [8-9]. 
In this study, we assessed the NCL-H157 proliferation 
inhibited by CIK using the inverted phase contrast micro-
scope and flow cytometer. NCL-H157 cells were detected 
after incubation with CIK at designed concentrations and 
times. CIK plays a critical role in providing the essential 
micro-environment for NCL-H157 at different CIK concen-
trations of effector-to-target cell ratios (E/T ratio) ranging 
from 10:1, 20:1 and 30:1 for 24 hours, 48 hours, and 72 
hours, respectively. These images are shown in Figure 
1. These results were further confirmed by MTS analy-
sis as shown in Figure 2. The percentage of NCL-H157 in 
the control group was less than the treated group. When 
the incubation time was prolonged to 72 hours, a marked </p>

<p>Figure 3: Effects of CIK on NCL-H157 viability (n = 5). Cell viability 
of NCL-H157 treated with different CIK concentrations of effector-to-
target cell ratios (E/T ratio) ranged from 10:1, 20:1 and 30:1, for 24h, 
48h, and 72h. (*, significant difference between the two groups, p 
&lt; 0.05) </p>

<p>Figure 4: A shows VEGF over-expression in NCL-H157 treated by CIK with western blotting analysis. In order to elucidate the pathway leading 
to proliferation, we examined the activation of VEGF, which was reported to initiate NCL-H157 generation by various stimuli. NCL-H157 
treated with CIK were analyzed for the enzymatic activity by western blot. The expression of VEGF was not activated after CIK treatment in 
NCL-H157 was down-regulated. The activity of VEGF had significantly changed. B shows densitometric analysis of the levels of VEGF by an 
image analysis system. (n=6. Mean±SD. *P&lt;0.01 vs control group) (ANOVA with subsequent multiple comparisons test) </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>The possible molecular regulation mechanism of CIK cells </p>



<p>decrease in the percentage of NCL-H157 cells was observed 
in CIK-treated groups. The results obtained from MTS 
analysis suggest that CIK can induce lack of proliferation 
of NCL-H157, which is consistent with the observation with 
the inverted phase contrast microscope. In the present 
study, however, the percentage of inhibition viability cells 
is not much more than that of the control group. 
CIK cells establish an appropriate scaffold and a 
complex network of cytokines, adhesion molecules, and 
extracellular matrix proteins. We showed that a VEGF 
pathway controls the proliferation of NCL-H157 treated 
by CIK [10-11]. NCL-H157 express some genes, suggesting 
the genicity and the superiority for clinical use. CIK cells 
appear to have cytotoxic effects, indicating their superior 
role in the management of clinic treatment, and CIK cells 
were examined for safety and efficacy for carcinoma treat-
ment [12-15]. We observed markedly enhanced anti-tumor 
cytotoxic activity of CIK cells after co-culture with NCL-
H157. Furthermore, CIK regulates NCL-H157 activity in a 
time-and concentration-dependent manner. Effective 
adoptive cell transfer faces numerous challenges, such 
as systemic immune tolerance and tumor local immune 
escape. The homing of immune cells to the tumor site is 
reduced, and the antitumor immune functions are inhib-
ited by tumor microenvironment and immunomodula-
tory properties of suppressive cell populations [16-18]. 
Collectively, these results demonstrate that VEGF signals 
coordinate and regulate the dynamics of CIK during VEGF-
induced migration of NCL-H157 in varying states of differ-
entiation. Genetic experiments indicate that the VEGF 
pathway functions independently of pathways govern-
ing NCL-H157 inhibition. Future studies using other gene 
expression should address the extent of the relative stiff-
ness of NCL-H157 mobility as seen in our experiments and 
elucidate the understanding of the mechanism of NCL-
H157 inhibition. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements: This research was supported by 
grants from the Key Medical Research Plan of the Hebei 
Province of China (No.ZD2013060) and the National 
Natural Science Foundation of China(No.31101638). 
Competing financial interests: The authors declare 
that they have no competing financial interests. </p>





<p>Dengrui Li et al </p>



</text></tei>