<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5129490" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective. To develop a new composite disease activity score for gout and provide its first validation. 
Methods. Disease activity has been defined as the ongoing presence of urate deposits that lead to acute arthritis and joint 
damage. Every measure for each Outcome Measures in Rheumatology core domain was considered. A 3-step approach 
(factor analysis, linear discriminant analysis, and linear regression) was applied to derive the Gout Activity Score (GAS). 
Decision to change treatment or 6-month flare count were used as the surrogate criteria of high disease activity. Baseline 
and 12-month followup data of 446 patients included in the Kick-Off of the Italian Network for Gout cohort were used. 
Construct-and criterion-related validity were tested. External validation on an independent sample is reported. 
Results. Factor analysis identified 5 factors: patient-reported outcomes, joint examination, flares, tophi, and serum 
uric acid (sUA). Discriminant function analysis resulted in a correct classification of 79%. Linear regression analysis 
identified a first candidate GAS including 12-month flare count, sUA, visual analog scale (VAS) of pain, VAS global 
activity assessment, swollen and tender joint counts, and a cumulative measure of tophi. Alternative scores were also 
developed. The developed GAS demonstrated a good correlation with functional disability (criterion validity) and dis-
crimination between patient-and physician-reported measures of active disease (construct validity). The results were 
reproduced in the external sample. 
Conclusion. This study developed and validated a composite measure of disease activity in gout. Further testing is 
required to confirm its generalizability, responsiveness, and usefulness in assisting with clinical decisions. </p>

<p>Disease activity is a challenging concept in gout. Based on 
the currently accepted model of the disease, high serum </p>

<p>levels of urate lead to joint deposits of uric acid crystals, 
which may provoke acute arthritis. Acute inflammation 
resolves but eventually evolves into chronic arthropathy, 
with development of disability and impairment of quality 
of life. </p>

<p>The Kick-Off of the Italian Network for Gout Study was 
supported by the Italian Society for Rheumatology as part 
of the Epidemiology Unit Development Programme. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Carlo A. , MD, PhD, Greta Carrara, PhD, Maria 
Manara, MD: Italian Society for Rheumatology, Milan, Italy; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cinzia Viroli, PhD: University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Marco A. Cimmino, MD: University of Genoa, Genoa, Italy; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>William J. Taylor, MD: University of Otago, Wellington, New 
Zealand; 5 Marcello Govoni, MD: University of Ferrara, Ferra-
ra, Italy; 6 Fausto Salaffi, MD: Polytechnic University of 
Marche, Ancona, Italy; 7 Leonardo Punzi, MD: University of 
Padua, Padua, Italy; 8 Carlomaurizio Montecucco, MD: IRCCS 
San Matteo Foundation, Pavia, Italy; 9 Marco Matucci-
Cerinic, MD, PhD: University of Florence, Florence, Italy; </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Giovanni Minisola, MD: San Camillo Hospital, Rome, Italy. </p>

<p>Dr.  has received advisory board membership fees 
from AstraZeneca and Novartis (less than $10,000 each). 
Dr. Cimmino has received consulting fees from Menarini 
International (less than $10,000). Dr. Taylor has received 
consulting and advisory board membership fees from 
AstraZeneca and Pfizer (less than $10,000 each). Dr. Punzi 
has received consulting and/or speaking fees from Abbott, 
Fidia, Menarini, Merck, and Pfizer (less than $10,000 
each). 
Address correspondence to Carlo A. , MD, PhD, 
Via Turati 40, 20121 Milano, Italy. E-mail: c.scire@ 
reumatologia.it. 
Submitted for publication August 6, 2015; accepted in 
revised form January 12, 2016. </p>



<p>An accurate measure of disease activity is an important 
component of appropriate and targeted treatment strate-
gies, as well as of evaluation of new treatments. 
Tissue deposits of uric acid (UA) are the best candidate 
to measure disease activity in gout because they reflect a 
still ongoing active disease process (1). Serum UA (sUA) 
approximates tissue levels well, and it is the main target 
of treatment in gout (2). The relevance of using sUA as the 
outcome measure in gout is strengthened by the consider-
ation that drugs without influence on sUA do not have 
any plausible effect on the disease process (3). Further-
more, sUA levels associate with the risk of acute arthritis 
in a dose-dependent manner, and their persistent control 
leads to a reduction of tissue deposits and risk of flare (4). 
However, sUA is only weakly associated with other relevant 
outcomes, such as disability and health-related quality of 
life (HRQOL) in patients with gout (2). 
Therefore, sUA is a necessary component of the measure-
ment of the activity of the disease process, but other com-
ponents might play a role (5). As recognized by Outcome 
Measures in Rheumatology (OMERACT), several domains 
should be assessed when evaluating the outcome of 
patients with gout, some of them relating more to the cur-
rent disease activity, while others relate mainly to the con-
sequences of the disease (6). Interfering with sUA might not 
be sufficient to control the activity of the disease process, 
and to achieve this goal we need a feasible, reliable, and 
valid measure to apply in practice and clinical trials. 
An effective and more comprehensive way to describe 
the activity of gout is to derive a composite measure of dis-
ease activity that includes and weights relevant variables, 
such as sUA, joint inflammation, pain measures, and tophi 
burden (5). Beyond its clinical (and statistical) relevance, 
the main methodologic concerns rely on the face validity of 
the items to be included, the assumption of a compensation 
among items, and the relative response to treatment of 
single items within the composite score (7). Previous stud-
ies explored the relative relevance of items belonging to the 
OMERACT domains to be included in a composite outcome 
measure, showing substantial disagreement among clini-
cians, researchers, and patients (5,8,9). Nevertheless, more </p>

<p>recently, a preliminary definition of remission has been pro-
posed, suggesting the potential validity of measuring a state 
within the continuum of disease activity in gout (10). 
This analysis aims to derive a new composite disease 
activity score for gout and to provide its first validation. 
For this purpose we applied a data-driven approach, ana-
lyzing data collected in a multicenter observational study, 
including a random sample of gout patients with complete 
baseline and followup clinimetric data. Candidate disease 
activity scores were developed according to a well-
recognized data-driven process and externally validated. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study design, setting, and recruitment. This is a longi-
tudinal analysis of a multicenter cohort study (Kick-Off of 
the Italian Network for Gout [KING] Study, promoted by 
the Italian Society for Rheumatology [NCT01549210]), 
including a nationwide representative sample of patients 
referred to 30 rheumatology clinics across Italy, with a 
clinical diagnosis of gout, recruited between June 2011 
and January 2012 (see Appendix A for members of the 
KING Study Group). A probability sample was drawn 
from clinical registers as previously described, and clini-
cal diagnoses were validated by the participating rheuma-
tologists (11). All the patients were assessed at baseline, 6 
months, and 12 months. The study protocol was approved 
by the local ethics committees of the participating centers. 
A validation sample of consecutive patients with crystal-
proven gout and acute symptoms was recruited between 
September 2015 and November 2015 at 4 KING sites. </p>

<p>Variables. At baseline, 6 months, and 12 months all 
patients underwent a full clinical evaluation that followed 
a structured case report form, including both general 
health and disease-specific variables. 
Gout-related variables included symptoms duration, 
classification according to the 1977 preliminary American 
College of Rheumatology (ACR) criteria (12), disease-
related comorbidities, previous and current treatment for 
gout, swollen and tender joint counts on 66 of 68 joints, 
measurement of tophi (count and tape measure of all the 
clinically evaluable tophi) (13), 0-10 on a visual analog 
scale (VAS) for pain, patient's global assessment of disease 
activity (PtGA), general health and physician's assessment 
of response to treatment (PhGA), flare occurrence (patient-
reported acute and significant worsening of joint pain) 
(14), and sUA levels. All patients completed the Italian 
versions of the Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ), 
the Short-Form 36 (SF-36) health survey, and the Gout 
Impact Scale (GIS) (15-17). In the external validation sam-
ple, a patient acceptable symptom state (PASS) VAS (0-
100) was also measured along with variables to be included 
in the activity scores and the HAQ. 
The underlying construct of disease activity was 
defined as the presence of tissue deposits leading to acute 
or chronic inflammation and as a consequence to pain, 
joint damage, and functional disability (see Supplementa-
ry Figure 1, available on the Arthritis Care &amp; Research 
web site at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ </p>

<p>Significance &amp; Innovations </p>

<p>There are currently no composite disease activity 
measures available for gout. This analysis pro-
vides a clinically useful instrument to define dis-
ease activity beyond the use of biomarkers as the 
sole guidance for clinical decisions. 
Based on the results of this study, a composite 
disease activity measure, including relevant 
domains (serum urate levels, acute flares, tophus 
burden, patient-reported outcomes) able to dis-
criminate between relevant states of disease, is 
proposed. </p>

<p>Further testing in different data sets is now 
required to clarify the responsiveness and clini-
cal utility. </p>

<p>Gout Disease Activity Score </p>

<p>
acr.22844/abstract). As a consequence of this concept of 
disease activity, the decision to change treatment at the 
baseline visit (a new prescription or increasing dose/ 
switch of urate-lowering treatment not related to adverse 
drug reactions, and/or prescription of symptomatic drugs, 
such as colchicine, nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs, 
or intraarticular/systemic glucocorticoids) or the occur-
rence of a gout flare within the following 6 months was set 
as the criterion marker of disease activity to develop the 
disease activity score. 
For the purpose of these analyses, the included sample 
size of .200 subjects is appropriate to develop response 
criteria according to the recommendations of the ACR 
Subcommittee on Classification and Response Criteria of 
the ACR Committee on Quality Measures (18). Therefore, 
a subsample of 214 patients from the study sample was 
drawn for the development of the scores. For the purpose 
of external validation, 60 subjects were deemed as suffi-
cient to detect correlation coefficients .0.35. </p>

<p>Selection of items and statistical methods. Starting 
from a list of items belonging to the OMERACT domains 
for studies on gout (6) (pain, sUA, joint swelling, joint ten-
derness, flare of gout, tophus burden, HRQOL, PhGA, 
PtGA, functional disability, and work disability), 30 rheu-
matologists actively involved in the KING study were 
asked to participate in a Delphi exercise to identify items 
suitable to be included in a measurement of disease activi-
ty for gout. 
After a brief introduction to the aim of the survey, par-
ticipants were asked to assign a 1-10 score of appropriate-
ness to each item to describe different constructs: disease 
activity, disease-related damage, and general health. Invi-
tations to the second and third rounds were sent only to 
participants who had completed the first round of the sur-
vey. Items were selected if more than 70% of the respond-
ers thought they were more suitable to describe disease 
activity rather than damage or general health status, and 
rejected if less than 30%. Items with an intermediate level 
of agreement were proposed again in the second and third 
rounds. Selected outcomes were then filtered based on 
feasibility, reliability, and availability in the data set. 
Two different methods to derive composite scores were 
applied. A 3-step method followed the methodology 
applied to other composite disease scores in rheumatic dis-
ease (19-21). Variables selected from the Delphi exercise 
were standardized. A factor analysis was then applied, and 
factors explaining more than 80% of the cumulative vari-
ance and eigenvalues .0.8 were retained. Factor loadings 
were then fitted in a linear discriminant function analysis, 
using the criterion of low/high disease activity as the classi-
fication rule. A classification table was used to evaluate the 
misclassification rates of the model. Discriminant scores 
were then computed for each subject and used as the depen-
dent variable of a multivariate hierarchical linear regression 
analysis including transformed variables as regressors. The 
combination of variables explaining more than 0.95 of varia-
tion of the discriminant score were selected to be included 
in the final disease activity score for gout (Gout Activity 
Score [GAS]). Finally, beta coefficients were normalized </p>

<p>and used to weight the transformed variables in order to 
compute the GAS at every time point. 
Given the low number of items to be evaluated in the 
factor analysis that might have threatened the validity of 
the 3-step approach, a second simplified method included 
the a priori selected list of items in a discriminant func-
tion analysis. Discriminant coefficients were then normal-
ized and used to derive a second score. Internal validation 
was performed by bootstrap (1,000 samples) and cross-
validation (20 samples) for the 3-step and the 1-step meth-
od, respectively. 
GAS scores, developed in a training sample at baseline, 
were then calculated on the overall study sample at base-
line, 6 months, and 12 months. 
Criterion validity (concurrent and predictive) was tested 
by comparing the GAS scores against the HAQ score, SF-
36 physical component summary and mental component 
summary subscales by Spearman's correlation coefficients 
in the overall KING data set. A further internal validation 
was performed evaluating the consistency of predictive </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline patients' characteristics* </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Value </p>

<p>Sex, no. males/total no. (%) 
368/406 (90.6) 
Age, mean 6 SD years 
64 6 11.5 
Current smokers, no./total no. (%) 
68/405 (16.8) 
BMI, mean 6 SD 
28.0 6 3.9 
Comorbidities, median (IQR) 
3 (2-4) 
Hypertension, no. (%) 
287 (70.7) 
Renal failure, no. (%) 
47 (11.6) 
Osteoarthritis, no. (%) 
226 (55.7) 
Cardiovascular disorders, no. (%) 
105 (25.9) 
Diabetes mellitus, no. (%) 
58 (14.3) 
Liver disorders, no. (%) 
32 (7.9) 
Neoplasms, no. (%) 
25 (6.2) 
Fulfills preliminary ACR criteria, 
no./total no. (%) </p>

<p>373/405 (91.9) </p>

<p>Disease duration (years), median (IQR) 
3.8 (1.6-10.2) 
Joint involvement, no. (%) 
Monoarticular (1 joint) 
87 (21.4) 
Oligoarticular (2-4 joints) 
239 (58.9) 
Polyarticular (.4 joints) 
77 (19) 
VAS pain (0-10), median (IQR) 
2 (0-5) 
VAS patient global (0-10), median (IQR) 
1 (0-5) 
Swollen joints (0-66), median (IQR) 
0 (0-1) 
Tender joints (0-68), median (IQR) 
1 (0-3) 
Presence of tophi, no. (%) 
79 (19.5) 
Tophi dimension, median (IQR) 
1.5 (0.5-6.5) 
Number of flares (3 months), median (IQR) 
0 (0-0) 
Flare (previous month), no. (%) 
120 (29.6) 
Serum urate level 
Mean 6 SD mg/dl † 
6.3 6 1.8 
Mean 6 SD mmoles/liter 
0.37 6 0.11 
Previous corticosteroids 
117 (28.8) 
Current NSAIDs or colchicine 
172 (42.4) 
Current allopurinol, no. (%) 
279 (68.7) 
Current febuxostat, no. (%) 
55 (13.6) </p>

<p>* BMI 5 body mass index; IQR 5 interquartile range; ACR 5 
American College of Rheumatology; VAS 5 visual analog scale; 
NSAIDs 5 nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs. 
 † Cutoff is 7 mg/dl. </p>

<p>1532 
 et al </p>

<p>validity at different time points (e.g., prediction of HAQ 
from baseline to 6 months and from 6 months to 12 
months). 
Construct (discriminant validity) was tested computing 
the standardized mean difference (21) against the decision 
to change treatment, categorized physician VAS of 
response to treatment, and patient's perception of being in 
remission, as coded in the GIS (17). 
In order to increase applicability to other existing data 
sets for external validation purpose and to practice, sim-
plified scores were developed following the same 
methodology. 
The GAS scores were categorized according to the best 
cutoff using preliminary remission criteria (10) as the clas-
sification variable, using the maximal sum of sensitivity 
and specificity from analysis of the receiver operating 
characteristic (ROC) curve at 12 months. 
Sensitivity analyses explored different recall periods for 
the count of the number of flares (past 3 or 6 months) and 
used only the "therapeutic" criterion as the classification 
rule. </p>

<p>In the external validation sample, Spearman's correla-
tion coefficients between GAS score and HAQ score, phy-
sician VAS, and PASS were estimated. Analyses were 
performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Stata</rs> software package (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">release 11</rs>) and R 
Statistical Software. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Delphi exercise. Twenty-six of the 30 solicited investi-
gators completed the first round of the survey, and 24 and 
23 completed the second and third rounds, respectively. 
After 3 rounds, 8 items (number of recent flares, VAS 
pain, VAS global patient, VAS response to treatment phy-
sician, tender joint count on 68, swollen joint count on 66, 
measurement of tophi, and sUA) covering 7 domains (flare 
of gout, pain, PtGA, PhGA, joint inflammation, tophus 
burden, and sUA) were selected to be included in the 
analyses (see Supplementary Table 1, available on the 
Arthritis Care &amp; Research web site at http://onlinelibrary. 
wiley.com/doi/10.1002/acr.22844/abstract). </p>

<p>KING data set. Baseline characteristics of the study 
cohort are given in Table 1. The study flow chart in Figure 
1 reports the study cohort included in these analyses. 
Of the 214 subjects selected to develop the scores, 94 
had a change in treatment not related to adverse events or 
reductions in therapy; further, 36 subjects without a 
change of treatment experienced a flare within 6 months 
from baseline. As a result, 130 patients (60.7%) were clas-
sified as "active." 
The external validation sample included 61 more 
patients (15 women) with a crystal-proven diagnosis of 
gout and acute symptoms. </p>

<p>Three-step derivation. In the first step, factor analysis 
using standardized variables revealed 5 components that 
described the following domains: patient-reported out-
comes, joint involvement, flares, tophi burden, and serum 
urate levels. These 5 factors explained 93.1% of the total 
variability. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Study flow chart. </p>

<p>GAS 
√sUA 
TJC 
SJC 
GAS </p>

<p>GAS 
√sUA 
TJC 
SJC 
GAS </p>

<p>GAS 
√sUA </p>

<p>GAS </p>

<p>Figure 2. Formula for the calculation of different candidate gout activity scores. GAS 5 Gout 
Activity Score; sUA 5 serum uric acid (mg/dl); VAS 5 visual analog scale (0-10 cm); TJC 5 tender 
joint count (0-68); SJC 5 swollen joint count (0-66). </p>

<p>Gout Disease Activity Score </p>

<p>
In the second step, the loadings of every single factor 
were used as independent variables in the linear discrimi-
nant function analysis. The linear discriminant analysis 
resulted in the correct classification of 79.1% of the cases. 
The discriminant function using the canonical discrimi-
nant function coefficients was used to calculate individual 
scores. 
In the third step, individual discriminant scores were 
used as dependent variables of a hierarchical linear regres-
sion using transformed original variables as independent 
variables. This model estimated the relative weights for 
each variable. Bootstrap validation of these coefficients 
showed absolute bias values ,0.01. </p>

<p>Single-step derivation. Variables to be included in the 
1-step process were selected on the basis of the consensus, 
when the score related to the concept of disease activity 
was the highest compared with scores related with disease 
severity and general health. 
Original variables (untransformed) were used as inde-
pendent variables in a linear discriminant function analy-
sis. The linear discriminant analysis resulted in the 
correct classification of 78.5% of the cases. Cross-
validation confirmed the robustness of this finding (cross-
validated correct classification of 79.9%). </p>

<p>Candidate scores. After normalization of the coeffi-
cients, a first (a) and second (b) candidate activity score 
for gout was constructed using both 3-and 1-step method-
ology (Figure 2). A simplified 4-variables score (c) was 
also derived, selecting variables with higher contribution 
to variance and easier to be measured and retrievable on 
other existing data sets, and clinical practice. </p>

<p>Validity of candidate measures. Candidate measures 
showed significant correlations with functional disability 
and HRQOL, both cross-sectionally, at baseline and </p>

<p>Table 2. Criterion validity: cross-sectional and longitudinal correlation between gout activity scores and 
functional disability or health-related quality of life* </p>

<p>Baseline 
6 months 
12 months </p>

<p>HAQ </p>

<p>SF-36 
PCS </p>

<p>SF-36 
MCS 
HAQ </p>

<p>SF-36 
PCS </p>

<p>SF-36 
MCS 
HAQ </p>

<p>SF-36 
PCS </p>

<p>SF-36 
MCS </p>

<p>Baseline GAS 3-step-a 
0.50 
20.57 
20.31 
0.38 
20.24 
20.34 
Baseline GAS 1-step-a 
0.50 
20.57 
20.31 
6 months GAS 3-step-a 
0.35 
20.36 
20.31 
0.43 
20.48 
20.33 
6 months GAS 1-step-a 
0.34 
20.36 
20.31 
0.41 
20.47 
20.31 
12 months GAS 3-step-a 
0.38 
20.34 
20.24 
0.40 
20.41 
20.25 
0.55 
20.60 
20.32 
12 months GAS 1-step-a 
0.38 
20.36 
20.24 
0.39 
20.40 
20.26 
0.53 
20.60 
20.33 </p>

<p>Baseline GAS 3-step-b 
0.50 
20.57 
20.31 
Baseline GAS 1-step-b 
0.50 
20.57 
20.30 
6 months GAS 3-step-b 
0.35 
20.36 
20.31 
0.42 
20.48 
20.33 
6 months GAS 1-step-b 
0.35 
20.36 
20.30 
0.41 
20.46 
20.32 
12 months GAS 3-step-b 
0.38 
20.34 
20.24 
0.41 
20.40 
20.25 
0.54 
20.59 
20.33 
12 months GAS 1-step-b 
0.39 
20.37 
20.23 
0.39 
20.40 
20.27 
0.53 
20.59 
20.33 </p>

<p>Baseline GAS 3-step-c 
0.45 
20.51 
20.29 
Baseline GAS 1-step-c 
0.44 
20.50 
20.28 
6 months GAS 3-step-c 
0.30 
20.30 
20.27 
0.38 
20.43 
20.32 
6 months GAS 1-step-c 
0.29 
20.30 
20.27 
0.37 
20.41 
20.31 
12 months GAS 3-step-c 
0.34 
20.30 
20.21 
0.36 
20.36 
20.20 
0.50 
20.53 
20.30 
12 months GAS 1-step-c 
0.34 
20.30 
20.20 
0.35 
20.35 
20.23 
0.49 
20.53 
20.30 </p>

<p>* All Spearman's rho coefficient P values , 0.001. HAQ 5 Health Assessment Questionnaire; SF-36 5 Short Form 36 health 
survey; PCS 5 physical component summary; MCS 5 mental component summary; GAS 5 Gout Activity Score. </p>

<p>Table 3. Discriminant validity of the Gout Activity 
Scores (GAS), and single items: SMD between patients 
defined as active or inactive according to internal and 
external constructs* </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Disease 
activity 
criterion </p>

<p>VAS 
physician 
(£4 vs. 
&gt;4) </p>

<p>Patient-
reported 
remission 
(GIS item) </p>

<p>GAS 3-step-a 
1.18 † 
1.26 † 
1.00 † 
GAS 3-step-b 
1.18 † 
1.25 † 
0.99 † 
GAS 3-step-c 
1.12 † 
1.22 † 
1.03 † 
GAS 1-step-a 
1.18 † 
1.25 † 
0.92 † 
GAS 1-step-b 
1.18 † 
1.24 † 
0.92 † 
GAS 1-step-c 
1.12 † 
1.23 † 
1.03 † 
12-month attacks 
0.58 † 
0.69 † 
0.80 † 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
sUA 
p 
0.49 ‡ 
0.57 ‡ 
0.70 ‡ 
VAS pain 
1.00 † 
0.92 † 
0.55 ‡ 
VAS patient global 
0.97 † 
1.16 † 
0.77 † 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
TJC 
p 
0.84 † 
0.77 † 
0.27 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
SJC 
p 
0.75 † 
0.77 † 
0.17 
ln(1 1 tophi dimension) 0.49 ‡ 
0.37 § 
0.33 
ln(1 1 tophi number) 
0.48 ‡ 
0.30 
0.26 </p>

<p>* SMD 5 standardized mean difference; VAS 5 visual analog 
scale; GIS 5 Gout Impact Scale; sUA 5 serum uric acid; TJC 5 
tender joint count; SJC 5 swollen joint count. 
 † P # 0.001. 
 ‡ P # 0.01. 
 § P # 0.05. </p>

<p>1534 
 et al </p>

<p>followup visits (concurrent validity), and prospectively 
(predictive validity) (Table 2). 
Discriminant validity of the candidate scores and single 
items were evaluated by the standardized mean difference 
(Table 3). For all the developed instruments, composite 
scores showed higher discriminatory ability when com-
pared with single variables, for every external criterion of 
disease activity. </p>

<p>Cutoffs. Based on the operating characteristics of every 
cut point, as derived from the ROC table, the cutoff associ-
ated with the lowest misclassification rate of patients in 
remission, according to the definition of remission by de 
Lautour et al (10), were identified for each candidate score 
(Table 4). </p>

<p>Sensitivity analyses. In order to evaluate the robustness 
of the results in a first sensitivity analysis, we varied the 
timeframe for the evaluation of previous flares from 12 
months to 6 months and 3 months, with no major impact 
on the results (see Supplementary Tables 2-7, available 
on the Arthritis Care &amp; Research web site at http://online-
library.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/acr.22844/abstract). A sec-
ond set of sensitivity analyses was done using different 
criteria for the estimation of the coefficient of the disease 
activity scores using only decision to change treatment as 
a criterion of disease activity, showing only a slight 
increase of weighting of swollen joint (see Supplementary 
Table 8, available on the Arthritis Care &amp; Research web 
site at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/acr. 
22844/abstract). </p>

<p>External validation. Based on its metric characteristics, 
the 3-step methodology showed the best results and, based 
on feasibility, the 4-variable GAS (GAS-3c) score was 
evaluated in the validation sample. The 4-variable GAS 
score showed a significant association with the HAQ 
(Spearman's rho 0.33, P , 0.05), VAS pain (Spearman's 
rho 0.61, P , 0.05), and VAS PASS (Spearman's rho 
20.37, P , 0.05). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this article we report the development of a new com-
posite disease activity measure for gout to be used in clini-
cal practice and clinical research. We derived the gout 
activity score following a data-driven methodology consis-
tent with that used for other composite measures in </p>

<p>rheumatic diseases and in accordance with relevant rec-
ommendations (18-21). 
Disease activity has been conceptually defined as the 
presence of urate tissue deposits that lead to acute arthri-
tis, which may evolve in chronic arthropathy with devel-
opment of joint damage and functional disability. This 
definition is not merely focused on acute symptoms but 
also on the patient-related consequences of a persistently 
active disease process. The list of possible measures to be 
included in the composite score derived from those whose 
validity, reliability, and responsiveness were evaluated by 
the OMERACT Gout Special Interest Group (22). Experts 
then chose by consensus those measures that better 
defined the concept of disease activity compared to other 
related constructs, such as disease severity and general 
health: sUA, flares, patient-reported outcomes, tophi, and 
joint inflammation. The candidate items comply with the 
most important ones identified by other studies, as well as 
the novel definition of clinical remission for gout (3,5,10). 
The most relevant difference is the inclusion of joint 
inflammation and the exclusion of measures of function. 
These differences might be due to the fact that items were 
entirely derived from the experts and were specifically 
chosen to discriminate disease activity from other con-
structs, particularly disease severity. The inclusion of an 
extensive joint count might threaten the feasibility of our 
instrument. Also, because of the lack of gout-specific 
restricted joint count, GAS scores without joint count 
were developed. In the absence of fully validated gout-
specific instruments for the evaluation of disability in 
gout (23), current instruments may potentially underesti-
mate the impact of the disease on function (24). Similarly, 
the clinical measurement of tophi is not the most sensitive 
method available (e.g., ultrasonography, dual-energy com-
puterized tomography), but is still the most feasible in 
clinical practice (13). Acute-phase reactants would be of 
interest as an additional item to be included, but because 
they are not routinely collected in gout databases they 
were excluded. 
Despite the experts having reached a consensus about 
the most relevant measures to include in a composite dis-
ease activity score, this does not overcome the substantial 
lack of consensus among clinicians and patients about 
their relative importance, as shown by recent robust quali-
tative research (3,5). Building on these results, we applied 
a methodology to weight variables, following the approach 
proposed by van der Heijde et al in the first development 
of the disease activity score for rheumatoid arthritis (19). 
This is a data-driven approach that statistically identifies 
the combination of variables and their relative weights 
that best discriminate between disease states, using an 
external definition of active disease. In the absence of a 
gold-standard definition of active disease, by analogy from 
other disease activity measures, we opted for a relevant 
decision point in patient management: the moment when 
the rheumatologist considered gout sufficiently active that 
the patient had to start treatment with or switch to or 
increase the dose of urate-lowering drugs or symptomatic 
drugs. This choice reflects the perception of the physician 
of a poor control of the disease process. Such a reference 
standard described the real process of decision making in </p>

<p>Table 4. Cutoffs of clinical remission estimated at 12 
months* </p>

<p>Score 
Best cutoff 
AUC (95% CI) </p>

<p>GAS 3-step-a 
,2.7 
0.864 (0.811-0.916) 
GAS 3-step-b 
,2.7 
0.865 (0.813-0.917) 
GAS 3-step-c 
,2.5 
0.858 (0.806-0.909) </p>

<p>* AUC 5 area under the curve; 95% CI 5 95% confidence interval; 
GAS 5 Gout Activity Score. </p>

<p>Gout Disease Activity Score </p>

<p>
practice, because the rheumatologists were unaware that 
their therapeutic decisions were part of the investigation. 
The choice of this classification criterion for disease activ-
ity alone would be quite arbitrary and may be associated 
with a high misclassification. Alternatively, although the 
occurrence of flare has a high positive predictive value 
(almost 100%) in identifying active patients, all patients 
with no flares in the followup might be misclassified as 
"not active." For this reason the performance of a score 
developed only on the risk of flare is likely to be insuffi-
ciently accurate. Based on statistical and conceptual con-
siderations, we combined the "treatment criterion" and 
"flare criterion" in order to increase the performance of 
classification and to cover all the aspects of our definition 
of disease activity. Sensitivity analyses support the 
robustness of this approach, showing only a slight 
decrease of weight for sUA and increase for joint inflam-
mation in the scores developed using only "treatment 
criterion" as the classification rule. 
Using the KING data set it was possible to develop the 
GAS because of the prospective followup of a large num-
ber of patients, belonging to the entire spectrum of disease 
and with a large number of variables prospectively collect-
ed. This is a rheumatology practice-based multicenter 
cohort that ensures high reliability in the assessment but 
selection of more severe or refractory disease. Of note, we 
included a relatively higher proportion of men than 
expected in a general population sample (25). Further val-
idation in a primary care setting is worthwhile to define 
its generalizability. 
We developed a first GAS, including all the relevant var-
iables. The robustness of the classification was also dem-
onstrated by the consistency of 2 different methodologies, 
by internal validations, sensitivity analyses, and external 
validation. Alternative scores were developed to make 
variable collection and score calculations more feasible, 
without major loss of discriminating ability. 
A first validation of the score showed significant corre-
lation with functional disability and physical function 
both cross-sectionally and longitudinally. All the scores 
also perform better than single variables in discriminating 
between physician-and patient-reported disease activity, 
and in predicting the risk of flare throughout the followup. 
Though essentially interchangeable based on the available 
data, among the set of scores we developed, those follow-
ing the 3-step methodology had the best metric properties, 
as also showed by the consistency of remission cutoffs. 
The 4-variable (GAS 3c ) is the best candidate to be fully 
validated and to be applied to clinical practice. The 
results of the external validation confirm the same correla-
tions observed in the development sample. However, 
results on the responsiveness of the different GAS will 
drive a more informed choice of the best instrument. 
In conclusion, we developed and validated a new 
instrument to measure disease activity in gout. In practice 
the gout activity score might be used to assess the disease 
activity of an individual patient and determine objectively 
when to modify treatment. In addition, the efficacy of ther-
apeutic strategies might be determined using an outcome 
measure that incorporates relevant patient-reported 
outcomes. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors acknowledge the contribution of the entire 
KING staff, including other collaborators and research 
nurses. They are also grateful to the rheumatologists of the 
KING centers for their former data collection and for making 
available their registers of patients with gout. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>All authors were involved in drafting the article or revising it 
critically for important intellectual content, and all authors 
approved the final version to be submitted for publication. Dr.  
had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsi-
bility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data 
analysis. 
Study conception and design. , Carrara, Cimmino. 
Acquisition of data. , Cimmino, Manara, Govoni, Salaffi, 
Punzi, Montecucco, Matucci-Cerinic, Minisola. 
Analysis and interpretation of data. , Carrara, Viroli, 
Taylor. </p>



<p>Gout Disease Activity Score </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>