<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5098290" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Continuous epidural analgesia with catheterization is a useful technique, because it has a wide adaptation range 
and provides prolonged analgesia. Problems that may arise from long-term epidural analgesia are changes in the analgesic area, 
duration of analgesia and catheter-related problems. Few articles have evaluated gradual changes of long-term epidural analgesia. 
In the animal models used in those studies, the catheter was inserted by an invasive surgical procedure. In the present study, we 
evaluated changes in a canine model in which the catheter was inserted by a minimally invasive procedure. </p>

<p>Objectives: To evaluate long-term changes in the efficacy of epidural analgesia in an improved canine model in which the epidural 
catheter was inserted and fixed for 5 weeks using a minimally invasive procedure. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods: Six beagles underwent epidural catheterization under general anaesthesia. The catheter tip was located 
in the sixth lumbar region; the catheter peripheral end was passed subcutaneously through the neck. Physiological saline was con-
tinuously infused (1.0 mL/h) via the catheter throughout the study. The efficacy of epidural analgesia was assessed weekly with 2% 
lidocaine once a week in 5 weeks. Peripheral blood analysis including interleukin-6 (IL-6) level in the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), his-
tological evaluations and epidurography were performed to evaluate the mechanisms underlying the changes. </p>

<p>Results: No dog died and the catheters were kept in place. The efficacy of analgesia was well maintained until 4 weeks; at 5th week, 
the efficacy decreased by half. The spread of injected medium was not observed in the cranial direction at 5th week and the tip of 
catheter was capped with granulation tissue. Throughout the study period, white blood cell counts and C-reactive protein levels 
were slightly high for catheterization and the IL-6 level in CSF was below detectable limits. </p>

<p>Conclusions: This was the longest study period with continuous epidural analgesia administered in canines. The effective period of 
epidural anesthesia was 4 weeks in this study. We speculate that time-dependent decrease in the anaesthetic efficacy was attributed 
to formation of granulation tissue surrounding the catheter tip. </p>

<p>Keywords: Anesthesia, Animal Experimentation, Epidural </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Continuous epidural analgesia is a useful technique, 
because it has a wide adaptation range and provides pro-
longed analgesia. This method has been used frequently to 
control postoperative and chronic pain. Problems associ-
ated with long-term epidural analgesia include changes in 
the analgesia area, decrease in efficacy and catheter-related 
complications (1-3). However, few reports have evaluated 
long-term changes in epidural anesthesia in large-size ani-
mals (4-6). 
Previous animal models in long-term studies had lim-
itations and procedures were relatively invasive; namely, 
the muscles around the vertebra were separated and the 
ligamentum flavum or the spine was exposed. Further-
more, the catheter was directly attached with an adhesive 
to a hole drilled at a surgically exposed vertebra or a fascia </p>

<p>near the spine. Such animal models do not reflect clinical 
challenges of maintaining efficacy of long-term epidural 
anaesthesia. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>To investigate changes over time after the administra-
tion of a local anaesthetic through a long-term epidural 
catheter, we developed an improved animal model and 
the catheter tip was allowed to move through the epidural 
space. </p>

<p>3. Materials and Methods </p>

<p>All protocols were approved in accordance with the 
principles of laboratory animal care advocated by the ani-
mal research committee of Kyoto university (Kyoto, Japan) </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016, Iranian Society of Regional Anesthesia and Pain Medicine (ISRAPM). This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in 
noncommercial usages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Sasauchi K et al. </p>

<p>(revised August 2011; experimental run number R-66-5). 
Animal care, housing, surgery and humane treatment of 
laboratory animals were in compliance with the guide-
lines established by the ministry of education, culture, 
sports, science and technology, Tokyo, Japan. </p>

<p>3.1. Animals </p>

<p>Animals were six beagle dogs weighing between 8.5 
and 11 kg. They were anaesthetized with an intramuscu-
lar injection of ketamine hydrochloride (5 mg/kg) and xy-
lazine (1 mg/kg). </p>

<p>3.2. Surgical Procedure </p>

<p>After removing the hair and disinfecting the area for 
general anaesthesia, we made a 10 cm skin incision in the 
lumbosacral region at the location of spinous process from 
L7 to S1; the puncture site was one intervertebral space. Af-
ter puncture, immediately, a skin incision was necessary to 
fix the mesh subcutaneously. A puncture was made by in-
serting an epidural needle into the canine epidural space 
from L7 to S1. This method was confirmed in our pilot study 
to be a relatively safe and easy epidural catheterization 
method. To be precise, an 18-gauge Tuohy needle (Epineed; 
Terumo, Tokyo, Japan) was inserted into the epidural space 
by the hanging drop method. An epidural catheter was ad-
vanced 5 cm through the needle, because approximately 
5 cm of indwelling catheter is associated with a lower in-
cidence of protrusion or bending (7, 8). The position of 
catheter was confirmed radiographically with an injection 
(1.5 mL) of iohexol (Omnipaque 300; Daiichi Sankyo Co. 
Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). The tip of the catheter was located in the 
sixth lumbar (L6) region. The monofilament polypropy-
lene mesh (BardMesh; Bard, Crawley, England, UK) used 
for reconstruction of tissue defects (9-12) was attached to 
the catheter near the puncture site with cyanoacrylate ad-
hesive, sutured and secured to the subcutaneous tissue. 
The peripheral end of the catheter was passed subcuta-
neously from the puncture site to the neck and connected 
to a syringe-type disposable infusion pump. Finally, the 
lumbar skin incision was sutured. The infusion pump was 
placed in the dog jacket. All dogs received 1.0 mL/h physio-
logic saline solution via the catheter for 5 weeks. </p>

<p>3.3. Evaluation of the Efficacy of Anesthesia on Motor Function </p>

<p>After catheterization, the motor function of each sub-
ject was assessed weekly to evaluate the anesthetic efficacy 
over a 5-week period. A 2% lidocaine solution was admin-
istered at a rate of 2.0 mL/min via the epidural catheter, 
within 1 minute and it was connected to an infusion pump 
to prevent a countercurrent microcirculatory blood flow. </p>

<p>Next, the duration of knuckling of the hind limbs was ob-
served. Generally, knuckling is defined as the ankle being 
flexed on the side of calf; in our study, knuckling was de-
fined as dogs placing their top of the foot on the ground 
during walking. The onset point was the time at which 
knuckling occurred on either side of the limb; the offset 
point was the time at which knuckling disappeared in both 
limbs. This motor function was also evaluated at 1, 2 and 3 
weeks after catheterization in all 6 dogs; also, it was evalu-
ated at 4 and 5 weeks in 5 dogs, because one dog was killed 
at 3rd week post-catheterization for histopathologic exam-
ination. </p>

<p>3.4. Contrast-Enhanced Computed Tomography </p>

<p>On two occasions, computed tomography (CT) was per-
formed to evaluate the spread of lidocaine: first, on the 
day of catheterization (n = 6) and again at 5th week, im-
mediately before the catheter was removed (n = 5). We in-
jected a contrast medium, iohexol (1.5 mL), via the epidu-
ral catheter under general anaesthesia. The spread of con-
trast medium was determined by counting the number of 
vertebral body units through a 16-detector low CT scanner 
(aquilion; toshiba medical systems, Nasu, Japan) (13). The 
contrast medium on CT images was colored blue by image-
editing software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Ziostation</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Ziosoft, Tokyo, Japan</rs>). </p>

<p>3.5. Histopathology Examination </p>

<p>Histological evaluation was performed on the lumbar 
vertebra at 3rd and 5th weeks after catheterization. The 
dog was killed with an overdose of sodium pentobarbi-
tal. After perfusion fixation, the fifth to seventh lumbar 
vertebrae were removed en block, fixed with formalin and 
embedded in paraffin. The specimens were sectioned ax-
ially at the middle of L5 (L5-midpoint) and the cephalad, 
middle and caudal planes of L6 (L6-cephalad, L6-middle 
and L6-caudad). The sections were stained with Mayer's 
hematoxylin-eosin (Sigma-Aldrich Corp., St. Louis, MO; 
USA). </p>

<p>3.6. Analysis of the Degree of Inflammation </p>

<p>As histological evaluation of epidural space in our pre-
vious study indicated an inflammatory state, peripheral 
blood and cerebrospinal fluid from 3 dogs were assessed 
to examine the degree of inflammation. </p>

<p>3.6.1. Hematologic Test 
Blood samples were taken from the cephalic vein peri-
odically 1 day before and 4 days after catheterization, and 
4 days after each assessment of motor function thereafter. 
We defined 4 days after catheterization as week 0 in the 
hematologic test and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) sampling. </p>

<p> 
Anesth Pain Med. 2016; 6(4):e35458. </p>

<p>Sasauchi K et al. </p>

<p>white blood cell (WBC) count and level of C-reactive pro-
tein (CRP) were monitored. </p>

<p>3.6.2. CSF Sampling 
After blood sampling on the same day, the cisterna 
magna suboccipital space was punctured with a 22-G 
spinal needle (Terumo spinal needle; Terumo, Tokyo, 
Japan), to obtain 1.0 mL of CSF and the samples were cen-
trifuged. The supernatant was stored at -80°C to assess 
interleukin 6 (IL-6). We used a canine IL-6 enzyme-linked 
immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kit (Quantikine Canine IL-6 
ELISA; R and D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA) (14). We 
considered that a mean minimum detectable value of 6.1 
pg/mL (defined by the manufacturer) had negative result 
for IL-6. </p>

<p>3.7. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Results of the motor function and hematologic tests </p>

<p>are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD). Dun-</p>

<p>nett's test was used to determine differences in motor func-
tion compared to that at 1 week and analyze differences 
in WBC counts and levels of CRP and IL-6 before and after 
catheterization. Results of CT analysis are expressed as me-
dian and range. Differences in the CT analysis between the 
two groups were analyzed by Wilcoxon's signed-rank test. 
In all analyses, P &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>4.1. Evaluation of the Effectiveness of Anesthesia on Motor Func-
tion </p>

<p>No dog had walking disturbances before epidural anes-
thesia. The dogs survived uneventfully and did not show 
any signs of neurological impairment throughout the 
study period. No catheter-related problems occurred (e.g., 
reinsertion, refixation or obstruction). 
Hind limb knuckling was observed after the epidural 
administration of 2% lidocaine. Knuckling appeared in 
one hind limb and then in both limbs; the dogs were un-
able to support their weight with the hind legs. They re-
covered in the reverse sequence. The duration of knuckling 
was significantly reduced at 5th week, compared with the 
duration of knuckling at the first week (Figure 1). </p>

<p>4.2. Contrast-Enhanced CT </p>

<p>There was no contrast medium above the sixth lumbar 
region where the epidural catheter tip was located at 5th 
week. The spread of the contrast medium had extended 
into the subvertebral space (Figure 2). Radiogram showed 
that the cephalad spread of the contrast medium was sig-
nificantly less at 5th week (Figure 3). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Changes in the Efficacy of Epidural Anesthesia </p>

<p>Time, min </p>

<p>0 
15 
30 
45 </p>

<p>1 wk </p>

<p>2 wk </p>

<p>3 vk </p>

<p>4 wk </p>

<p>5 wk </p>

<p>28'31"(12'17") </p>

<p>29'20"(3'51") </p>

<p>25'17"(4'48") </p>

<p>24'02"(7'57") </p>

<p>13'06"(6'22") </p>

<p>The duration of knuckling is expressed as mean ± standard deviation; P value was </p>

<p>0.000783. </p>

<p>4.3. Histopathological Examination </p>

<p>Specimens from L5 at both 3rd and 5th weeks showed 
accumulation of inflammatory cells in the epidural space. 
Specimens from L6 showed different histological findings 
at 3rd and 5th weeks. At 3rd week, small granulation tis-
sue without a tubular construction was present at the L6-
cephalad. Granulation tissue surrounded the catheter at 
the L6-midpoint (Figure 4A) and L6-caudad. The lumen of 
the granulation tissue was narrow and contained a mass of 
inflammatory cells. Neutrophils congregated in the layer 
of the granulation tissue near the catheter (Figure 4B). 
At 5th week, circular granulation tissue consisted of an-
nulations of a large lumen in all specimens from L6 (Fig-
ure 4C). The lumen extended between the dura mater and 
the vertebral periosteum. Neutrophils formed the inner-
most layer around the catheter, lymphocytes surrounded 
the layer of neutrophils and plasma cells were located in 
the outer area of the granulation tissue (Figure 4D). </p>

<p>4.4. Analysis of the Degree of Inflammation </p>

<p>4.4.1. Hematologic Test 
WBC count and CRP levels were increased slightly at 0 
week, the time after catheterization but before administra-
tion of 2% lidocaine. Increasing levels of WBC and CRP re-
turned to baseline by 1 week after catheterization (Figure 
5). </p>

<p>Anesth Pain Med. 2016; 6(4):e35458. </p>

<p>
Sasauchi K et al. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Computed Tomography Images With Contrast Medium </p>

<p>A, at week 0 (left side); B, at 5th week (left side). Radiogram showed that the cephalad spread of the contrast medium was significantly less at 5th week. </p>

<p>4.4.2. CSF Sampling 
Concentration of IL-6 in the CSF was below detectable 
limits in the CSF throughout the study period. </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>In the current study, the effect of epidural anaesthe-
sia was determined by visual observation of hind limbs af-
ter the injection of lidocaine. Knuckling of the hind limb 
was the primary experimental parameter for measuring 
the level and duration of epidural anaesthesia. Knuckling 
involves motor and sensory nerves and results from pro-
prioceptive impairment of the hind limb. The duration 
of knuckling of the hind limbs at 4th week was approxi-
mately 80% of that observed at the first week; by 5th week, 
the duration of knuckling decreased to half of that ob-
served at the first week. Thus, anesthetic efficacy did not 
significantly differ from the fourth week. </p>

<p>Results of CT performed immediately before the 
catheter was removed, showed no contrast medium at 
the L5 side of the epidural space. Nagaro (4) reported 
that the contrast medium spread only to the cephalad 
side of the catheter tip after long-term catheterization. 
Differences between their report and the present study are 
the methods of catheterization and fixation and interval 
of administration. In their report, the epidural catheter 
was directly attached with cyanoacrylate adhesive to a 
hole drilled at a surgically exposed vertebra. The catheter-
ization method that required invasive surgery may have 
induced inflammation. In our study, the catheter was in-
serted and fixed with minimal tissue damage and minimal 
hemorrhage. Furthermore, our study fixation method, 
fixing the catheter on subcutaneous soft tissue with mesh, 
can replicate catheter movement in the epidural cavity. 
In a previous report on epidural anaesthesia in dogs, 
swalander and colleagues fixed the epidural catheter to </p>

<p>4 
Anesth Pain Med. 2016; 6(4):e35458. </p>

<p>Sasauchi K et al. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Comparison of the Spread of the Contrast Medium </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0wk 
5wk </p>

<p>7 (8/6) 
2 (3/2) </p>

<p>Spread </p>

<p>of </p>

<p>Contrast </p>

<p>Medium </p>

<p>(Count </p>

<p>of </p>

<p>Vertbral </p>

<p>Bodies) </p>

<p>Data are expressed as the median and range. At 5th week, the spread of the contrast 
medium was significantly decreased. *, P value was 0.034231. </p>

<p>the skin with suture and butterfly-patterned adhesive tape 
and could maintain the catheter at the site for 1.85 days 
(median 2.0 days) (14). In contrast, the present study se-
cured the catheter tip at the targeted epidural space at 5th 
week, as confirmed by CT. Mesh reinforcement is thought 
to be an effective method for securing the position and 
replicating the catheter movement. Moreover, Nagaro 
(4) intermittently injected lidocaine daily via epidural 
catheter. Physiologic saline solution was infused continu-
ously for 5 weeks and lidocaine was injected weekly. The 
difference in inflammation levels around the catheter tip 
may have been due to the interval of lidocaine adminis-
tration. The difference in radiological findings between 
their report and our study may be due to the amount 
of inflammation caused by differences in the methods 
of catheterization and catheter fixation and different 
administration interval. 
Tissues around the tip of the catheter were exam-
ined at 3 and 5 weeks. Histological evaluation indicated 
that the catheter tip was capped with fibrotic granula-
tion tissue, which was confirmed by CT. These results sug-
gested that this granulation tissue prevented the contrast 
medium from spreading over the cephalad and caused 
leakage of contrast medium from the intervertebral fora-
men. This similarly suggested that the spread of local 
anaesthetic administered via the catheter into the epidural 
space was blocked by granulation tissue. In specimens col-
lected at the 3rd week, there were neutrophils indicative 
of acute inflammation in the granulation tissue layer. At </p>

<p>the 5th week, both acute and chronic inflammation were 
observed. The formation of granulation tissue is thought 
to be caused by slight movement of the catheter, foreign-
body reaction to the catheter, continuous dosing of saline, 
chemical stimulation with lidocaine or infection. Further-
more, the specimens of L6 samples collected at the 3rd and 
5th weeks suggested that continued inflammation may 
have led to thickening of the granulation tissue. An in-
flamed area shows acidic conditions, as demonstrated by 
a low alkalinity (pH); thus, this widens the gap between 
the ionization constant (pKa) of lidocaine and the pH of tis-
sue around the catheter. Therefore, the anaesthetic efficacy 
of lidocaine was reduced. Consequently, we concluded 
that granulation tissue surrounding the tip of catheter de-
creased the efficacy of anaesthesia. Suppression of inflam-
mation around the catheter tip to prevent granulation is 
considered important for successful long-term epidural 
anesthesia. Previous studies have reported that adding var-
ious drugs to the epidural solution can decrease clinical 
unwanted effects (15-17). Long-term epidural analgesia re-
quires comparative studies with other drug groups. 
Evaluation of local inflammation in the epidural space 
is difficult, especially regarding the craniocaudal direc-
tion. The sampling of vein blood and CSF is minimally in-
vasive and repeatable. WBC and CPR increased 4 days af-
ter catheterization, but there was no significant difference. 
WBC count and CRP level recovered to normal levels within 
one week. This change may have been attributable to the 
irritation from subcutaneous passage of the catheter. The 
CSF reflects an inflammatory response in the subarach-
noid space and IL-6 in CSF is one of the important indica-
tors of meningitis, subarachnoid hemorrhage and spinal 
cord injury (18-22). To our knowledge, no report has mea-
sured the IL-6 concentration in CSF after long-term epidu-
ral catheterization. The unremarkable level of IL-6 in CSF, 
coupled with lack of signs in any dog with neurological 
impairments, may suggest the absence of inflammation in 
the subarachnoid space. Catheterization produced granu-
lation tissue in the epidural space, but it may have been be-
low the level to induce inflammation in the subarachnoid 
space. The catheterization and fixation method used in 
this study seems safe and useful for future studies on long-
term epidural catheterization. Furthermore, this study 
may have followed clinical changes more closely than con-
ventional models since the gradual changes were moni-
tored. To our knowledge, this is the longest study period 
performed regarding continuous epidural anesthesia in 
dogs. 
The limitations of this study were the small number 
of subjects and studying only a single group. Although no 
inflammatory sign was detected in this study, obtaining a 
bacterial culture of the tip of the catheter is necessary to </p>

<p>Anesth Pain Med. 2016; 6(4):e35458. </p>

<p>
Sasauchi K et al. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Microscopic Images </p>

<p>A, L6-midpoint at 3rd week (scale, 5 mm). The lumen of the granulation tissue was narrow. B, L6-midpoint at 3rd week (magnification of granulation tissue layer in A: scale = </p>

<p>50 µm). Capillary angiogenesis and neutrophils were present. C, L6-midpoint at 5th week (scale = 5 mm). The lumen of the granulation tissue was enlarged. D, L6-midpoint 
at 5th week (magnification of granulation tissue layer in C: scale = 5 µm). </p>

<p>Figure 5. Changes in White Blood Cell (WBC) Count and C-Reacive Protein (CRP) Con-
centration </p>

<p>Before 0 wk 1 wk 
2wk 3wk 4wk </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>-1.5 </p>

<p>-2.0 </p>

<p>CRP, mg/dl 
WBC (×10 2 </p>

<p>/µl) </p>

<p>300.0 </p>

<p>250.0 </p>

<p>200.0 </p>

<p>150.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>50.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>WBC 
CRP </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation. WBC and CPR slightly increased </p>

<p>4 days after catheterization (0 wk), but there was no significant difference. </p>

<p>determine the cause of granulation tissue formation. Fur-
ther comparative and well-conceived time course studies 
would be helpful in evaluating optimal methods of sup-
pressing proliferation of granulation tissue. </p>

<p>In conclusion, the efficacy of epidural anaesthesia at 
4th week in a canine model using a tuohy needle, monofil-
ament polypropylene mesh and subcutaneous tunneling 
was fair and did not significantly differ to that at the first 
week. We speculate that the efficacy of epidural anaesthe-
sia was subsequently limited by the formation of granula-
tion tissue, which capped the catheter tip. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We gratefully acknowledge the work of past and 
present members of our laboratory. </p>

<p> 
Anesth Pain Med. 2016; 6(4):e35458. </p>

<p>Sasauchi K et al. </p>

<p>Footnotes </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution: Study concept and design: 
Kyoko Sasauchi, Katsuhisa Sunada and Tatsuo Nakamura; 
analysis and interpretation of data: Kyoko Sasauchi, Kat-
suhisa Sunada and Tatsuo Nakamura; acquisition of data 
and drafting of the manuscript: Kyoko Sasauchi; critical 
revision of the manuscript for important intellectual con-
tent and study supervision; Katsuhisa Sunada and Tatsuo 
Nakamura. </p>

<p>Financial Disclosure: We declared no financial support. </p>

<p>Funding/Support: We had no disclosure and financial 
support. </p>



</text></tei>