<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5271396" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: The aim of this study was to identify prognostic significance of microRNA-100 </p>

<p>(miR-100) in solid tumor. 
Methods: Literature search was conducted in databases such as PubMed, Embase, and Web of </p>

<p>Science, using the following words "(microRNA-100 OR miR-100 OR mir100) AND (tumor 
OR neoplasm OR cancer OR carcinoma OR malignancy)." The search was updated up until 
July 10, 2016. Newcastle-Ottawa scale was used to evaluate the quality of studies. Pooled 
hazard ratio (HR) with 95% confidence interval (CI) for patients' survival was calculated by 
using a fixed-effects or a random-effects model on the basis of heterogeneity. Subgroup analysis, 
sensitive analysis, and meta-regression were used to investigate the sources of heterogeneity. 
Publication bias was evaluated by using Begg's and Egger's tests. 
Results: A total of 16 articles with 1,501 patients were included in the present meta-analysis. </p>

<p>It was demonstrated that a lower expression of miR-100 plays a negative role in the overall 
survival (OS) of patients with solid tumor (HR =1.92; 95% CI =1.25-2.94). In addition, the 
association between miR-100 and prognosis was also revealed in the following subgroups: non-
small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC; HR =2.46; 95% CI =1.98-3.06), epithelial ovarian cancer (EOC; 
HR =2.29, 95% CI =1.72-3.04), and bladder cancer (BC; HR =4.14, 95% CI =1.85-9.27). 
Conclusion: This meta-analysis indicates that lower expression of miR-100 is related to poorer </p>

<p>OS in patients with solid tumor, especially in those with NSCLC, EOC, and BC. MiR-100 is a 
promising prognosis predictor and may be a potential target for therapy in the future. 
MicroRNAs, noncoding small RNAs, regulate mRNA at the posttranscriptional level, 
leading to degradation or inhibition of the target mRNA. Research on microRNAs 
began in 1993. 1,2 Since then, an increasing number of microRNAs were discovered, 
and it was found that play an important role in a variety of biological activities includ-
ing proliferation, differentiation, invasion, and apoptosis. 3-5 The association between 
microRNAs and cancer was first reported in 2002 by Calin et al, who observed that 
miR-15 and miR-16 acted as negative regulators of Bcl-2 in cancer, especially chronic 
lymphocytic leukemia. 6 It is now clear that microRNAs play a crucial role in cancer 
cells. Moreover, the clinical use of microRNA is being widely investigated. As a result, 
currently, multiple research studies have been exploring the prognostic function of 
microRNA-100 (miR-100) in cancer patients in order to find a reliable biomarker to 
guide for cancer treatment. 7,8 
As a member of the miR-99 family, miR-100 is located on Chromosome 11 at 11q24.1. 9 
Its aberrant expression was reported in various cancers including nasopharyngeal 
cancer (NPC), 10 oral squamous cell carcinoma, 11 esophageal adenocarcinoma (EA), 12 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Yufeng Cheng 
Department of Radiation Oncology, Qilu 
Hospital of Shandong University, No 107 
West Wenhua Road, Jinan 250012, 
People's Republic of China 
Tel/fax +86 531 8216 9114 
email qiluflk@163.com </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
23 January 2017 </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>494 </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>small cell carcinoma of the cervix (SCCC), 13 non-small-cell 
lung cancer (NSCLC), 14,15 endometrioid endometrial carci-
noma (EEC), 16 epithelial ovarian cancer (EOC), 17,18 bladder 
cancer (BC), 19,20 renal cell carcinoma (RCC), 21 esophageal 
squamous cell carcinoma (ESCC), 22,23 hepatocellular carci-
noma (HCC), 24 colorectal cancer (CRC), 25,26 and pancreatic 
adenocarcinoma. 27 This aberrant expression of miR-100 not 
only has diagnostic implications but also can predict cancer 
patient survival. 28 From this perspective, it may be feasible 
to predict prognosis based on miR-100 expression level. 
However, the correlation between them remains controversial 
to some extent. In some studies, miR-100 was reported as a 
tumor suppressor, whose low expression level was a negative 
prognostic factor. 16,17 In contrast, in some articles, miR-100 
was regarded as an oncogene. 21,27 Therefore, this meta-
analysis was conducted to identify the relationship between 
miR-100 expression level and the survival of cancer patients, 
by pooling the hazard ratio (HR) from studies addressing the 
correlation between miR-100 and overall survival (OS) of 
patients with solid tumor. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
search strategy </p>

<p>A literature search was conducted in databases such as 
PubMed, Embase, and Web of Science, using the following 
words "(microRNA-100 OR miR-100 OR mir100) AND 
(tumor OR neoplasm OR cancer OR carcinoma OR malig-
nancy)." The search was updated up until July 10, 2016. In 
order not to miss the potentially related articles, reference 
lists were also screened. </p>

<p>inclusion and exclusion criteria </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria were as follows: 1) studies exploring any 
of the following solid tumor (eg, head and neck, thyroid, 
non-small-cell or small cell lung, breast, esophageal, gastric, 
pancreatic, hepatobiliary, colorectal, anal, prostate, blad-
der, renal, cervical, endometrial and ovarian carcinoma, 
melanoma, and sarcomas); 2) studies dealing with miR-100 
expression and OS; 3) studies that categorized patients into 
low-and high-expression groups based on the miR-100 
expression; 4) studies providing HR directly or key infor-
mation to calculate HR indirectly, such as Kaplan-Meier 
curves and original survival data; and 5) studies assessing 
miR-100 expression in tissue or blood. The following were 
the exclusion criteria: 1) studies on myelomas, lymphomas, 
or leukemia; 2) nonoriginal articles, such as reviews, articles, 
or letters; 3) laboratory studies on cell lines or animals level; 
4) studies on a set of microRNAs but not miR-100 alone; 
and 5) studies on nondichotomous miR-100. </p>

<p>Qualitative assessment </p>

<p>Newcastle-Ottawa scale was used to evaluate the quality 
of the studies based on the following three aspects: selec-
tion, comparability, and outcome. 29 A study can be given a 
maximum of one star for each item within the selection and 
outcome categories, and a maximum of two stars can be 
given for comparability category. The total stars that can be 
given for a study ranges from 0 to 9. Studies with 6 stars 
were considered as of high quality. 30 Otherwise, studies were 
excluded from the final meta-analysis. </p>

<p>Data extraction </p>

<p>Data extraction was carried out by Wang and Cheng. The 
following details of each article were recorded: publication 
year, first author's last name, cancer type, treatment, sample 
size, stage of disease, miR-100 assay, the cutoff value to 
discriminate high or low expression of miR-100, sample 
sources, follow-up time, and HR (low versus high expres-
sion). HR 1 indicates that lower expression of miR-100 is 
an unfavorable prognostic factor, and HR 1 suggests that 
lower expression of miR-100 confers survival advantage to 
the patients. If the HR value was calculated by a multivari-
ate analysis, then it was extracted directly; if multivariate 
analysis was not available, then results from univariate 
analysis were also accepted in the meta-analysis. If both mul-
tivariate analysis and univariate analysis were not offered, 
Kaplan-Meier curves were used to estimate HR value by 
using the described method. 31 In addition, original survival 
data obtained, if possible, can also be used to calculate HR 
by conducting survival analysis. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>In order to test the heterogeneity of pooled HR, Cochran's 
Q-test and Higgins I 2 statistics were performed. P0.05 
was considered statistically significant. Random-effects 
model was used to calculate pooled HR when between-study 
heterogeneity was revealed (P0.05), and fixed-effects 
model was conducted when between-study heterogeneity 
did not reach the statistical significance (P0.05). Subgroup 
analysis, sensitive analysis, and meta-regression were used to 
investigate the sources of heterogeneity. Publication bias was 
assessed by using Begg's test and Egger's test. 32,33 <rs id="software-1" type="software">STATA</rs> 
version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">12.0</rs> (Stata Corporation, College Station, TX, USA) 
was used to perform all the analyses. </p>

<p>Results 
study selection </p>

<p>In total, 179, 482, and 292 records were identified from 
PubMed, Embase, and Web of Science, respectively </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>495 </p>

<p>MicroRNA-100 and prognosis </p>

<p>(Figure 1). After excluding the replicate records, 272 articles 
were left. Reviewers Wang and Huang carefully read the 
abstract or full text as required and removed 658 records 
because they were review articles, laboratory studies, and so 
on. Then, 23 publications were retrieved for further analysis; 
of these studies, two studies focused on biochemical-free sur-
vival and recurrence-free survival of prostate cancer instead 
of OS; 34,35 three articles did not address solid tumor. 36-38 
In addition, a study by Wang et al used malignant effusion, 
rather than tissue or blood, to assess miR-100 expression 
in NSCLC patients. 39 Therefore, according to the inclusion 
and exclusion criteria in the present study, 17 articles were 
accepted for Newcastle-Ottawa scale. </p>

<p>Qualitative assessment </p>

<p>Results from Newcastle-Ottawa scale demonstrated that 
two studies received eight stars, eight articles received 
seven stars, six articles received six stars, and one article 
received one star. Thus, a study by Zhang et al was excluded 
as it was a low-quality article (Table 1). 40 </p>

<p>Summary of the analyzed studies </p>

<p>After filtering, 16 studies published between 2011 and 
2016 were considered for the final meta-analysis (Table 2). </p>

<p>The cancer types included EA, SCCC, EEC, human EOC, 
BC, NSCLC, RCC, ESCC, HCC, CRC, and pancreatic 
ductal adenocarcinoma. Only four studies clearly stated the 
research-related treatment. As revealed in Table 2, most 
studies (11 of 16) did not clarify whether patient received 
adjuvant therapy after surgery. Study sample sizes ranged 
from 42 to 172 with a total of 1,501 patients from the People's 
Republic of China, the USA, Poland, Iran, and Germany. 
Nine studies enrolled patients with stages I-IV, whereas 
a study by Dhayat only explored miR-100 in patients with 
Stage II pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma. 27 Four studies 
did not specify the stage of disease in the study population. 
Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) 
was used to assess miR-100 expression in all the studies, and 
the cutoff value varied among studies with median expression 
of miR-100 the most widely used. All the authors used tissues 
as the source of miR-100. The majority of HRs (13 of 16) 
were reported in the present analysis, all of which were cal-
culated by using a multivariate analysis, whereas four HRs 
were estimated by analyzing Kaplan-Meier curves. </p>

<p>Meta-analysis results </p>

<p>Due to obvious heterogeneity (I 2 =85.9%; P0.001), 
random-effects model was used to calculate pooled HR </p>



































<p>
Figure 1 Flow diagram of filtering studies. 
Abbreviations: NOS, Newcastle-Ottawa scale; OS, overall survival. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>496 </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>(HR =1.92; 95% confidence interval [CI] =1.25-2.94), 
suggesting that lower expression level of miR-100 sig-
nificantly predicted poorer OS in patients with solid tumor 
(Figure 2). 
In order to identify the potential source of heterogene-
ity, subgroups analysis was conducted based on the patient 
origin, cancer type, and the methods used to calculate HR 
(Table 3). The association between miR-100 and OS was also 
revealed in the following subgroups: NSCLC (HR =2.46; 95% 
CI =1.98-3.06; fixed-effects model), EOC (HR =2.29; 95% 
CI =1.72-3.04; fixed-effects model), and BC (HR =4.14; 
95% CI =1.85-9.27; fixed-effects model). Notably, significant 
heterogeneity was not found among these studies, with P-value 
of heterogeneity being 0.696, 0.07, and 0.146, respectively. 
However, no statistic difference was reported in esophageal 
carcinoma (HR =1.82; 95% CI =0.32-10.32; random-
effects model) and CRC (HR =1.70; 95% CI =0.93-3.09; 
random-effects model). The prognostic role of miR-100 was 
also significant in the following subgroups: HR by report 
or multivariate analysis (HR =1.91; 95% CI =1.91-3.06; 
random-effects model) and Asian patients (HR =2.38; 95% 
CI =1.56-3.66; random-effects model). 
Sensitivity analysis was conducted by sequentially 
omitting individual studies, indicating that there was not a 
single study that significantly contributed to heterogeneity 
(Figure 3). Furthermore, a meta-regression was also conducted </p>

<p>to explore the potential factors that are responsible for 
heterogeneity. The results showed that the following factors 
could partly explain the heterogeneity but did not reach 
statistical significance: patient origin (I 2 =85.68%; adjusted 
R 2 =16.54%; P=0.06), cancer type (I 2 =83.65%; adjusted 
R 2 =10.95%; P=0.59), and multivariate analysis (I 2 =86.84%, 
adjusted R 2 =−8.60%; P=0.97). 
Publication bias was evaluated by using Begg's funnel 
plot and Egger's test. Although the funnel plot revealed 
slight publication bias, P-values of Begg's and Egger's tests 
were 0.753 and 0.056, respectively, showing no evidence for 
significant publication bias (Figure 4). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Lack of a reliable biomarker to predict prognosis is a main 
hurdle to realize individualized treatment. Fortunately, 
emerging data favor the potential use of miR-100 as a cancer 
prognostic predictor. In recent years, downstream targets of 
miR-100 have widely been investigated in several signal 
pathways, which may provide evidence for its potential 
clinical use at a molecule level. First, miR-100 facilitated 
cancer cell proliferation and growth by targeting the mam-
malian target of rapamycin (mTOR) and fibroblast growth 
factor receptors (FGFRs). By using GeneChip ® miRNA Array 
and qRT-PCR, Xu et al 41 identified decreased expression of 
miR-100 in bladder tumor tissues and found that ectopic 
restoration of miR-100 expression suppressed tumor cell 
proliferation. Furthermore, bioinformatic analysis indicated 
that mTOR was the direct target of miR-100. 41 Consistently, 
another study on esophageal squamous cell cancer also sup-
ported this report. Sun et al transfected esophageal squamous 
cell cancer cell lines with miR-100 precursor molecules and 
reported the subsequent inhibition of cell proliferation, which 
was attributed to the fact that miR-100 downregulated the 
expression of mTOR by directly targeting its 3′UTR in a post-
transcriptional manner. 22 In gynecologic cancer, this interac-
tion exists. Torres et al observed that decreased miR-100 in 
EEC tissues coexisted with increased mTOR kinase. 16 With 
respect to cell growth, another potential target of miR-100 
may be FGFRs. Bi et al transfected U2OS cells (human osteo-
sarcoma line) with a miR-100 construct or with an antisense 
of miR-100. 42 It was observed that overexpression of miR-100 
led to decreased expression of FGFR3 protein. Conversely, 
inhibition of miR-100 induced FGFR3 protein expres-
sion. Bioinformatics analysis and luciferase reporter assay 
implied that 3′UTR of FGFR3 mRNA was the direct target 
of miR-100. Based on these experimental results, Bi et al 42 
pointed out that miR-100 served as a tumor suppressor by </p>

<p>Table 1 newcastle-Ottawa scale </p>

<p>Selection Comparability Outcome Total </p>

<p>Feber et al 12 
4 
0 e,f 
2 g 
6 
huang et al 13 
4 
0 e,f 
2 g 
6 
Torres et al 16 
4 
0 e,f 
2 g 
6 
Peng et al 17 
4 
1 e 
2 g 
7 
Wang et al 19 
4 
1 e 
2 g 
7 
liu et al 14 
4 
1 e 
2 g 
7 
Wang et al 21 
4 
1 e 
2 g 
7 
sun et al 22 
4 
2 
1 g,h 
7 
chen et al 24 
4 
1 e 
2 g 
7 
chen et al 25 
4 
1 e 
2 g 
7 
Zhou et al 23 
4 
1 e 
3 
8 
cao et al 20 
4 
1 e 
2 g 
7 
Zhang et al 40 
0 a-d 
0 e,f 
1 g,h 
1 
luo et al 15 
4 
0 e,f 
2 g 
6 
Dhayat et al 27 
4 
1 f 
3 
8 
Zhang et al 26 
4 
1 e 
1 g,i 
6 
Azizmohammadi et al 18 4 
1 e 
1 g,h 
6 </p>

<p>Notes: Reasons for lost stars: a no description of the derivation of the cohort; b no 
description of the derivation of the nonexposed cohort; c no description of exposure 
ascertainment; d no description of whether outcome of interest was not present at 
the start of study; e study not controlling the most important factor such as TNM 
stage; f study not controlling other additional factors, such as age, gender, and smoke; </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>no description of outcome assessment; h inadequacy of follow-up of cohorts; i follow-
up not long enough for outcomes to occur. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>497 </p>

<p>MicroRNA-100 and prognosis </p>

<p>Table 2 Characteristics of the included articles </p>

<p>Authors </p>

<p>Year </p>

<p>Origin </p>

<p>Cancer 
type </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>Number of 
patients </p>

<p>Stage </p>

<p>miR-100 
assay </p>

<p>Cutoff </p>

<p>Sample 
source </p>

<p>Follow-up 
(months) </p>

<p>Hazard 
ratio </p>

<p>Multivariate </p>

<p>analysis </p>

<p>Feber et al 12 </p>

<p>2011 </p>

<p>The USA </p>

<p>ea </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>i-iV </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>21.8 c </p>

<p>K-M </p>

<p>no </p>

<p>huang et al 13 </p>

<p>2012 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>sccc </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>i-iV </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>6.515 b </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>23.6 d </p>

<p>K-M </p>

<p>no </p>

<p>Torres et al 16 </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>Poland </p>

<p>eec </p>

<p>surgery </p>

<p>+ radiotherapy 
+ chemotherapy </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>i-iV </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>150 e </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Peng et al 17 </p>

<p>2012 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>eOc </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>98 </p>

<p>i-iV </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>72 e </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Wang et al 19 </p>

<p>2012 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>Bc </p>

<p>surgery </p>

<p>+ chemotherapy </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>nr </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>36 e </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>liu et al 14 </p>

<p>2012 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>nsclc </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>110 </p>

<p>i-iii </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>60 e </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Wang et al 21 </p>

<p>2013 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>rcc </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>nr </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>81.8 c </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>sun et al 22 </p>

<p>2013 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>escc </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>61 </p>

<p>i-iii </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>nr </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>120 e </p>

<p>K-M </p>

<p>no </p>

<p>chen et al 24 </p>

<p>2013 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>hcc </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>i-iV </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>60 e </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>chen et al 25 </p>

<p>2014 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>crc </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>138 </p>

<p>i-iV </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>60 e </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Zhou et al 23 </p>

<p>2014 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>escc </p>

<p>radiotherapy </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>i-iV </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>60 e </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>cao et al 20 </p>

<p>2015 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>Bc </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>nr </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>60 e </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>luo et al 15 </p>

<p>2015 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>nsclc </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>nr </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>18 e </p>

<p>K-M </p>

<p>no </p>

<p>Dhayat et al 27 </p>

<p>2015 </p>

<p>germany </p>

<p>PDa </p>

<p>surgery </p>

<p>+ chemotherapy </p>

<p>91 </p>

<p>ii </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>5 b </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>30.5 c </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Zhang et al 26 </p>

<p>2015 
People's Republic </p>

<p>of China </p>

<p>crc </p>

<p>surgery a </p>

<p>172 </p>

<p>i-iV </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>50 e </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Azizmohammadi et al 18 </p>

<p>2016 </p>

<p>iran </p>

<p>eOc </p>

<p>nr </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>i-iV </p>

<p>qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>40 c </p>

<p>report </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Notes: a 
No description of postoperative adjuvant therapy; b </p>

<p>did not state the definition of cutoff; c </p>

<p>median; d </p>

<p>mean; e 
maximum duration of follow-up. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BC, bladder cancer; CRC, colorectal cancer; EA, esophageal adenocarcinoma; EEC, endometrioid endometrial carcinoma; EOC, epithelial ovarian cancer; ESCC, esophageal squamous cell carcinoma; HCC, hepatocellular </p>

<p>carcinoma; K-M, Kaplan-Meier curves; NR, not reported; NSCLC, non-small-cell lung cancer; PDA, pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma; qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction; RCC, renal cell carcinoma; ROC, 
receiver operating characteristic; SCCC, small cell carcinoma of the cervix. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>498 </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>preventing translation of FGFR3s. Another study on BC also 
revealed that the reduction of miR-100 expression induced 
sixfold upregulation of FGFR3 protein through an interac-
tion with FGFR3 mRNA. 43 Similar result was also reported 
in non-small-cell lung. 15 Second, miR-100 participated in 
cancer cell apoptosis, which also determines the development </p>

<p>of the tumor. Chen et al observed that miR-100 precursor 
elevated expression of cleaved caspase-3 and pro-caspase-3 
protein, which are two key apoptosis proteins. 24 In order to 
find the mechanism, flow cytometry and Western blot analysis 
were used to assess the apoptosis in siRNA/plk 1-transfected 
human hepatocellular cells. The outcome showed that </p>

















































































































<p>Figure 2 Forest plot of the relationship between miR-100 and overall survival in solid tumor. 
Note: Weights are from random-effects analysis. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; ES, effect size. </p>

<p>Table 3 subgroup analysis </p>

<p>Subgroup 
Heterogeneity 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>I 2 
P-value </p>

<p>Patient origin 
asian 
84.6% 
0.001 
2.38 (1.55-3.66) a 
0.001 
Non-Asian 
90.0% 
0.001 
0.60 (0.10-3.50) a 
0.574 
cancer type 
Non-small-cell lung cancer 
0 
0.696 
2.46 (1.98-3.06) b 
0.001 
epithelial ovarian cancer 
69.6% 
0.070 
2.29 (1.72-3.04) b 
0.001 
Bladder cancer 
52.7% 
0.146 
4.14 (1.85-9.27) b 
0.001 
esophageal cancer 
88.5% 
0.001 
1.82 (0.32-10.32) a 
0.497 
colorectal cancer 
77.1% 
0.037 
1.7 (0.93-3.09) b 
0.084 
Multivariate analysis 
Yes 
88.0% 
0.001 
1.91 (1.19-3.06) a 
0.007 
no 
79.4% 
0.002 
2.03 (0.55-7.42) a 
0.286 </p>

<p>Notes: a Random-effects model; b fixed-effects model. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; HR, hazard ratio. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>499 </p>

<p>MicroRNA-100 and prognosis </p>

<p>siRNA/plk 1 could mimic the effect of miR-100, indicating 
plk1 as a potential target of miR-100. In another digestive 
cancer, gastric cancer, Notch pathway was reported to partici-
pate in the miR-100-mediated apoptosis, which is initiated by 
the interaction between miR-100 and HS3ST2. 44 Third, miR-
100 regulated several components of Wnt/β-catenin pathway, 
including β-catenin, metalloproteinase-7, T-cell factor-4, and 
lymphoid enhancing factor-1, which were closely related to 
cell invasion and tumor metastasis. 45 Transwell migration and 
invasion assay by Jiang showed that transfection of miR-100 
mimic suppressed migration and invasion of breast cancer 
compared to the control group. The direct target of miR-100 
in Wnt/β-catenin pathway may be FZD-8. 46 Bhushan et al 
also found that downregulation of miR-100 may account 
for less invasion of breast cancer cells. 47 In addition, Fu 
et al also consolidated the role miR-100 played in invasion 
and metastasis of esophageal squamous cell cancer by using </p>

<p>bioinformatics analyses. 48 Fourth, cell cycle arrest, which 
is responsible for radio-resistance or chemo-resistance, 
was mediated by miR-100. Xiao et al discovered that the 
introduction of miR-100 mimic in H69 cells (human small 
cell lung cancer cell line) led to downregulation of HOXA1 
protein, inducing G0-G1 and G1-M cell cycle arrest, which 
was associated with drug resistance. 49 A study by Shi et al 
documented that miR-100 can target plk1 and mediated G2/M 
arrest in NPC. 10 Together, miR-100 might be a promising 
prognostic predictor. 
Despite the sort of inconsistency, clinical investigations 
favor predictive use of miR-100 for the survival of cancer 
patients. Peng et al retrospectively collected fresh surgical 
tissues from 98 patients with EOC and used qRT-PCR assay 
to assess the expression level of miR-100. 17 It is revealed 
that the expression of miR-100 was significantly lower in 
epithelial ovarian tumor tissue than in adjacent normal tissue. 
Multivariate analysis demonstrated that lower expression of 
miR-100 was accompanied by shorter survival (HR =2.12; 
95% CI =1.88-3.41). Further evidence on endometrial car-
cinoma also supported the finding that decreased expression 
level of miR-100 worsens prognosis, with a HR of 2.94 (low/ 
high). 16 Similar results were obtained for digestive system 
cancers. Zhou investigated 120 patients with esophageal 
squamous cell cancer who received radiotherapy alone 
and concluded that HRs for locoregional progression-free 
survival (PFS), distant PFS, and OS (low/high) were 8.9, 
8.34, and 8.02, respectively, suggesting that downregulation 
of miR-100 indicated poor prognosis. 23 In BC, Wang et al 
reported that 3-year OS and 3-year PFS for high expression 
level of miR-100 were 33 and 26 months, respectively; on the 
other hand, for low expression level of miR-100, they were 
merely 23 and 16 months, respectively. 19 However, it should 
be noted that literature on the prognostic value of miR-100 
reveals conflicting findings. Wang et al found increased 
miR-100 expression in cancer tissues compared with normal 
tissues in patients with renal cell cancer. 21 HRs for OS and 
tumor-specific survival were 0.28 and 0.41, respectively, both 
of which were statistically significant, suggesting that lower 
expression of miR-100 confers survival advantage. Dhayat 
et al focused on pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma Union for 
International Cancer Control stage II and found that lower 
level of miR-100 is a favorable factor to predict treatment 
response and OS. 27 Apart from studies revealing the survival 
difference, a study by Zhang showed that the difference in 
miR-100 expression level did not lead to statistic difference 
in the survival of patients with CRC. 26 In order to clarify the 
relationship between miR-100 and survival of patients with 
solid tumor, this meta-analysis was conducted. </p>

















<p>Figure 4 Publication bias: Begg's funnel plot with pseudo 95% confidence limits. 
Abbreviations: HR, hazard ratio; SE, standard error. </p>





















<p>
Figure 3 Sensitivity analysis: meta-analysis of random-effects estimates (exponential 
form) with studies omitted. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>In order to ensure reliable outcome, the inclusion criteria 
were strictly limited. First, source of RNA was restricted to 
tissue or blood. As a result, a study by Wang et al was not 
accepted, because it explored miR-100 in malignant effusion 
in NSCLC. 39 Second, Newcastle-Ottawa scale was used. As 
shown in Table 1, most studies (16 of 17) were evaluated 
as of high quality; however, only two studies received nine 
stars, the highest score. The most common reasons why 
the research was deprived of stars lay in the comparability 
and outcome aspects. In terms of comparability, majority 
of the studies (15 of 17) did not control the most important 
factor such as TNM stage; some studies (6 of 17) did not 
control other less important factors, such as age, gender, and 
smoking status of the patients, which would bring potential 
bias to the survival outcome. In addition, it is necessary for 
prognosis studies to describe whether the survival outcome 
was attained by self-report or blind assessment, which was 
stated in Newcastle-Ottawa scale. However, only two studies 
mentioned this category. 23,27 Lastly, follow-up rate is not fully 
recorded. Only a minority of studies described the number 
of lost patients and offered the reason for loss. Considering 
these reasons, more stars have been provided in outcome 
category. It is noteworthy that Zhang et al analyzed survival 
data from the TCGA database and did not provide sufficient 
related information to get at least six stars according to 
Newcastle-Ottawa scale. 40 Hence, although it investigated 
the association between miR-100 expression and OS, it was 
excluded as a study of low quality. 
Finally, 16 studies were included. According to the 
present study, decreased miR-100 expression level con-
fers survival disadvantage in patients with solid tumor 
(HR =1.92; 95% CI =1.25-2.94). This relationship was also 
found in the following subgroups: NSCLC (HR =2.46; 95% 
CI =1.98-3.06; fixed-effects model), EOC (HR =2.29; 95% 
CI =1.72-3.04; fixed-effects model), and BC (HR =4.14; 
95% CI =1.85-9.27; fixed-effects model). In order to 
find the potential source of heterogeneity, first, subgroup 
analysis was conducted, which revealed that heterogeneity 
declined dramatically in NSCLC group (I 2 =0; P=0.70), 
EOC group (I 2 =69.6%; P=0.07), and BC group (I 2 =52.7%; 
P=0.15). Therefore, cancer type might partly account for 
heterogeneity. Previously, several meta-analyses classified 
subgroups according to the method used to assess RNA 
(qRT-PCR versus in situ hybridization) and the source of 
RNA (blood versus tissue). 30 Nonetheless, these variants 
were similar between the studies included in the present 
meta-analysis. As a result, the possibility of these variants as 
the source of heterogeneity was eliminated, and there was no </p>

<p>requirement to perform further subgroup analysis. Owing to 
the results that sensitivity analysis did not reveal the source 
of heterogeneity, meta-regression was further conducted, 
which revealed that P-value of patient origin, the method 
used to calculate HR, and cancer type were all 0.05, with 
adjusted R 2 being 16.54%, −8.6%, and −10.95%, respec-
tively. Meta-regression results showed that although these 
factors might explain part of heterogeneity, but it did not 
reach statistical significance. Meta-regression could have 
been used to analyze whether other factors such as follow-up 
time, related treatment methods, and cutoff value had an 
impact on heterogeneity, but, due to insufficient information 
on or remarkably different definition of cutoff value, the 
necessity and scientific implication to carry out this meta-
regression in these variants were uncertain. 
As it is well known, meta-analysis results are more robust 
than the result of single research. However, it is noteworthy 
that strict inclusion and exclusion criteria are a prerequisite 
for pooled data, which made the present results more reli-
able than the previous ones. 50,51 Despite careful assessment 
of study quality, there are limitations in the present study. 
First, heterogeneity among the studies included is relatively 
high. According to subgroup analysis, tumor type could 
partly explain the source of heterogeneity. Nonetheless, other 
potential factors may also exist. For instance, pathological 
type may be a potential source. The pooled HR from ESCC 
subgroup was 4.61 (95% CI =2.36-8.99; I 2 =0; fixed-effects 
model) compared to esophageal cancer (HR =1.82; 95% 
CI =0.32-10.32; I 2 =88.5%; random-effects model). 22,23 
In addition, because of insufficient data, it was difficult to 
further assess the effects of other variants on heterogeneity. 
For instance, TNM stage, postoperative treatment, and 
follow-up method were not clearly stated in all the studies. 
Second, the power of miR-100 as a stand-alone biomarker 
is presumably weak and varies for different tumor types, 
given the fact that interaction between microRNA and its 
target is complicated. Undoubtedly, microRNA signature 
may be a better option that has been investigated in other 
microRNAs. 52 However, to date, such microRNA signature 
comprising miR-100 was not reported. Third, the definition 
of cutoff value varied among the studies. Some research 
studies chose median value to define the expression level 
of miR-100, yet some used mean value or value calculated 
by receiver operating characteristic curve. Finally, although 
publication bias was not revealed by Begg's and Egger's 
tests, the funnel plot is slightly asymmetric. The limitations 
emphasize the need for well-designed and well-conducted 
prognostic studies on miR-100 in the future. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>501 </p>

<p>MicroRNA-100 and prognosis </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>This meta-analysis indicated that lower expression level of 
miR-100 is related to poorer OS in solid tumor, especially 
in patients with NSCLC, EOC, and BC. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by Youth Science Found of Qilu 
Hospital of Shandong University, Science and Technology 
plan project of Shandong province (2012GSF11852) and 
National Natural Science Foundation of China (81572958). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>References </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>502 </p>



</text></tei>