<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5339929" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:27+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>However, a long-term follow-up study showed cumulative 
probabilities of hepatitis relapse in inactive HBsAg carriers 
of 10.2%, 17.4%, 19.3%, 20.2%, and 20.2% after 5, 10, 15, </p>

<p>20, and 25 years of follow-up, respectively, with an annual 
rate of 1.55%. 
[3] Another long-term longitudinal study (up to 
23 years) showed that 1-17% of inactive carriers reverted 
back to HBeAg-positive chronic hepatitis. 
[4] Cirrhosis and 
HCC may still develop in some inactive hepatitis B surface </p>

<p>Background: Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) loss/seroconversion is considered to be the ideal endpoint of antiviral therapy and 
the ultimate treatment goal in chronic hepatitis B (CHB). This study aimed to assess the patterns of HBsAg kinetics in CHB patients who 
achieved HBsAg loss during the treatment of pegylated interferon (PEG-IFN) α-2a. 
Methods: A total of 150 patients were enrolled, composing of 83 hepatitis B envelope antigen (HBeAg)-positive and 67 HBeAg-negative 
patients. Patients were treated with PEG-IFN α-2a180 μg/week until HBsAg loss/seroconversion was achieved, which occurred within 
96 weeks. Serum hepatitis B virus deoxyribonucleic acid and serological indicators (HBsAg, anti-HBs, HBeAg, and anti-HBe) were 
determined before and every 3 months during PEG-IFN α-2a treatment. Biochemical markers and peripheral blood neutrophil and platelet 
counts were tested every 1-3 months. 
Results: Baseline HBsAg levels were 2.5 ± 1.3 log IU/ml, and decreased rapidly at 12 and 24 weeks by 48.3% and 88.3%, respectively. 
The mean time to HBsAg loss was 54.2 ± 30.4 weeks, though most patients needed extended treatment and 30.0% of HBsAg loss occurred 
during 72-96 weeks. Baseline HBsAg levels were significantly higher in HBeAg-positive patients (2.9 ± 1.1 log IU/ml) compared with 
HBeAg-negative patients (2.0 ± 1.3 log IU/ml; t = 4.733, P &lt; 0.001), but the HBsAg kinetics were similar. Patients who achieved HBsAg 
loss within 48 weeks had significantly lower baseline HBsAg levels and had more rapid decline of HBsAg at 12 weeks compared to 
patients who needed extended treatment to achieve HBsAg loss. 
Conclusions: Patients with lower baseline HBsAg levels and more rapid decline during early treatment with PEG-IFN are more likely to 
achieve HBsAg loss during 96 weeks of treatment, and extended therapy longer than 48 weeks may be required to achieve HBsAg loss. </p>

<p>Key words: Chronic Hepatitis B; Hepatitis B Surface Antigen; Kinetics; Pegylated Interferon Alfa-2a </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.200554 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Dr. Yao Xie, 
Liver Diseases Center, Beijing Ditan Hospital, Capital Medical University, 
Beijing 100015, China 
E-Mail: xieyao00120184@sina.com </p>

<p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, 
tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited 
and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms. </p>

<p>For reprints contact: reprints@medknow.com </p>

<p>© 2017 Chinese Medical Journal ¦ Produced by Wolters Kluwer -Medknow </p>

<p>Received: 30-11-2016 Edited by: Yi Cui 
How to cite this article: Li MH, Zhang L, Qu XJ, Lu Y, Shen G, Wu SL, 
Chang M, Liu RY, Hu LP, Li ZZ, Hua WH, Song SJ, Xie Y. Kinetics of 
Hepatitis B Surface Antigen Level in Chronic Hepatitis B Patients who 
Achieved Hepatitis B Surface Antigen Loss during Pegylated Interferon 
Alpha-2a Treatment. Chin Med J 2017;130:559-65. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ March 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 5 </p>

<p>
antigen (HBsAg) carriers. 
[3] Interestingly, no cirrhosis 
or HCC occurred in patients with HBsAg loss after IFN 
treatment, indicating that HBsAg clearance is currently 
the only parameter associated with an excellent long-term 
prognosis. 
[5] HBsAg loss/seroconversion is considered to be 
the ideal endpoint of antiviral therapy in both HBeAg-positive 
and -negative patients, 
[6] and the ultimate treatment goal in 
CHB. 
[7] However, HBsAg loss is rare in the natural course of 
CHB infection, with an annual rate of only 1.15%, 
[3] though 
treatment with pegylated (PEG)-IFN α-2a for 48 weeks can 
increase the incidence of HBsAg loss to 3%. </p>

<p>[8]   PEG-IFN α-2a treatment is expensive and may be associated 
with adverse effects, and it is, therefore, crucial to identify 
those patients most likely to achieve HBsAg loss as a result 
of IFN-based therapy. </p>

<p>[9]   We performed a retrospective study to assess the clinical 
characteristics and patterns of HBsAg kinetics in 150 CHB 
patients who achieved HBsAg loss/seroconversion during 
treatment with PEG-IFN α-2a. As a retrospective study, there 
were no shedding cases or dropouts in our entire study. In 
this study, only the data for clinical indicators were collected 
from the CHB patients during the IFN-treatment period, and 
all patients are currently being followed up. To the best of 
our knowledge and PubMed search results, this is the largest 
study enrolled 150 HBsAg loss/seroconversion patients 
during PEG-IFN α-2a treatment in the world. </p>

<p>MEthods </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>The study population comprised 150 consecutive patients 
with CHB who achieved HBsAg loss/seroconversion during 
96 weeks of PEG-IFN α-2a therapy at the Department of 
Hepatology of Beijing Ditan Hospital from December 
2008 to May 2016. All patients had no contraindication to 
PEG-IFN therapy, aged from 18 to 55 years. HBsAg loss 
is designated as HBsAg from positive to negative, and 
anti-HBs is still negative; whereas, HBsAg seroconversion 
is designated as HBsAg from positive to negative, and the 
anti-HBs from negative to positive. Participants included 
naïve patients, patients reached undetectable levels of serum 
hepatitis B virus deoxyribonucleic acid (HBV DNA) on 
nucleoside (acid) analogs (NA) treatment and those were 
HBV DNA-positive on NA treatment composing of relapse, 
resistance, or poor response. </p>

<p>All patients were positive for HBsAg and negative for 
anti-HBs before treatment of PEG-IFN α-2a. The exclusion 
criteria included active consumption of alcohol and/or 
drugs, coinfection with human immunodeficiency virus or 
hepatitis C virus, cirrhosis, autoimmune hepatitis, evidence 
of neoplastic liver disease, and contraindications to IFN. </p>

<p>Patients received PEG-IFN α-2a 180 μg/week by 
subcutaneous injection until HBsAg loss/seroconversion 
was achieved. Serum HBV DNA and serological 
indicators (HBsAg, anti-HBs, HBeAg, and anti-HBe) were </p>

<p>determined before and every 3 months during PEG-IFN 
α-2a treatment. Biochemical markers and peripheral blood 
neutrophil and platelet counts were tested every 1-3 months. 
HBsAg loss was defined as HBsAg &lt;0.05 IU/ml, and 
seroconversion was defined as HBsAg loss with anti-HBs 
level ≥10 mIU/ml. Undetectable serum HBV DNA after 
treatment was considered as a response. The study was 
conducted according to the guidelines of the Declaration of 
Helsinki and approved by the Ethics Committees of Beijing 
Ditan Hospital, Capital Medical University. All patients gave 
their written informed consent. </p>

<p>Laboratory measurements </p>

<p>HBsAg was quantified using the Architect HBsAg QT 
assay (Abbott Laboratories, Abbott Park, IL, USA; 
dynamic range, 0.05-250.00 IU/ml). If HBsAg levels 
were &gt;250 IU/ml, samples were diluted 1:500 with 
Architect HBsAg diluents to obtain a reading within 
the range of the calibration curve. Anti-HBs (range 
0-1000 mIU/ml), HBeAg, and anti-HBe were detected 
using Abbott Architect i2000 kits (Abbott Laboratories), 
based on an automated chemiluminescent microparticle 
immunoassay. Serum HBV DNA was quantitated using a 
commercially available real-time fluorescence quantitative 
polymerase chain reaction kit with a limit of detection 
of 500 copies/ml (Piji Company, Shenzhen, China). 
Liver function parameters, including serum alanine 
aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase, 
albumin, and total bilirubin levels, were measured using 
an automated biochemical analyzer (Hitachi 7600-11; 
Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan). Peripheral blood neutrophils 
and platelets were counted using an automatic blood cell 
analyzer (Beckman Coulter LH750, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">11.5</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). Serum HBV DNA levels and 
HBsAg concentrations were logarithmically transformed 
for analysis. Continuous variables were expressed as 
mean ± standard deviation (SD) or median (range), and 
categorical variables as absolute and relative frequencies. 
Characteristics were compared between groups using Mann-
Whitney or two-sample Student's t-tests for analysis of 
continuous variables, and Chi-square or Fisher's exact tests 
for analysis of categorical variables and Mann-Whitney 
and two-sample Student's t-tests for analysis of continuous 
variables, as appropriate. A two-sided P &lt; 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>rEsults </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics </p>

<p>Among a total of 1215 CHB patients, 680 HBeAg-positive 
and 535 HBeAg-negative, treated with PEG-IFN 
α-2a, 150 patients composing 83 HBeAg-positive and 
67 HBeAg-negative patients who obtained HBsAg 
loss/seroconversion during PEG-IFN α-2a treatment 
were enrolled for analysis. One hundred and one patients </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ March 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 5 </p>



<p>were naïve, and 49 patients experienced NA treatment 
(20 lamivudine, 18 entecavir, 8 adefovir dipivoxil, and 
3 telbivudine) for a median of 24 months (range: 6-108 
months), in which 38 patients with undetectable HBV 
DNA load and 12 patients with positive for serum HBV 
DNA load. </p>

<p>The baseline HBsAg level in all patients was 
2.5 ± 1.3 log IU/ml, and the levels were significantly higher 
in HBeAg-positive (2.9 ± 1.1 log IU/ml) compared with 
HBeAg-negative patients (2.0 ± 1.3 log IU/ml; t = 4.733, 
P &lt; 0.001). The overall baseline serum HBV DNA load 
was 5.3 ± 1.8 log copies/ml, and this was also significantly 
higher in HBeAg-positive (5.9 ± 1.6 log copies/ml) than in 
HBeAg-negative patients (4.3 ± 1.7 log copies/ml; t = 4.249, 
P &lt; 0.001). Baseline HBsAg levels were significantly 
lower in patients with undetectable HBV DNA on NA 
treatment compared with patients who remained serum HBV 
DNA-positive (1.8 ± 1.3 log IU/ml vs. 2.7 ± 1.2 log IU/ml; 
t = 4.010, P &lt; 0.001). The mean serum ALT level was 
219.6 ± 355.0 U/L, and 25.3% of patients had ALT levels 
≥5 upper limit of normal (ULN), including 15.3% of patients 
with ≥10 ULN [Table 1]. </p>

<p>Virological response </p>

<p>Among 112 patients who were HBV DNA-positive 
before treatment, serum HBV DNA reached undetectable 
levels within 60 weeks (median: 15; Q1, Q3: 11-26), and 
cumulatively, 34.8%, 72.3%, and 91.1% of viral response 
occurred at 12, 24, and 48 weeks [Figure 1]. The time to 
viral response was significantly longer in HBeAg-positive </p>

<p>patients compared to HBeAg-negative patients (18.5 weeks 
vs. 14.0 weeks; t = 3.081, P = 0.003) [Table 2]. </p>

<p>Treatment time to hepatitis B surface antigen clearance </p>

<p>The study population comprised 150 consecutive 
patients with CHB who all achieved HBsAg loss during 
PEG-IFN α-2a therapy. Among 150 patients, there were 
117 patients who achieved HBsAg seroconversion. 
The treatment time to HBsAg loss and seroconversion 
were 54.2 ± 30.3 weeks (median, 53.0; Q1, Q3, 
25.0-80.0) and 56.5 ± 28.5 weeks (median, 55.5; Q1, Q3, 
28.0-77.0), respectively. However, 55.3% of HBsAg loss/ 
seroconversion occurred after extended treatment (longer 
than 48 weeks), and 30.0% occurred during weeks 72-96 
of treatment [Figure 2]. The time to HBsAg loss was 
significantly longer in HBeAg-positive patients compared 
with HBeAg-negative patients (62.0 weeks vs. 41.0 weeks; 
t = 2.905, P = 0.004) [Table 2], and patients with higher 
HBsAg levels needed longer treatment than patients with 
lower HBsAg levels to achieve HBsAg loss (F = 10.091, 
P &lt; 0.001) [Figure 3]. </p>

<p>Serum hepatitis B surface antigen kinetics </p>

<p>Among all patients, HBsAg levels decreased significantly 
at 12 and 24 weeks, with declines of 1.6 ± 1.5 log IU/ml 
and 2.3 ± 1.4 log IU/ml (48.3% and 88.3% of baseline), 
respectively [Table 2]. HBsAg levels at 48 weeks 
reached &lt;100 IU/ml in 93.3% (140/150) of patients and 
only one patient had HBsAg levels &gt;1000 IU/ml. The 
kinetics of HBsAg decline was similar in HBeAg-positive 
and -negative patients [Figure 4]. In HBeAg-positive </p>

<p>Table 1: Demographic and baseline characteristics of study population </p>

<p>Characteristics 
All patients 
(n = 150) </p>

<p>HBeAg-positive 
patients (n = 83) </p>

<p>HBeAg-negative 
patients (n = 67) </p>

<p>Statistical 
values </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Age (years), mean ± SD 
32.3 ± 10.9 
29.8 ± 10.3 
35.4 ± 11.0 
3.198* 
0.002 
Gender (male/female), n 
106/44 
54/29 
52/15 
0.107 
NA-naïve, n (%) 
101 (67.3) 
53 (63.9) 
48 (71.7) 
0.382 
Patients reached viral response on-NAs, n (%) 
37 (24.7) 
21 (25.3) 
16 (23.9) 
0.040 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.841 
Baseline HBV DNA load (log copies/ml), 
mean ± SD </p>

<p>5.3 ± 1.8 
5.9 ± 1.6 
4.3 ± 1.7 
4.249* 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>ALT levels 
Values (U/L), mean ± SD 
219.6 ± 355.0 
259.4 ± 363.6 
170.3 ± 340.3 
1.535* 
0.127 
Values (U/L), median (Q1-Q3) 
66 (28−201) 
105 (42−223) 
41 (21−98) 
&lt;1 ULN, n (%) 
51 (34.0) 
18 (21.7) 
33 (49.3) 
1 ULN ≤values &lt;2 ULN, n (%) 
29 (19.3) 
15 (18.1) 
14 (20.9) 
2 ULN ≤values &lt;5 ULN, n (%) 
32 (21.3) 
24 (28.9) 
8 (11.9) 
5 ULN ≤values &lt;10 ULN, n (%) 
15 (10.0) 
11 (13.3) 
4 (6.0) 
≥10 ULN, n (%) 
23 (15.3) 
15 (18.1) 
8 (11.9) 
Baseline HBsAg level 
Values (log IU/ml), mean ± SD 
2.5 ± 1.3 
2.9 ± 1.1 
2.0 ± 1.3 
4.733* 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;1 log IU/ml, n (%) 
15 (10.0) 
4 (4.8) 
11 (16.4) 
23.797 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1 log IU/ml ≤values &lt;2 log IU/ml, n (%) 
28 (18.7) 
10 (12.0) 
18 (26.9) 
2 log IU/ml ≤values &lt;3 log IU/ml, n (%) 
48 (32.0) 
24 (28.9) 
24 (35.8) 
3 log IU/ml ≤values &lt;4 log IU/ml, n (%) 
47 (31.3) 
33 (39.8) 
14 (20.9) 
≥4 log IU/ml, n (%) 
12 (0.8) 
12 (14.5) 
0 
*Student's ttest; 
 † Chi-square test; others using Fisher's exact test. NAs: Nucleoside (acids) analogues. SD: Standard deviation; HBsAg: Hepatitis B 
surface antigen; ALT: Alanine aminotransferase; ULN: Upper limit of normal; HBV DNA: Hepatitis B virus deoxyribonucleic acid. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ March 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 5 </p>

<p>
patients, HBsAg levels decreased by 40.7% and 85.9% of 
baseline, at 12 and 24 weeks, and those in HBeAg-negative 
patients were 56.3% and 92.3% [Table 2]. </p>

<p>However, baseline HBsAg levels were significantly lower 
and HBsAg decrease at 12 weeks was more rapid in patients 
who achieved HBsAg loss within 48 weeks, compared to 
those who needed extended treatment longer than 48 weeks 
to achieve HBsAg loss (2.0 ± 1.4 log IU/ml vs. 3.0 ± 0.9 
log IU/ml; t = 5.171, P &lt; 0.001) and (77.2% vs. 29.2%; 
t = 2.461, P = 0.015), respectively [Figure 5]. </p>

<p>discussion </p>

<p>HBsAg is the most important serological marker of HBV 
infection, and serum HBsAg level correlates with the </p>

<p>intrahepatic amount and transcriptional activity of covalently 
closed circular DNA (cccDNA), the main replicative template 
of HBV. 
[10] HBsAg loss and seroconversion to anti-HBs 
is generally considered to be the ultimate goal of therapy, 
indicating a complete response to treatment and the resolution 
of the disease. It reflects immunological control of the infection 
and confers an excellent prognosis in the absence of preexisting 
cirrhosis or concurrent infections with other viruses. </p>

<p>[11]   IFN has antiviral and immunomodulatory properties that 
result in direct inhibition of viral replication and enhancement 
of the cell-mediated immune response in the process of virus 
clearance. Reportedly, PEG-IFN therapy can only achieve 
30-40% HBeAg seroconversion in HBeAg-positive patients, 
19.2-40.0% sustained viral response (SVR) after cessation </p>

<p>Figure 1: Viral response during treatment. Most patients achieved hepatitis B virus deoxyribonucleic acid response after 24 weeks treatment (a), 
and all patients reached serum hepatitis B virus deoxyribonucleic acid undetectable within 60 weeks of treatment (b). </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Table 2: Viral and HBsAg responses during treatment </p>

<p>Variables 
All patients 
(n = 150) </p>

<p>HBeAg-positive 
patients (n = 83) </p>

<p>HBeAg-negative 
patients (n = 67) </p>

<p>t 
P </p>

<p>Time to viral response (weeks) 
3.081 
0.003 
Mean ± SD 
21.7 ± 13.4 
24.8 ± 15.1 
17.2 ± 9.0 
Median (Q1-Q3) 
15.0 (11.0-26.0) 
18.5 (11.0-37.0) 
14.0 (11.0-20.0) 
HBsAg decrease at 12 weeks (log IU/ml) 
0.899 
0.370 
Mean ± SD 
1.6 ± 1.5 
1.7 ± 1.6 
1.5 ± 1.3 
Median (Q1-Q3) 
1.1 (0.2-2.7) 
1.3 (0.2-2.7) 
1.0 (0.3-2.7) 
Percentage of HBsAg decline at 
12 weeks (%), median (Q1-Q3) </p>

<p>48.3 (47.2-99.7) 
40.7 (34.0-99.4) 
56.3 (47.2-99.7) 
1.379 
0.171 </p>

<p>HBsAg decline at 24 weeks (log IU/ml) 
0.286 
0.775 
Mean ± SD 
2.3 ± 1.4 
2.3 ± 1.6 
2.3 ± 1.2 
Median (Q1-Q3) 
2.2 (1.1-3.4) 
1.9 (0.9-3.6) 
2.3 (1.2-3.3) 
Percentage of HBsAg decline at 
24 weeks (%), median (Q1-Q3) </p>

<p>88.3 (60.9-100.0) 
85.9 (53.5-100.0) 
92.3 (70.4-100.0) 
0.066 
0.948 </p>

<p>Time HBsAg loss (weeks) 
2.905 
0.004 
Mean ± SD 
54.2 ± 30.3 
60.6 ± 29.8 
46.5 ± 29.3 
Median (Q1-Q3) 
53.0 (25.0-80.0) 
62.0 (38.0-85.0) 
41.0 (21.0-71.0) 
Patients with seroconversion, n (%) 
117 (78.0) 
67 (80.7) 
50 (74.6) 
0.430* 
Time to HBsAg seroconversion (weeks) 
2.420 
0.017 
Mean ± SD 
56.5 ± 28.5 
61.9 ± 28.2 
49.3 ± 27.5 
Median (Q1-Q3) 
55.5 (28.0-77.0) 
62.5 (39.0-85.0) 
49.5 (24.0-70.0) 
*Fisher's exact test. SD: Standard deviation; HBsAg: Hepatitis B surface antigen. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ March 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 5 </p>



<p>of therapy in HBeAg-negative patients, 
[12] and 2.0-7.0% 
HBsAg loss/seroclearance, 
[8,13] which remains far from 
satisfactory. Even if HBeAg seroconversion and SVR are 
well-recognized, continuous long-term viral suppression 
does not ensure HBsAg clearance when treatment is 
discontinued. Therefore, it is important to identify 
pretreatment and on-treatment parameters for predicting 
patient response and nonresponse to IFN, especially with 
the aim of identifying patients likely to achieve HBsAg loss. </p>

<p>Well-known predictors of an SVR include low baseline HBV 
DNA, high ALT levels, younger age, female gender, and HBV 
genotype. Sustained responders tend to have lower baseline 
HBsAg and HBV DNA than nonsustained responders. </p>

<p>[14]   Low baseline HBsAg was shown to be more reliable than 
serum HBV DNA levels for predicting good response to 
PEG-IFN and lamivudine treatment in HBeAg-positive 
patients. 
[15,16] An important clinical characteristic of patients </p>

<p>in the present study was low baseline HBsAg levels; 
2.9 ± 1.1 log IU/ml and 2.0 ± 1.3 log IU/ml in HBeAg-positive 
and-negative patients, respectively. However, HBsAg levels of 
3.0-4.4 log IU/ml and 2.5-4.0 log IU/ml have been previously 
reported in HBeAg-positive and -negative patients in similar 
studies. 
[17] Although there were no control groups involving 
patients without HBsAg loss during PEG-IFN treatment in the 
current study, others demonstrated that low baseline HBsAg 
level was the only significant prognostic predictor of HBsAg 
seroconversion following conventional IFN treatment. </p>

<p>[18,19]   These results suggest that CHB patients with low HBsAg levels 
should be considered PEG-IFN therapy to achieve HBsAg loss. </p>

<p>A 48-week course of PEG-IFN is recommended for CHB; </p>

<p>[6]   however, only 3% of patients obtained HBsAg loss after this 
recommended course. Long-term follow-up of PEG-IFN </p>

<p>Figure 2: Proportion of and time to hepatitis B surface antigen loss 
during pegylated interferon α-2a treatment. More than half of hepatitis 
B surface antigen loss occurred after extended treatment and one-third 
of patients needed 96 weeks of treatment to achieving hepatitis B 
surface antigen loss. </p>

<p>Figure 3: Time to hepatitis B surface antigen loss on the basis of 
baseline hepatitis B surface antigen levels. The longer treatment time 
was needed in patients with higher baseline of hepatitis B surface 
antigen level for hepatitis B surface antigen loss. </p>

<p>Figure 4: Kinetics of hepatitis B surface antigen levels during pegylated 
interferon treatment. HBeAg-positive patients had higher hepatitis B 
surface antigen level baseline than HBeAg-negative patients, however, 
their kinetics during treatment were similar. </p>

<p>Figure 5: Kinetics of hepatitis B surface antigen levels in patients who 
achieved hepatitis B surface antigen loss within and after 48 weeks. 
Patients achieved hepatitis B surface antigen loss within 48 weeks of 
treatment had a lower hepatitis B surface antigen level baseline and 
sharp hepatitis B surface antigen decline during treatment compared 
with patients obtained hepatitis B surface antigen loss by extended 
treatment. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ March 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 5 </p>

<p>
trials showed continuing HBsAg loss up to 11% at 3 
and 4 years after stopping treatment, 
[20] but only 63% of 
HBeAg-negative patients had HBV DNA ≤400 copies/ml 
3 years after treatment, despite HBsAg levels ≤19 IU/ml 
at the end of 48 weeks of treatment. 
[21] This suggests that 
individualized treatment programs may be needed to consider 
extending the duration of therapy for CHB. Extended duration 
of therapy can increase the rate of SVR in HBeAg-negative 
patients treated with either standard or PEG-IFN therapies, </p>

<p>[22]   and can enhance the rate of HBeAg seroconversion after 
treatment in HBeAg-positive patients, 
[23] and the rate of 
HBsAg clearance after or during treatment. 
[23-25] In the present 
study, more than half of the HBsAg clearance occurred after 
extended treatment, with 30.0% of patients needing treatment 
for 72-96 weeks to achieve HBsAg loss. This indicates that 
extended treatment was essential for HBsAg clearance during 
PEG-IFN-based therapy. </p>

<p>Treatment should be optimized by careful patient selection 
and individualized treatment decisions in order to increase 
the success rate of IFN treatment and to minimize the risk 
of adverse events. Many studies have demonstrated that 
decrease of HBsAg during treatment was predictor of 
response and indicator for stopping IFN. HBsAg &lt;1500 IU/ml 
at 12 weeks 
[26,27] and at 24 weeks 
[28,29] were associated with 
and predictive of HBeAg seroconversion after IFN treatment 
in HBeAg-positive patients. A decrease in HBsAg levels 
compared to baseline predicted SVR in HBeAg-negative 
patients. 
[18] Moreover, a decline in HBsAg was also 
significantly associated with HBsAg clearance after IFN 
treatment. 
[21] However, the pattern of HBsAg decline 
in patients who achieved HBsAg clearance during IFN 
treatment remains unclear. </p>

<p>The present study showed that HBsAg levels decreased by 
48.3% and 88.3% at 12 and 24 weeks, respectively, while 
93.3% of patients achieved HBsAg &lt;100 IU/ml and nearly 
all patients achieved HBsAg &lt;1000 IU/ml. Although HBsAg 
levels in HBeAg-positive patients were higher than those 
in HBeAg-negative patients, the patterns of decline during 
treatment were similar in both groups. These results suggest 
that a rapid decline in HBsAg levels, regardless of baseline, 
is essential for HBsAg clearance during PEG-IFN treatment 
in both HBeAg-positive and -negative patients. Notably, 
baseline HBsAg levels were significantly lower and the degree 
of HBsAg decline at 12 weeks was significantly greater in 
patients who achieved HBsAg loss within 48 weeks, compared 
with those who needed extended treatment to achieve HBsAg 
loss. Thus, patients who achieve HBsAg loss within 48 weeks 
should have characteristics of lower baseline levels, sharp and 
rapid decline at early treatment time. </p>

<p>A decline in serum HBV DNA reflects a reduction in viral 
replication while a decline in serum HBsAg represents 
a reduction in the translation of mRNAs produced from 
transcriptionally-active cccDNA or integrated sequences. </p>

<p>[30]   The viral response during treatment alone may not represent 
a reliable indicator of SVR to antiviral therapy, and the 
kinetics of HBV DNA and HBsAg level are dissociated </p>

<p>in NA-treated patients and relapsers to PEG-IFN. Several 
studies have shown that combining cutoff levels for HBsAg 
and HBV DNA can reliably identify patients with inactive 
disease, 
[31,32] and that HBsAg and HBV DNA kinetics are 
parallel in sustained responders to PEG-IFN. </p>

<p>[13,21,33]   In the present study, all patients who were HBV 
DNA-positive before IFN treatment achieved viral response 
within 60 weeks, most within 48 weeks. However, most 
patients needed extended treatment for HBsAg clearance, 
suggesting that a strong immune response stimulated by IFN 
treatment could efficiently control viral replication and clear 
HBV-infected hepatocytes. Viral response was the essential 
condition for HBsAg clearance during IFN-based therapy. </p>

<p>In summary, the results of this study demonstrate that patients 
with lower baseline HBsAg sustained and rapid decline of 
HBsAg during treatment, and early viral response are more 
likely to achieve HBsAg clearance 
[34] during IFN-based 
therapy. However, most patients needed extended treatment 
longer than 48 weeks to achieve HBsAg loss during 
treatment. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank all those who have been involved in this study, 
including the patients, the investigators and colleagues from 
Liver Diseases Center and Clinical Test Center (Beijing 
Ditan Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China). </p>

<p>Financial support and sponsorship </p>

<p>This study was supported by grants from Beijing Science 
and Technology Commission (No. D121100003912001), 
and Beijing Municipal Administration of Hospiatals 
Clinical Medicine Development of Special Funding, (No. 
ZY201402). </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>There are no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>rEfErEncEs </p>



<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ March 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 5 </p>





</text></tei>